Chris Bache: What is? What is a
group mind, or collective
consciousness? The way I have
experienced patterns of
collective mind, the primary
ways in which context in which
I've experienced them in my work
has been working with students
in the classroom, and there i i
find that using Morphic, sheld
Rupert Sheldrake work in Morphic
field theory and the theory of
formative causation, to
understand some of the patterns
that were emerging in the
classroom were very helpful. Was
very helpful. So that when a
group of students come together,
and they come together with a
common intention, if you can
strengthen that common
intention, if you can strengthen
it and attend to the quality of
engagement, which injects our
common work with an emotional
intensity, not simply a passive
intellectual intensity, which
you often get in a, you know,
introductory course at a
university, Just a passive
engagement, but if you can
elicit active engagement and
focus that engagement in
meaningful exercises with in
which the students have freedom
of choice, and therefore the
choices they make freely have
greater power than the choices
which are pushed upon them with
time and with repetition,
meeting not just once or twice,
but meeting week after week,
month after month, and in some
cases, when students take
multiple courses with you, year
after year there, There seems to
form a certain porosity, a
certain transparency, so that
students sometimes find
themselves showing up in each
other's dreams and synchronistic
experiences begin to increase
among students in the class, or
often, as I described, in dark
night, early dawn, a certain
transparency would sometimes
open between my mind and their
and my students mind, so that
they would find sometimes when I
would just be reaching, you
know, in the in the void, so to
speak, reaching, for the
example, to illustrate a
particular point in the lecture,
I would end up using as a what
would be, to me, a randomly
chosen example, something which
would have drawn from the
immediate life experience of one
of the students in the
classroom, in a way which, when
they heard that woven into the
lecture, would hit a nerve in
their life that would trigger a
reaction and engagement, even
though I was not in any way
myself conscious of making any
paranormal or psychic contact.
Yet there seems to be this
process of flow, osmosis,
exchange of information that
takes place between the
different parties in the room.
At first, I thought of this in
terms of some kind of psychic
bridging taking place between my
mind and their mind, right? But
over time, I began to adopt a
more collective representational
model that this is, this is the
emergence into into conscious
expression of a literally, of an
entity you can get when you can
think of it as an entity, as a
standing wave within larger
currents of mind.
xcite83: Say more about that?
The standing wave? Yeah, we're
just, well, I realize you have
to use metaphor. Yeah, it's all
weird for this, I
Chris Bache: use metaphors sort
of drawn out of fluid dynamics
and chaos theory and non linear
mathematics and Jung Ian
psychology and Transpersonal
theory, just using this assembly
of metaphors to express a very
simple observation, and that is
that mind is an inherent quality
of life that that characterizes
every pattern of life. And if
the pattern in the physical
world is collective social,
there will be corresponding
patterns of mind in the domain
of spirit. So where people
gather regularly, repeatedly,
with common intentionality,
there is an accumulation of
energy in the world of
consciousness. So that I began
to understand that classes have
minds. Not only do classes have
minds, but a course has a mind.
And so the course is the
cumulative learning effect in
Rupert Sheldrake terms of all
the learning of all the students
who have ever taken this
particular course with this
particular professor the class.
Mind is the most recent layer of
the course mind, but the course
mind is, in a sense, a dynamic,
a truly psychically potent
dynamic force which influences
the patterns of learning of the
present class of students who
have just taken this course,
taking this course this
semester, that's the class. But
they are influenced in their
attempt to learn these ideas.
They they are influenced from
inside, so to speak, by the
cumulative effect of all the
students who have ever studied
this material with this
professor, which in my case,
would be about 25 years
xcite83: of students,
fascinating. Do they enter at a
higher level? Is that your
experience? Yeah, basically,
Chris Bache: find that every few
years, every so many years, I
have to redesign my entire
course, because the students are
starting at a higher level. They
kind of get it faster. You know,
when you develop a 15 week
course, you have a certain
agenda, and you you have two or
three weeks to get to a
particular point in the course,
and then two or three weeks to
get to another point. And
sometimes you get into class the
first week, and the students
will signal you that they're
already about three or four
weeks ahead in the syllabus,
just because they have a you
don't have to persuade them of
certain things that you used to
have to persuade students. It's
like they those ideas are more
easily available to them. You
can do it, give it to them in
shorthand, and then you have to
redesign the curriculum on the
spot in order to kind of keep up
with where they are. Now, there
could be several things
contributing to this. It could
be improved pedagogical
delivery. It could be cultural
shifts that are taking place in
the background, right? But I
think one of the things that's
happening is literally the
learning which previous students
have undertaken literally make
it easier for subsequent
students to pick up certain
concept, this, these same
concepts, and so they learn it
much faster, and you can move
through things much more
quickly. And that's what Morphic
field theory leads to
xcite83: expect, right? How
about individual mind? You know,
would you say individual mind is
a misnomer in some sense, that
whatever our individual mind is
is inherently an expression of
something collective. Or, you
know, because in our culture,
everybody, there's such a
particularly in America, there's
such a strong emphasis on
individualism, and I think
there's a kind of conviction
that, you know, I'm an
individual, and people hear a
word like group mind or
something, and they just what,
you know, it sounds terrifying,
like the worst possible thing,
because it sounds like the loss
of the of their individuality.
But I was, I mean, well, but
isn't everybody lost? It? Isn't
everybody in a group mind. And
actually some, some of it's more
pathological, you know, and some
are more awake, but in some
sense culture and, you know,
every thought that we think is
in some sense conditioned by
larger collective events and
forces. And you kind of get the
general sense. So I'm just, what
does that say about whatever we
think our individual mind
actually is?
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think, by
the way, you're absolutely right
about our cultural paranoia
about this group mind thing, and
we can see it in the Star Trek
series around the Borg, yeah,
which is, if there is a group
mind, then it has a de
humanizing, a de individualizing
effect, right? When actually
it's just the opposite, that
somehow the mystery is that what
that evolution has learned found
a way to evolve, not only whole
groups, whole species, but has
now found a way to evolve
individuals within the species.
That's how I connect
reincarnation to evolution, so
that this whole evolutionary
trust which evolves groups upon
groups upon groups now is
evolving individuals within
groups, and at the same time
that individuality, while
extremely precious and from an
evolutionary perspective, extra
ordinarily important. If you
really look carefully at what
that individuality is, you find
it is an open system which
reflects the entire cultural and
psychological history of the
species that we're talking
about. I think that we have for
several 1000 years, been on a
journey which has been
potentiating individuality.