Chris Bache: I think that we
have for several 1000 years,
been on a journey which has been
potentiating individuality and
all the patriarchal religions,
the whole masculine focus has
been, as it were, a decided
potentiation of the individual,
even to the point of asserting
the survival of the soul for the
reward. You know, the soul lives
forever and ever in heaven or
hell based upon the quality of
choices of the that the
individual makes. It's an
enormous potentiation of
individuals, at the great cost,
of course, of tearing the
individual free of the matrix of
life. Now we seem to be moving
into a new direction, where
we're recontextualizing the
stupendous accomplishment of the
fully empowered individual.
We're recontextualizing that
individual within the subtler
matrix of what Buddhism
sometimes called the Buddha
womb, or the matrix
consciousness, the Source
consciousness, so that what was
previously an unconscious
relationship of embeddedness is
now becoming a conscious
relationship of embedded the ego
can get frightened, because the
ego thinking that its
individuality requires
separation and unchanging Self,
and that's usually the two
concepts that go along with
self, is that the self has to be
separate And it's unchanging.
Neither of those are really true
that you there is an actual
higher form of individuality
that emerges and is compatible
with the condition of
interpenetration, not
separability, and the condition
of perpetual change, not
unchanging. And I think that's
really what Buddhism wanted to
deny when it went with the
option of anata no self, what it
was fundamentally denying was
separability and unchanging
Self. It rejected those in lieu
of a concept of self which is
dynamic and is interpenetrating,
and that, I think, is where we
are moving, evolutionary so that
we have an individuality of a
true self, reflective
consciousness, potentiated over
hundreds and 1000s of
incarnations, increasingly
potentiated self, directive,
self, emergent, self, learning,
self creating, but
contextualized within a matrix
that supports and is nourished
by that process. It truly does
support it. It is, it is the
mother matrix which births this
individual genius, and it is
nourished by the learning of the
individual genius. And that's a
long way from the board. Yeah,
absolutely, that's great. And I
think that, you know, that's the
larger issue behind, you know,
the fundamental challenge of the
21st Century that we're pushing
towards, I think, is towards a
global consciousness, you know,
global citizenship, which
mediates between all the various
divisions and nationalism and
factions and religionism of the
of history into into a much More
complex, not boundaryless, but
to some degree, boundaryless
condition which doesn't
suffocate individuality, but
definitely recontextualizes it
in a different with a different
force.
xcite83: Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
What do you see as sort of the
ultimate applicability of this
group wisdom or collective
wisdom potential that's
emerging. So what do you see
that as
Chris Bache: I have a lot of
energy around that question,
right? Because it has very far
reaching implications from
everything from Think Tank the
phenomena think tanks and
dynamics for augmenting
creativity, for enhancing
creativity, all the way to
understanding of a new context
for understanding some of the
dynamics of social and cultural
evolution And psycho spiritual
evolution. So I think, for
example, I think of an
individual, a person, as, from a
reincarnational perspective, as
a living walking group, all
right, and so they the more
lifetimes a person has
experienced, the more likely it
is that they're going to. Have
kind of more intelligence, more
to show, more empathy, more
understanding, more skills of
various things. But in a sense,
they are a living community of
themselves. When you have a
group of people come together,
if, if you're coming together,
either for spiritual purposes or
for social discussion or for
research purposes or think tank
purposes. What this suggests is,
if you can harmonize yourselves
psychologically, socially and
even physiologically, you can
augment, you can stimulate and
augment your own functioning by
by augmenting a group
consciousness, a group mind,
which can have an uplifting and
animating and creativity
enhancing effect on the
individual minds of those
present. And this, I think, has
significant implications for how
we go about learning at a more
pedestrian level, and how we go
about creating new knowledge at
a collective level. It also has
profound ramifications for
understanding some of the social
dynamics involved if we have if
we have a classroom context, and
this would generalize out to the
culture at large, which is
highly divisive, then we don't
have this kind of intelligence,
enhancing empathy, enhancing
effect of a unified field,
drawing us into a higher state
of sensitivity, a higher state
of knowing if we do have a
congealed group, if we have a
good social process for
congealing a group, then we
actually stimulate, I believe, a
more potent form of knowing, a
more potent kind of discovery,
because the group mind is like a
more powerful transceiver that
connects the individuals to the
divine mind, so to speak, even
to the point where we are
clearly at a certain
evolutionary impasse. We need to
break through certain barriers
in order to intellectual
barriers, in order to solve
certain major technological
questions and that we have come
to in physics, in in the
sciences which are really
important for environmental
purposes, cold fusion, number of
important unified Field Theory,
I think we're looking at here,
at a planet which, if the planet
continues to be fragmented,
politically, racially, gender,
even fragmented in terms of in
terms of speciesism, then that
condition of collective
fragmentation is preventing a
potentiation of our individual
genius. Where on the
alternative, if we move towards
greater integration, greater
social cohesion, greater
inclusiveness in medical care,
for example, towards political
democracy, so on, so forth, then
that would have the cumulative
effect of potential literally
potentiating the performance of
our individual minds and and
therefore making it easier for
us to Have the breakthroughs
that would have profound
implications in technology, as
well as the humanities and the
arts, but I'm thinking
particularly of the sciences,
where we have a sense that we're
really up against some Real,
major barriers for solving some
of the technologies that we need
to solve for to really get a
grip on some of the
environmental issues we're
dealing with. So I think to
understand the non local quality
of mind has profound social
implications once we begin to
understand that how our mind
functions, not only how
comfortable it is with itself,
but how creative it is, how
imaginative it is, is not simply
a function of the individual
health, the health of my
individual mind, but is a
function of the health of our
collective mind, then we have a
vested interest in the health of
our collective mind, and we have
a vested interest in the health
of a in a healthy society, in a
healthy culture, in a healthy
globe. To serve that end, cannot
but have a rebounding effect, an
uplifting effect on our
individual well. Being directly,
not indirectly, and not by
virtue of not because of virtue,
but directly because of Morphic
resonance, because of the nature
of mind itself. I.