Chris Bache: Tonight, let me
throw two more books, just so I
want to get into the next
category, but I realize I didn't
put up the last two. The
experiences are wonderful. The
experience is extra ordinary.
But how do we know these people
aren't just imagining and how do
we know that they aren't really
this kind of beautiful story,
but how do we know it's really a
story and pebble Van Loan. He's
a Norwegian doctor, and this
book is, there have been a
number of books of this type,
but I think this book is the
very best scientific evaluation
of the near death episode
phenomena. He just, he really
puts it through all the paces.
He looks at it from different
angles. He looks at the cases,
he looks at the arguments
against their legitimacy, and he
just patiently sifts it out. And
so if you want to look at a
book, or you have that, if you
have a husband at home, that's
just an engineer, he's
hypercritical of thinking that
this is just not real. This is
the book you want to look at,
just because this is the best,
best critical analysis of
phenomenon. And lastly, I would
mention the fourth of Proof of
Heaven. Eben Alexander, some of
you met him and know his work.
He's kind of the man of the hour
on some of this work, and we
have this in the bookstore. Emmy
Ray has his work in the
bookstore, and I think Eben is
doing great work really out
there. He's pitching hard. He's
absorbing a lot of abuse from
the academic community, but his
experience really powerful, and
really he's doing good work, and
I think this is a beautiful
experience. Okay, so let's go to
the next category, life, between
life theory. Now this work
actually began with this book
published in 1988 by Joel Witten
and Joe Fisher. Joel Witten is a
Canadian psychiatrist who was
doing past lives therapy on
behalf of the Canadian
government. By the way, he was
interested in foreign news, and
he accidentally gave an
ambiguous direction to one of
his clients, and suddenly he
found that his client was not
remembering a past life. He was
remembering a life between past
lives. He didn't even think that
this was possible, but he
discovered and he began to
regress people back. He went
when you went back into a former
life, and then you went through
the death in that life. He found
that he could escort people into
the place they went to after
they died. And when he had done
this many times, he published
this short book with Joe Fisher,
who's a newspaper reporter life
between life. And this is really
the beginning of this research.
But the man I'd like to show you
primarily around this work is
this guy, Michael Newton.
Michael Newton and all three of
these books are Michael Newton,
and we have two of them, right?
Ann Marie, we have two of them
in the bookstore. These are
wonderful books, and these are
just wonderful books. Michael
Newton, likewise, was doing
research, doing past lives
therapy. He was taking people
back to heal their circumstances
and their present life by taking
them back to their former lives
and, you know, uncommon trauma
and so on so forth. And then the
same thing happened to him. He
gave an ambiguous instruction,
and he discovered that people
had the capacity to go back into
their life before they were
born, the life between life,
what happens between death and
birth? And he began to
incorporate this into his
therapy. And after he had taken
600 people, right? So just
imagine, if you're a therapist,
how long does it take you to
have 600 clients going back into
this phenomenon? He kept
detailed records. He wrote this
first book, journeys of soul,
journeys of journey of the soul,
in which he basically
summarizes, always staying close
to his cases, the what people
experience in the structure of
the post mortem state. And then
that was following the date I
consider the bibliography I gave
you 2000s the next one destiny
of souls. And these two are
really kind of like two halves
of the same book. I mean,
they're really destiny of souls
gives you more detail, but the
phenomenon is the same. You're
just going into it in greater
detail. And. Off because and
then memories of the afterlife.
What happened is Michael live in
the seeing so many patients,
psychedelic psychotherapists
began to come to him, and he
began to train the therapist. He
began. So he stopped working
with patients, so much as he
began to work with therapists,
and he created an institute, and
so now he now this is the
fastest growing area in
hypnotherapy and past lives
therapy, and people who are
being trained not only to do
past life regressions, but to do
life between life therapy,
because it deepens and
accelerates the therapeutic
process, so that all of this
last book are collections of
cases by a different therapist.
So they will get the therapist
describe their background, how
they got into this, and they
present one case and they move
on to the next therapist. So you
see that the third book, in
fact, was published by the
Newton Institute. So the first
two books are Michael Newton.
The third book comes from the
Newton Institute. Now,
there are so many wonderful
things to share with you from
this material, like the near
death episode research, it just
is so consoling and it is so
illuminating to have a clear
description of the death
experience as the return to
ecstasy. Here we go into the
next step, into the nuts and
bolts of the world we return to
when we die. So let me just kind
of share some observations that
come that you'll find in these
first in these books of Newton,
he says. And first of all,
everything that we talked about
with near death episode
research. All of that phenomenon
is replicated in life, between
life therapy, the same
phenomenon taking the tunnel,
the encounter with the light,
layers and layers of light. He
talks about levels that his
clients talks about levels of
light, all woven together in
stratified threads a series of
rising dimensions above the
physical or tangible world. They
become less dense as one moves
farther away from the heavy
influences of earth. He talks
about there is a period of
orientation that when people
would die in this past life
therapy, they would go into some
type of very comfortable,
consoling environment, a park, a
lake, something very familiar,
and they would orient. And then,
once they were activated to this
new condition, then they would
go beyond that into deeper into
the death process. So this and
there is, there is a technology,
and there is a whole cadre of
beings whose job it is to help
catch people when they die, to
help them reorient to the true
nature of infinity.
Unknown: Just watch your mind,
there's a movie. Is a movie and
PM, you probably know
Chris Bache: exactly your life.
It's ending your life.
Very similar, maybe, okay, very
similar, because this is what
just get busy, is what would
happen if IBM could get the
Bardo contract. They go to this
place, it looks like Dallas, and
you can eat as much as you want,
you know, and you're defending
your life, your kind of life is
reviewed and what you could want
in that it's something like
that. I mean, how many people
die every day in the world?
Hundreds of 1000s of people die
every day. Well, that's a lot of
people to catch and integrate,
and it doesn't happen like some
big machine. It takes personnel.
It takes me to catch several
100,000 people
Margaret Hiller: every day. Do
they have a health and
retirement retirement plan
Unknown: is pretty good.
Chris Bache: Good. He says that
there is a whole, I don't want
to there. First of all, where we
go when we die. There are many,
many, many layers where we go
when we die. There are many
layers of the spiritual
universe, and not everybody goes
to the same place. Everybody
goes to the same home, but not
every there's like a condo of
many layers, and you don't all
go to the same layer of the
condo. He says there. Are many
guides, many beings, and even
the guides have guides. And the
basic principle is, the more
experienced coach, the less
experienced. And this happens up
and down the system that they
are, that you find that you had
to have guides, and those guides
have supervisors, and those
supervisors, you know, they have
guides, and there is a hierarchy
of guides, and what is it that
determines one's placement in
that hierarchy is really simply
their spiritual maturation. It's
open ended. It's a spiritual
maturation process. He says that
ghost as Hollywood presents,
actually, they're very rare.
It's very rare for people who
get hung up. You can get hung up
in the exiting process. But what
Hollywood has inculcated as all
these kind of shadow phenomenon
and scary things that happen
when we die. It's just, it's an
insignificant percentage of the
number of people who are dying.
The large majority of people go
through those intermediate
territories without problem.
Margaret Hiller: Now we're all
worried. Are we in that small
percentage?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, he
actually, I'll give you some
percentages in a minute, because
he he's he gives you some he has
some statistics. He's worked out
on stages of soul development.
But a couple of other things.
First, first of all,
reincarnation is just an obvious
fact of life. He said, If you're
out of your body, you know the
reincarnation is just true. No
ifs ands and buts, that's it.
I'm sorry, but that's the way it
is, right, period. Secondly,
there's no help. Concept of
health is just a distorted, you
know, incomplete perception.
Everybody goes home. Now that
doesn't mean, I mean if you
were, if you were a mean son of
a bitch, and you hurt people,
and you cause people pain and
suffering, you got to deal. You
know you're going to have to
deal with that. And there is
processes and beings who are
there to help you deal with
that. And there are people.
There are people who can be so
damaged by their Earth
experience, they become so
hateful and so filled with so
much malice that very special
circumstances are required to
bring them back into the
wholeness of spirit, and he
discusses those, particularly in
the second book destiny and
stolen souls. He discusses this
in great detail. There are
beings whose specialty is
working with highly damaged
souls, damaged beings hurt so
traumatically. He says there are
soul clusters, and we are not in
this alone. We actually it's
like going to college everybody
you matriculate in a group, and
this group stays intact through
the entire journey process. He
says that after he calls them
soul clusters, he says there are
five to 20 beings in soul. In
your soul cluster, the average
he finds, is about 15 beings
who, at the every incarnation,
they come back together. They
don't necessarily incarnate
together sometimes, but when
you're in between life, you come
back together and you are
immediately transparent. I mean,
one of the things that happens
in the spirit world is you can't
hide anything. Everybody knows
everything about you, and you
know everything about the beings
that you are with and and your
debriefing of your most recent
life experience is done in the
context of your soul cluster.
And each of the members of your
soul cluster may have guides,
and sometimes they're different
guides, and sometimes they're
the same guides. But that there
is, there is a social matrix
within which this is all taking
place. Younger souls tend to
stay more tightly clustered with
their soul cluster. Older souls
tend to kind of go off and do
things more individually, but
they always come back. They're
always part of the soul cluster,
and the soul cluster basically
goes through the experience
together, but not necessarily at
the same pace. Some members of
the soul cluster may proceed
very slowly, and other members
of the soul cluster may proceed
faster. How do you know who's
going faster? He says, Well, all
you have to do is look at the
color of the light. He says, As
as you become more mature, the
energy of your being, which is
light, changes color. And he has
kind of a model of a sort of a
rainbow spectrum of the stages
of development reflected in the
colors. And he says it's
immediately obvious where a
person is in their development.
And just by looking at their
color, he says he he says he
talks about stages of
development. He does his
statistics, he keeps track of
things, and he differentiates
five stages of soul development
that he's been able to identify.
So the question is, what's the
percentage in stages? Here's his
statistics. Level 140, 2% level
230, 1% level that's kind of
discouraging, isn't it, that
means 73% of all the souls that
he's worked with are at levels
one and two. That's three
quarters of the world's
population in levels one and
two. Level three, 17% level
four, 9% level five, 1% here is
a couple of he says, quote, I
have had many cases where a
client has been incarnated for
up to 30,000 years on earth and
is still in the lower levels one
and two.
On the other hand, he said, I
once had a client who entered
into a level three state of
awareness after Only 4000 years
an outstanding performance,
percentage level. 142,
231-317-4951, 495, 1% now,
honest mentioned something. One
of the things I really like
about Newton is he stays with
his dad. He is true to his dad.
He gives you cases for
everything he says. He gives you
examples that come from his
cases, that's, I love the
empirical side, you know, the
discipline side of his work in
that respect. But that's also,
from my perspective, is also the
limitation of the work, because
he can only reflect the
statistics of the people who
come to him to work. And as he
himself says, it tends to be
kind of younger souls who take
find their way to him. I mean,
the Dalai Lama has never gone to
work with Michael Newton. Great
saints and great beings don't
tend to need working with
therapists to explore these
dimensions so that his figures
tend to be skewed somewhat, I
think, in the lower direction.
Also his description of the
nature of post mortal existence
is skewed to what in the
Tibetan, you would say is the
lower half of the Bardo. He
tends to give a more, from my
perspective, a more detailed and
accurate description only of the
lower half of heaven, not of the
higher dimensions of
Unknown: heaven. That's okay,
because that's where most of you
are going.
Chris Bache: It's good, and
believe me, there's plenty of
joy to go around. It really is,
but it's not, I don't find it to
be reflective of the totality.
Is reflective of half of the
totality.
Margaret Hiller: In my Father's
house. Are many mansions, so
we're in the house. We're just
in different mansions. We're in
different aspects.
Chris Bache: You know The
Tibetan Book of the Dead
Buddhism, we talked about six
levels to the six locus, the six
realms of existence, hell
beings, hungry ghost beings,
animals can mark by ignorance,
human beings, low, low heavenly
beings, high heavenly beings.
Each of these are subdivided
into eight hot hills, eight cold
hills, the eight intermediate
hills. There are 26 high
heavenly realms. So it's like
hundreds and hundreds of realms
divided and at one level, this
is a teaching about what
happened, where we go, when we
die. From another level, it's a
teaching about what's happening
right here, because in this
city, there are hell realms.
There are some beings who are
living in the hell of violence
and anger. There are some beings
who are living in the realm of
greed and insatiable appetites.
There are some beings who are
living in the high, heavenly
realm. Everything there silver
in their mouth. Everything is
fine. They've always had plenty.
They've always, you know, so
it's Bardo reality, the
intermediate state, but it's
also in the physical world.
We're in this condition right
now. Those who have more
experience help those who have
less experience, guides. Help
souls. Souls help each other.
High guy. Help lore guides. He
differentiates. He has his own
vocabulary. He talks about
watchers. They're junior and
senior watchers. He talks about
sages. He talks about the old
ones, who are beyond level six.
You know? That says there are
the the old ones, and the old
ones are kind of, you know, he
talks about a council of elders
when you die, when you orient
and when you debrief with your
spirit guide, somewhere in
there, you're going to be
brought before the council of
elders. And the elders are these
old ones, and before you
incarnate when you've chosen
your life, when you've done a
number of things, you go before
the council of elders. So this
is like we're all in this
together. It's a collective.
That's why I talked about the
community of heaven. There is a
social matrix. There's a world
in which there is a social
structure, and it's a social
structure, which is not
hierarchical, in the sense of
the old ones are more valuable
than the younger ones. There's
not a value there's not a value
hierarchy, because we're all
divine. We're all of the Divine.
That's the fundamental truth.
But there is a gradient of
expertise. There's a gradient of
development, and that's just
accepted as an obvious truth. So
on the one hand, everybody is
equally valuable, and older
learners help the younger
learners to grow. There's a
structure to it. There's a logic
to it, and it's he talks about
some of the different worlds of
that reality. He talks about the
world of altered time. Is one of
his languages for it. He talks
about the world of creation and
non creation, and the world of
all knowing. Let me translate
those phrases, the world of all
your time is like a holodeck.
You've seen Star Trek. You go to
the Holo deck, and when you go
on the Holo deck, you can have
any experience you want to. He
says, You can do that when you
die too, and they're, you know
when you're What are you doing
with all your time in between,
from birth, from death to birth?
He said, Well, you can go into
this place called the world of
altered time, where you can go
into this holodeck and you can
experiment creating reality. You
can just create anything that
you can imagine. It's a
holodeck. He says, There is a
world of creation and non
creation. I call it Earth too.
There is an actual physical
world where you can go and you
can experiment with your
creative abilities. But it
actually is a tangible world,
and you can have as you can
spend as much time there as you
want, where you're flexing your
new muscles and you're
experimenting with doing things.
He talks about, what are you
doing? He says, well, one person
reported that they were learning
how to make fish. That's a real
aspiration. They're literally
using your mind to create
physical form and the idea is
that, you know, where did all
these new forms that show up in
evolution? You know, our current
thinking is Life creates things
randomly, and then they're
screened by survival of the
fittest. But from Newton's
perspective, that's not really
quite the whole story. There is
a creativity inherent in the
universal process, and you can
practice that creativity. And
there are beings who practice
the creation of new life forms.
And eventually, some of that
practice manifests in the
manifestation of new life forms
on Earth, which I like to think
about when I'm looking at those
coral reefs with all those
beautiful fish and thinking, How
is this all coming about by
accident?
Margaret Hiller: It gives me
something to hang on, that hope
where Jesus said, Ye are gods.
We are creative beings, and
whatever else he may have meant
by that, but this is in that
chapter for me, that ye are
God's place, yeah, that we're
creative being
Chris Bache: creative beings,
and we you have to practice
creativity. You have to learn to
control the powers that are
yours by your virtue of your
nature. But you can practice it
and get better and better. It's
like learning how to play chess.
Everybody's got the capacity to
be a master, but, you know, to
practice at it. Practice create.
He also talks about this world,
the world without ego. This is
the spiritual maternity ward. I
mentioned this to. You before,
this is a place where new souls
begin, and even it's one of the
most beautiful sections of I
think it's destiny of souls,
where he talks about these
beings who are kind of like
maternity ward nurses who catch
the new souls. They don't have a
self identity, yet, they're raw.
It's like a solar flare coming
off of the sun, and they catch
them and hold them and care for
them and basically help them
awaken to individual existence,
world without ego, meaning world
without sense of self. By the
time they leave the maternity
ward, they have a sense of
individuality. They have a sense
of self. It's a very and not all
beings, not all pieces of
energy, make that transition.
It's like some of them don't
congeal into an individuality,
which if they are kind of
reabsorbed into the totality,
and they catch more. So it's not
like there's an assembly line.
And he says, one person said, I
didn't know myself, asked myself
until I was moved into this
quiet place. So a new soul is
not capable of choice. They
don't have. He says they're not
self shaped. Once you have a
self, once you have a sense of
individuality, he says it's your
signature, and you'll have that
signature forever. He says.
Quote, once given, ego becomes a
covenant between oneself and the
givers to do the best I can with
who I am, who I am changes. What
I am doesn't change, the essence
doesn't change, but who I am,
the form changes, but the
covenant with the Divine is to
do the best you can with who you
are, as the covenant of
individuated existence, as I
mentioned before in my dialog
with her and Laszlo, my
experience is that individuality
is one of The precious gifts of
existence. In fact, I think it's
probably the greatest gift given
by the great mother. So for me,
only part of the Divine
manifests as the physical
universe. Part of the Divine is
outside the physical universe.
The physical universe is the
only thing that is hard enough
that it has the strength to
break up the wholes of the
Divine into individual parts. So
it's kind of like the being of
God has such power that it takes
something as dense as physical
matter to break off little bits
and pieces of the Divine to
develop individual capacity,
that individuality is the great
gift of the mother. It actually
is the great gift of physical
existence itself, the experience
of being an individual, so that
whatever happens, we will always
be an individual. We won't be
swallowed up and lose our
identity forever. Now you know
that most idealistic
philosophies like
interpretations of Hinduism and
some spiritual missions, say,
Well, you see, when you achieve
enlightenment, then when you
die, the Grof returns to the
ocean, the self just you
dissolve in the totality of
being. You cease to exist as an
individual. I'm thinking of a
bad word
Margaret Hiller: right now. We
can all we can all hear it.
Chris Bache: I don't believe
that that's true. That's not the
truth in my experience, in my
experience that no matter how
many times the ego dies, it
gives birth to a deeper
individuality. When that
individual individuality dies
and gives birth to a still
deeper form of individuality.
Individuality is one of the
great gifts of the creative
enterprise, and I don't think we
do return to the source. We do
return to the all. But the
universe didn't spend 13 point 7
billion years gestating this
individuality just to have it
reabsorbed into the totality, so
we go back to the totality, but
not so as to suffocate our
individuality, but actually
enhance and deepen our
individuality.
Unknown: Can you define that
individuality as, I said,
between the oneness and funny
the personality. Where does that
individuality fall? What is that
Chris Bache: in dark time early
on, where I'm exploring a lot of
different areas I'm exploring
that can. Connective tissue of
consciousness. I'm exploring
collective consciousness and
exploring the relationship
between individual evolution and
collective evolution, how
they're all intertwined so with
a deep appreciation for the
connective tissue that we are
all part of. The last chapter in
that book is called The fate of
individuality. As I address the
question what? You know, some
religious systems extinguish
individuality, and I don't think
there is, what is that
individuality? And the closest I
can get to a definition of it is
a functional definition, a
process definition is the
capacity for integrated
experience. I can't get more
specific than that, because the
nature of individuality changes
as the soul matures. And so if
you can't, you can't define it
in terms of content, because the
content is open ended. But what
does seem to be consistent is
the capacity to integrate
experience. So you're
integrating. You learn, you
integrate, you become more. You
learn you integrate, and you
become more. And this is why I
really don't agree with that
with Lazlo, that when we are at
the universe just creates egos
and then swallows them up into
the Akashic memory. The Akashic
field is real, but
individuality, is also real, and
it's a both and and I think we
can use last Well's field theory
to actually describe the
dynamics of the soul in a way
which is more accurate, but it's
truly a both and situation.
Thank you, Gary. And then here
and here, what do you think
about the concept of I've heard
from Shinto and other traditions
that ultimately, the soul
creates their own universe.
Newton and some others have said
that when a soul, when a soul
kind of graduates at a point
where you can continue in the
spiritual world if you want to,
or you can stay within the
physical enterprise if you want
to. But if you are a graduate, a
graduate, you can create an
entire universe. Because you can
create an entire universe. We
are the types of beings we think
of ourselves in such
underestimating terms. We are
beings who can create galaxies
once mature, that's what that's
the size and scale of what we're
talking
Margaret Hiller: about. We're
doing that workshop next week.
Unknown: To what Gary was saying
in 86 I experienced and I was
talking at lunchtime with others
in here. I called in this I
didn't know, at the time of
spiritual emergency, for lack of
a better word, and rather than
having all of the beauty, it was
like I created Dante's Inferno.
You know, I was born Pentecostal
wholeness, and I created that
hell within myself. To me, as I
was going through that, it was
18 months that I was in that my
family just kind of lifted open
for me to pretty much
experience, although they were
scared, you know. But through
that time, I knew that my soul
was so damaged, until I was
experiencing what my soul was
feeling. And somehow I knew that
I was working things out, you
know. But 18 months, I was like
that, and then all of a sudden,
one day, you know, I said, well,
I need to go and get some help.
So I had myself committed. But,
you know, after that time, it
didn't happen immediately, but
two or three years after that,
the entire time that I was
inside, I called it where I went
within. I didn't really feel
like I was individualized. I
didn't feel like I I felt like I
was I didn't have, I was a part
of nothing, yeah, you know, I
didn't, I wasn't anybody. I
wasn't, you know, I couldn't do
anything. I was nothing. I was
little. Everybody else was big,
but I was little, yeah, and, but
I everything that went on and
that time when I was within, I
wrote about it, yeah, so through
that writing and what I
experienced, you. Yes, I found
out that I could write, and
whenever I got outside of that,
that he'll become heaven. That
makes sense, because it gave me
an opportunity to pull from that
hell that I was in and see that
beauty. Because I had been
there, I had done something. I
was an individual person. God
had took me in and told me
secrets and showed me things
that nobody else had seen. So
whenever I came back out, I had
an absolute I was a totally
different person with a
different concept than the
person that I went in with,
yeah. So I guess in a sense of
what Gary was saying, My soul
did create the world that it
wanted, but ultimately it was to
get me. It was like, wake up.
It's time to wake up. Yeah.
Chris Bache: I don't believe in
an eternal Hill. I think that's
an abomination, but I do believe
that there are Hill realms, and
if a person has goes through a
very terrible traumatic
experience, they have nightmares
because they've got a hill
experience living inside their
psyche and until they clear that
it's there. Now, just think of
all the terrible things that
have happened to human beings.
And use the history. Think of
all the people who died World
War One, think of all the people
who died traumatically. War Two,
the people who died in the
Philippines this last week. Just
think of the human family with
all of the trauma that humanity
has undergone. And if the human
psyche has is a single
consciousness, if there is a
collective psyche, then there,
just as we have levels of our
mind which have pockets of hell
inside of them, then there are
pockets of hell in the human
psyche. And if you read the
biographies or autobiographies
of some saints and great
practitioners, you'll they go
into these hell realms, and they
spend a long time in these hell
realms in order to heal, not
themselves, but to actually help
heal, I think, the collective
psyche of humanity and so I
think those realms are there. We
get into them for all sorts of
different sometime, like a
spiritual emergency. And they
they are. They're bigger than we
are. They have, they have a
power all of their own. And
ultimately, even though they are
long live in terms of history,
they are ultimately temporary,
because all trauma can be
healed, and when it's healed,
it's it clears and but humanity,
if we are giving birth to a new
human if we are giving birth to
a higher form of human life, we
have to heal all their human
history in order for human
history to move forward. And
that's why I think a lot of
people who do spiritual
practice, very deep spiritual
practice, they spend a lot of
time in the hell realm. I
mentioned Roger Wilber, and I
was giving a talk on this at a
conference one time, and Roger
was there. He and I had lunch
together, and I was talking
about the hell realm, and I was
talking about the discovery that
when you go into the hell realm,
it's not about healing yourself,
it's about healing the
collective. And he came to the
same conclusion on his past life
therapy work. He was taking
people into past life, and he
said they were just one lifetime
after another, lifetime after
another lifetime, trauma after
trauma after trauma. And he
eventually came to the
conclusion that this couldn't be
simply people who were had
amassed a long history of
trauma. Something else had to be
afoot. And he became convinced
that his clients were people who
were taking on collective pain,
taking on like other people's
lifetimes in the way of
suffering in order to clear the
collective fear. And I think
actually, we are in one of those
periods of history where the
hell realm is coming to the
surface. We are 21st Century is
going to be a hellish century,
and all of this is part of a
collective transformative
process, so you have to get out
the paint in order to clear the
system so that the system can
take in greater joy and greater
beauty. Thank you for sharing
your experience. You.
Audience 3: School, yeah, when
you were talking about
signature, I mean when, when I
meet a person, and, you know,
and I don't have to know them
that well, but there is a sense
or feeling that I have about
them over on above their words,
looks anything, it's like an
essence. You know, I think that
what you're talking about, but
could, could it be that that
aspect, that signature that
you're talking about, could be
just a divine gift of
personality that goes with us
throughout eternity, you know,
just like we have a soul, and
just like we have the spark of
the divine within us, all those
eternal elements, you know,
they're helping build the
miraculous body. Yeah, you know
that personality, that that
distinguishing mark, that even
if a million years passes by and
we see that person. You don't
have to say a word, and we can
feel their essence, that
personality.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think I
agree with the concept. I use a
different vocabulary, because
our word personality is so
connected to individual ego that
it tends to carry that quality.
So I I just prefer the word
individuality, but the way
you're using the term
personality, I think it's
interchangeable. That basic
concept that there is a unique
identity, that identity is us at
the deepest level, and it is a
gift we didn't give it to
ourselves. You know, it was
birthed in the system, and once
burned, it never goes away. It's
always there. And I think you
can, you can feel it, besides
people, yes, about
Unknown: a year and a half ago,
I purchased couple of bottles of
extra time on I was going to end
my life, so I took about of the
275 and I wound up in Cedar
Sinai. And it was really weird,
because I was very at peace with
what I was doing. I really,
really wanted to go. But then,
when I spoke to the first
doctor, he said to me, well,
you'll probably have permanent
liver damage, and you probably
only have, like, two or three
days to live. But I didn't know
how to feel about that, because,
like, I, you know, I didn't plan
to wake up and have to deal with
well, do I Yeah, but that's not
my question. My question. My
question is, there's quite a bit
of suicidality in my family. So
is this show up in the books
about suicidality? Or have I
picked
Chris Bache: another In fact,
this also there was a question
asked earlier, what about
suicide? You know what is, well,
I didn't answer we came up very
great. So what about suicide?
First of all, the past life
therapy. Evidence is that
suicide can become a habit like
anything else, if you have a
ticket, we need another
anonymous group. If you get if
you get overwhelmed, you get in
a situation where you just feel
like you can't deal with it
anymore. I'm going to end it.
Unknown: It is a coping it's a
lack of coping skill.
Chris Bache: What we find is
that people who commit suicide
in one lifetime sometimes have a
tendency to choose that as an
option in subsequent
Margaret Hiller: life. Chris,
can you hold the mic closer?
Chris Bache: Okay, there you go.
Thank you. It's I feel like I'm
smoking. It can become habit
forming. It can become an exit
strategy, but it doesn't really
solve things now, what are the
consequences of committing
suicide? I think the best wisdom
I've seen in all of the
literature is the consequence of
committing suicide is you have
to repeat the grade. If you
flunk the fifth grade, we don't
take you out torture you for the
rest of your life. We just
simply say you have to take the
fifth grade over again. So if
you choose, if you know, not
everybody commits suicide for,
quote, bad reasons, but if you
choose suicide of inability to
cope, the worst that happens, I
think, is that you have to come
back and maybe even more
demanding circumstances in order
to face the challenges that you
work in, to solve the issues
that you weren't able to solve
before. But I've mentioned
Robert Monroe, the Monroe
Institute, and he's the guy who
wrote three books. He's an out
of body kind of person. He.
Created the Monroe Institute in
favor of Virginia. He says, you
can check out anytime you want.
Anybody can leave anytime they
want, without cosmic judgment.
He feels very strongly about
this, but it doesn't mean that
there isn't, there aren't karmic
consequences, not in the sense
of judgment, but of habits that
can get established. And I don't
think suicide is a successful
coping strategy. It just
interrupts the process. Then you
got to get born again. You got
to go through diapers again just
to get yourself back into the
situation where you can face
whatever it was that took you
out the last time. So it's one
of those things where I don't
think it's the worst thing that
you can do, but it's not the
best thing either. So best to
work with what it is that you've
got yourself into until you can
get through it. But if you've
lost someone to suicide, they're
not outside of love. They're not
outside the universe. They go
home. They don't go to hell.
They go home. I'll tell you
another piece of research. There
was a guy who wanted to study
near death episodes of people
who attempted to commit suicide.
So he studied, this is an early
study. David Rosen, he studied
people who tried to commit
suicide by jumping off the
Golden Gate Bridge in San
Francisco. You jump off the
Golden Gate you got about a 97%
chance of dying, so it's a
pretty serious suicide attempt.
He found that they were eight
people who had jumped and
survived. He was able to track
down seven of them. He also
tracked down six people who had
jumped off the Golden Gate
Bridge, I guess the Bay Bridge.
I guess if the Golden Gate is
busy, here's what he found. He
found that every person who
attempted to commit suicide by
jumping off either of these
bridges, went instantly into
ecstatic Transcendence, state of
consciousness, they went
straight into the near death
episode, white light, totality
of consciousness, instantly and
not a single person ever tried
to commit suicide again, because
they learned the soul was not
killed when you kill the body,
nothing is solved by committing
suicide. It just delays the
inevitable. So they weren't
punished, but they never tried
to commit suicide again, because
they discovered that suicide is
an illogical action, because you
think you can solve the problem
by killing the body. You solve,
you do not solve the problem
like killing the body. I think
that's that work. I thought was
really I've heard
Unknown: one of those people
interview the lady, yeah, and
she said that she just was
grateful that she survived and
never tried again process
whatever her issues were, yeah,
Margaret Hiller: Chris, yes. Do
you and your perspective and
research? Do you feel like the
research is showing that our
prayers, our blessings, our
thoughts are impacting those
beloveds who did suicide or
impact those beloveds we know
have crossed over with huge
amounts of angst or fear our
prayers and thoughts impact them
in a
Chris Bache: positive way. Yes,
I think so. The community of
Heaven is a community that is in
rapport with the community of
Earth, and we, who are embodied
can communicate with and assist
those who have died. And in the
Monroe Institute, there's a
program you can they actually
train people how to go into a
state of consciousness where
they they literally kind of
leave their body and find people
who are stuck in the post mortem
state and actually assist them
and take them into the park. He
calls it the and once you're in
the park, then you'll be able to
get on and there. But a lot of
people, some people, not a lot,
a few people, when they die,
they don't know that they're
dead, or they're confused. They
just kind of disoriented. We
can, we can get to those people
and help them move beyond their
uncertainty and their fears. In
Tibetan Buddhism, which I
practice within, among other
things, there is a practice
called she troll, which is a
practice for the recently
departed. And you do the
practice precisely for someone
who is dead, in order to bring
to them the opportunity to turn
to move to their soul who might
otherwise get caught. My sister
works for hospice, and so when
she gets clients who are having
very good. Difficult death
processes. When she'll ask me to
do, she troll for them and and
so I do a lot of chi troll for
people I don't know. And it
often happens when I'm doing
this practice, so that I see
things, I just get visual
impressions. And so I always
really careful, because you
know, you don't, never really
know exactly the truth of what
it is you're saying. But I relay
them to her, and she relates
them to the client's wife,
mother, whatever. And I find
consistently, we find that what
I what I see, that what is seen
contains a core truth, which
identifies that it's real, that
this person is actually there.
They're wearing a particular
shirt, or they're sitting in a
particular chair, and it's the
real shirt, their favorite
shirt, or their real chair. And
you I have many times, help
people get into the clear space,
the diamond light space. And
this is a practice which has
been taught for over 1000 years.
So there's 1000s and 1000s of
beings as a matter of course,
think that they can help the
beings who have died to get
where they need to be in order
to make clear decisions. So I
very, very much believe that we
can do that. Yes, my
Unknown: husband died last year,
and I was having, I was having a
hard time, like I didn't feel
energy, but trying to block it
off, yeah, because I thought it
would go with her if I did that.
So I really thought it started
feel like I was going crazy a
little bit. So this very
intuitive person told me that he
was in a learning place and that
he couldn't process a lot while
he was alive because he had
autism, which no one knew about,
I mean, those days. So he was in
a burning place to process this
life, but he couldn't. And that
she thought, like she thought
his grandfather, or someone like
that was with him, someone who
loved him and helping him. And
what after she told me that all
of a sudden it just his energy.
Everything made sense. Yeah, and
and she said, Just be open to
it. Just open to his energy. And
I really felt then that my
relationship with him wasn't
over, and then I was actually
helping him while he was in that
learning place, like when I
would remember him, or feel his
energy very strongly, like I was
helping him to understand, yeah,
yeah.
Chris Bache: Thank you. Thank
you for sharing that. That's you
know, I don't remember the exact
percentage, 60, 70% of husbands
and wives whose spouse dies have
experience of being in contact
with them in some form or
another. I mean, it's a majority
experience that people have the
experience of the recently
departed, and that's the most
natural thing to in the world,
in a universe that I'm
describing here. Of course they
would want to come back and
touch base. Of course there
would be some rapport. And if
there is that rapport, then we
can help them.
Unknown: Yes. So, so her
husband, who she's speaking of,
was a very good friend of mine,
and it was so interesting when
he was very, very, very close to
death, so he had a hospice come
in. So this hospice woman,
because of there was so much
prayer in her prayer, and she
could feel so much prayer and so
much going on just prayer. I
mean, it was basically prayer
that she was feeling. Saw
Maureen and people with
Buddhists that we can so she saw
so much prayer, for lack of
better word, even on Randy's
dying moments, he was still able
to encourage somebody, this
hospice worker with with his
wife, even though, even though
He was ready to go here. He was
still here in spirit. And this
woman, this hospice woman, was
so encouraged by the family and
by the praise that she sought,
and by Randy's life, rather than
Randy's death. And. And we know
that to be so because she's come
back to his year memorial
service. She's come back to, I
think she came back twice, to
something we have. It was all
this incredible experience, even
though here, there was still so
much encouraging going on here,
prayer. Prayer. There was so
much prayer that was clearly
seen
Chris Bache: all this. I mean,
we understand that death is
weeping and hurting. We are left
behind, but for the soul who's
leaving, it's joy and
celebration. And the more we can
hold joy and celebration, where
we can hold the deep vision,
more we can support them in the
process that they're going
through. The worst thing is the
Weeping and Gnashing here to
really think that this is real,
that death is taking place,
termination, end point. This is
all there is. And that's what my
students are taught in
practically every course at the
university they take except
mine. You know, they're taught
biology, biology classes,
chemistry, all their courses
that death is the end doctors or
failures. If they if your
patients die, death is
graduation. Death is a great
release. Not this for permanent
release, but it's a great
release. Let me do a time check.
Okay, it's time to shift
categories. Are we ready to
shift? Yeah,
I hope you read we got two of
these in the bookstore. I hope
you read these books. These are
wonderful books. Did
Unknown: you bring
Chris Bache: it up for everybody
this workshop I'm working right
now on dark night, early on is
about psychedelic research, and
I'm working on a book which is
kind of the next book in this
series, and psychedelic research
is my area of specialty as a
philosopher. And so we said,
Okay, I said, How about if we do
this on the discussion of death
from the different perspectives,
and psychedelic work is part of
that for me, and if people are
okay with it, if we find that
people are comfortable, maybe
I'll come back next year and
we'll do an entire workshop on
psychedelics, because we have so
many misunderstandings and so
many fears about psychedelics,
and it's, I think it's so
important, I think represent a
before And after in
philosophical work, because it
just it changes the landscape.
So just a couple of things.
First, we've been doing this for
a long time, and these are three
books which I've just bring
here, just to point out that
psychedelics have been with
humanity for a very long time.
And I'm not going to talk about
these books. I just want to
mention them. The first book for
us, the visions, written by Alex
pallari Omega that he's one of
the founders of their two
psychedelic two Ayahuasca
churches in Brazil, Santo Daime
and vegetal. Ayahuasca is a very
powerful psychedelic which
results in combining two
particular plants. It's about
its usage goes back 1500 years.
It's integrated with
Christianity. You know, once the
Spaniards came and brought
Christianity, kind of, there's
an amalgam. And it's a very,
very powerful healing substance.
They are now Americans are doing
Ayahuasca, and there is a
community in Ashland who has
taken their case all the way to
the Supreme Court and won the
right to use Ayahuasca as not
Brazilians, as Caucasian
Americans in their community. So
when they bring the Ayahuasca
from Brazil, they're met at the
airport by a Department of Drug
Enforcement Agency and a
representative of the church.
It's coming into this country.
There is another Ayahuasca
community in Houston, which is
likewise won the right to be
doing Ayahuasca. The second book
is a book by Ralph Metzner on
Ayahuasca. It's an anthology
people's experiences so on and
so forth. And the third book is
also by Ralph Metzner. It's an
anthology on sacred mushrooms,
Psilocybin mushrooms, Native
Americans who've been using
mushrooms for years as a healing
ritual. That use Peyote, that
use Mescaline. This is nothing
new. So what I'm going to talk
about is not new. What I'm going
to talk about is the rediscovery
of this ancient healing modality
in contemporary scientific
context. So the person I'm going
to talk about is Stanislav Grof,
who is the foremost authority, I
think, today, on integrating
psychedelics into the
therapeutic process. He was
Czechoslovakian, born. He
started his work after
graduating from medical school.
First day after he graduated
from medical school, he did his
first LSD session. He is the
foremost authority on the
psychoactive effects of LSD and
integrating it into therapeutic
process. He's written about, I
think, 1516, books by now. Stan
is in his upper 70s. This book,
realms on the human unconscious
changed my life. It was
published right about the time I
finished graduate school. So
when I came out of graduate
school and I began work at
Youngstown State, it was only
then that I became aware of the
real significance of
psychedelics. I didn't do drugs
in high school, I didn't do
drugs in college. I did not do
well a little bit I didn't do
drugs in graduate school. Was
only when I was 29 years old
that I began to systematically
begin to work with psychedelics.
Now, in 1978 when I finished
graduate school, my government
had made psychedelics illegal.
It said in 1969 1970 there is no
value to these substances.
They're going to be scheduled as
we criminalize them. That put me
in a hard spot, because Stan had
just begun to publish. He had
already published hundreds of
articles. There were literally
3000 essays published on
psychedelics in the 60s and 70s,
tremendous therapeutic
potential. But no, it happened.
The 60s happened, and then
everything came crashing to a
stop in 1969 i i knew that
psychedelics were going to come
back eventually. I knew that
they were so important that our
culture was going to not abandon
them, that we would find our way
back to working with these very
powerful sacred medicines. But I
knew that by the time we did
that I'd be an old man, and I
was not willing to wait. So what
I did was I began to work with
psychedelics using Stan Grof
methodology, and I'll describe
that methodology in a second,
but that meant going
underground. And there are I
became part of a community of
people who are working
conscientiously, therapeutically
and philosophically with
psychedelics, not like Timothy
Leary, not like Ram Dass, not
like Richard Albert Ram Dass in
his previous reincarnation at
Harvard, but doing it in a
different kind of modality. But
that meant going underground,
and I'm now beginning to write
up that work between 1979 and
1999 I did 73 high dose LSD
sessions, massive quantities of
LSD. Probably the more LSD than
just about anybody you know. But
I don't look that crazy.
Margaret Hiller: You're not
talking about street drugs.
You're talking about rubber LSD,
Chris Bache: I'm talking about
pure pharmaceutical grade. LSD,
what you get on the street, very
different animal. And I'm not
talking about tripping. I mean,
I've read all the literature on
psychedelics, and if you want to
see all the things that went
wrong in the 60s, you can read a
book called storming heaven,
which is a history of
psychedelics in the 60s. There's
another book called tripping,
where people share their
experiences of tripping. I'm not
talking about tripping. What's
the difference between the
therapeutic use of psychedelics
and tripping? First of all, let
me just restrict myself to
those. Yeah, go ahead.
Unknown: I really hate to do
this, right? I didn't ask two
questions I had about the
previous really regret. They'll
tie into this. But um, okay,
well, people are the one we're
at, that jumping off place and
that clarity that, if you know
or suicide are checking out that
that realization that we can't
leave, we can get rid of the
body. I had that experience. It
was very powerful. It was just
one of the most powerful
experiences I've ever had. And
it was so clear that I would
just have to start over, be
stuck there just was not an
interesting place. And it never
cost my money, and in a real
way, yeah, I've also. Had an
experience, kind of induced by
some of this stuff and other
things, where there was no way I
could see the things I was
seeing with my eyes, and I was
way too far away, but I could
normally hear people, and felt
like I was leaving and torn in
that, in that state of absolute
bliss, but also not done here,
and knowing that I wasn't done
here, but what I thought was a
hallucination over time, after
connecting with people that were
within a few short distance in
that place where everything I
heard them say was what they
were saying, the direction they
were standing, facing what they
were everything they were doing
and saying they told me was
real. I thought it was all. I
thought it was hallucination,
but these were all real
experiences. Yeah, and the
questions of this forgiveness.
So the other things said that,
yeah, when we're you, I got
really confused when I first got
here, because I just have a
strong releases and some that I
can't really understand. But the
one, this illusion of
separateness, I believe that
we're all interconnected, but I
don't comprehend it in words and
but also the solution of time
and space. Do you believe? Do
you believe we talk about these
different spaces, that we go
through different transitions,
that we can access any time in
space, if we're in tune, it's
tricky.
Chris Bache: Einstein taught us
that the universe we live in is
a time space. It's a four
dimensional universe, right?
Three dimensions of space and
one dimension of time. And so
time and space is a Unified
Fabric. And we have reasons to
think that there are parts of
the universe which are traveling
faster than light, and therefore
they they are not inhibited by
time the way we are in the large
size of things. If you are able
to enter into a state of
consciousness in which you move
beyond space as we know it, part
of that is also moving beyond
time as we know it, and so I do.
I know from personal experience
that it is possible to move into
trans, what psychologists call
trans temporal experience, or to
move in a different temporal
reality, to move outside time
and space as we ordinarily think
of it. But it's not like there's
time and then no time, there may
permeability, there's a
permeability, and there may be
variations on the time space
continuum. So that you can move
into states of awareness where
1000 years will pass in five
seconds. You're in a temporally
dilated state. You can move into
100,000 million year time
landscapes. These are, this is
just the way time exists in
those variables. And you can
move completely outside time and
space reality altogether, and go
into reality which is not time
limited at all. So I think that
there are variations on this
process.
Unknown: And when we tap into
those things where you're
talking about, you know, what
shirt someone was wearing, or
examples like that, which I've
experienced. And like I said, I
thought they're hallucination.
You think that's a amplified
clarity just hyper senses.
Chris Bache: It's not that there
are not hallucinations, which is
to see something which isn't
real, but there are true,
legitimate visions where you see
things which are real, but are
are not restricted by time,
space, reality the way we
eventually think of it.
Traditionally, we say all of its
hallucinations, but there are
people who have experiences, and
people who have near death
experiences, who go into the
future, and that future happens
the way they saw it, enough that
we know that it is possible to
have vision, to have experiences
of future reality, even in
times, in this time and space
moment. So we know that it's
possible. Then after that, we
have to go to the particulars.
Margaret Hiller: Well, also what
he's talking about, our
consciousness can be in more
than one place at a time. So our
consciousness can be expansive
enough that we can pick up on a
conversation or see things, hear
things, sense things where our
body isn't over there, but our
our sense, our spiritual
sensing, I guess, is the best
term that's coming down we can
where we have that available
Chris Bache: to us. A woman's
playing golf and a particular
tea at a particular time,
suddenly she has an overwhelming
sense that one of her children
is in trouble. It, and she plays
out the golf game, and she goes
home, and she gets a phone call
as soon as she gets inside, and
it turns out her son had just
had a car accident exactly at
the minute when she felt it at
that particular time on the golf
course. So part of her is
obviously capable of sensing
beyond her physical senses. And
we have lots of cases like that.
What's the difference between
tripping and serious psychedelic
work? First of all, and of
course, there are many
psychedelics. I mean, you have
to take them individually. LSD,
Psilocybin, MDMA, MDT, DMT. So I
don't want to oversimplify, but
basically what we mean when we
classify a substance as a
psychedelic. And I never use the
word hallucinogen, because
that's a pejorative materialist
description, because the
hallucination is when you see
something which isn't there, but
that's to make a metaphysical
judgment, and I want to use that
category. Some people call it
entheogenous, that which awakens
the divine within. That's okay.
If you have a pretty broad
definition of God, I prefer the
term psychedelic mind opener,
mind expander. What these
substances do is they
hypersensitize consciousness.
They amplify consciousness. They
do not give you a particular
experience. They do not cause
you to see two people, 100
people on a psychedelic do not
have the same experience. They
hyper amplify your
consciousness. And then what
happens is a function of
consciousness itself, not a
function of the drug. It's a
function of the aroused state of
consciousness. Usually when
people take psychedelics,
they're usually a recreation
taking in recreation. They want
to, kind of have fun, have a
party, and they use this hyper
stimulated state, and they stay
in dialog in the physical world,
and the physical senses come in.
Their hypersensitive
consciousness kind of rises up.
They get a swirling mishmash of
hallucinations and trails and
spins. And they kind of have
some fun. Go to a party. The
music is so intense and and the
insights are sort of so
interesting. And when it's all
over, nothing has changed.
They've just kind of entertained
themselves for a few hours. The
Native Americans are not
interested in tripping. They
were only interested in serious,
sacred medicine work. And the
difference is this, when you
work in a therapeutic modality,
first of all, you isolate
yourself from the physical
world. In the old days, they
would climb into a Kiva. You
know what a Kiva is an
underground cave, underground
hole in the ground, where they
go down a ladder, and then
you're sitting around the fire.
You pull up the ladder, you're
there till dawn. So you in
contemporary context, you're
lying down and you're wearing
eye shades. You're not in any
contact with the physical world,
so that whatever you experience,
you know what's coming from you.
That's kind of important. And
then you're listening to very
carefully selected music. And we
if psychedelic has a particular
time curve, we know if you're
taking LSD, it's going to have
an acceleration. It's going to
impact within about total 45
minutes. You're going to be on a
peak that's going to last maybe
four or five hours. It's going
to have a tail that's going to
last another three or four
hours. And we know that we can
choose music that will support
what happens in each of those
stages. So there's essays and
works which have been written on
the kind of music you want to
help you break through and to
confront what you need to
confront, and then slowly
integrate and then slowly come
back and return. It's a
complicated process, but the
basic vision is this, when you
hyper stipulate your
consciousness, what starts to
happen is that your
consciousness starts to purify
itself. It starts to heal
itself. And in order to heal
itself, it has to bring forward
what needs healing. So it has to
bring forward all the pain. It
has to bring forward anything
which is unfinished business,
and sometimes from this life,
sometimes from other lifetimes.
It brings forward physical
trauma, when you had whooping
cough, when you were five years
old, and you almost died, and
the physical memory of that is
still in your mind.
It brings forward all the
existential questions. It brings
forth all the deep, deep
philosophical questions. It
brings forward all the
uncertainty we have about
whether life is meaningful,
whether there is any logic to
the process. And basically what
happens is, as the system begins
to detoxify itself, you come to
Christ. Crisis points. And most
people, when they confront these
crisis points, the same thing to
do is kind of go away. You do
not want to go into the pain.
You want to get away from the
pain. But in therapy, when
you're working therapeutically
or as a sacred medicine, you
learn to go into the pain. You
learn to go deeper and deeper
into what it is. It's causing
you problems. If you learn to go
into the pain, the pain becomes
your ally, and you suffer. You
suffer terribly. You suffer
physically. There's tremendous
physical pain involved, and you
suffer psychologically, and you
suffer existentially and
spiritually. But if you navigate
that crisis skillfully, if you,
if you have a good sitter, by
the way, you never, ever want to
do this by yourself. I mean,
it's just it's not safe. You
need somebody there who's going
to control the outer world. You
need somebody who's going to be
your lifeline. If you navigate
that confrontation successfully,
the pattern is you reach a
crisis point. You reach a
breakthrough point, and you have
to be comfortable losing
control. Because you lose
control, your mind is
functioning 100 times more power
than it normally functions. You
lose control, and you go through
some type of death process. You
go through some type of absolute
loss of your life as you know
it, you die. And the miracle is,
after you're completely dead,
you wake up in a different
reality, in a different world,
as a different kind of being
than you were going into it.
There have been people who have
done psychedelics, heavy
psychedelics, for 100 150 times
that have never, ever gone
through this process. It's not
easy, it's not fun, it's
excruciatingly difficult work.
And all the Native American
traditions know this. The
Ayahuasca traditions know this.
The Eleusinian Mysteries know
this. In ancient Greece, at
Plato Aristotle Bardo as a
philosopher, when I read Stan's
work, I knew that this was a
methodology that allowed us to
actually explore the
consciousness of the universe in
a way that
there are other traditions,
there are other ways to explore
the universe. I mean, there are
people who withdraw into the
mountains for decades and
decades of isolation and
meditation to explore the
universe. The Kalahari Bushmen
explore the universe through
trance dancing. Some people
explore by nearly dying. It's a
very effective way. It's kind of
difficult going through sacred
medicine, work is simply a
different modality of doing what
human beings have always done,
and that is to explore the world
that we live in. And very
quickly, you find out that your
individual ego is just a shell.
It's just a shell that you can
you can dissolve. You can pop
it. It's a balloon that just
pops. And when you pop it, you
move into a deeper state of
consciousness where you
literally are a different life
form. You're not simply a human
being, but you can kind of move
into a state in which you
literally become humanity
itself. You can move into merger
with the collective psyche of
the human species, and the
purification continues at that
level. You don't you go through
the Death-Rebirth process again
in subsequent sessions, but now,
no longer as an individual, but
now as humanity, you go through
the cycle of Death-Rebirth, I've
learned is a cycle that repeats
itself over and over again, the
deeper and deeper you go along
the way, when you break through
into this deeper reality. That's
why I feel deep kinship with
Eben Alexander and near his
episode people, because they're
talking about things that I know
from personal experience. You
can go through the death process
before you actually die
physically, and then, in many
ways, the spiritual death
process is much worse than the
physical death process, because
when you go through the physical
process of dying. Part of you
knows that the psyche is okay,
because you've been through this
before. The psyche is going to
not going to be killed by the
body dying. But if you go
through a spiritual death
process, you're going through a
process which is actually deeper
than physical dying, because
that nucleus which transfers
intact. After the death of the
body, it is that Numinous which
is itself dying in this process.
Why would you do something as
stupid as that? Why would you go
into that much suffering in
order? And the answer is, well,
I was trained as a philosopher.
I wanted to know what the
structure of the universe was. I
wanted to explore whether there
was any meaningful tapestry. I
mean, I wanted to cross the
ocean. I wanted to see what was
there. And you can, you can
explore what's there. You can
come to have first hand personal
experience of the larger cosmic
we are part of and it's not for
everybody. It's not, certainly
not for I don't advise it for a
lot of people. You don't need to
do it, but you can do it. And if
you do it, one of the things
that happens is you lose your
fear of death, absolutely, for
the same reason that here this
episode of people lose their
fear of death, because you know
experientially that you are a
being who cannot die. It's
impossible for you to die as a
spiritual being. Your physical
being can die. Your personality
can die. But that germ you were
talking about, the underlying
essence that cannot die. It can
only be liberated in deeper,
deeper manifestation. So if you
want to look well, this all the
books I've shown you are kind of
pretty easy reading. This is not
a difficult book to read. This
is first book. But if you're in
terms of death, these books are
what I consider the most
important of Stan's many books
focused on the issue of death.
Now the first one, and the
reason these look all kind of
rumpled is because these are my
books. I snapped them on the
scanner and took a picture of
them. LSD therapy. Psychotherapy
is a manual that was written in
1980 a manual written for
doctors and nurses and
psychologists on how to do LSD
psychotherapy. It's a nuts and
bolts methodology. He wrote this
after LSD was illegal, and he
wrote it for two reasons. One,
he knew people were doing this
work anyway, underground. And
two, he knew that we would get
back to it. We would bring it
back within our repertoire of
scientific investigation, and it
was important to document and
Stan. By this time, had over
5000 sessions with LSD, sessions
with with his clients. He had
been doing this work for 20
years before it was illegal, and
he wanted to bring it down to
document. This is a technical
manual on how to run LSD
sessions, counter indication,
screening, indications. How do
you manage it? The difference
between low dose therapy and
high dose therapy very
different. Low dose therapy is
kind of peeling the onion by
layer by layer. High Dose
therapy is like blowing through
the layers very quickly, going
right through the layers. It's a
very different kind of project.
He did logos therapy and
Czechoslovakia, taking people
into 100 sessions, layer by
layer, layer by layer, resolving
it, layer by layer, gave them a
very detailed map. When he came
to Spring Grove Hospital,
Baltimore, Maryland. They
started a new research project
working with terminally ill
patients, cancer patients, they
were terminally ill. It was not
any attempt to try to heal them.
What they were trying to do was
prepare them for dying. And so
they did a maximum of three
sessions, high dose. Basically,
they were experimenting with
triggering a Near-Death
Experience deliberately under
controlled circumstances. And
they succeeded. They succeeded.
Tell us how, how? Yeah.
Margaret Hiller: I mean, what
did people report? I mean, was
the anxiety about death so
diminished that it was
completely gone? Or how? Give us
a report.
Chris Bache: Well, there's he
wrote. He co wrote a book with
his then wife, Joan Halifax was
an anthropologist who's now a
Zen Roshi called a human
encounter with death. If you
wanted to see the actual
details, go to that book, a
human encounter with death. What
they were found that we can if
you take a very, very high dose
of LSD and you contain it, you
compress it, you go through lots
of layers. You go through a lot
of psychodynamic layers. But you
can you go through a
Death-Rebirth process that
basically projects you into a
state of consciousness, which is
the consciousness that. You move
into when you die. From that
perspective, you can, you can
awaken the awareness that we saw
in near death episode. People
said I was remembering. How
could I have forgotten this? I
was remembering. Well, that's
what happens in these sessions.
People remember who they are.
They remember the deeper truth
some people, one person was a
very, very modest he was a
janitor, a very modest
intellectual. And he was
Catholic, very traditional
Catholic. And he had a very,
very detailed encounter with
reincarnation, and he came back.
He was all embarrassed. He
really didn't know what to do,
because he saw the truth of
reincarnation in his sessions,
and he had integrate that into
his Catholicism.
Unknown: Yeah, okay, so what I'm
hearing is okay, so I don't have
the experience I never, for lack
of a better word, tripped, but I
was very, very much in that
realm. Many, many people around
me in that time and everything
you're saying, everything you're
saying, sound exactly what I've
personally witnessed in people.
Of course, it was underground.
Yes, underground. So I'm not
understanding the difference.
And I don't want to get caught
up here, just on the words, but
what you're saying, I have, I've
seen that happen with people,
not, you know, in a not in the
climate that you're talking
about, but
in, yeah, outside of that, yeah,
Chris Bache: you know, if you,
if you take a psychedelic, if
you take, Let's, let's stay with
LSD from the end,
you do if you stay in touch with
the world. You know, people talk
about a bad trip. That was bad
ass, you know, that was a bad
trip. I don't ever want to go
back there again. But in
therapy, a bad trip is a good
trip. Yeah? Well, in the street,
a bad trip is just a bad trip.
It's something you want to
avoid. You do not want to go
into it. What you learn in
therapy is a bad trip means your
system is purifying itself, and
you want to, you want to purge
those poisons, and you want to
go deeper into that, because
when you purge those poisons,
your system is going to move
into a deeper experience of
reality. You There are lots of
times, and if you read the
literature like this book
tripping, you'll see people have
all sorts of glimpses into
interconnectivity and glimpses
into and they'll have, you know,
various psychic experiences
where they can merge with the
mind of people around them, or
things like this. The difference
is one of degree and one of
clarity and one of lasting
impact. It's the degree clarity
and lasting impact.
Unknown: So if you did ask it,
and you changed your whole life,
you know reason to ask it when
sand those trucks got hijacked,
and that was like the ultimate
aspect, because it was
pharmaceutical acid, and it was
my 60s, and it was exactly like
what you're talking about. I
mean, I you, one of the things
Steven Job said was one of the
better choices he made when he
was in college was to do acid.
You know, I see that as having
lasting impact with him. I mean,
a lot, somebody said you
wouldn't have your iPad. Was it
for acid? Definitely wouldn't
have the music on it, you know.
So I've been around people in
all realms of drug use, people
that are just screwing around
and want to have a good time.
And the stuff that passed for
LSD for some recent decades
which bore no resemblance, I
remember as LSD,
Chris Bache: the Discover of DNA
now kind of as admitted to see
the critical breakthrough came
through when he was on LSD and
Rupert Sheldrake and this
important Morphic field theory
was LSD that gave you that
breaks,
Margaret Hiller: and Alex Gray,
so
Unknown: we may not have been
doing it in a clinical setting,
but you can't just write off all
the things that came from that
because they were entirely life
changing. I don't
Chris Bache: mean write it off
or diminish it. I certainly
don't. And they are life
changing, and they were culture
changing. They gave us a
different culture. And yet, at
the same time, there is a
difference. Because if you read,
for example, I think the best
history of the 60s is storming
heaven, and I can't remember the
author's name, it's a wonderful
book. But what happened is a lot
of that. Catalytic energy. It
washed through us, but it didn't
take root. It didn't hold it
kind of it changed lives, but it
didn't change our culture the
way we hoped it would. It just
washed through and what I hope
is that when we come back into
it, in this next wave, we can
get a leverage that will help us
change the fundamental culture,
that will help us change the
understanding
Margaret Hiller: Chris, as you,
as you know you and I talked
about this, my hesitation even
having this segment in the
workshop, because there's still
so much misunderstanding about
psychedelic research. So there's
a cultural prejudice about still
so, but the whole idea that
these substances are naturally
occurring and have been used for
1000s of years for expanding
consciousness, that there's
there has to be some good reason
why these substances were a part
of our human experience. And
what I'm really interested in is
looking at how many people, now
current day who are returning to
this as the sacred medicine
you're talking about. It hasn't
always been used as sacred as we
know. We can take anything and
make it sacred or unsacred. It's
certainly been used in unsacred
ways, but the sacred ceremonial
use to expand our consciousness.
This is what I'm and I'm looking
at a lot of the I know medical
doctors who actually do
Ayahuasca with their patients a
week or so before they do major
surgery. You know, they're doing
it as sacred medicine, and
that's really what I'm
interested in, and I'm
personally, I'm encouraged that
more people in the medical field
are catching hold of sacred
medicine, versus medicine that's
killing us. We're being killed
by, quote, medicine. So if
there's another way to use
sacred medicine, especially with
treating depression and anxiety
fear,
Chris Bache: Johns Hopkins is
doing a research project.
They've already published out
that they're continuing on the
use of Psilocybin in depression.
The use of Psilocybin to treat
post traumatic stress syndrome
and DNA is being used with
returning vets to treat post
traumatic stress syndrome, so
we're beginning to bring it back
into a therapeutic modality. IPO
gain is an African psychedelic
which has extra ordinary
capacity to interrupt addiction,
even cocaine and heroin
addiction, which, as you know,
is the most powerful. The one
gets a grip on the soul and it's
hard to let go. IPO gain can
produce a window of
detoxification of about two
months that will allow you to
then intervene, follow up with
interventions of conventional
therapeutic interventions. So we
have a whole new kind of
generation of young researchers
who are beginning to use the
sacred medicines for healing.
Now, personally, I'm not a
psychologist, and I'm not
interested. I'm not my project
is not healing. Stan is a
psychiatrist. His project is
healing. He's been all over the
world, and he's developed non
drug modalities for entering
into these states. You know, I
should mention No, he was always
doing certain certified
protocols, government sanctioned
protocols. And when LSD was no
longer legal, he and his wife
developed a non drug protocol
for entering into these states
called Holotropic Breathwork, so
that there are other modalities
for entering into these states.
I was a philosopher. I was kind
of like Aldous Huxley, you
mentioned. I'm interested in
cosmology. I'm interested in in
the structure of the universe,
in that's a different project
than healing. But if we can get
the sacred medicines back into
the repertoire of healers, then
underneath healing the
personality, and underneath
healing the heart, there is
healing the soul. And the only
way to heal the soul is to
connect with the essence of
life, the essence of the soul
itself. And when you connect,
when you take it the healing
down to the. That level, the
only way to heal the soul is to
connect with the universe and to
enter into communion with the
universe itself. And that is the
classic work of Mystics and
Saints. And you know, lifelong
meditators, to me, psychedelics,
they're not they're not a
shortcut,
but what they are is an
intensifier of spiritual
process. You can accelerate it.
Now, I wouldn't do what I did
again. I mean, I I chose to work
with very high doses. I did
psychedelic work for 73
sessions, and this is wear and
tear the customer. I wouldn't
take that aggressive an approach
now, now that I know what I
know, I would take a much
genitalr path into it, having
said that I wouldn't trade the
tentative name I'm working with
on this book. You know, you'll
Chene, maybe, but right now. I'm
calling it stealing diamonds
from heaven, because imagine you
could have a near death episode
like we just touched on you read
in some of these books, imagine
if you could have that
experience 40 times. That's what
we're looking at. What if we
could, not only just a few
handfuls of individuals, what if
we could take 1000 individuals
and take them into this
initiatory process 100 times and
gather all of their experiences
and integrate them into a
visual, a picture of the
structure of the universe.
That's what I think wrong. We're
right on the cusp of doing we're
on the edge of being able to do
that work in the traditions that
work with sacred medicines. You
know what they say? They say
these medicines were given to us
by the sacred, because the
sacred knew when we incarnated
we were going to forget. And so
the sacred medicines are about
remembering. They're about
waking us up and helping us
remember what we forgot when we
incarnated. And what are we
trying to remember? We're trying
to remember who we are, what we
are, what the purpose of life
is, what is our connection to
each other. We're trying to
remember the fundamental truths
of life. When you remember, then
just along the side death
disappears. There's not an
anxiety around death. The same
insights that emerge near death
episode work emerge in sacred
medicine, work you just that is
not a problem.
Audience 3: Yeah, Chris, I write
the legal form across 10 times.
Yeah. And, and
what you're talking about right
now is I had an experience
there, but I never had in my
life. And I was transforming it.
I don't see the world, you know.
I lost all sensation on my body.
I was flying around, out in
space. I was hearing a lot of
booming voices saying, where I
am with God and, you know? And I
felt totally, totally bliss. I
did not want to come back, and
the next thing I knew is the
facilitator opened my eyes, and
she said, Are you all right? But
that that was an absolutely
tremendous experience like that.
I can't it's, it's like, anybody
who goes for any of the
experiences, you can say words,
there's no language to describe
that. It's an experience that I
had, and there's been none in
life,
Chris Bache: in a wedding. The
psychedelic aspect is a red
herring. It's like, it's not
about psychedelics. It's
Holotropic Breathwork. You know
how they do it?
Hyperventilation, internal body
work, music and hyperventilation
for a couple of hours at a time.
It's psychedelics. It's just a
method. It's not what we're
looking at is the Release
Potential of consciousness,
nature, mind itself, and that's
important, and you can you can
release that power by nearly
dying. You can release that
power with hypnosis, or you can
release it through psychedelics
or meditation. Meditation. My,
my first wife, whom I love
dearly. She was my sitter for
all of my work. For 20 years,
she was my sitter. She's a
clinical psychologist. She never
did a single session herself.
She's one of the most she's very
spiritually oriented person. Her
path is meditation. She's
completed her. Three year soul
meditation retreat to the
Tibetan Buddhist tradition.
She's a natural meditator. She
never did a psychedelic session,
but she was my she was my
lifeline during all of my
psychedelic sessions. And it was
only after doing about 15 years
of this work that I began to
understand her. It's not about
psychedelics, it's about
different methods for working
with consciousness. We're coming
to the end of our time. Let me
just mention. The cosmic game
was written four books after LSD
psychotherapy. Stan wrote
several books about for written
for clinicians, written in the
clinical methodology, looking
for all the indications, and so
on, so forth. Eventually, he
wrote a book which is about the
cosmic logical implications of
this work, the model of the
universe that emerges from deep,
psychedelic work. And that's
this book, The cosmic game. It's
a wonderful, wonderful book. And
then later, he wrote this last
book, the ultimate journey,
which is specifically the
ultimate journey, is death. And
so he's looking it's a masterful
scholarly work, but also
integrated with his own personal
experiences and other
psychedelic voyagers
experiences, exploring the
phenomenon of death from that
perspective. So it's just, it's
the straight on implications of
psychedelic work for the
experience of dying. And then I
just mentioned one last piece.
Oh, this is dark night, early
dawn. All of my work basically
situated within Stan Grof
tradition. This is my first book
on psychedelic work, and so I
incorporate, I think if you're
going to do philosophy in this
genre, you have to reveal the
experiences that are the
foundation of your thinking. All
philosophical reflection assumes
a shared experience. If I give
an indication, a counter example
in an argument, I'm assuming
that we have a certain body of
experience, and so if I give an
example, you'll understand what
I'm talking about. But most
people don't have advanced
psychedelic experience. So if
you're going to present a
philosophical argument based
upon experience, you have to be
willing to put your experiences
on the table and say, these are
not perfect. These are
incomplete. Tell me where I went
wrong, but these are the
experiences that I'm using to
draw these conclusions. And so I
integrate my own psychedelic
experiences in this book, I put
them on the table, and I
integrate it in a discussion
with other people's exploration
and using different
methodologies, this way of doing
philosophy is a new way of doing
philosophy. Here we temporarily
lose contact with the physical
world. We go into a non ordinary
state. We have a set of
experiences. We come back and
write them down, and then we
analyze them. I've spent now 14
years analyzing 20 years worth
of psychedelic experience, and
it's only now that I'm really
beginning to write the whole
story. It's not enough to have
an exotic experience. You have
to understand it. You have to
think about it. You have to plug
it into the literature. You have
to think about the you have to
plug it into an intellectual
landscape in order to extract
its philosophical value along
the way. I'll just, I'll end
with just one experience, small
experience, just along I was
being
taken out into what I call deep
time, out in a deep time, into
the opportunity to see where
humanity is being taken into,
into the future, human time into
that world. So we're on a on a
scale of hundreds of 1000s of
years, and I was going all of a
sudden, everything expanded real
quickly. All of a sudden is just
going pop, everything pop. And I
said, what happened? And the
Intel, the voice I was, the
intelligence I was with, said,
Oh, we just, we passed your
death. It's like I was going
forward in time, and I passed
when I would die. And when you
pass your death, you don't have
the glue that holds you in a
particular configuration. You
just expand in that larger
domain. I've gone in and out of
that space so many times that
it's kind of become more
comfortable there, and that's
why I love the near death
episode research. The difference
with the near death episode
research and this type of
research is this, when most near
death episode people only have
one shot at that reality. A few
of them have had two or three
near death episodes, but mostly
you get one shot. Up, you get an
intense experience, but you
don't always see the full
landscape, because you get a
quick it's like seeing a
landscape in Arizona at night
and you got a flash of lightning
that shows you the landscape.
And you see it all, but you
don't see it all. But if you
could go back 4050 times, then
you have a much deeper
perception of that reality.
Also, because you go through
many death and rebirth, you go
deeper and deeper into reality,
deeper into the cosmic itself,
and you get a more complete
portrait of what's real. It's
not about psychedelics. It's
about the nature of mind. It's
about exploring the nature of
the mind of the universe. And
along the way, along with all
the other work, we're looking at
death. What is death? Death is
your best friend. Death is you
know, absolutely nothing to be
afraid of. I can't tell you how
much I look forward to not
that's the last thing I want to
be I want to avoid. So I have a
I have an agreement with Jesus,
don't you come for me. I'm gone.
I'm not fighting this. This is,
you know, don't come for me
until you're ready for us to
wrap this thing up. Thanks very
much. So, Chris, I know that
there
Margaret Hiller: will be a group
here who will always love you to
come back. And everybody knows
that Chris is our guest speaker
in the morning at 11am service.
And also, we have a surprise
guest musician, singer from
agape, international choir and
the Center in Santa Monica. So
she just happens to be passing
through and has family in
Georgetown, so she's coming to
us tomorrow. We have the divine
duo. Thank you, everybody coming
Unknown: Back. Batteries.
So I To be off check and yeah,
take a walk
on the beach. Yeah, that was
great. So.