Unknown: You as I me. I can See
that I Forgot to be Me. No man
I know that life is meant for
Living free, yay,
look inside and Find a place
Your I am
Margaret Hiller: Jennifer,
please me and Y'all, she's
moving back to the area. You
so welcome back. Welcome back to
your neighborhood. We want to
welcome everybody here today, so
we are going to now stand again
and sing, Rise up, you. And
follow. Oh, Oh, I have a church
now First order of business
after rise. Up is to turn off
your cell phone. Please. Cell
phones interfere with our sound
system, and we're already having
to deal with two poles that
interfere with the sound system.
So let's make it a little kinder
and turn off our cell phone.
Okay, let's all take a deep
breath, and if it feels
comfortable for you, close your
eyes and let's allow ourselves
to be fully present in this
place that has been dedicated
for A very long time to opening
hearts, awakening minds. It's
been dedicated for a long, long
time to take us into the core of
our being, where we know our
magnificence. We know that we
are the light of the world,
where we can access our joy, our
peace, our wisdom, our
creativity, and our faith and
our strength and our commitment
to keep growing, keep deepening,
keep awakening. So we give
thanks for this place, all those
who came before us, those who
had the vision to establish such
a movement called Unity. So
today, we once again open our
hearts and minds to feel our
unity, our oneness with all of
life, all of humankind, with the
one presence known by many
names. The service is turned
over to spirit. And so it is,
and so we let it be okay. Here
we are. We're now going to do
together the Lord's Prayer,
translated from the Aramaic
language of Jesus, all together,
Please, father, mother, birther
and the breath of all create a
space inside of us and fill it
with your presence. Let oneness
now prevail. Your one desire
then flows through ours as
energy fills all forms, Give us
this day our physical and
spiritual nourishment and
untangle the knots of error
behind us. As we release others,
do not let appearances make us
forgetful of the source, but
free us to act appropriately.
From age to age through you flow
the glorious harmonies of life.
May these words be verbal
statements through which our
future grows. Let's take a deep
breath every Sunday when we
gather together like this and we
say these words, I hope you can
feel the power, the incredible
presence of spirit that happens
within us and around us when we
say this in a conscious way, not
wrote, not like just ho hum, but
really connecting with the
words. It's a powerful thing.
Okay, for all of you who I don't
know yet, and maybe you don't
know me yet, my name is Margaret
Miller. I'm privileged to serve
as spiritual leader here at
unity. And I'd also like to
introduce our morning team. It
takes a village to have a church
service. Our ushers this morning
are Carl O'Brien and Terry de
Mario. They're back there on the
bench. And our readers and
ushers on video this morning is
funny on Healy. Sound is Melody.
And our music team Ryan on
saxophone, you have the chair
taking the rest after that. So
and our singers this morning are
Marley. And Ann and Lori and
Mary, Lou Paula patty and Dave
back there is Ozzy His flute and
harmonica. Bill on the piano,
Kevin on his guitar, Dan on
drums, Tom on drums. And then
that doesn't speak to your board
of directors. Charles staff
administrator, all the people,
the volunteers, many, many
people that it takes to create
this experience. So okay, we're
going to sing another song.
Lily's going to help us with
this one too. Want to tell you a
little bit about Lily. Russ.
Lily is originally from
Georgetown, South Carolina.
She's going
to be doing that West Coast
thing that a lot of people here
did at one time or another, and
she sounds like she's going to
be making her way back home. So
we're glad about that. And she
thinks she performs all over the
place, doing plays and special
events. And you also are with
the agave International,
Unknown: agape international
spiritual center. But I'm not in
the choir, but I've
Margaret Hiller: been sitting
there, and I speak there, and a
lot of y'all know agape from
Michael Beckwith work and Ricky
buyers work, so welcome. Okay,
y'all, we are going to sing
another song. When we do, we're
going to pass the duo Kansas is
not our regular offering. This
is for your loose change, and it
goes to help folks in our
community who need a little
extra support from time to time.
And we are going to stand when
you're ready, and we're going to
sing a song that we used to sing
in the Pentecostal and
charismatic church, and my other
one peace like a river.
Unknown: I have peace by river
in My soul.
Speaker 3: I've Got joy.
Mountain
life, I'm like the ocean in my
soul. Oh,
Margaret Hiller: this morning,
so I would like to invite all
the children tall and less tall
up here. Chris, would you hold
my head? Yeah, I'm coming ready
to take notes. I'm taking notes.
Hey, everybody.
I want to know everybody's name.
There's only one person up here
whose name I know right now, and
that's Elijah. And is it Caleb
and is it Tristan? Yes, wow.
Okay, so Caleb and Tristan and
Elijah, sorry, and
our teachers this morning are
Miss pan and Miss Rachel. Hey,
Rachel, so there is a very
special holiday coming up.
Anybody know where it is
Thanksgiving?
Speaker 3: What happens on
Thanksgiving? And it's all about
love, that's what I want. Ah.
Oh, you
Margaret Hiller: know, we have a
guest speaker today, but if we
didn't, Thanksgiving is all
about love. I'm so glad. And is
it a time when we give thanks?
What if? What do we give thanks
for?
What is included, Caleb and
everything? What do you think?
What what do we have to be
grateful for? Someone up closer
if you want to say something in
the microphone. We want to hear
it now. What do we have to be
grateful
for? What about your new hobby?
What about being able to go to
school? Is there something
that's in the world you can't go
to
school? Do we give thanks for
living near the beach? Yes, you
know what I give thanks for? I
give thanks for my fig trees and
the birds that come to my bird
feeders,
Speaker 3: and I do things like
life and for God,
Margaret Hiller: so one of The
things that we are here very,
very grateful for is that you,
you guys, come here to remind us
that we are the light of the
world, to remind us that you
have a lot to teach us and
remind us of we're really glad
that you're here. That's one of
the biggest things I'm grateful
for today, that all of you are
here because each one of us have
a part in telling the wonderful
story of our human family,
waking up and realizing that we
really can be love and kindness
in the world. We can make a
world that works for everybody.
That's what we learn about when
we come here, and you're a part
of that. So let's all stand
we're going to give thanks for
you. I'm doing our blessing, and
it is going to be up on the
screen, and I'm going to ask you
to turn towards all these people
out here and put through with
your hands. Remember love and
blessing comes through our
hands, our words, our eyes, our
presence. So you're going to
bless all of them out there, and
they're going to bless you right
back. Okay. We love
Speaker 3: you, we bless you, we
appreciate you, we behold Christ
in
Unknown: you, and we love you
just the way you are.
Margaret Hiller: Okay. No, we've
got just a few announcements to
begin with right now, and that
is, our meditation class is
fabulous. I am so grateful to be
a part of this community and
this kind of meditation class.
So it will continue through
December 10 and our
contemplative service is
Wednesday night at 530 and then
we continue on into the peace
chapel for the oneness blessing.
And tonight, my sister Pam and I
are going to be going to this
I'll be one of the speakers, and
any of you are welcome to go.
It's the day of remembrance from
Memorial for people who've been
killed in hate crimes because of
their sexual orientation. That's
tonight, 7pm at dance Plaza. Now
this is a really important
thing. It's time to decorate our
sanctuary for the holidays and
Sue. Sue stand up. She's the
first one to sign up for this
beautiful project. We're going
to have a Christmas tree back
here, a giving tree for Hope
House, the homeless kids in
Myrtle Beach High School, and
then we have a tree over here
for Regency hospice. So if you
would like to participate in
creating the wonderful energy of
the holidays here, then please
see Sue. And Sue that sign up.
She is on my desk. So if you
want to sign up, see Sue after
service. Okay? So. Please do and
that's it.
Unknown: There's one more.
Margaret. I'm sorry I forgot to
do a slide. We are starting a
new book in our Wednesday Book
Group, which is a fabulous
group. So anybody who didn't
want to come in the middle of
the book a week from Wednesday,
we're starting a new one.
Margaret Hiller: Okay, so the
new book will be Daring Greatly
by Rene Brown, and so that will
be happening probably a couple
of Wednesdays from now. Okay,
all right, so let's take a deep
breath, and once again, we are
reading this morning out of how
to speak unity. If you didn't
know how to speak unity, you can
buy a book of different terms
about unity, and one of the
words that this author, Temple
Hies defines is the word being.
And so this is what Unity
teaches. Are we human beings or
human doings? In our culture, we
have created a belief that
levels of busyness equal levels
of importance. We need a 12 step
group for that to achieve this
sense of importance, we often
push ourselves past our natural
limits. We were created as human
beings rather than human doing
let's all say that together, we
were created as human beings
rather than human
Unknown: doings. It is
Margaret Hiller: imperative that
we remember to take time to
simply be incorporating regular
routines such as meditation or
walks in nature rejuvenate our
spirits and lower our stress.
That's a good thing. What some
of us were doing last Saturday
at the main Earth spiritual
center. We were walking in
nature. Nature is free to us and
allows us to connect with our
inner stillness. Or the book of
Psalms we read my Remember, be
still and know I am so part of
what we try to do here. In what
we hope to do is to create a
space of stillness and peace,
even within the atmosphere of
singing and teaching and
listening and learning and
encouraging one another. It's
all about healing, and we give
thanks for that. Okay, now we're
going to read our unity
statement of purpose. Please,
all of us together. I am the
consciousness of unity. Christ
Church, a unified board and
congregation, nurturing
spiritual growth, inspiring
creativity, sharing time,
talents, treasures and expanding
awareness of divine awesome and
Lily, we invite you back to Do a
song for us. Thank you Very
much. You
Unknown: Good morning,
everybody, good
Speaker 3: I just need to tell
you briefly about this song. So
the song that I'm getting ready
to sing to you was a dream.
I was sleep, and Beyonce was
singing this song in my dream.
Wow. And I always have to give
people space to laugh. There was
a man, and he had moved, was
very distraught. Apparently,
something tragic had happened in
his life, and he had moved into
mental illness, and he began to
walk around the middle of a
water tower, and Beyonce lived
on the second floor, and she
could see the man in the water
tower, and she looked out of her
window and started singing this
song to him. Then she invited
the man into his house, to her
house, and started stroking his
hair and singing these words
into his eyes. And I woke up,
and I just kept singing the
song. And so there will be a
point in the time while I'm
singing that I will ask you to
look into somebody's eyes and
say these words you
in your night and when your eyes
start feeling. Take a breath.
Unknown: In God. Comfort you.
It dreams
have died and no one knows how
you feel
inside, where you can hide, You.
Oh, find Somebody to sing.
The party, your dreams have died
and no one knows how You feel
inside. Come to you can hide for
Margaret Hiller: you. Moon,
beautiful. Thank you. Okay, I
would like to welcome everybody
and make a special note of
welcoming first time visitors.
So if you're here for the first
time, would you please, if you
want to stand, give us your name
and where you're visiting from?
Yes, ma'am. Pat Chene,
Washington, DC, welcome.
You're here with Lily from
Georgetown, welcome Georgetown
from California.
He let people in from
California. Who else is here?
And I'm here from Los Angeles,
Unknown: California, but I was
born in Georgetown, and this is
my first time back since 1987
I've
Margaret Hiller: been curious.
To know if you see any changes.
Yes. Ma'am. Cindy Perry, I live
in Myrtles inlet. Welcome. I'm
Jane, and I live in Myrtle
Beach. Welcome. You. Okay, and
anybody back who hasn't been
here in a long, long time, and
we might just want to make a
special note that you're here.
Yes, ma'am, welcome. Welcome
back. I never my soul never
left. Welcome. Welcome anybody
else?
Unknown: Yes, I'm Carl, Bella,
Sarah. We just moved here from
the Washington DC area, and I
was here in September, so I'm
back. Good. Welcome
Margaret Hiller: anybody back
row, bench? Anybody? Okay, going
once, going twice, and here we
are, welcome. Everybody. Okay,
we are going to now read the
Daily word. This is one of our
oldest publications, and we have
a beautiful affirmation up here
this morning. And the word is
comfort, right? You know, from
the in the South, in
Jacksonville, you say comfort.
And then my voice teacher
drilled it into my brain,
comfort. And I see that you sing
that word just like that. You
sing your comfort song. God is
my comfort and my refuge. Let's
say that together, God is my
comfort and my comfort and my
refuge, beautiful and the daily
word goes on to say, this life
is full of joy and sorrow, but
no condition is beyond the
comfort of spirit, whatever my
experience, even before I voice
My prayer, the comfort I seek is
available to me. I have what I
need for any situation I ask and
I receive. No request is too
great or too small. Each one
invites answers, abundance and
comfort to arise within me. All
that I need is available for me
to claim in this very moment.
Spirit in me is my comforter,
inspiration and guidance to
manifest what I need. Gratitude
fills my heart as I know my
needs are met. I am sheltered in
the loving embrace of the Divine
Presence. Peace fills me heart
and soul. God is my comfort and
my refuge. And from the book of
Hebrews, we who have taken
refuge might be strongly
encouraged to seize the hope set
before us and again our
affirmation. God is my comfort
and my refuge. Okay, now, for
those of you, how many of you
were here yesterday in the
workshop? Look around there
really a lot of people here
yesterday. I heard as people
were coming in this morning
saying, this is one of the best
workshops they've ever been to,
not just here, but any of their
workshop journeys. So thank you,
Chris. Dr, Chris fish is family.
He's a part of the neighborhood,
partly because his mother in law
is our own, Ann Marie, and our
bookstore manager, and she first
brought to us the word of Chris
and his books. He comes to us
after over 30 years of being a
professor of religious studies
philosopher teaching at
Jonestown state, and he's former
Director of Education with
Institute of Noetic Sciences.
Two of his books are down in the
bookstore, and he brings to us
wonderful wisdom and insight. So
he is our speaker this morning,
and for those of us who want to
stay after service, he's going
to do a brief Q and A so you can
plan going to the bathroom real
quick, getting some water,
coming back upstairs after
service. Okay, so this is the
title of his talk today, and we
are going to go into a
meditation song, and then Chris
is going to take over from
there. Okay, alrighty. So let's
all stay seated, and let's,
let's dim the light you
Speaker 3: I take the time. It
takes me down the road so
slowly, and I can't ask bring my
thing and die, but as a folk, I
surrender in the cry, Holy,
Holy. Oh.
What a beautiful place I live my
life to see your face. I live my
life to so bright
I cannot see. Who would you hope
who isn't? Who would you
hold? Who is me? Somebody? Help
me. Help you, please. As I fall
down on my knees and I cry,
Holy, holy. Holy.
Unknown: Holy to see your faith.
Live my Life
to see your
Speaker 3: face. Face, my
Unknown: place
To see
Speaker 3: Yo there you
Chris Bache: Good morning,
everybody. I've been told I have
to remember to hold this mic
close up to my face, so if I
drop off, you just shoot your
hand up and remind me it's a
pleasure to be here with you.
Today was Labor Day, I think
Labor Day weekend when I was
here last with you, it's nice to
be back. So the topic today I
like to talk with you about is
no fear of death. And so begin
with meditation. You.
It on the ground, nice and
solid, feel a chair underneath
you, close your eyes, settle
into your breathing,
and in your mind's eye, see all
of us in the room in one large
circle, just transpose us into a
circle.
Take your left hand and put it
on the shoulder and in your
mind's eye, put it on the
shoulder of the person next to
you, so that we're all together,
touching each other, sharing
touch, Sharing the energy of our
lives.
Yield that circle and and
now bring to mind someone above
who's died, and see them stand.
Standing behind you
for more than one and let them
put their hand on your shoulder,
our hand and
we've all lost someone, so now
we have two circles. Second
circle is probably larger than
the inner circle. So it.
Now they have also known death,
love, separation from someone
they love. So imagine, bring to
mind in your mind's eye, someone
that the person you loved also
lost, and let them stand behind
them in the third circle and put
their hand touch the second
circle you
wearing older clothes of their
time in history, men and women,
old and young and
it now that third generation,
they were separated from someone
in death. So we're going to let
the process repeat itself and
repeat itself, adding ring,
touching our shoulders, touching
their shoulders and touching
each other until The ring goes
back four at the time,
spreading out through history.
Feel the enormity of the
community of those who are
united in death and
now in your mind's eye, bring to
Mind the next generation, the
children in front of you.
And put your hand on their
shoulder,
and then in your mind's eye,
picture their children, and then
their children, and again, put
their hand on their shoulder,
and then they put their hand on
the Next Generation shoulder and
on the next generation shoulder,
those who have died and those
who will
die Feel the enormity of this
community, and we just started
out from the people in this
room,
and feel the naturalness of The
coming and going of life, just
the natural simplicity of the
cycle of birth and death,
sharing life experience and
letting it go you.
Reaching back as far as we can
imagine, reaching forward, as
far as we can see, far as we can
imagine, the community of life,
the.
And feel in your heart your
oneness with this community,
and relax into
the utter simplicity of this
truth
okay, wiggle your fingers and
toes, bring your awareness back
into your body and back
everybody back. We didn't lose
anybody.
So many things are changing the
world around us, so many
exciting developments, so many
powerful transformative
processes taking place in our
life, and for me as an academic,
one of the great transformative
changes taking place in
universities is around this
topic of is there is around
Death and around the research
which is changing our
relationship to death, because
up until about 30 years ago,
many people believed in life
after death, and many people had
faith in life after death, but
not many people had knowledge,
but they would Consider, you
know, knowledge of that reality.
And today, this is changing. Now
we have so many areas of
research which seem to be
penetrating the veil of death,
and so this pervasive terror
which haunts the modern world
view ever since the rise of
science in the 17th, 18th, 19th
century, with this vision that
the physical world is the only
world that's real, and it all
came about through chance,
screened by necessity, and
there's no meaning to life. And
when we die, when our brain
dies, you know, our
consciousness just disappears.
What a horrible philosophy. But
that is the orthodoxy that's
taught in the university where I
teach, and which is taught in
universities around the world,
and it is all outdated. Even
though it's gospel, it's all
passe, it's fading. So what I'd
like to do is just give you a
sample of 12 books that I think
give us interesting insights
into this larger cycle of life.
Because if you're afraid of
dying, you really don't know
what life is about. If you're
afraid of dying, you've got it
all backwards. When really it's
when you're born, that's when
the hard work begins, but when
you die, that's when recess
come, that's when graduation
takes place. So if you're afraid
of graduation, then you don't
know what you're doing. So let's
get clear on what we're doing
here. So today, I just wanted to
talk about 12 books, and I've
tried to identify the books
which I've shared with my
students through the years,
which have meant the most to
them around the topic of death
in four areas. One,
reincarnation research, cycle of
life. Second, near death,
Episode research, what it's like
becoming third, life between
life therapy, which is the
fastest growing area in
hypnotherapy, a subdivision of
past life therapy and fourth
psychedelic research. Now, I
know you may be surprised to
hear that one mentioned here,
because we have a whole lot of
negative conditioning about
psychedelics. We all kind of
went through the Reagan era and
just say no, and we kind of
forgot that for several 1000s of
years, human beings have been
gathering in sacred circles,
using sacred memories, medicines
to remember, help them remember
who they are and recover their
place in the universe. So that's
the context for it. So I just
want to give you three books, or
pick three books in each of
these areas. So, oh, okay,
keeping an eye on the clock,
here we go. Three books in
reincarnation research, and I
apologize for putting my own in
the list. We already have it.
Otherwise, other cells by Roger
Wilber, who is a past lives
therapist, is now. He just
passed about a year and a half
ago, and he's so he's in the
bleacher seats. If I am asked,
What's the best single book by
one author who is a past lives
therapist, person, I always say,
who is Roger Wilber? It. He says
he's a wonderful writer. He's
good. He's got a good, solid
grasp on the history of the
tradition. He's a wonderful
therapist. He takes you into the
act of helping people recover
their what I call their deep
memory, helping people recover
the deeper sense of who they
are. Helping them remember who
they were before they were born,
helping them trace down the
knots that they find in their
present life. Where did those
knots come from? Some of them
come from their childhood. Some
of them come from a previous
life or a life before their most
recent previous life. He just
untangles it beautifully. And
then Carl Bohm, who's a nurse
who wasn't really interested in
past lives therapy until her
child started having night
terrors. Her child started
having fears come up in his
dreams. And she got, like any
good mother, she got involved in
helping him untangle those
dreams, and helping him uncover
what was scaring him. And it
turned out what was scaring him
was the memory of a previous
life that was beginning to
bubble up inside his soul. And
he helped her. He she helped him
accept that memory, live it. And
then the dreams, the bad dreams,
stopped, and she got involved,
and she began to put something
up on the web, and hundreds and
hundreds of people began to
contact her. And she started
working with children and with
parents of children who
basically have these memories
bubbling up. And so she became
kind of a significant writer and
Plato in the field, and this is
a wonderful book. It's filled
with lots and lots of case
histories of children
remembering their former lives.
And she talks to parents and
helps them understand that this
is a totally natural innocent
thing, and how to help your
child if your child starts to
have these memories which are
not all negative, sometimes
they're very positive, ecstatic
memories, helping the children
integrate those memories into
the larger because what we're
doing is remembering our soul.
That's the soul that's holding
all of those lives and life
cycles. Was the first book I
wrote, which as an academic.
This was my response to Ian
Stevenson's work. His studies
small children from all over the
world, when they begin to talk,
they remember their previous
lives. And he's been able to
document this I've been in I
think Stevenson is the Charles
Darwin of reincarnation theory,
and this is my reflection on his
research, bringing it forward,
making it available, and then
asking the question, so what if
reincarnation is a fact of life?
What are the RAM conclusions of
living in a reincarnation
universe? And I think they're
profound RAM conclusions,
because if you don't understand
reincarnation, you don't
understand what's happening.
It's impossible to understand
the logic of life, or the wisdom
of life, or the intelligence of
the Creator. If you think that
we only live in life one time,
that's like taking a Sherlock
Holmes novel, pulling one
chapter out of the middle of the
novel, reading it, and trying to
understand what's going on. You
have to sort of think large. You
have to learn to think in the
perspective of God. If God would
spend 13 point 7 billion years
evolving a galaxy, why would God
only invest 100 years in the
soul? So reincarnation the cycle
of life, but it dissolves the
fear of dying when you
understand that dying is
followed by a rest and is
followed by a return, which is
followed by life, which is
followed by death, which is
followed by resting, and then is
followed by return, this
Wonderful cycle of life. What's
it like to die? We know what it
looks like on the outside. It's
kind of unpleasant to look at
from the outside, but what's it
like to experience it on the
inside? Well, let's ask people
whose heart has stopped. Let's
ask people whose brain waves
went flat, and yet our medical
technology pulled it back. Now
we have millions and millions of
people who have gone through
this experience since the Korea
War, where we began to develop
trauma medicine. Here are my
three favorite books in this
area.
The first two were written by
David ring, who was a professor
at University of Connecticut all
his professional life. He's one
of the founders of the near
death episode movement, founder
of the Journal of thanontology.
This isn't his first book
heading toward omega. Is not his
first book. It's his second
book, his first book where he
documented the phenomena of near
death, near death episodes, the
second book he's asking. It,
what's the meaning of near death
episodes? What are we supposed
to learn about life from
studying near death episodes?
And he decided the best way to
do this was to study people who
had the deepest Near-Death
Experience, because not all near
death episodes are as deep. Some
of them are kind of superficial,
some are leading and some very,
very deep. Well, he said, let's
focus on the ones who went
really, really deep, who not
only got out of their body, went
through the tunnel, not only saw
the light, but went into the
light, what he calls core envy
ears. And he studies them in
heading toward omega. And
they're wonderful, wonderful
personal accounts. It because he
has collected from all over the
world wonderful experiences
people share their stories with
Ken. And he's a he's a wonderful
Archivist of their stories. And
chapter three of Eddie toward
Omega contains 13 people's
experiences, very, very deep
near death experiences, and it
just touches your heart. It
touches your soul. These people
have gone into God, and it's
clear that they're touching
something profound. And it
changed their life, it changed
their mind, it changed their
emotions, it changed their
values. It changed their
religion, change their their
priorities, and even change
their physiology. Having lessons
from the light is Ken's last
book on near death episode
research. So it's kind of a at
the end of the long,
distinguished career studying
these things. This is his last
volume on it really pulls
together the research he studies
near death episodes of those who
are blind from birth, who have a
near death episode, and they can
see even though they've been
blind. And there is a chapter,
chapter 13 at the end, where
it's called returning to the
source, where he has the deepest
near death episodes and again,
these are spiritual Odysseys
which are just profound. I mean,
they're they're just extra
ordinary, and their story is
your story. Their story is
yours. And you can feel this,
because when you read it, we've
all die. We've been through this
before, you know, and this is
just remembering. It helps us
remember our experience. It
helps us connect with this
larger landscape that life is
part of. Now. What if this is
just endorphin rush from
extinguishing? What if this is
really just fantasy? What is it?
This is just kind of a wish
fulfilling kind of exercise.
Well, here, let's take a look at
this last book pin womel, who's
a Norwegian psychiatrist. There
have been many studies by
scientists of the near death
episode experience. I think this
is the best one. It's that if
you really, if you have a really
skeptical spouse, or you are a
skeptical spouse, and you really
want to look at the near death
episode from a critical,
scientific, philosophical
perspective, read this book.
It's just really good. It's
hardcore analysis. And his
conclusion is, every attempt to
explain away these experiences
fails. They fail to do justice
to the reality experience. When
you get into the detail of the
cases, these things withstand
critical scrutiny, just fine.
Thank you very much. This is one
I get my academic colleagues
when they want to go, Boo Boo
this and Boo Boo that I said,
Okay, read this and then come
back and talk to me now, just to
throw a fourth one. And I
couldn't help it, Proof of
Heaven. You know, you know, even
Alexander's work, we have this
in the bookstore downstairs.
Wonderful, wonderful account.
There are numerous accounts of
one individual who has a
profound near death episode had
guts to write it down, and took
guts for this guy to write it
down, because he's a
neurosurgeon. Everybody knows. I
mean, if the Hindus want to go
to heaven when they die. That's
fine, but Harvard and
neurosurgeons do not go to
heaven.
It's a very brave and courageous
book. One more area, all right,
trying to stay on schedule here,
life between life therapy. What
is that? Well, here are the
three books here, and these are
wonderful. We have two over in
the bookstore downstairs. Occurs
to Michael Newton's work. I like
Michael Newton's work a lot. If
there were any one single.
Little book I recommend to
people who really want to
address the nature of what
happens when we die. I say start
with Michael Luke, because I
know if they read journey of the
soul of souls, they're going to
read destiny of souls. And the
two of them really make up one
volume work. Michael Luke was a
past life therapist. He was
doing past lives therapy was
taking people into hypnotic
regression, is healing, helping
people heal by uncovering the
deeper sources of their issues
in this life. And one day, he
gave an ambiguous instruction,
and he found that his client not
only remembered their previous
life, but remembered what
happened to them after they died
in their previous life, they
were able to remember the time
between death and birth. And he
said, Well, damn, that's
amazing. And so he started
taking people back into that
life between life state and when
he had taken 600 people. How
long does it take you to develop
cases like that? 600 people into
that life, between life state.
He wrote this first book,
journey of souls, and he just
describes what his clients
described happening to them. And
then later, a few years later,
he wrote destiny of souls. He
kind of thickens the plot a
little bit, and people were very
interested, and they began to
come to Michael and therapists
coming wanting to be trained.
And eventually he created an
institute where professionals
can come to be trained in doing
life between life therapy. And
that's what's happening in the
third book, memories of the
afterlife, where you have
therapists who have all been
trained by Michael, who
basically there's a short
introduction explaining who they
are and how they got in this
work. And then there's a case
history from their clients, of
someone who remembers the time
between life and this is the
missing piece of life. Reason I
called my book life cycles is
because it life is a cycle, and
right now, we're mostly paying
attention to only one half of
the cycle from birth to death.
But if you don't understand
what's happening from death to
birth, you can't understand the
whole cycle there. There is a
logic to it, there is a
progression, there's a de brief
time when you die. There is the
return to home, return to source
time. And Michael emphasizes,
it's a social time. There is a
community in heaven, and there
are community you are part of a
soul cluster. He says, average
number of souls he finds from
his research is 15 souls in a
cluster, and you It's like your
class, your matriculation class.
And no matter how many times you
incarnate, no matter many
hundreds or 1000s of times you
incarnate, you always return to
connect with these individuals.
They're part of like your soul
family. You go through life
together, they don't always
evolve at the same rate, because
some are slow learners and some
are fast learners, but you
evolve together, and they're
guides, and the guides have
guides, and the guides guides
have guides. And he describes in
great detail the texture of this
community, and what I love about
Michael's work is the detail,
the detail of people who die,
who have lived a life so mean,
so vengeful, so hateful, they've
done so much harm, they've hurt
so many people. What happens to
them when they die? And he says,
there's no help. We all go home,
but some people have been so
mangled in life that it takes
special they take special care.
Their energy has to be healed
and realign before they can
return to the community of
heaven. He goes and there are
specialists who work with them,
engage them, intercept them,
hold them, heal them, and help
them find their way back home.
There's just layer upon layer.
Michael fills in some of the
missing pieces. And if you know
the spiritual literature, if you
know the mystical literature of
the great saints and sages from
Eastern and Western mystical
traditions, everything Michael
is showing us is coherent and
congruent with what the mystics
have been telling us, the
difference is that now we have
hundreds and 1000s of people
just like you and me who are
going into this territory,
instead of being simply monks
and nuns and isolated monastic
retreats going into this
territory, the Secret Knowledge
of these things is becoming
public. It's becoming part of
our public record, and it's
becoming part of your students
education. In college, if
faculty want to take them there,
and it's it changes lives. I've
just seen so many students, it
changes their lives, because
once you understand what's going
on, not only do you lose. Is
your fear of death, but you you
grab a deeper meaning to life.
You begin to understand what
your life is about, the
challenges that are embedded.
And by the way, Michael Newton
describes the choices that we
make in order to incarnate what
happens. And he shows how people
know what they're getting into
before they're born, they make
conscious choices to enter the
life they're true they're
entering. Now we might think,
why would I choose a life like
this? Why choose pain and
suffering? Why choose handicap?
Why choose early death? Why? Why
choose these things? But you
have to look at life from the
perspective of the soul, not
from the perspective of the ego.
You have to look at the purpose
of life from the perspective of
the deep soul's agenda. And the
soul's agenda is much larger
than our personal agenda. Life
is not about being comfortable.
Life is about becoming more
being more challenged, and that
happens to be challenged. And
lastly, psychedelic research,
sacred medicine work in the in
the indigenous traditions, they
call these things, not
hallucinogens, because that
implies that the visions which
these trigger are false, but
sacred medicines, and their
tradition is that the gods knew
when human beings incarnated,
they would forget. They would
forget who we are and what's
going on. And these medicines
help us remember. They help us
remember who we are and what the
game of life is. Now I'm not
talking about tripping, though
tripping is interesting and fun.
I'm talking about serious psycho
therapeutic work and the van
here, the foremost person is
man, the fellow, the founder,
one of the co founders of the
Transpersonal psychology
movement, along with Abraham
Maslow, is a man named Stanislav
Grof, and he's written about
1516, books by now. And this is
the him here, one of the great
thinkers of the Transpersonal
psychology movement, and my
favorite three books of his,
particularly pertaining to the
issue of death, what happens to
us when we die? Are these three
books. Now, a little warning,
this is not exactly easy
reading, just because this first
book is LSD psychotherapy. This
is a technical manual written
for doctors and nurses and
psychotherapists on the how to
manage psychedelic therapy, how
to manage a therapeutic session,
low doses, high doses, counter
indications, how to screen,
managing the session, managing
after the session. This is, this
is not Tim and Lee. Lee. This is
a different this is serious
therapeutic work. This is the
modern recovery of an ancient
tradition after writing lesson
psychotherapy and writing
several books on the clinical
implications for the
implications of psychedelic
research for psychology and
theories of consciousness, and
several intervening work and a
book on their work in
psychedelic therapy with the
terminally ill, helping them
adjust to the reality of their
impending death. He wrote this
book, The cosmic game. The
cosmic game is basically a
discussion of the philosophical
and theological ramifications of
psychedelic research. So it's
the cosmology book, it's the
it's the big picture. And Stan
has a profound portrait of the
big picture. And not
surprisingly, once you
understand it's it's nothing
new. We've seen this before.
We've seen it in the great
mystical traditions of the
world. We've seen it in the
great meditation traditions of
the world. Psychedelics is not
the issue. Psychedelics is
simply a method, one more method
that humanity has used to tap
into the very deep foundational
core of our lives and the life
of the universe. Meditation is a
method. Transcendence is a
method. Fasting and isolation is
a method. Silence is a method.
The careful, conscientious use
of sacred medicines is a method
for entering into this reality.
The third book, ultimate journey
is specifically where Stan is
addressing the issue of death.
And he looks at death from a
cross cultural perspective, from
a historical perspective. He's
drawing upon South American
traditions, Native American
traditions, Indian traditions
and psychedelic. Research
traditions, bringing it all
together.
Is there any mention of
Ayahuasca in any of those books?
Yes, there is. There is now
Ayahuasca basically another
psychedelic used. It's used in
Brazil. It's legal in Brazil.
The Brazilian government chose
investigated the communities
that were using Ayahuasca. They
chose to keep Ayahuasca legal.
Now, Ayahuasca is legal in this
country. There is a community in
Ashland and in Texas, in Houston
that went took the right to the
Supreme Court and won the right
to use sacred medicine Ayahuasca
in their church. So these are
not renegades. These are not
people who are pushing the
outside, you know, just on the
outside of society. These are
trying, people who are trying to
help society recover the
powerful agents of self
transformation that has
historically been the role of
the sacred substances. Can they
be a youth abused? Yeah, they
can. Were they? Yeah, they were,
but if we have the wisdom to use
them properly, they can be truly
agents of Deep, sacred
transformation. And I would just
add the fourth book. My second
book is in this lineage of dark
night. Early on, I'm writing as
a philosopher of religion, and I
believe psychedelics are very
important to the psychology of
consciousness and understanding
the psychology, you know, the
depth of this human psyche, and
this capacity to enter into the
mind of the universe at large.
So I'm kind of, I'm putting it
out of the line. One of the
things that happens in
psychedelic therapy is just like
in all the other areas, you lose
your fear of death when you are
able to tap into who you are
underneath the body, who you are
inside the very essence of the
body and the wonderful universe
that gave birth to you have
brought you forward, well, then
you just stop being afraid of
dying. Dying is your best
friend. Dying is graduation.
Dying is the culmination of your
life. It's part of the cycle of
life. If you read those 12
books, if you were afraid of
dying before, I don't think
you're going to be afraid of
dying now, and even if you
weren't afraid of dying, you're
going to really understand the
life process much more deeply if
you read these books. Thanks
very much. You
Margaret Hiller: Thank you. So
what I hear you saying, Don't
worry behind I hear you saying
that there's much more to our
world and to our lives, than
simply getting more living life
and leaving life, that there's
an entire spectrum of life
experience in the body and out
of body, that we're Surrounded
by a community of heaven. I love
your term for that. The Bible
says a great cloud of witnesses,
like you said, your friends in
the bleacher seats. Many of us
here can feel the presence of
our heavenly friends and loved
ones. So I appreciate all the
research, personal research and
learning, being mentored with
some of these great thinkers. So
thank you for bringing these
ideas to us. You're always
welcome. So let's take a deep
breath. We're going to do our
sacred have our sacred
opportunity to give tithes and
donations for the ongoing health
and well being and continuing of
work with this wonderful
community. How many of you know
you're part of an incredible,
beautiful spiritual community
here. And we have many
communities, don't we, and some
of our communities blend here.
We have people have their other
spiritual paths, other
communities. They come here to
unity, sometimes, all the time.
So for our ongoing blessing, we
receive our tithes and
donations. I have my tithe check
here. It's my great privilege to
be a tither and to tithe on my
paycheck that I am getting
today, right?
Okay, so we have a blessing and
a hand Buddha that goes with it
every. Way, please. I am light
flowing through me, blessing
these gifts to radiate peace and
our handful bless us With music.
Thank you.
And away we go. Did Oh,
Chris Bache: it a couple
Unknown: minutes, three, Very
nice for the song.
Chris Bache: Two, you
Nothing. I mean,
Unknown: I'll be you might have
to leave The game. Up
For Don't worry, You. Don't
worry. Wow.
Chris Bache: Don't bring
everybody down. Bring everybody
down. Don't worry. Don't worry.
Be happy.
Margaret Hiller: I have heard
the story, and I wonder if it's
true that Bobby McCarry received
that message from Mayor vara.
Don't worry. Happy. There you
go. Okay, y'all, let's bless our
officers one more time with our
hand Mudra. I am white, glowing
through me. Let gifts to radiate
peace. Can y'all see the smiles
on their faces? Y'all want to
bring your attention to this
table over here, Lily has
brought a few of her CDs. If you
want to take the blessing of her
music home, you can see her over
here at this table after
service,
one is blessing will be
happening in here, in the Peace
chapel, and tomorrow, I probably
started this work. It started at
the workshop yesterday. I
continue to do my meditations
for Susan. I'm ready for you. Me
too. So tomorrow, 11 to one
closer walk with God, Susan will
be here supporting us to catch
hold of some of that cheaper
work that she brought back with
her from India on this
university. And we are also
doing our annual unity art day.
If you're going to get a table
and you're going to be artist
craftsperson at that event, you
need to sign up downstairs on
the lobby sign up sheet for that
art day. Okay? And the
attractions book is downstairs
for sale, and I've already
gotten my money back on it with
the coupons. I love coupons.
Okay? And next Sunday, we're
doing again, a topic out of our
meditation book from the
meditation class, opening your
heart, love, compassion and
forgiveness. And I'll just share
with you that we're going to
jump off what Chris brought us.
We're going to jump off that
into some really great
information that all came to me
was a great download this
morning, and my meditation, yes,
okay, all right. And next week,
there will be a possible
repaving of this road out here
in front of the church. They did
it incorrectly. Imagine, so
they're going to come and read
pave and restrike. So if there's
a problem parking out here next
week, you can park behind the
church. Yes, ma'am, I like to
make it calm that moment. I did
park this morning. I was told
that an individual down the road
is attempting to toe. Okay. So
anyway, so there may be some
parking issues next week, you
can Carl pool. You can park in
the back of the church. A few
folks parked at old time pottery
and walked over. It's not a long
walk. Or tell us you need a ride
from old time pottery, and we'll
get some folks to do a little
Carl, is that okay? Alright,
here we go. Let's all stand and
make our circle. Where did sue
go?
Okay, everybody see this? I know
that there are at least. I know
there are at least four or five
creative people who want to be a
part of decorating the sanctuary
for Christmas. I know you're out
here in the circle and Sue,
here's the sign up sheet. See
Sue about helping decorate.
December 1 is the first Sunday
of Advaita, and that's when we
want our trees done. Okay?
Everybody got that? Okay, so
let's say our prayer for
protect. Question. This is James
bill at Freeman wrote this, and
we say it for ourselves and all
those we're holding in our
hearts. The light of God
surrounds
Chris Bache: us, the love of God
unfolds us. The power of God
protects us, the presence of God
watches over us wherever we are,
God is and all is done.
Margaret Hiller: After you say
it a couple 1000 times, you
might memorize it correctly, all
right? And now we do our peace
song, We sing it like a prayer
Song,
Chris Bache: guide it all For
me, I
play. One
Margaret Hiller: more thing, if
you want to stay for a quick QA,
we're going to meet back.