Unknown: You are listening to
part one of two of Our
conversation with Chris Bache.
You
Susan: foreign. Welcome to Sky
Blue symposia, a convivial
gathering for stimulating
conversation and a free exchange
of ideas. We're so glad you
could join us, friends. I'm
Susan, your host, and here at
our round table, our bridge
sibell and chipper and today,
Chris Bache is kind enough to
join us for a new symposium as
we continue consciously
exploring welcome, Chris, it's
so nice to have you with us.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Susan,
it's a real pleasure to be part
of your conversation today.
Well, we've
Susan: been anticipating this,
and we're all very interested in
your field, so I think we're
going to have a cracking time.
Good. But I'd like to start off
by talking a bit about Stanislav
grofs, his extra ordinary
accomplishments as a scholar,
healer, pioneer of Transpersonal
theory and practice. I wonder if
you'd be happy to tell us a bit
about Stan's work, and most
especially, how it's influenced
your path, your decisions and
your use of psychedelic inquiry.
Chris Bache: Well, Stan's been a
huge influence on my life. I met
Stan's work, his books, the
beginning of a series of books
when I first came out of
graduate school in 1978 and his
work, and Ian Stevenson, the
scholar on reincarnation, but
particularly Stan's work,
changed the direction the course
of my personal and professional
life. Stan is a psychiatrist and
the foremost authority of the
influence of LSD and
psychedelics in general, on
consciousness and the
integrating of psychedelics into
the psychotherapeutic process.
He had been working for many
years in Czechoslovakia at a
psychiatric institute. He came
to the United States and was the
director of research at Spring
Grove Hospital in Baltimore, and
after a number of years there,
he went to eslin, where he was a
senior research fellow and
worked for many years in that
peculiar, that very distinctive
hotbed of humanistic and
Transpersonal psychology that we
all know and love. As Esalen, he
has written over a dozen books.
I think he's really one of the
most seminal thinkers in
psychology and consciousness
studies. He's was the president
for many years of the
International Transpersonal
Association. Co founder of
Transpersonal psychology, with
Maslow and the ITA, the
International Transpersonal
Association, bringing
Transpersonal psychology and
consciousness studies around the
world and the series of
conferences held in multiple
countries. He's just been a
seminal thinker, and what he did
for me was, when I came out of
graduate school, I was a very
well educated atheistically
inclined agnostic. I had
assimilated the modern and
postmodern critique of religion,
and I was trained as a
philosopher of religion. I had
assimilated that critique,
moving from medieval theology
and the Protestant Reformation
and the emphasis on scripture,
and then the social and
scientific and psychological
critique of religion. And then I
met Stan's work, and Stan
basically put in front of me not
only an extra ordinary model of
consciousness, but he outlined a
methodology for using
psychedelics to explore the deep
recesses of consciousness, both
for therapeutic purposes, but
eventually the therapeutic
trajectory. When one goes deep
within, it's like the bottom of
your there is no bottom to your
mind. You drop right out of the
personal psyche into the vast a.
Expanse of the mind of the
universe itself. So as a
philosopher, I mean, I mean, I'm
not a therapist, and have not
primarily been concerned with
exploring psychedelics potential
to heal, but I've been a
philosopher, and so my interest
has been to use psychedelics to
explore the deep structure of
consciousness, to explore those
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness through which we
can experience the deeper
structure of reality itself. Now
of course, that involves a lot
of healing, but healing in a
shamanic sense, going beyond you
know, conventional Western
senses of healing, healing of
not only the psyche, but healing
of the soul, but then exploring
healing at a deep existential
level, as one explores the very
structure of of of well, of the
universe. I just couldn't pass
that opportunity down. So my
problem was, it was 1978 we were
past the the Timothy Leary era
and the all the were past the
60s. Things had calmed down
some, and my government had made
psychedelics illegal. And so I
had a hard choice to make, and
the choice I made was to
conscientiously and respectfully
use these substances in a
systematic, 20 year long
inquiry, which I kept separate
and out of my professional life
as much as possible. I'm an
academic, so I'm a university
professor here in Ohio, but in
my background life, I began this
regimen of systematically
exploring the deeper reaches of
consciousness, and that
influence, I brought that into
my academic work in a very
modest way, but it's really been
only now that I've retired that
I'm trying to give a systematic
accounting of the full nature of
that journey that I went on
Susan: that is fabulous,
absolutely fabulous. And it's so
needed right now. And I think
the time is actually ripe for
this. And as we were discussing
before we started the symposium,
it seems that Ayahuasca is the
path that is most available to
people, at least in North
America, and but I think people
will find their own way to
whatever they need, whatever
they can, to open up these
avenues. I think we're we're
starving for it.
Chris Bache: Yes, yes, yeah.
Susan: And so I appreciate very
much what you're saying. And
sibell, you had the next
question you were going to ask,
yeah.
Cybele: So, Chris, for a
beginner, what actually happens
in a psychedelic session, and
what's the difference between
using psychedelics
recreationally or using them
therapeutically or spiritually?
Chris Bache: Yeah. Well, there
are many different psychedelics,
of course, and so if we were to
take this conversation down to a
more precise level, would have
to discuss specific psychedelics
and how they interact with
consciousness, but generally the
category of drugs that we call
psychedelics are are
consciousness amplifiers. They
are amplifiers and catalysts of
consciousness, so that what they
do is hypersensitize
consciousness with a particular
perhaps a tilt one way or the
other. But they hypersensitize
consciousness so that what
happens in a session is actually
not simply a function of the
psychedelic but it's a the
function of consciousness
itself. So consciousness becomes
hyper energized,
hypersensitized, in a very short
period of time, and then there
is a confrontation the deeper
contents of the what is
previously we would call, you
know, the unconscious. Of the
contents of the unconscious
begin to surface into one's
awareness, and one literally
becomes aware of dimensions of
one's mind that one previously
had not been aware of. If you
take psychedelics
recreationally, you basically,
most people would be trying to
stay in contact with the
physical world and stay in con
in the identity of their ego.
And then they're entertaining
the ego by having some type of
hallucinatory experience where
there is. Blending between the
what's arising from the
unconscious and one's physical
environment. And there is a
tendency to sort of often focus
on esthetic aspects, visual
aspects, hallucinatory aspects,
engaging in sensory awareness
through music or sight or sound
and or if there is a kind of
therapeutic aspect, it's
engaging the surface of
consciousness, the psychodynamic
level one's personal history, a
second modality of working well
is working therapeutically and
working spiritually, what I
would call much more serious
work, where you try to harness
all that energy of that
hypersensitivity, so you isolate
yourself from the physical
world. People will work at
night, they'll work you
basically create a psychological
space of the Kivas of the
southwestern Native Americans,
where you isolate yourself from
the world. You're wearing
headphones, you're wearing eye
shades, you're listening to very
carefully scripted music. You
have a sitter where you're
basically create conditions
where you provide maximal
confrontation with the content
of your consciousness that opens
up depths which very seldom
surface in just recreational
tripping, and I have very little
experience with recreational
tripping. All of my work has
been in this therapeutic
modality, in this shamanic
modality of working with
psychedelics, and so when the
content of one's consciousness
begins to surface, i Yes, one
literally usually what happens
in the early stages is stresses
and strains that we have kept at
arm's length are existential
questions or doubts and
uncertainties that we usually
try to stay away from.
Paramount, for example, would be
the fear of death and
extinction. These, these begin
to surface and come at you and
how you meet them, if, if you
meet them in an embracing way,
one goes through a certain
encounter, a certain engagement,
where you confront your deepest
fears. You engage the most
profound questions that human
beings ask themselves, and you
let the universe take you where
where it wants to take you. And
there are a series of crises
that emerge of varying depths
and the varying types, and
usually, usually there is a
crisis that ferments and
develops into a critical crisis,
a critical kind of point of
impasse. And if you surrender to
this impasse, if you surrender
to whatever it is that wherever
your session is taking you,
wherever consciousness is taking
you, you will go through a type
of death and rebirth process.
You'll go through a complete
surrender where some part of
your life, or some part of life
as you have known it will fall
away, will just combust. You'll
die. Some part of you will die,
and then you find yourself
waking up in a completely
different reality, a larger
reality, a new reality, a
reality that you had never
expected previously, and a
reality where the universe
operates by different laws, and
you're you are a different kind
of being than you were in your
previous reality, and that can
be an exciting and A terrifying
process all at the same time,
yeah.
Cybele: So kind of what I'm
hearing, though, is that, like
someone will take an anti
depressant, and there's some
brain chemistry going on with
this, this medication. And even,
you know, with with
psychedelics, there's some brain
chemistry that's going on, but
you're really talking about
consciously taking this and and
moving it forward in a certain
direction rather than just
having brain chemistry, is that,
yes,
Chris Bache: I'm not addressing
the physiology of psychedelics
at all, the brain chemistry of
psychedelics. I'm not really
competent to discuss that. I'm
really addressing. Just the
psychoactive properties of these
substances. My understanding is
basically we don't yet know how
psychedelics work. I mean,
really, we don't, we don't
understand, we understand some
of the biochemistry of it, but
we don't really understand
completely how they work. But
we've been using them for 1000s
of years as a human species, and
we have a great deal of
experience working with them, so
we do understand a lot about how
they work psychologically and
spiritually.
Cybele: Yeah, yeah. Well, thank
you.
Susan: Well, this is Susan,
again, Chris, when psychedelics
are not used to entertain the
ego, sort of a spiritual
materialism, but instead the
intent is this spiritual process
that with an intention of a
personal ego, death. What
happens is, is it this
existential death is that a
guaranteed before you can, you
can move past that, that you it
is about facing one's deepest
existential fears. And that's
kind of the ring pass, not that
you have to go through.
Chris Bache: I think that's
inevitable. I want to, if I get
lost in this, in my answer,
bring me back to the question of
dose in low dose versus high
dose. But I think it's
inevitable that one comes to
these thresholds of impasse,
because we have to reverse
image, reverse imagine
everything we know about
consciousness. We tend to think
of our consciousness as small,
and by doing this, we are
opening our consciousness to
something larger. But actually,
I think it would be better to
start with what emerges in the
work itself is that an
understanding that consciousness
is our consciousness is actually
infinite, absolutely so it
starts and somehow, in taking
birth, In incarnating we have
voluntarily accepted a
contraction of consciousness,
and we stayed within that
contraction so that we begin to
think that that's what our
consciousness is, that our
consciousness is kind of person
sized, but a consciousness is is
really as large as the universe
itself. So if one, if one,
starts to open to the natural
dimensions of your own mind, you
have to free yourself from that
contraction. So the the easier
it is for you to surrender the
identity that you have developed
over all your lifetime, the
easier it is to open to these
deeper currents of mind. If it
the harder it is, the more
challenging it is so but that
there will always be a crisis
that challenges you to let go of
everything you think you are,
everything you have known as
real, your whole vision of
yourself and reality that seems
inevitable If you if you're
going to push the limits deeply
to basically remember what
you've forgotten. Now, you can
do this in two different
modalities. You can do it in low
dose work, where you basically
energize the psyche just a
little bit and you peel back the
layers of these contracted
identities in small increments,
or you can work with high doses,
where you basically consume
those contractions. You break
through those contractions in in
leaps and bounds, in a way where
you force a larger confrontation
and explode through those shells
and run more quickly and more
into the deeper nature of mind.
Susan: Now, you mentioned shells
plural, yeah, lots. That implies
that yes, that there's more than
one. Yeah. That suggests cycles
of death and rebirth and
initiation, and does that happen
through the course of this long
period?
Unknown: Well, I can't
Susan: imagine that you would
want to that it even we would be
capable of doing that in a short
period of time.
Chris Bache: Yeah, the universe
is so big. She's so beautiful,
and there's so many layers of
depth to her. She's so
magnificent. And. That it takes
years, I think, and even
lifetimes, more than one
lifetime, to explore the farther
reaches of her. Let me give just
put myself back in my own
history so I don't make false
claims. I mean, I made a choice
early on in my work, after a
half dozen or so sessions to
work exclusively in a high dose
regimen. So that really has
shaped the trajectory of my
work. I've always worked with
very high doses of LSD, kind of
causing maximum combustion,
maximum explosion and maximum
absorption into the universe
itself, it would have been, I
don't recommend that, if looking
back on it, what I If I knew
then what I know now, I think I
would have taken a gentler
approach. But at the time, it
seemed like you know the most
reasonable way to go into this,
this adventure of learning, but
the fool's journey, the fool's
journey, yeah, and I what you're
absolutely right you go through.
What I found is that there are
many layers of death and rebirth
that you go through in the
beginning. Death and Rebirth is
often related to your personal
identity, your personal history.
You're confronting the
limitations of that personal
history. And then Stan, as Stan
Grof describes it, you go into
what he calls the perinatal
level of consciousness, which is
the interface between physical
reality and spiritual reality,
where the overarching themes
tend to be biological birth and
physical death, overlaid with
all sorts of existential
Death-Rebirth, the meaning of
life, Whether life has any
meaning, whether it's
significant, whether we have any
significance in the larger order
of things. And one often
experiences this existential
crisis in the context of
actually reliving your
biological birth. And one also
can be reliving deaths that you
have experienced from previous
lifetimes. It's a very complex
amalgam. And the reason is
because death and birth is a
revolving door. It's how we get
back and forth between the world
of spirit. So if you are going
back through the world of
Spirit, through the door into
the world of spirit, it's not
surprising that we would
activate memories of how we came
back from the world, the spirit
into matter that is through the
womb. So people relive their
their births. And birth is a is
a very often painful and
challenging experience. I mean,
put yourself in the fetuses
position being forced out into
the world. And then when one
relives one's birth, one is kind
of born back into the states of
consciousness, that the state of
consciousness that you were in
before you were born. So you're
in spiritual reality. But it
doesn't stop there, because,
because that spiritual world is
so vast, if you want to explore,
it, has layers to it, and often
these layers are they've been
described. Ken Wilber uses the
categories of psychic levels,
subtle levels, causal levels.
And non dual are absolute
levels, different levels of
Transpersonal reality. If one is
going to allow yourself to be
solved, to be dissolved deeper
and deeper into the universe,
one goes through layer after
layer after layer, and there is
a there's a tax, so to speak, as
one goes into those layers,
there is a deeper yielding, a
deeper letting go, a deeper kind
of confrontation that takes
place as One opens to deeper and
deeper dimensions of existence.
So death and rebirth in this
type of work is a cycle. It
repeats itself many times along
the way, and that simply is a
function of the the enormous
depth and breadth of the
universe and of the Divine
Susan: that is so so beautiful
and so rings true to my own
experience. Yeah, really,
really, really appreciate this.
Cybele: Yeah, Chris, I have a
follow up on this. Did you ever
reach a point of complete?
Complete? A. Am giving of
yourself or relaxation, allowing
into the experience of
dissolving into universe or into
source. Because on a recent
experience of mine, I
experienced the dissolving into
source and then rebuilding
myself and dissolving into
source. And, I mean, it was a
continual process of cycling
through, but there was, I didn't
have any tax or any any losing
of parts of myself, other than
losing myself completely.
Chris Bache: I I think many
people who do spiritual
practice, whether it's with
psychedelics or meditation or
long term retreat, you know
their psychedelics is nothing
that happens in psychedelic
sessions of this sort are unique
in the larger spiritual
landscape of spiritual practice.
There are many methodologies
that open us up to these very
deep dimensions of life. So
people have, and one of the most
common experiences that people
have who use these practices at
one at one time or another, is
return to source. You know, it's
just the most natural thing in
the world as it is, a waking up
to who we always have been. We
don't become source. We just
return to source. We waken up,
we dissolve into it, we relax
into it. And when, and as you
say, we kind of, you can move
back and forth, kind of, into
the source mode, and then back
into the individualized, the
catalyzed individual, and then
back into source mode, back and
forth, and yeah, those those
hours spent opening up to that
part of consciousness that you
have always been. You were
before you were born, you are
while you were born, after you
were born, that you always will
be the the Absolute Source and
ground of all existence, that
which is alive in you, and that
which is the aliveness in all
other life forms that is
considered one of the one of the
great healing and awakening
experience that humankind can
have to awaken to what you truly
are. So our individual identity,
whatever it is, whoever we have
developed over hundreds, 1000s
of incarnations, that individual
identity and the truth of our
individuality plays itself out
against a backdrop of the other
identity, the identity of
totality, the identity of
source, the identity of the
Divine, if we use theological
language, my there is a sense in
much of the literature, the
Vedic literature, and different
spiritual systems, to think that
it's all about return to source,
that the Ultimately, the goal of
spiritual practice is simply to
return to source. And if you
dissolve completely into source,
that is, that is the end of the
line. There is a there is an end
point, and that is the end point
to return to source. And I don't
agree with that entirely for two
reasons. One of them is that
it's been my experience that if
you do return to source, and if
you return to source frequently
and in a systematic fashion,
that oneness, oneness itself,
has many layers to it, and
oneness cracks open, to revolt,
to reveal many different
modalities and layers of depth,
even into oneness. So that
rather than think that oneness
is once, you arrive at oneness,
that is the end of the journey,
I think what the universe shows
us is they're actually infinite
depths of the one, infinite ways
in which the oneness lives in
the universe, or it lives as the
universe. So that I personally
have given up the goal of ever
reaching the end of the journey.
I think that the Divine is far
too vast and far too extended a
reality to reach an end point of
the inquiry. It just, it just
keeps, has kept opening and
opening to me. But the other
reason I have reservation.
Questions about the goal of the
journey is simply to open up to
source is, is a larger cosmic
logical question. I think we
come from source. We come from
the one, and the one has birthed
the universe, the domain of
differentiation, and we exist
here as individual beings. But
if the goal were simply to
return to one that ultimately
leads to the metaphysical
visions that have dominated our
our cultures in the last 5000
years, which are up out
cosmiclogies, you achieve
awakening and you leave. You
achieve spiritual consciousness,
or you return to source, you
awaken into nirvana or Moksha
and you leave because if you can
be in heaven, why would you want
to be on earth? Because the
spiritual world is infinitely
more satisfying than we can be
on Earth. And so all the
cosmology is of Hinduism and
Buddhism and Christianity and
all the world religions have
basically been up and out.
Cosmology. The goal, one way or
another, even for a Bodhisattva,
is to empty the world so that we
can all become enlightened and
return to spirit. But that, I
think, is an incomplete
cosmology, I think a deeper
cosmic, logical vision is
emerging more recently, now that
we truly are absorbing the scale
and scope of evolution, and that
is the goal is not simply to
awaken to source, but to bring
source into and empower the
evolutionary project to actually
embody, to incarnate the divine
ever more fully in history, so
that we'll be doing this for
billions and billions and
billions years more. So
awakening to source is, to me,
midpoint. It is the turning
point, and then this next point
is to continue and deepen
consciously the evolutionary
project,
Cybele: so bringing heaven to
earth, rather than bringing
Heaven
Chris Bache: Heaven to Earth,
yeah, bringing heaven to earth
and basically Creating a greater
porosity, so that there are
fewer membranes between heaven
and earth, so that one can live
more consciously the by
citizenship that we all have. We
are physical beings, but we are
spiritual beings. And I think
the evolutionary trajectory is
towards ever greater inner
penetration, which is actually
changing and redefining what we
think of as our natural
capacities, what we have, the
capacities that we think of as
human capacities, and are being
dictated and limited by our
biology, by our Physics, of our
bodies, I think are actually
simply evolutionary staging
areas. They're just evolutionary
midpoints that are our senses
are evolving as consciousness
evolves, and just as we are
becoming more soulful over
multiple incarnations, literally
are the way in which we see and
hear and think and feel the
depth of it, the entire project
of being human, I think, is
expanding and will continue to
expand, so that literally, in
the future, we will see
differently, we will hear
differently.
Cybele: Thank you. It's
definitely something to work on
achieving, I think chipper has
the next question,
Chipper: Chris, that sounds a
whole lot like what I think of
as field work in that that inner
penetration, that conscious
inner penetration, of awareness,
of of shared awareness of this
individuality that returns to
source over and over again, each
of us brings in the Divine as
we're capable is a is happening
quite rapidly. Over the last two
years, I've talked to people
that have become way more
sensitive to what they ingest,
what they associate with, what
they take care of themselves
with, and I have that
sensitivity I've felt personally
as a as an expanding capacity
for for field work, I guess.
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah. Uh.
Yeah, you know, scientists are
now telling us that everything
that we had thought of
previously as particles,
particles are really feels, if
you get down into the deep
quantum level of reality, that
particles are really feels we
are. We are, fields are primary,
particles are secondary. And I
think that's true of us as of
human beings too, that we are
all interconnected in these vast
fields. And we are
interconnected to our own
history, our reincarnational
history, through the fields of
consciousness. And we are
connected to each other through
the fields, the Morphic fields
of the human of the human
psyche, and these fields, I
think, are becoming more
energized in history, that it's
almost like nature has turned up
the fire and it's bringing the
human psyche to a boil. I think
that the collective unconscious,
Jung's collective unconscious of
the or the mind of the species,
is actually becoming more and
more energized for a variety of
reasons, so that, and we all
feel it. I mean, we can feel
this kind of urgency, kind of a
crescendo that's coming up
underneath us. And I think
there's a, you know, the first
book I wrote was on
reincarnation. And for me,
reincarnation is just one of the
simple facts of life, I mean.
And I think we're coming to see
that, that the empirical
evidence for reincarnation is
incredibly strong, stronger than
it's ever been historically. And
I think there is a, I think that
the evolutionary sequence, which
is underwritten by
reincarnation, this is
progressive, becoming more
conscious, more aware, more
empowered, learning from our
mistakes, exercising new
capacities. There is something
happening now on the planet,
there's an interrelationship
between the global crisis that
we have entered and a deep
individual soul fermentation
that we have entered. I think
the way I language this is that
I think the planetary crisis is
driving us past our limitations
of the past, driving us to a
global citizenship, driving us
to a consciousness of oneness on
the planet that's forcing us to
outgrow the divisions of our
history, of our of our egoic
consciousness, what they are
anyway, for sure, yeah, seeing
for what they are. I mean,
they're they're real, but they
aren't the they aren't the whole
story. And I think that there's
a parallel process taking place
at the very depths of the
psyche, that there is a
psychologically at a soul level,
all of our previous lives are
coming together into critical
fusion. So that s above, so
below, s without, so within. So
that as the world enters deeper,
more and more deeply into this
crisis, there is an inner
gestation which is taking place.
So I think that where this is
taking us is that we are
literally giving birth to the
soul in history. And by the
soul, I mean the consciousness
that integrates all of our
previous lives into a singular
consciousness. Usually we only
make contact with the soul when
we're dead, when we enter the
Bardo. We retain, we recover,
our full memory. And we usually
give that memory up when we are
incarnate. We shrink our memory.
But if we keep that process
shrinking and expanding,
shrinking and expanding, sooner
or later, I think inevitably,
the process is not just towards
more sophisticated individual
egos, but to the birth of soul
consciousness on the planet
intact, so that our
consciousness never is tempted
to shrink to the limits of just
this body, just this individual
of physical embodiment, right? I
think we're giving birth to
soul. And so many people are
feeling this. They're feeling
this kind of deep awakening in
their in their body, in their
psyche. And I think there's a
relationship between the crisis
that we're all facing on the
planet, so that the global to in
a nutshell, the global crisis is
actually the womb which is
engendering what I call the
birth of the diamond soul in
history. And the diamond soul is
simply my way of language. And
what many people are intuiting
that consciousness of a higher
order, a more complete order, is
manifesting in time.
Chipper: And by order, I'm, I'm
going to assume that you're,
you're talking structure.
Chris Bache: Structurally
conscious of itself, yes, yeah,
the deep identity, the soul
identity, is emerging underneath
the egoic identity, and it is
absorbing and bringing to
fruition egoic identity. I
think, I really think, like many
other people, I think we are at
a cusp. We literally cannot
afford to stay at the egoic
level of conscious evolution,
because ego is a divided
consciousness which leads to a
divided world, which leads to a
competitive world, and a world
of rampant consumption and
violence,
Chipper: right, in order to
aggrandize that ego. Yeah.
Chris Bache: I mean, a divided
consciousness leads to a divided
world and an awake
consciousness, an integrated
consciousness, a soul embedded
consciousness, which is
conscious of the breath of our
existence, conscious of the
breath of of mind, leads to a
compassionate world, leads to a
world which is first healed and
then carried forward into, I
think, into in the creation of
new cultural forms. I think we
are just, we are really on the
cusp of creating an entirely new
cultural form, as many of your
your your participants in
previous conversations have
pointed to, right?
Chipper: It does seem to be a
widespread topic of conversation
these days.
Susan: Yeah, Chris, for years,
I've been feeling like we've
been approaching a collective
initiation process. Yeah, and we
may have to do it individually
to kind of get the ball rolling,
so to speak. But also that as
individuals do it. It's done for
the collective yes and but also,
is the collective doing it to
individuals? Yes?
Chris Bache: I think, yeah, the
relationship of individual
consciousness and collective
consciousness, particularly in
this evolutionary pivot that we
are making is really the
dominant theme of my second
book, dark night, early dawn,
where, here I'm talking about
the dark night of the soul and
the dawn of the rebirth
consciousness. But here the
emphasis is not on the rebirth
of the individual or the dark
night of the individual soul,
but the dark night of our
collective soul. Let me just
back up and just give you my
particular perspective here,
when I I reached a certain point
in the early stages of my own
psychedelic work where I had
already gone through a series of
death and rebirth experiences at
the individual level. Had had my
ego shattered in the different
ways that it shattered in this
type of work. And then what
happened is that I entered into
what I would describe as the
ocean of suffering I began to
have just for years sessions
where the suffering that I was
confronting was not personal,
the suffering was collective,
just vast tracks of human
suffering of all sorts of
different orders of magnitude,
just shattering levels and And
first I was I asked myself, What
are all these people doing in my
therapy? You know, what's
humanity doing showing up in
work which I had previously
thought of in terms of
individual transformation? And
what I came what I came to
understand over time is that I
may have thought that I was
doing a process of individual
transformation to maybe
contribute something to the
collective good. But the
universe doesn't think in those
terms. That that the universe,
the game that the universe is
involved with on our planet
right now, is nothing less than
the transformation of humanity
as a whole. That's the game.
That's where we have to go.
That's what's happening. So the
collective psyche is boiling and
is bringing its history forward,
outpouring in all sorts of
historical and social movements
as all the sins and toxicities
of our past are coming forward
naturally, we feel this at an
individual as well as collective
level. And if you do deep
spiritual work, it's people find
in hypnotherapy and in yoga work
and deep meditation practice, or
in psychedelic work, shamanic
work, that they begin to you. To
open up into these vast tracks
of human suffering, which, in my
experience, went on for about
three and a half, four years,
and I began to understand that
the patient in these sessions
was not me. The patient was some
some aspect of the Morphic field
of the human species, so that
it's the collective psyche which
is trying to heal itself and
taking advantage of the
opportunity that I had provided
to heal itself. And I think
that's happening in all of our
lives, that we are all with one
foot in a personal world and one
foot in a collective world, and
so we're all channeling a hen a
healing energy, which is pulling
poisons out of the collective
psyche and putting healing
energy into the collective
psyche.
Susan: Well, this actually
answers a long time question of
mine, because I've had two near
death experiences, and I trained
as an existential and
Transpersonal therapist, and
then practiced at it as one for
years, but I was in that field
of experiencing things that had
nothing to do with me, but, and
I was very aware it wasn't mine.
It was not only the ancestors,
not just personal, but the
collective. And, you know, I
take it back and back and back,
but when you said the universe
may or source, makes use of
those opportunities that makes
sense to me. So if an
individual, through whatever
means, as you mentioned, makes
themselves open or available,
that source is going to use that
opportunity that is really,
really helpful and insightful.
Chris Bache: Wow, that that,
since we're all and I think we
all chose this, we got knew what
we were getting into before we
were born, we chose to enter
into this time in history, even
though we may have forgotten
that choice temporarily while
we're here there. There are no
victims here, and there are no
innocents, in a way we all
knowingly embrace this time in
history in order to be a co
participant in this evolutionary
journey that we are on. And
clearly, the fire is heating up,
and it's bringing out these
collective threads where I think
they probably maybe weren't as
pronounced 1000 years ago, but
they're very pronounced now. Now
my students have, they have
people who are not doing, even
doing this sort of deep,
introspective work. I've had so
many students recognize that
there is more going on in their
pain and suffering and their
healing of their pain and
suffering than could possibly be
explained in terms of simply
their own personal life. And I
was talking years ago to Roger
Wilber, who's you know is passed
on now, one of the great past
lives therapists, and he said he
had come to the same conclusion
that he was working with clients
who were just uncovering so many
lives, lifetime after lifetime
of pain and suffering. He began
to realize that there was that
somehow, in doing past lives
therapy, they had become a
midwife to a healing that was
reaching beyond the soul
history, as you said, reaching
into the ancestors, reaching
into the collective so that
their work may have begun as an
individual soul healing, but it
actually had had changed into a
much larger collective healing
exercise,
Susan: absolutely, absolutely
and like you said, it's speeding
up so much now and it's quite
overwhelming at times for some
people. Hopefully there's enough
information going out and like
our program here that give
people some sort of structure
that they might be able to make
some sense of things, or if they
don't know about it, they feel
that somebody else can resonate
with what they're going through.
Because I imagine if people do
experience it and don't know
what they're going through, that
quite dangerous. It would be
awful. Yeah, yeah.
Chris Bache: And there are times
when, when you want you may need
to step back from the intensity
of this work and and there are
other times, would, yeah, you
just. There are other times when
your life allows you to step
more deeply into it,
Susan: and then sometimes and
just take a break and time to
integrate it all and be you with
it and even see how your life,
whole life, changes as a result
of it, because it will be
drastically changed. Yes, no
doubt about it. Yeah. Chris,
could you tell us the names of
your books and maybe just a
brief synopsis about them?
Chris Bache: The books are the
first one is called life cycles,
reincarnation in the web of
life. It's basically a book on
reincarnation. It looks at
reincarnation through the issue
of the empirical evidence. It
looks at it as a psychological
and spiritual phenomenon, and
then it once it documents the
empirical evidence for
reincarnation. It then asks the
question, so what? What's the
difference if we see ourselves
as reincarnating beings versus
one time through beings? So it's
just one of the early attempts
to explore this, the universe as
a pulsing, throbbing,
reincarnating universe. The
second one is dark, night,
early, Dawn, which is a book in
the philosophical study of
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, specifically
psychedelic states of
consciousness, but integrating
Psychedelic Studies with near
death episode research and out
of body research, trying asking
the question is, the question is
The universe as it shows itself
in near death episode research,
in out of body research,
particularly Robert Monroe's
work at the Monroe Institute,
and psychedelic research. Are
those pictures cohering, or are
they fragmenting? And so
exploring that and exploring the
ways in which our the collective
psyche shows up in the work of
individuals, and the way the
individuals work influences and
contributes to our collective
evolution. That integrated part.
And the third book is called the
living classroom. And all of
these are you can get them on
Amazon or other book sites. The
living classroom tells the story
of it's about fields of
consciousness, collective
consciousness, the subtler
background textures of
consciousness as they surface in
the classroom. Because what I
found over time was, while I I
kept my personal life, my quote,
personal spiritual practice out
of the classroom, because it's
not appropriate to bring it into
the classroom. That was my
weekend work. What I found was
that the work I was doing in
these very deep states of
consciousness outside of the
classroom began to impact my
students in the classroom, and I
began to understand and had to
think about and theorize about
the collective the nature of
collective consciousness, not at
the species level, but actually
at a very intimate level of the
students that I was working
with, week in, week out, year
after year. So it's about
teaching and collective
consciousness. So those are the
three. And now I'm going back to
the topic of psychedelic work
and trying to give some type of
philosophical description or
exploration of that 20 year
psychedelic Odyssey that I went
on between 1979 and 1999
Unknown: this completes Part One
of two of Our conversation with
Chris Bache. You you You You
You.