Chris Bache: So some images, how
do we imagine soul? How do I
ever imagine this reincarnation?
Well, one of my favorites is
what happens in trees we are
eating time, and the more time
we eat, the more soul weight we
put on trees. Do that get bigger
and bigger and bigger and
we have other images nature does
all these
things. We have these suggestive
natural phenomenon where nature
just kind of builds and builds
and spirals on. But images are
imagining the soul for flowers.
And so when I'm with my
students, I ask them to imagine
that each one of those petals
and each one of those pistols
and stamens is an entire life.
So this each one of those petals
is 100 years. Each one of those
little 1000s of Sagan in the
center is 100 years of life. And
the soul is the beautiful,
magnificent integration of all
of that experience into an
identity that is bigger than
anyone, but which honors
everyone. And just as there are
many, many different types of
followers, we're not all
becoming the same thing.
Actually, we're becoming more
and more different, more and
more individualized. We're
cutting ourselves. We're
developing ourselves in
different directions with
different aptitudes. We have to,
but we have to do something to
imagine the soul that we are
underneath something large,
something magnificent and
something beautiful. Many of you
have seen Carl Jung's mandalas
and these beautiful images that
he would draw. Those to me, in
some ways, are like images of
the soul. They're not just
images of the state of common of
mind, but they're images of this
deeper identity that's moving
through so you ready to go to
the next topic, yes, one very
basic question, where are all
this like as the population
increases? Where are they coming
from? Same question,
I answer all of these questions
in life cycles because I wrote
life cycles after I've been
teaching this stuff for 10
years, and the students pretty
much asked every question that
you could possibly imagine. I
try to, you know, get the
answer. Here's way of thinking
of it, the problem of the growth
of the human species, and where
those souls are coming from, is
only a problem if we make two
assumptions. One is that the
number of souls is limited, it's
finite, and that they're really
very small. So in the beginning,
there were maybe 60,000 human
beings on the planet. If we
assume that there were only
60,000 souls, and somehow we
must be dividing them or doing
something to get 7 billion
souls. But here's a different
way of thinking. My university
was at one time we had about
3000 students. 50 years later,
we have 13,000 students, if you
never left campus, you saw the
students coming and going
semester by semester, you would
see that they're more and more
students. You might be asking
yourself, where are they coming
from? But of course, they're
coming from the surrounding
area, because this is a much,
much bigger community than our
than our campus. Likewise, we
have no reason to think that
there are only a small number of
souls. There could be trillions
and trillions of souls. There
could be souls lined up waiting
to get into the classroom that
we're in right now. They cannot
get on this planet until there
is space available for them to
get in. So every semester, there
are some new freshmen and there
are some graduating seniors.
There's a matriculation, there's
some humans who are leaving and
some humans who are coming, but
they're always more souls
available and who are eager to
be part of this exercise. Robert
Monroe, who I talked about in
dark, that early dawn, my book,
second book, and we're not going
to talk too much about today,
but he's an interesting man.
Went out of his body when he was
40 years old, traveled over the
universe and wrote three books,
autobiographical books
describing what the book what
the world looks like from
someone who's been exploring it
in the out of body state. He
says, every one of us is here
because somewhere in our
travels, in the spiritual, non
physical world, we came across a
graduate of the earth school,
somebody who had gone through
this curriculum, and we were so
blown away by the beauty and the
quality of their energy that we
track down how they got that
quick, and we tracked them down
to here, and we began the
incarnational process so that We
could become like what we saw,
so massive, massive population.
He says the majority of
intelligent life in the universe
is non physical. The majority is
non physical. Do you have
questions or hand up here, yes,
yeah, I was born three times,
three answers.
Unknown: Born three pounds,
three ounces. And I was
wondering, would there be any
reason? Because I, you know, I
always said, well, smoking, you
know, my mother like that smoky
environment, like I feel like
I'm getting out of here, you
know, seven kind of thing. But
any reason why
somebody would be born?
So I would be born so premature
and low birth weight?
Chris Bache: I don't, I can't, I
don't know of any kind of
formula that kind of gives us
that, I think reincarnation. Of
course, this doesn't answer all
our questions. It just gives us
a new context within which we
can explore answers and once,
and we're going once we get into
the past lives therapy, where we
have a context in which people
have asked that question, why am
I this way? Why did I Why was I
born with this particular set of
circumstances? And what we find
is when you actually go into the
details of their memory when you
can help them remember the
choices that they made before
they were incarnated. There are
reasons. There are reasons for
everything. What that particular
reason is behind that particular
thing? I don't know, but we have
context in which we can explore.
Yeah, that would have come up.
Yeah, okay, all the all the
various conditions. Why am I
born this way? Why am I in this
family? Why am I in this
context? Why did I lose my legs
in this accident? Why there is a
deeper context? But we have to
get into the soul in order to
retrieve the memories that give
us the information
we need, first here and then
here.
Unknown: Okay, this is Carl. I
don't think this is well, it
could be about reincarnation,
but years ago, I heard concept
of the term called walk ins,
people that come and they're,
they're from there, coming to
watch us.
And I don't know if it's to do
back or what,
but that has never left my mind.
This isn't a book group that I
was in years ago, and I've never
forgotten that concept. Is it?
Is it a concept that's out
there? Do we know of this, of
these people, or these souls
called walking?
Chris Bache: The idea here is
that usually the way to get here
is to be born. You know, you got
to go through nine months of
gestation and become, you know,
go through diapers and go
through adolescence in order to
be an adult. In some instances,
we have some cases where it is,
it seems as if the personality
of a person, of a person, a
child or an adult, leads and a
different personality is
suddenly there. And this, these
are sometimes called walk ins,
that there's kind of a deal
where they switch, where someone
voluntarily leaves their
incarnation, and someone
voluntarily takes over the body
so that they can be here without
going through the whole
gestational process. That's a
complicated topic. Some people
are skeptical about that
interpretation of the walk in
phenomenon. Other people are
more supportive of this idea
that you can have a step in or
walk in, but the basic idea is
that there's kind of an exchange
taking place between spiritual
beings and physical beings, or
between embodied beings and
distance. Embodied beings.
Because if what I'm saying is
true, we already are spiritual
beings, right? You don't become
a spiritual being when you die.
We are spiritual being with our
body. We are an embodied
spiritual being. And then there
are disembodied spiritual
beings. So the normal cycle is
what we've been talking about,
but maybe there are some
variations on
Unknown: that interaction. So it
is a phenomenon. Then you said
the walking phenomena. So it's,
it's that out there,
Chris Bache: it is, it is out
there, and it is discussed, and
it does come up, and it's kind
of a minor thread that does come
up, I was just gonna
Audience 2: ask reincarnation.
I've believed in it forever, and
it hasn't been popular in my
church. So I kept very quiet,
always to myself, but the
question I've always had in my
head was, when is
Unknown: it over. Are there
completed
Audience 2: souls, so that you
keep coming back, keep coming
back, and you learn more and
more and more. But are there
ever, once in a while, I know
what person you guys that I
think myself
Unknown: soul, but I'm not sure
that
Chris Bache: that's a large
question, the classic way to
think. See, we only began. We
became self conscious about
35,000 years ago as a species,
right? And until about 5000
years ago, when we began to
develop the psycho technology to
explore the deep unconscious, to
really explore the nature of
mind itself. We began
meditating. And we began
meditating for 4000 years ago.
And when we began meditating, we
first began to push deep into
the psyche. We discovered the
mother universe. We discovered
Brahman. We discovered the soul.
We discovered this beautiful,
beautiful spiritual reality
which is gestated the physical
world. You know, the source of
the Big Bang. And when we
discovered it, our first
reaction was, my God. This is
magnificent. This is beautiful.
This feels so good. This is
home. This is where I want to
be. I want to be in Myrtle
Beach. Even though I like
Boston, I want to be I want to
be there. And so the religions
that came into existence about
3000 years ago are all
variations on an up and out
cosmology. So we want to achieve
breakthrough. We want to go
home. So we want to be good, to
achieve salvation, so we can go
home. We want to become
enlightened, so we can achieve
moksha, so we can go home. So
it's all kind of up and out and
then, so if it's an up and out,
then you have to what are the
criteria? There must be some
threshold that we must pass in
order that we can get our ticket
punched so we can get out of
here. I understand all those
systems, and by the way,
Hinduism, Buddhism,
Christianity, Islam, Judaism,
all of them fundamentally with a
few variations among the most
spiritually sophisticated
elements, all of them are up and
up cosmology. The purpose is to
get up and away. That leaves a
fundamental riddle unsolved, why
the physical universe? Remember
these pictures we were showing,
why the physical universe? Why
did the divine, or whatever you
want to think of as this, what
was before the Big Bang, when
everything was in that reality.
Why did that reality create the
magnificent, physical universe
that we are part of? Up and out?
Cosmiclogies Leave that
unexplained. It becomes a veil
of tears. It becomes a
challenge. It becomes an
obstacle course, but it doesn't
really explain what the divine
was thinking when he created the
physical universe. I think the
eponopic cosmicologies are
simply the first stage of human
discovery. A more mature
discovery takes place when we
realize, when we wake up, when
we begin to realize we are we
can't we come from this reality.
We are part of this reality. The
physical world is an expression
of this reality. The goal is not
simply to return. The goal is to
integrate that reality and this
reality into conscious presence
wherever we are. So the goal is
to literally draw more of
spiritual the mother universe
into the daughter universe, that
reality into this reality, so
that these worlds become more
integrated, so that eventually
Heaven is a state of awareness.
It's not a place you. Can be in
heaven. On Earth, you can be in
heaven. In the spiritual world,
it's a state of awareness. It's
not a place. Once we have a
species which is able to have
more conscious and continuous
and unbroken rapport between
spiritual reality and physical
reality, then the evolutionary
game changes, and we move into a
new direction. But we're going
to be doing this for another
billion years. We're going to be
doing it for 10s of billions of
years, right? So it's as I
think, when we die, we we get to
go home, we get to be renewed.
We get to be rejuvenated. We
return to source. We all these
wonderful things that we're
about to look at happen. But the
goal is not simply to get away
from all. The goal is to become
more to become more completely,
a more magnificent manifestation
of the creative process itself.
So I'm distrustful of the
criteria which have been
established for up and up
cosmiclogies. To me, that's just
midway and the most
sophisticated spiritual
traditions recognize that. But
the Western thinker, he's
actually a Hindu thinker, who
really drove this point home,
and underscore this very
powerfully in his teaching, is
Sri Aurobindo. Sri Aurobindo was
very critical the up and out
cosmology. And he said not it's
an incarnational theology. What
we need is an incarnational
presence, a greater
incarnational presence, near
death episode research, I bet if
there's if any of you have
looked at the literature for any
of the four areas we're talking
about today, most of you have
probably looked at some of the
near death episode literature.
Isn't that a magnificent
literature, because the stories
are just phenomenal. Here are my
four, my three favorite books
for going into this literature.
And I've taught this for years,
and we all know Raymond Moody
was the one who started it, you
know, and got things going. One
of my great heroes here is a man
named Ken ring. He wrote his
dissertation. He was at
University of Connecticut,
professor in the Psychology
Department. He wrote his
dissertation. His first book is
called Life of death. This is
his second book, Ted internal
omega, and his third book on it
is lessons from the light.
Heading from heading toward
omega is a little hard to find.
It's out of print. Now you have
to do a little digging in the
libraries, and lessons from the
light is still available, still
in print. Ken is a size being,
just a deliciously sweet human
being. He is a very he's one of
the founders of near death
episode, the German near death
episode, study of what was
originally bad oncology. He's a
good clinical clinician. He
probably knows more about near
death episode, research than any
other single person alive today.
His he's got file cabinets and
file cabinets of cases, and he
lets the people speak for
themselves. So chapter three and
heading toward omega, to me, is
one of the most if there's a
person who's really suffering
from death in their life, and
they are. They've lost someone.
I'll zero box. CHAPTER THREE OF
heading toward omega and give it
to them is just, it's 13
accounts of people who have
unusually deep near death
episodes, and also in lessons
from the light. You're going to
get all sorts of research there.
This is the last book he wrote.
There's a chapter towards the
end of it called returning to
the source, and once again, he's
distilled people's case
histories, and he shares their
case histories. There's also a
chapter on near death episodes
of the blind, because we find
that some people who have been
blind from birth or blinded
shortly after they were born,
when they have a near death
episode, they can see. And that
was kind of an anecdote that we
couldn't document, but Ken, he
documented it, and so he
presents the evidence for this,
and he also documents the long
term changes in personality
structure that happens to people
who have unusually deep near the
episodes. So he's been part of
the second generation of
scholars. We're not interested
simply that whether this
happens, we now know it.
Happens. We've got millions of
people. About 35% of the people
who nearly die have conscious
recall of their experience. What
is an in depth Near-Death
Experience? He differentiates
five stages of Near-Death
Experience, and not everybody
has the same depth of experience
some people may experience the
first stage is the feeling of
peace. Then there may be a stage
of separation from the physical
body, the tunnel, kind of
phenomenon we go on to the
confrontation, meeting of being
of light.
So people for a variety of
reasons, not everybody has the
same deep experience. What Ken
does in heading toward omega is
he hypothesizes This is asking
the question, not whether near
death episodes occur. He's
already written a book on that.
He knows that they occur. He's
asking the question, what does
it mean? What is the meaning of
the near death episode? And he
hypothesizes that the most
likely way to understand the
meaning of this event is to
study the people who have the
deepest form of the experience.
And he calls these core and the
ears, they go right to the core.
So it's not simply people who
have separation from their body
going into another reality,
meeting the light. The fifth
stage is to go into the light,
to actually merge with that
light, and to go deep into it.
This is what he calls a core nd
even, and that's where, I think,
where people have the deepest
homecoming experience, the
deepest experience, and then
they come back out of that
experience. And those are the
people who are often the most
profoundly changed by that
experience. And for the changes,
you know, he runs the list of
changes. They're not only
changed by their their values
change. They lose all fear.
That's one of the most
widespread phenomenon. They lose
all fear of death. They become
disinterested in material
possessions. You know, that
whole consumer culture just kind
of falls away. It's just silly.
They become more compassionate,
they become more spiritually
attuned, but their physiology
actually has changed. Sometimes
they can't be around electrical
appliances and computers. They
can't wear digital watches
lights blow out around them. So
there's something about going,
in fact, to source, which seems
to involve an immersion into a
higher form of energy, which
changes people physiologically
as well as psychologically.
Okay, so that he just very
carefully lays them out layer by
layer, and he documents all the
phenomena that we're finding, he
documents them piece by piece.
Can I can I share the beauty of
this is in the people's own
experiences. So how about if I
just read for you one of the
cases that's in in Ken's book.
You Yes,
this one is a case that comes
from chapter 13 of lessons from
the light. And do we have that?
Yes, we do have
Unknown: that book. They have
such a great book
Chris Bache: store. There's a
woman named Virginia rivers,
right? And I'm going to jump to
the juicy part, and she has the
usual she separates from her
body, and he explains why she's
having this episode, and she's
traveling through the tunnel,
and she's bowling through the
universe, and then she comes to
the end of this journey, and she
says, galaxies are flying by her
sensation, and she begins to
receive knowledge. She says,
quote, the farther forward I was
propelled, the more knowledge I
received. My mind felt like a
sponge, growing and expanding in
size with each addition, the
knowledge came in single words
and in whole idea blocks. I just
seemed to be able to understand
everything as if it were being
soaked up or absorbed. I could
feel my mind expanding and
absorbing, and each new piece of
information somehow seemed to
belong. It was as if I had known
already but forgotten or mislead
it, as if it were waiting here
for me to pick it up on my way
back. She goes on a melody man
could not possibly have
composed, yet so totally
familiar and in complete harmony
with the very core of my being,
as if it were the rhythm of my
existence, the reason for my
being. And then she encounters
she goes into the ecstatic state
of great peace, great love. She
says, love poured into me from
all the corners of the universe.
And she eventually arrives at
her end destination. And she
What stands out for her again,
is the experience of knowledge.
She says, all at once, there was
total and absolute awareness.
There was not a question I could
ask for which I did not already
have the answer. Can you
imagine, as I tell myself, the
purpose of life is to get
questions, because when you're
with God, you want to be and you
could have any answer to
anything you wanted to know.
What if you have just cheap, two
bit questions? You want to have
some good questions. Stir it up.
Imagine anything you wanted to
know you could know. I looked
over to the presence. She's with
this light presence I knew would
be there. And thought, God, it
was so simple. Why didn't I know
that? Then she goes on, I'm
skipping pieces. It was God, His
love, His light, his very
essence, the force of creation,
emanating to the ends of all
eternity, reaching out as a
pulsing beacon of love to bring
me home. She puts home in
quotation marks. He told me many
things of which I have little or
no recollection. Now I remember
only two things from all of that
exchange. First, God told me
that there were only two things
we could bring back to it with
us when we died, love and
knowledge. So I was to learn as
much about both as possible.
Secondly, God told me I had to
return. I could not stay. There
was something I had yet to
accomplish. I remember knowing
at that moment what it was, but
I have no recollection. Now,
here's a little bit of a
paradox, two things we can bring
back, love and knowledge.
However, she just made it very
clear when she died, she went
into a state of absolute
knowledge. So we return to
absolute knowledge. But one of
the things that God wants us to
do is bring back knowledge. What
could we possibly bringing back
that would be that would equal
the knowledge that's waiting for
us when we die? You see that
paradox. That's a paradox really
only if we think that the
purpose of life is to go home,
is to return. That's not the
purpose. What if the purpose is
to bring more and more knowledge
into time and space. So the
knowledge that we discover here
we bring back, not to add to the
knowledge that's there, but
because we are integrating here
the knowledge which is freely
available there, the purpose is
to bring more loving more
knowledge here, which we bring
back, because we're sowing there
and here into one being.
Margaret Hiller: Well, it's hard
to talk about this stuff and not
feel like it's an up and out
cosmology, because even the way
you're talking right now talks
about we're going out there to
bring it back here, when, in
fact, like a mandala, isn't it
flowing from and through us? I
mean, we look into ourselves,
and it's like looking into an
atom. We expand back up. It's
all happening here, right? Yes,
okay,
Chris Bache: yes. It's very hard
to talk about it without lapsing
into those old rabbits.
Margaret Hiller: So we don't
really bring something back,
except in our memory, right?
It's all where we have access to
it right now, yes, so when we
talk about bringing it back,
we're bringing it back into
memory or into consciousness,
right?
Chris Bache: I think it's a
both, and I think it's a both,
and I think that plainness, i
Yes, we don't really go anywhere
when we die, but if we were to
die right here, in some sense,
we don't leave the room, but in
another sense, we leave the
room. Them. So it was a monk,
Abraham Asante Club, an
Augustinian monk in the 17th
century, who said, He who dies
before he dies does not die when
he dies. Those who die before
they die before they die do not
die when they die. What does he
mean by that? If there's a sense
in which there's physical death,
and then there's spiritual
death, if we go through the
spiritual death, which is to
say, we drop away the ego, wake
up to our deeper spiritual
knowing, if we go through the
Death-Rebirth process, it
actually changes what happens to
us when we die. And there is a
it's more and more clear that
we're really not going anywhere.
We're just shifting our
register, shifting registration.
So I think the key is we're
bringing more and more of it
here. We're we're changing the
conditions where we're changing
the conditions within which life
takes place, but we're not
really going anywhere. So in
that sense, we're not going
anywhere. Robert Monroe says
he's going out of his body in
the early stages. You kind of
have a sensation that you're
traveling. You're going out. But
then later that disappears. He
says, You just kind of think and
you're there. So it's not that
you're going somewhere where
there is a physical distance to
travel. You're really just
you're opening up to a depth of
consciousness where that reality
is here, right here, right now.
And I think that speaks to what
you're saying. It is all here,
it's all right now, but we just
keep ourselves shielded from it
in some way, so we're just
taking down barriers of our
mind.
Unknown: It sounds like that.
That shape the Taurus, the
Taurus and you expand out, but
where you actually are back in
the center.
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah. We keep
bringing it all back into the
into the center. Yes, here, and
then here,
Unknown: I lost my father. And
the way that I understand that,
or I think about that, and I
think about him being with me
still is, whenever a person
walks out of a room, they leave
behind there's something that
essence or whatever that they've
left behind, that print, that
imprint that they were there.
And that's the way that I stay
in touch with my dad. Yeah, that
makes sense,
Chris Bache: it does. And this
maybe allows us to address
something else. My father died
about 45 years ago. Now,
according to Stevenson's data,
he or his soul was probably
incarnated again. And so one of
the questions my students ask me
is, I really want to see my dad
again. I want to see the bones I
love. What if I died and get up
to heaven and they're already
incarnated? They're not there
anymore. They just left.
But actually, a couple of things
help us understand this from a
larger context. First of all, we
don't incarnate all of our
energy in every incarnation, the
large majority of our souls,
energy stays outside of time and
space, even while part of it
incarnates into time and space.
So the way I would put it for
your father and my father, that
their soul, your father has now
returned to his soul. So your
father is now very much living a
deeper life, a larger life, the
life of the soul, even if that
soul has sent out a distillation
of threads into and started a
new incarnation. When you die,
you you meet your father's soul,
and the face that your father's
soul wears is the face that you
are most familiar with. So
where's the face of your father?
But you are not just you, right?
You are beginning to be your
soul. So it may, in the first
stage, it may be like you
meeting your father or me
meeting my father, but very
quickly, it's your soul
connecting, reconnecting with
his soul. And that's a different
that's a bigger enterprise, a
larger enterprise, so that your
father leaves a trace. All of
our loved ones leave a trace in
us and on the earth. It. But
they are living presence. They
continue to be a living presence
in this larger world that we
encounter when we die so and
we're going to see Michael
Newton is very clear, we only
incarnate a fraction of our at
this present time, a fraction of
our souls energy. And we choose
how much of our energy of the
soul we incarnate into our
present body. He says, If we
incarnated our entire soul in
our present body, we'd shortly
blow all the circuits of our
brain. We couldn't handle the
energy. And that's why I think
we picture great saints and
sages like with this light
coming off of them, because,
literally, they are carrying
more energy than an ordinary
person.
Unknown: Talking about a process
where there is a God who,
through this process of
expansion, expansion
and compassion, is actually
making the souls all more like
God. It's like this expansion, a
bigger expansion and
contraction. That's kind of so
that we do bring heaven on earth
in a new realm, or a new place,
or whatever, and then would
go from there. Yeah. Yeah,
Chris Bache: we're going to see
when we get a little bit further
along. Michael Newton, if you
ask, where does the soul come
from? Where do souls come from?
And the answer seems to be, the
soul is actually kind of teased
out of God. The soul is like the
sun's throwing out silver
flares, and the soul is kind of
the essence of the Divine is
teased out, and it's actually
incubated very carefully. There
are beings whose sole job it is
to catch and nourish that energy
and to and to birth it help it
birth into self awareness that
it starts with the divine, but
it's birth as an individual self
awareness. But it's pure
potential, it's unnaturalized
potential. And then the system
seems to be set up so that that
self awareness begins this
journey of self actualization.
So it has all the potential of
the Divine, but it's kind of
like in potency, not in
actualization, and it's
actualized more and more, and
it's almost as if this isn't
quite the right image, but it's
kind of like God is cloning
herself, and God is just
throwing out stars, and each one
of us is is that the ancient
Greek theologians called It
logos for Monica, you know, the
seeds of the Logos, the seeds of
the Divine, and we're incubating
that seed potential into deeper
and deeper actualizations.
Sooner or later, we develop
enough that we remember who we
are. We remember that our
essence is the divine, and the
essence of everything and every
person we see around us is also
the divine. Holy smokes, we're
all part of the Divine. We're
all differentiating and becoming
more and more, and it's all
taking place inside the divine.
So the classic phrase is from
God to God, always in God. So we
come from God, we go back to
God. Where are we now? We're in
God. We never leave. We never
left, except in our lack of
understanding. So we are
becoming more and more, in some
sense, what we were in the
beginning, but not exactly
because we haven't actualized
it. We haven't brought it into
full conscious expression. And
there's another one other last
thing I want to mention is that
we're going to, I'm going to get
to Newton soon. We'll probably
Newton's people very clearly
suggest that the God of this
universe is not necessarily the
ultimate god. They talk about
God's grandfather, this system,
this entire physical universe,
which we measure in light years,
which is 6 million million
miles, is one light year. You
measure the universe in a
yardstick of 6 million, million
miles and 1000s, millions of
light years across, billions of
light years across. This entire
universe is not the only
universe. There are other
universes. There are many
universes, and there is kind of
a. A being who is the generator
and responsible for each
universe, and none of those
beings are the ultimate,
ultimate being, okay? That kind
of,
yeah. I'm getting ahead of
myself. But when people do, when
people remember what they were
doing before they were born,
they they experience divine
presence, like people who have
near death episodes, but they
don't, they don't draw the
conclusion. They don't use the
concept, the concept of God, to
describe it. Their vision is
that the concept of God that we
are born with and we kind of
work with in our churches, is so
inadequate to describe the
reality that they don't want to
use that language to describe
the reality that they're
confronting, and that this
reality which is magnificent
beyond measures, we saw from
Virginia's experience that
reality is not necessarily the
end reality. It's just the
magnificent reality. This is the
generative intelligence of this
system. So all of a sudden, we
kind of, whoo, we're in a bigger
universe than we even imagine.
Question is, are we safe? What's
going on? Are we are we part of
an intelligent, meaningful
exercise, or are we lost on this
chaos? And I think we're getting
more clearly this awareness that
we are safe. First of all,
there's nothing that can ever
happen to us that will truly end
our life, extinguish life. We're
not hell, by the way. This
disappears out of the system.
The concept of Hell is is
primitive beyond measure, and
we're doing something that's
creative and immensely
satisfying in the long term. It
may hurt the pinch in the short
term, but taking us, if we're
going someplace, we're going
into a developmental process,
it's just profound and
satisfying that it's hard, and
that's, I think that's more
important for us, and to know
the ultimate, ultimate, ultimate
is to believe that this is
meaningful, worthwhile exercise
that we are part of here, and
then back here, could
Unknown: that be why We come
back with knowledge so that we
start at a higher level than we
left, or at not starting all the
way at the beginning again, so
we come back with this
knowledge, so that we can go
further, or perhaps bring back
our knowledge others.
Chris Bache: I think so. And as
long as we keep a flexible
vision, like in college, we may
have a student who decides to
major in math and takes
mathematics courses for several
semesters and gets really
develops a good ability in math,
and then says, Well, I think I
dropped that. I'm going to start
being an artist. I'm going to
try art for a while. Now, they
may be a beginner artist, but
that doesn't mean they're a
beginner student. They're just
beginning a new set of skills.
So you really can never it's
always a mistake to think that
any level of proficiency in one
set of skills is a reliable
barometer of the measure of the
soul that you're dealing with.
Somebody can look like a
beginner when they're not a
beginner at soul level, they're
just a beginner in a particular
discipline. This is your first
time to learn whatever you look
like a beginner, but you may not
be a beginner. Sooner or later,
all of those skills, I think,
will be integrated into one
conscious presence. But the
whole system is we work in
stages. We're working in stages,
one minute at a time. Last
question before I'm going to
read you one more near death
episode, there was a question
here. Somebody had their hand
up. Yeah.
Unknown: It's part of our
development. I've noticed that
if you read books, I like to
read old books, like in the 40s
and 50s, and even before, about
what you're talking about. Now,
there's a book called The
unobstructed universe, and I
think it was done in the 40s or
50s, and it was so hard to
understand. I mean, I knew there
were like little glimmers,
really good stuff in there, but
it was so the person expressing
it, it was so hard. They had
such trouble expressing,
expressing it and writing and so
hard to understand. But now,
like the way you express things,
it's just like in those few
years. The ability to even
express it has gone by leaps and
bounds.
Chris Bache: Yeah, and I think
the more people understand a
particular idea, it actually the
collective psyche is also
understanding that idea. And
when enough people understand
the idea, then it makes it
easier for the next human being
to understand that idea. So it
gets easier and easier, and
people who do past lives
therapy, like when it removes
told me when they were first
doing hypnotic regression in
past life therapy, you had to
take people into very, very deep
stages of trance before you can
get to the level where they
could remember their previous
lives. But over the following
years and decades, they found
that they they didn't have to go
so deep. It was like it was
getting easier and easier to
access those memories. Now, from
Morphic field theory, you know,
from Rupert Sheldrake vision,
the more people acquire a
particular capacity, they not
only acquire it as an
individual, but the species is
acquiring it. So if remembering
our former lives is a capacity,
the first people who remember
their previous lives, they may
have to go very, very hard, but
very, very deep, but it gets
easier. The more people do it,
the easier it gets. So always,
we are always standing on the
shoulders of the men and women
who went before and we are then
becoming the shoulders that our
children and grandchildren will
stand on. Isn't it exciting
unity 200 years from now?
Unknown: But when you think
about it, they will be us.
Chris Bache: Yeah, let me read
you one more dear episode here,
these things are just so
beautiful.
This comes from heading toward
omega, and it's the experience
of a woman named Carl Parrish,
Hanna. Carl, and she, usual, I
skip the early part. She's
traveling to the university
Tolle of light. And then she
gets to, she gets to the
combination part. She says, by
my side, there was a being with
a magnificent presence. I could
not see an exact form, but
instead a radiation of light
that lit up everything about me
and spoke with the voice that
held the deepest tenderness one
can ever imagine as this loving
yet powerful being spoke to me.
I understood vast beings, much
beyond my ability to explain. I
understood life and death, and
instantly any fear I had ended
there was a totality, a
completeness in the realization
that I could continue to
experience and that there was
absolutely no reason to continue
my frantic struggle to exist.
For what seemed to be endless
time, I experienced this
presence, this light, being
pure, powerful, all expansive,
was without a form. And it could
be said that great waves of
awareness flowed into me and
into my mind as I responded to
these revelations, I knew them
to be so. Of course, it didn't
matter if one lived or died, it
was all so clear. There was a
complete trust and greater
understanding of what these
words meant. It seemed whole
truths reveal themselves to me,
ways of thought, ideas greater
and purer than I have ever tried
to figure out came to me
thoughts clear and without
effort revealed themselves in
total wholeness, although not in
logical sequence. I of course,
being in that magnificent
presence, understood it all. I
realized that consciousness is
life we will live in and through
much, but this consciousness we
know that is behind our
personality will continue. I
knew that the purpose of life
does not depend on me. It has
its own purpose. I realized that
the flow of it will continue,
even as I will continue. New
serenity entered my being as
this occurred, an intensity of
feeling rushed through me, as if
that light that's as if the
light that surrounded that being
was bathing me, penetrating
every part of me as I absorb the
energy I sense what I can only
do. Scribe as bliss, that is
such a little word, but the
feeling was dynamic, rolling,
magnificent, expanding, ecstatic
bliss. It whirled through me,
around me, and entering my chest
flowed through me, and I was
immersed in love and awareness
for ineffable time.
Margaret Hiller: That's the kind
of thing we can read our
beloveds when they're in their
passing time. So what a gift
Chris Bache: to be afraid of
dying is to have everything
turned upside down. Dying, I
tell my kids all the time, it's
a great life, and at the end you
get to die. There are some
cultures that warm Earth because
birth is when the work begins.
Birth is when you begin the
class, the session. Dying is
returning home. Dying is
graduation. Dying is recess is
coming in joy. I usually don't
share
Unknown: this, and certainly
didn't 30 years ago, if
Audience 2: you would understand
them, but 30 years ago, I must
die, and I had the
Unknown: Near-Death Experience,
and
Audience 2: I went through those
stages of calm and everything,
and I went up to the to the
ceiling, looking down at my
body, which was in so much pain,
everybody working on me down
there, you know, and the calm
and the everything that was
there and the light was behind
me. I didn't get to go through
the light, and I remember, and I
felt bad about it ever since I
was so and I had two small
children, there's certainly a
reason for me to stay on this
earth. But what I was feeling at
that time was so wonderful, and
the light was behind me. I
wasn't going toward the light,
but it was pulling me, and all
of a sudden, bam, I was right
back in my body with all of that
pain and everything, I was so
angry ever since, because I
certainly came back with a whole
new concept and even energy
spiritual, you know. But still,
I remember being I was ready to
go.
Chris Bache: It was even with
children. There never
Audience 2: entered my mind when
I was there. Though it wasn't
like, oh, I have responsibility.
I need to go back. There was
nothing of that. It was like
complete serenity,
Unknown: complete bliss. And I
was going home, yeah, and then
all of a sudden,
Audience 2: body, I just, that's
first thing. I remember just
being because I had been in
shock, and I just remember being
Chris Bache: angry that I was
and that's and other people
would have shared that
experience, because people, when
they come back, sometimes
they're angry. They get angry
the doctors, why did you bring
me back? And it takes them a
long time, some time, to adjust
to life back on Earth, because
once you touch infinity. I mean,
really, he wants to be a young
stone. Yeah. Ah,
before you were born, you were
in that ecstatic space. You were
in ecstasy. You were in the
light. You were with the divine.
You were in your soul, all the
joy that pulls you so
instinctively, there you were
there, and then you made a
series of choices where you
voluntarily left it in order to
come here. And
Unknown: that's what made you
scrub.
Chris Bache: There must have
been some great purpose for you
to come here, to leave that to
leave that joy, there must be
great purpose that draws us to
here. And some, some mystics,
Juliana of Norwich. You know,
she's a 16th century, I think,
Catholic saint, wonderful woman.
She had a vision on her
deathbed, she had a Near-Death
Experience, and she spent the
rest of her life meditating on
this vision and and she unpacked
it in this book that eventually
called revelations of love,
divine love. And she says, she
says she rejected the concept of
original sin. She said, that's
just not true. God is not angry
of us, and we're not sinful,
we're not bad. She says, God
asks us to come, and God knew we
were going to it's like you send
out your beloved son on a
journey, or your daughter, and
they're going to they fall into
a ditch and they get stuck in
the bottom of the ditch and they
can't get out. And God knew we
were going to get stuck. We knew
we were going to forget. We knew
we were going to get stupid. The
malls were going to be our
favorite places to go.
But we love God so much. We went
where she asked us to go, and
when we when we die, we remember
why. When we die, we touch back
into the foundation, and we are
restored. We debrief, but then
sooner or later, it's time to
come into it again. It's time to
grow, because we're constantly
learning and expanding and
becoming more. And the reason
we're learning and expanding and
becoming more is because our
nature is God, and this is what
God is doing. This is part of
the fabric of existence.
Unknown: Yes, it's amazing to me
that we can have these I hadn't
Near-Death Experience years ago.
It did change my life. What's so
amazing to me is that we can
have these miraculous
experiences, and I've also had
experiences in meditation that
are very similar to some of
these. So you have these
miracles, and then two days
later you're pissed off in the
traffic jam. No wonder we forget
whole lifetime, then you can
have this miraculous
understanding and know that
there's nothing to be afraid of,
and then run up and lock your
doors. That's that stupid thing.
Chris Bache: Time and space it's
tricky, isn't it? I mean, it's
really, it's so dense here, it's
incredibly dense. And it kind of
the bail comes down, and we feel
like we're, you know, we're
trapped again. We're involved in
things. And a weight lifter
becomes strong by putting more
weight on the bar. The weight
lifter doesn't complain about
the weight in the bar because
the weight allows them develop
the muscles. Time and space is
the weight on the bar. It's
allowing us to develop muscles
faster than we would develop if
we stayed in heaven. So, but
it's hard. It's hard being here.
It's tricky being here. There's
more ways, kind of we feel like
there's more ways to go wrong
than the article right? It's
challenging to go here. Thank
God for unity. Thank God there's
a place where people can go and
put these pieces together and
and find their way back to this
deep sanity, which allows them
to live not only with a measure
of dignity but your enthusiasm
to actually consciously embrace
the challenge of being human,
instead of feeling like you're
being punished, or you're
exiled, or this all this
nonsense, we're exiled from
paradise. No, I mean, you can
understand where that came from,
but no, that's just not right. I
mean, you know, God is right
here. God wouldn't send us here.
The Goddess wouldn't send us
here without giving us all means
available to make it work. Now
it's time to take a break for
lunch before we go
Margaret Hiller: down, before we
go downstairs for this
incredible lunch that Miss
Charlene has put together for
us. Some of you are clamoring
for us to receive the donation,
and if you're making.