Unknown: You are listening to
part two of Two of our
conversation with Chris Bache.
You
Susan: Chris, now, Chris, you've
mentioned this crisis or pivotal
point for humanity, and what
insights or experiences have you
gained as from that, from your
psychedelic work about this
crisis or pivotal point, and
what do you see as the
evolutionary trajectory of
humanity as a whole coming
through that?
Unknown: Well, that is a big
question, isn't it? That's a
huge question, and it has
absorbed a lot of my time and in
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, it's been one of
the recurring themes. And
because what happens when you
when your individual bubble of
consciousness dissolves when the
drop opens you, you fall into
the divine at different depths.
And one of the things that
happens, I think, is that one
falls into deep time. So one
falls out of linear time into
the deeper expanse of time. So
the the universe seems to have
many different time signatures,
and one can experience arcs of
time over 1000s and 1000s of
years as if it were a simple
hour, and even hundreds of 1000s
of years and so as I dissolved
at the individual level, I was
drawn into repeatedly into the
evolutionary arc that underlies
my individual existence. I was
drawn into the arc of human
evolution as a whole, which is
just, of course, one layer of
the larger evolution of the
planet and solar system so on.
And just as I was drawn into
these large episodes of
collective suffering, when I
would spin out, when eventually
these would peak, and I would go
through some large combustion,
Death-Rebirth process, when I
would spin out into spiritual
spaces, ecstatic experiences, or
the deeper warp and woof of the
universe. I was often drawn into
our head. Various visions are
drawn into the experience of
what's really taking place
behind the scenes, and that is
the this evolutionary crescendo
that's building in time, this
breaking forth of this deeper
consciousness in history that's
breaking forward into time and
eventually in in the 55th
session Out of a 73 session
series, I had an extra ordinary
experience in which I actually
what seems to have happened, as
best as I can understand it, is
that at some collective level, I
went through the Death-Rebirth
of our species. It it was I was
in a state of consciousness,
hard to describe, but I was at
that time. I was literally
billions of people
simultaneously, and every
individual and all billions at
the same time simultaneously,
were beginning to go through a
life death crisis that was
literally global. It was just a
profound restructuring of life.
Life was being broken down to
the very core. It was, I think,
in this massive die off that's
that's coming down to us. Which
is simply the fallout of our,
our ecological foolishness.
Susan: So this was just an
existential death. It was a
physical possibility as well.
Unknown: Yeah, this was an
entire species brought to
extinction, brought to the very
edge of extinction. This is,
yeah, this. This was being taken
into the very essence, the depth
of this historical crisis, which
seemed to be peaking somewhere
in the 21st Century. And this is
an imminent kind of crisis, and
it looked like, in the center of
this crisis, it looked like we
would all die. It looks like
this was this. Was it. This was
the end of it. We were going to
go extinct. And then when it was
like being on an island with a
hurricane coming over, in the
end, everybody was forced to
just hunkering down and holding
on and hoping that they weren't
being blown away. And it looked
like death was inevitable, and
then at the in the last minutes,
suddenly the storm crested and
passed, and there were
survivors, and survivors began
to find each other and began to
reconstruct. But then what
happened was the most extra
ordinary explosion of of new
social structures, new forms
that had that reflected the
birth of a new consciousness
that was literally birthed by
the pain of our near extinction
event, and out of this trauma of
a species brought to the very
edge of extinction, There was a
a tearing away of what is in
essential and and a birth of
what is essential. And I this, I
think of the birth of soul
consciousness, but not just a
birth of soul consciousness. Or
put it this way, the nature of
soul consciousness is to know
the truth of our
interconnectivity. It is to know
the common ground that we all
share. It is to know our place
in the universe and our
camaraderie with all other
beings, not just human beings,
but all other beings who share
this planet that sprang into an
augmented capacity. It sprang
into an empowered position, so
that when we began to
reconstruct our lives, we
weren't really reconstructing we
were creating a new culture. We
were creating new social forms
that were reflecting new
realities that had been birthed
in the throes of this crisis.
This was a shattering and a
profound experience for me,
because it took me. It took me
several years, really, to absorb
the experience, because it's
like, it's like being in
Hiroshima, yes, on the week
before the bomb goes off, and
knowing that every human being
that you see on the face of the
planet is about to go through a
nightmare of great suffering And
then to and to have so much, so
profound, much profound respect
for these beautiful beings who
volunteered to undergo this
crisis as part of our collective
transformation. And then in
years following, as the work
continued, and I continue to go
into this. There were several
episodes where I entered into
deep time and spent time with
what I call the future human.
Just had the opportunity to be
with this new archetype that's
coming forward in history, and
it's only in the experience of
the future being that humanity
is becoming, that we really
begin to understand the larger
evolutionary trajectory and what
we are actually giving birth to.
It's, it is as if we're going
into labor. Yes, we we didn't
know we were pregnant. It's only
in seeing the baby that we
really understand the whole
gestational process. So nature
has been gestating this human
being for 100,000 years. I mean.
Ever since Sapiens emerged on
the scene, we've been behind the
scenes gestating the next layer
of our evolutionary story.
Susan: Well, you're perfectly
describing the prenatal Peri
matrix outlined by Stan Grof too
and it's, but it's just on a
collective level,
Unknown: so on a collective
level, and this the future human
is, is such an extra, ordinarily
beautiful being. I mean, it's
just when I focus my mind on it,
even now, it brings me to tears,
because it's, it's a humanity
healed of its divisive history.
It's a humanity of all of its
wounds resolved. It's a humanity
with its with its heart
completely open at a deep and
profound level, in collective
embrace. It's a humanity with
its mind open into deep
communion with the
Transcendence. It's a humanity
where war ends and and
cooperation and collaboration is
the norm. It's a planet that has
outgrown its its divisiveness,
and has entered into a time of
history of collaboration, not
monolithic, safe sameness, but
tremendous creative
collaboration, where we begin to
consciously cooperate with the
divine, rather than
unconsciously cooperate with
divine.
Susan: And this is what you've
termed the diamond soul.
Unknown: The diamond soul Yeah,
because our Yeah, this birth of
this new human on the face of
the planet.
Susan: I've also heard it termed
homo luminous, which sounds
about the same. And do you think
that this is not just our human
evolution, that this
reverberates all through the
beingness of the source, that
this is not just about us,
Unknown: it's not just about us,
and whatever is happening on
this planet, I'm sure, is
mirrored in similar processes
that are taking place in other
planets and other solar systems
and other galaxies, so that this
gestational process is a natural
process. It's simply an
extension of evolution reaching
a new critical point. Yes, and
that, and everything we're
learning about the evolution of
our galaxies and the universe at
large is that whatever is taking
place here in one way or
another, is taking place in
other corners of the universe.
So we are
Susan: just send our fields out
further and further and further
we start to get a feel for what
you're saying.
Chris Bache: Yeah, we are cosmic
citizens. We're not only global
citizens, but we are cosmic
citizens, and I'm sure there'll
come a time when higher orders
of community, intergalactic
communion will emerge as part of
the natural sequence. Whether
so, of course, many people
believe that's already begun and
and maybe it has, but it's
almost an it's inevitable that
it will be part of our future.
Susan: So beautiful, Chris, so
beautiful. Thank you for that,
Chipper: and it'll speed up the
more of us cooperate with that
process.
Unknown: Yes, it's speeding. It
speeds up. The more we
collaborate, the faster it moves
for us, individually and us
collectively. That's the other
thing that emerged from that
critical session I described,
and that is an understanding of
how we actually we have a huge
distance to travel as a species,
and a very short period of time
to travel that distance. And
there have been many people who
have pondered, how can we
possibly change as much as we
have to change in order to
survive in as little time as the
ecological crisis seems to be
giving us to change. And I think
the key is understanding the
collective dynamics that are at
play that it's it's not simply 7
million, 7 billion individual
minds that have to change at
core, it's this collective mind
of the species which is
undergoing a change. So if you
take what we know about fields
and. Fields theory and non
linear systems and tipping
points and catalytic points, and
you make the assumption that the
collective psyche is in some way
a unified field, and that what
we know about non linear systems
applies also to the collective
psyche, then we can understand
how we might actually make it
the as far as we need to travel,
as quickly as we need to make
the traveling. And that is all
the suffering and all of the
confrontation with our divisive
ways are not simply registering
on our individual psyches, but
everything that the individual
registers is fed into and
registers at the collective
level, and that when enough
individuals come to a tipping
point and begin to choose a
different way of living
themselves, individually, Sooner
or later, the species comes into
a tipping point, and at that
point, 100th monkey phenomena,
kind of thing, the pace of
evolution accelerates
exponentially. The new common
sense emerges.
Chipper: It's like playing chess
with koyana scotsie
Chris Bache: Yes, yes. And
that's why programs such as
yours is so important, because
just because of the depth and
breadth of the outreach, the
number of synapses of our
collective brain, that you're
able to bring together, the new
technology is just opening up
exponential increase of
understanding
Chipper: in your advanced
sessions, I'm going to change
back to a question here, you
experience various permutations
of the Divine and domains that
lie beyond the story of
humanity's evolution and beyond
all form but the Other
intimately related. Would you
share your experiences and
insights with us regarding that?
I mean, you have been all along,
but with a specific focus
Unknown: on Yeah. You know, this
is hard to do without sounding
like a mad man, yeah, well,
that's the that's the challenge
of even trying to speak about
psychedelic experiences, because
it's so it expands exponentially
the frame of a conversation that
unless you're willing to enter
into that conversation, it's
just and Since I live at a
university. I know how easy it
is for very intelligent, well
educated people to write off
this entire conversation, sure,
but so if we let go of all of
that and go into the possibility
that one can open up to the mind
of the universe, then the most
extra ordinary story begins to
unfold, the invitation here.
There's so many ways one could
put it, I don't know. The
invitation the privilege is to
experience the ways in which the
universe is alive in depth that
are hidden, to simply physical
consciousness, to enter into
archetypal reality, and I don't
mean that in a narrow Jung Ian
sense, but to enter into the
flows of intelligence, the flows
of consciousness, the flows of
life that actually are giving
structure to and giving form to
time space itself, to go outside
of time and space to go enter
back into time and space to just
to be drawn into, in some way,
the intimate, in an intimate
way, the very birthing of time
and space as an ongoing event to
experience the enormity of the
intelligence of the universe. I
mean, it's, I mean, we know what
it's like when we're around very
intelligent people. They're just
different than people who aren't
intelligent and but to enter
into orders of magnitude of
intelligence that's actually
behind the universe is a it's a
mind shattering experience. And
to be, to to dissolve, and to
be, for a time, that kind of
being to touch the edges of the
garment of the Divine, is it
just it radically reframes, you
know, one's understanding of the
life that one is part of and
then equal to the entire.
Intelligence is the compassion,
the love, it just it shatters
again and again all frames of
reference, the the love that's
behind the universe is as large
as the intelligence that's
manifesting in the universe. And
you know, this is this planet is
hard. Life is hard. There are so
many there's so much suffering,
and it's such a difficult place
to be, that the very intensity
of time, space experience has
been used to argue against the
the intelligence of that there
is an intelligence and that
there is a love, a compassion
behind existence, but to
actually experientially enter
into communion with that
intelligence and to feel that
love, and to begin to understand
some of the ways In which, once
you open up to the true depth of
the project of an emergent
universe and the depth of the
project of the Divine, then you
begin to understand the ways in
which it there really is
compassion manifesting this
suffering that we have been
going through for So many
hundreds of 1000 years is just a
phase. It's not an enduring
condition. It's a phase that
reflects the limitations of our
species. At our particular time
in evolution, there is a an
ongoing fullness that is
expressing itself. We will move
beyond all this pain generation.
We will move beyond all the the
hate and bigotry of our divisive
ego consciousness and then and
then and then and just there to
be moved to go into experiences
that Stan calls the super cosmic
and meta cosmic void, to go into
the domain of the formless, the
domain that is the great plenum.
Yeah,
Susan: is this beyond even the
creation and the evolution?
Unknown: Yeah, it's where
creation and evolution comes
from. It's it's in, it's
transcending all time and all
space, going into some kind of
fundamental reality where form
does not exist, none of the
forms exist. And it is that
reality which actually gets
birth to all form. So it's,
it's, it's often described as
the void, but it's also the
plenum, the divine plenum, that
it is the it's, sometimes in
Buddhism, sometimes calls it the
Buddha womb, the awakened womb,
the Cosmic Womb. It's the mother
universe. It's it's that which
is just dating everything, which
is because this physical
universe, as vast as it is, as
enormous as it is, and
magnificent as it is, time and
space as we know it, is not the
only universe. There are other
universes. So we have to get to
a radically expanded cosmology.
And all of these universes are
manifesting out of a primal
reality which is formless in
itself, the sheer the majesty of
the mother. She's so beautiful.
Yes, are you so beautiful?
Chipper: With Sri Aurobindo? And
yes,
Unknown: yes, yeah, I think Sri
arrived.
Chipper: Is his super
consciousness, yeah.
Unknown: I Sri Aurobindo, I
think is one of the great
thinkers helping us make the
pivot away from the old
cosmology, the up and out
cosmology, into an incarnational
cosmology. Great, a great
thinker.
Chipper: Yeah, well, I earlier
you had, you had talked about
you would recommend a less than
high dose regimen. What would
you recommend from your
development state at this point
to an earlier self?
Unknown: Yeah, if I were talking
to my younger self, or if I'm
talking to my own children, who
are young adults now, well, I
would recommend it partly it
depends upon what are you trying
to accomplish? I when I got into
this work, what I was seeking
was enlightenment, you know,
like what most of us were
seeking, to be a better human
being, to be more awake and.
Conscious individual being. And
what I found was, if you want to
seek classically, what we mean
by enlightenment, to be able to
become completely open to the
depth of reality in the
immediate moment in a way which
ego yields, and what I call leaf
consciousness yields to tree
consciousness to the transparent
life of the totality. I think
it's actually better to work
with low doses, to work to go
track down the ego where it
lives and the ego lives in
close. It lives on the earth,
and it needs to be tracked back
to its layer. And really working
that means really working with
lower doses, and really taking
it apart bit by bit, integrating
that type of work with with
meditation, various classical
meditation practices, and I
should mention, all my life I've
also been a teacher of religious
studies. So I've taught courses
in world religions and Eastern
religions and comparative
mysticism all my life. So I've
spent my entire life learning
from the sages, and have just
deep, abiding respect for the
spiritual levels of spiritual
realization achieved by the
great masters of and men and
women of all lineages. And I've
always tried to combine
contemplative practice with
shamanic practice. I've became a
Vajrayana practitioner 15 years
ago, and I've tried to integrate
my Vajrayana practices with my
shamanic psychedelic work, and
tried to put those together, but
I found it over time that a lot
was taking place in these
sessions that were not serving
the purpose of individual
enlightenment at all. And I
think that has to do really when
you start working with high
doses, you get involved in a
different game here. The game is
collective enlightenment and and
the game is actually the the
game of exploring the universe.
And I don't think you need to
transcend time or take evolution
back to the Big Bang or be
absorbed in archetypal levels of
reality in order to achieve
enlightenment. That's, it's just
a it's a different enterprise.
As a philosopher, I was drawn
into the enterprise of knowing
the universe. But if we, even if
we focus on that enterprise, I
would do it differently. And
that is, of course, I would, I
would continue to always embed
working with psychedelics into a
daily spiritual practice. And my
the rule of thumb is the deeper,
non ordinary state you go into
on a temporary basis, the more
important it is to have a strong
daily practice, to anchor your
temporary practice, right? So
it's not an alternative. It has
to be grounded in the regimen of
spiritual life, which is moral
living, social commitments,
social relationships, and what
you do every day when you get
up, right? But in working with
non or with psychedelics, I
would alternate, I think I would
work at more strong doses. But I
think working, for example, if
you're working with LSD, 300
micrograms is a lot easier than
working at 500 or 600
micrograms, just to get
specific, yeah, and I, and I
would alternate working with
synthetic psychedelics like LSD
with organic psychedelics. You
know, we all know Terence
McKenna was a great advocate of
Psilocybin and Ayahuasca and DMT
derivatives. And I would
alternate, I would I think
Psilocybin mushrooms, for
example, really helped the body
absorb. It's very it to me, it's
a very physical kind of
experience, yes, and if you're
working with high dose LSD inter
spacing, those sessions with
Psilocybin sessions or Ayahuasca
sessions, can really kind of
help the body and the subtle
energy systems absorb the deep
visionary states you go into
when you're working with LSD.
Because I think of LSD is kind
of a high altitude drug. You
know, tends to in high doses. It
tends to blow you into cosmic
territory,
Chipper: a black diamond run
Yes, yes,
Unknown: and, and, and. There
are other the organic
substances, and the two that
come to mind particularly are
Psilocybin and Ayahuasca really
kind of help the body and ground
these very deep states of color.
Consciousness more completely
into the physical body, into the
mental body, into the emotional
body. So I guess I would do
fewer high dose LSD sessions,
and I would work with the with
an alternate regimen of organic
psychedelics.
Chipper: Well, that does tend to
take the common place away from
it. If you were to alternate, I
can see how time after time
after time of doing a high dose
without the intention that
you've brought to it, of of
expanding rather than just
playing, could get tiresome if
all you were doing was playing.
Unknown: Yeah, yeah. And to me,
it's been interesting. How many
people have felt that if you, if
you work with, let's say, LSD,
that eventually you keep going
back to the same level, and you
just keep re experiencing the
same lessons. And therefore, you
know you sort of, as Huston
Smith said, when you get the
message, you hang up the phone,
right? But that hasn't been my
experience. My experience is, if
you're working in a very
internal way, internalized way,
as long as you were willing to
throw another log in the fire,
the universe will keep taking
you through break point after
break point after break point
and the reason I stopped. I
mean, in 1999 I stopped, what I
call my serious work the very
high dose work. And I stopped
for a couple of reasons, but one
of the reasons was it was
producing too much wear and tear
on my physical body, and
particularly my subtle energy
body. I was literally running
quantities of energy that were
just larger quantities of energy
than even I could handle, even
using these archetypal Vadnais
deity practices. In between
sessions, I just had to step
away. I had to slow down and let
my energy recalibrate and adjust
to what had been, what had been
realized in all these years of
work. And the other reason I
stopped was it I couldn't it was
getting increasingly difficult
to come back, not not
psychological, but it was too
painful, yeah, to come back into
time and space. When one has
gone into the the fields of
diamond Luminosity, they are
just they're so magnificent.
They're so beautiful. And to be
that intimate with the divine,
and then have to come back into,
you know, the beautiful earth,
but the more limited
circumstances of ordinary
consciousness, even
consciousness is being
transformed. That is the real
drawback of what I call the path
of temporary immersion. It's a
it the the methods that move you
more slowly into these deep and
profound spaces allow you to
keep those tart, to keep those
spaces after your retreat is
over, but the path of temporary
immersion punches you ahead of
yourself in a way, right? So,
it's a temporary,
Chipper: yeah? It's just a visit
rather than a move.
Unknown: It's a visit. It, yeah,
you know, Ram Dass said it opens
windows, but it doesn't allow
you to go out the door. It's, I
understand that, and it's true,
but it's a visit that changes
the course of your own
evolution. One Spirit told me
one time when I was backing away
and said, 20 years in, 20 years
out. So 20 years of work in,
don't you can't assimilate that
without expecting to spend 20
active years of assimilation.
And now I actually think it's
even more than that. I think
that when you work in very deep
states of consciousness like
this, it doesn't just affect you
for the rest of your life. It
affects you at a soul level. So
that I think it really would
take many lifetimes to
assimilate the full scale and
scope of what has unfolded in
the work. So it changes your
deep evolutionary trajectory. So
the challenge at this point, I
think, is now that we have these
technologies that allow us to
blow out the levels and to
plunge deeply into these places
of the universe. The challenge
really shifts not from breaking
out. The challenge shifts to
integration, deep, deep
integration. In your mind, in
your heart, in your social
relationships, in your body on a
day to day basis.
Chipper: I guess that's why the
DAO say Before enlightenment
chop would carry water, yes, or
enlightenment chop would carry
water,
Unknown: yes, yeah. Yes.
Cybele: Fascinating. Chris,
would you say that ultimately,
the unconditional love that you
experienced on your journeys is
the lesson that we all need to
learn?
Unknown: Well, to me, love,
unconditional love, unrestricted
compassion is it is the
correlate to oneness. If the
universe exists as a single
entity, if God is ultimately the
fabric of existence, and if
oneness is the great truth
within which we live, then
oneness manifests in all sorts
of ways, but one of the ways it
manifests is in this profound,
emotional, ecstatic embrace of
everything, which is of all
life. You know, the shaman comes
out of Transcendence, cries all
my relations, I Am One With All
my relations with all the beings
of the world. So love really is
of the essence, because oneness
is of the essence, and love is
the manifestation of oneness in
the human heart. So that deep
feeling of acceptance of all
beings and every human being,
even human beings that are doing
stupid, terrible, hurtful,
injurious things to themselves
and to each other, but to not
close your heart down to them
and to hold them in that embrace
of oneness, yeah, I think you're
right. I think one love is, you
know, the breathing of the
universe as one. Thank you.
Chipper: Do you sense this
experience and experiences
others have that are similar,
they co create a meeting with
the divine so we can all
remember what we have forgotten?
Unknown: Yeah, I do. I really
do. I think, you know, the
classic story of reincarnation
is when we die we remember, and
when we're born we forget, you
know, so when we die, you know,
the near death episode research
shows us very clearly, when
people die or nearly die, they
experience a tremendous,
accelerated expansion of
consciousness and a sense of
remembering. How could they have
forgotten the spiritual world?
But then, when we're born, at
least at this stage of our
evolution, we have a tendency to
forget. We contract into these
time space suits the egoic
identity. So these all these
technologies, whether it's trans
dancing or silence or fasting or
meditation or deep tissue
Rolfing, or all these various
methods for loosening up the
shell of our body, mind identity
ultimately opens us into this
more intimate dialog with the
universe, in which, over and
over again, we experience it As
a remembering. So I think
collectively, we are remembering
who we are. We're remembering
what the purpose of life is.
We're remembering, you know,
what the project is. And every
time one of us remembers, it
makes it easier for other people
to remember. So that, I think
collectively, we are really
trying to incarnate a field of
remembrance, which ultimately
converts into, in a sense, a
field of communion. Because when
we remember that there is this
reality there, there is a
universe surrounding the
physical universe. There is a
mother universe. There is a
spiritual reality. It's always
there. It's it's always tapping
at the back of our
consciousness. It's always
sustaining our bodies and our
hearts and our minds. Then
remembrance yields to communion,
really deeper communion. So that
mean, as long as we believe that
the universe was a Dead
universe, who would want to
commune with a Dead universe,
but if it's a living universe,
if it's saturated with
intelligence and saturated with
intentionality, then that's a
universe I'd want to enter into
communion with. So remembering
becomes an ongoing process of
entering into. Sustained
communion, where that which we
are here and that which is the
totality Together, we create
something that's never been
before. Really, that's where
we're in the process of creating
thoughts, feelings, visions,
social realities that have never
existed on this planet before.
Cybele: Yeah. Thank you.
Thank you, Chris. This is
Sabella again. So in all the
work that you did and the
personal transformation you did,
and then you were going back to
the university and being in a
very academic world, how did
your personal transformation and
practice impact how you were in
in the, you know, quote,
unquote, real world and and the
other people, you weren't a
mumble anymore, you know,
Chris Bache: yeah, but you only
get promoted for your
muggleness. You know, at the
universities is a different
order. That's a complicated
process, and it wasn't entirely
comfortable. And I I learned how
to live in two worlds. I mean,
this work, because of its
legally problematic nature,
cannot be discussed openly in
academic circles. It can be
discussed in certain avant garde
circles. It can be discussed in
Bay Area circles and in very
progressive institutions. And
I've taught courses on this type
of work at the California
Institute of integral Studies in
the Department of Philosophy,
cosmology and consciousness. But
here in Ohio, it's it's a much
more conservative environment
and and they have the right to
be where they are. And so there
were tensions between but there
were tensions that ultimately I
found I could work with
creatively, and as my
consciousness changed naturally
who I was or what I was changed,
and that meant the experience of
my teaching, what I taught
changed, and so they're kind of
two levels. One is content, and
then some, there's a deeper
level that has to do with the
energetic being underneath the
content. So content wise, I was
able to design courses where I
was able to discuss some of
these phenomena in a certain
way. So I've taught a course
called Transpersonal studies. So
we studied reincarnation
research, and we studied near
death episode research, and we
studied out of body research,
and I taught a course called
psychology of religion, but it
was really Transpersonal
psychology of religion, and
there I traced the history of
depth psychology, and spent
about a third of the course
talking about Stan grofs work in
psychedelic research, never
referencing myself, simply
referencing The literature and
Stan grofs work so and I've
taught seminars through the
years in advanced Transpersonal
theory, where I created academic
context for students and I to
have conversations about some of
these realities. And my
colleagues have always, you
know, I've always had good
relationships with my
colleagues, and they've known
that I've been out on the far
side left, but they've given me
room to work there. And I found
that if you have student
numbers, if you have if you have
students who want to take your
courses, and if you're a good
citizen of the university, you
know if you do your work, and
you support the department, and
you you work on all the
committees, and you do all the
things that's expected of you,
then you really have much more
room to improvise and push the
boundaries than might at first
appear. So many people have
asked me, how did you get away
with teaching the courses you
teach, you know, at this open
enrollment State University, and
I found that, you know, we
really have much more freedom
and flexibility if you're
willing to seize it than we
might initially think. And there
are other people who are pushing
those boundaries. Tom Roberts,
in Illinois at a state
university, has been teaching
about psychedelics in his
classes for years, and they're
in an academic context where you
pay your academic dues to that
discussion, but there's there
was a deeper process going on,
and that is. As the deeper my
experience became of this
universe, it changed how my mind
works. It changed how my psyche
works, and it changed my energy
in a way, so that when I was
coming into the classroom and
simply teaching things that were
not about any of these things I
was teaching intro world
religions, or introduction to
Eastern religions, or something
like this, it began. I found
that at a subtle psychological
level, at a collective level,
things began to happen between
myself and my students that were
somewhat unusual. For example, I
found that when I would just be
reaching for an example, just to
make a point, to make a
theoretical point, I would reach
for an example, and I'd create
an example out of my
imagination. And then after
class, one day, a student came
up to me, and when he was sure
that there was no one around who
could hear what he was about to
say, the room was empty, he
said, You know, it's strange
that you use that example in
class today, because that's
exactly what happened to me last
week. And I found that that
happened began to happen
repeatedly through the years,
and students were finding bits
and pieces of their life showing
up in my lectures, very in very
precise and exact ways, without
my intending it, without my even
being consciously aware when it
was happening. And not only were
they finding pieces of their
life showing up in my lectures,
but often it was the parts that
were showing up were touching
them in very, very deep and
personal ways. It was as if
their soul was whispering to my
soul, which is passing it up
into my conscious awareness,
pieces of information that they
needed to heal themselves, that
they needed to take the next
step in their own evolutionary
journey. So during these years
when I was doing this work, I
became kind of a lightning rod
of the soul for many of my
students. And this became so
pronounced that I had to
actively, consciously engage
this process and understand it
more deeply and to work with it
so that I would, so that it
wouldn't become too intense for
my students, so that it would,
it would stay within the bounds
of what's appropriate in a
classroom, and that's the story
that I tell in the living
classroom. I tell the story of
that dance that unfolded between
my students and me, and then I
began to understand that it was
more than just resonance between
my students and me. There was a
resonance that was being created
by the field of our coming
together, that there was the
field of a group focused in
intense study actually has an
animating effect on the
individual minds that are
present there in a way which
activates These collective these
are Morphic fields for groups.
And my students, you know, if
the faculty had reservations
about what I was doing or what
was happening, my students never
did. The students were always
there. They were much more
forward thinking, I think, than
the faculty. They always met me
well, and we just had just
wonderful adventures in the
classroom and at the same time,
I could not bring everything
that I knew to be true into my
undergraduate classroom. It just
wasn't fair. It wasn't
appropriate. And so I had to
hold back a lot, and in the
later years of my career, and
I've retired now that holding
back became difficult for me
because I could feel a tension
that literally a catch that
would happen in my throat when
my instinct was always to share
more information than my
circumstance allowed me to
share. And I would sometimes
lose control of my voice for
short seconds at a time was kind
of like a bark. So it's a
tension between the forces that
were holding me in check and the
forces that wanted to express
itself. And this is basically,
you know, I went through I was a
professor for 33 years, and I've
stopped that. And I love being
in the classroom. I love being
with the students, but I've
stopped that in order to write
books that I could not I did not
feel that I could write while I
was working. As an academic
books that are more openly
embracing the hidden side of my
life, the psychedelic side of my
life, which I hope will put me
in conversations with
Unknown: a different group of
adults, more spiritually
informed, more progressed in
their own spiritual evolution.
For two years, I worked as the
Director of Education for a
nonprofit, the Institute of
Noetic Sciences, where I had
many opportunities to speak with
and engage and do workshops with
people like yourselves. People
who have been consciously living
the spiritual life and engaging
these issues are not afraid of
these issues or plunging into
them, these transformative
processes, and I hope to be
doing more of that work in the
last phase of my life. So I've
kind of entered from an astral,
logical perspective, the third
turning of the wheel of Saturn.
My the second Saturn cycle from
when I was 29 to 5860, was my
academic career, and now I've
entered the third cycle, which I
think is really more exclusively
focused on this, these deep,
transformative practices and the
insights that emerge from them.
Cybele: Yeah, it sounds like
your experience with your
students was really beautiful.
Unknown: And I think it was. I
think they were, we were all we
all were touched, and we all
learned many things from them.
In fact, the last third of the
living classroom is all essays
written by my students. What
would happen I have my students
do a lot of writing, and most of
their writing is intellectual,
academic kind of writing, but
every once in a while, a student
would take the chance and write
a more personal essay. So they
would share the deepest, most
profound experience they had
ever had. They would share
stories of their father's death,
or their own conversion
experience, or their own
experience of nearly dying. And
I began to collect these through
the years. I would ask him if I
would could keep a copy of this
to use sometime in the future.
And I collected a beautiful
folder these magnificent stories
of transformation. And when I
wrote the living classroom, I
knew that this was the time to
give these back. So the whole
last third of the book, it's
really a second book is really
students. It's sharing these
students stories with the
public, because they they're
just so beautiful. So I think, I
think it was a very positive
experience for all of us. I know
I learned a lot from it.
Cybele: Yeah, it sounds like
it's the stretching dance of
straddling two worlds in that
way. And then, you know, I think
we've all experienced where you
might know something, but the
person you're talking to is not
ready for that yet. And now
we're getting to have this free
rein to talk about things and
just let people be drawn to it
or not. Yeah, it's really
lovely. Yeah.
Unknown: And again, I think the
the undergraduate students were
much more receptive than the
faculty. I believe that, yeah,
no, they're just, they're just,
they are different generation.
They are already now. They have
this in their bones. They are a
different generation of souls.
Susan: But Chris, don't you
think that those that are doing
this work, enable the newer, the
younger generations to come in
already knowing a lot of this
stuff, because the works being
done,
Unknown: I hope so. I mean, I we
all have different roles in
this, in this evolutionary saga.
And you know, if there is a
seventh generation, as the Hopi
prophecies predicted, and are
the Indigo generation I am, and
maybe some of you are part of
the sixth generation, you know.
And our job is to hold, to break
ground for these young people,
and to hold to create the
container that allows them to
come to a speedier fruition of
their own capacities, of their
own consciousness on the planet.
And I hope that what we're doing
creates an in a very tangible
social structure, but also a
subtler psychic structure, way
creates fields that empower them
absolutely,
Susan: yeah, absolutely, because
it is a collective
consciousness, and what what we
learn or discover affects them,
especially because they're more
open to it, they don't have the
letting go to do like us old
Dinosaurs.
Unknown: Yes, yes, and it's,
it's a complex feedback cycle.
Giving an example, I I often had
the experience where I would
read a book and it would contain
a high experience for me, and it
would give me insight into
something that I hadn't
understood before. I would have
a particular experience in a
psychedelic session where
something new would open. I
would understand something that
I hadn't understood before, and
within a week, a student would
ask me a question, and I would
have an answer, which two weeks
previous, I wouldn't have had an
answer for that was helpful to
them. And I thought, oh, isn't
that interesting, isn't it
wonderful how the universe uses
one person's learning to
facilitate the learning of other
people. And then over time, I
began to realize, wait a minute,
I'm only seeing one half of the
circle. I have the cart before
the horse. I began to understand
that the students need to know
the question that was coming
toward me, the student who was
coming to me was actually
influencing my own field and
causing me to read some of the
books that I was reading and
even have some of the
experiences that I would have
was having, in order to have
something available to them when
they came and actually asked the
question. So, so it's not simply
that I'm doing this work and the
universe is taking advantage of
distributing this information,
but the cycle, it's a circle
between students and teachers,
and I mean that in a broader
sense, that their need to know
was actually seeding my need, my
capacity to understand, so that
it's a circle, and I wouldn't be
reading or thinking what I'm
thinking if it weren't for the
seeding of these Students coming
to me. So at that point, you
truly open up to the mystery and
majesty of the universe and just
bow in prayer to the grandeur of
what's coming forward. We are
all in it together.
Susan: Oh, I love this. This is
wonderful. Thank you. Yeah,
thank you.
Cybele: So what are your
thoughts on the legal use of
psychedelics and therapy and
healing, and what's going on
right now with using
psychedelics as tools,
philosophically cosmic. Lee, you
know, making inquiry. What do
you think is the future of that?
Unknown: Well, I think we're
tilting back in the right
direction. I'm sure many of your
listeners are aware of maps, the
multi disciplinary association
for Psychedelic Studies, which
is a an educational and lobbying
organization which is trying to
change our laws around
psychedelics, and is
successfully moving psychedelics
back into the area of
respectable research, supporting
research with psychedelics,
bringing it back into the
therapeutic arena. I think we
are the this class of chemicals
is so important that I don't
think we're going to lose them
forever. You know, we're going
to step away from these very
repressive policies of the late
60s and 70s, so that we are
going to re appropriate with
this new wave of scholars and
researchers these substances for
their therapeutic potential
sooner or later, as we do that
we will, and I think this is
also happening with as we open
to Ayahuasca, the Ayahuasca
circles, the indigenous shamanic
populations which have been
using psychedelics, not only to
heal psychologically, but to to
engage the universe spiritually
and philosophically. I think as
we re appropriate these
substances for their clinical
therapeutic value, we are also
in the process of re
appropriating them for their
philosophical, illuminating
value. I just don't see how we
can keep pushing these things
away from us, the world, which
reveals itself through
psychedelics, is profoundly
compatible with the world that
we are studying, that we are
learning through science and
it's it's particularly
compatible with quantum theory
and field theory and and all the
sciences which have been given
birth in the post Newtonian era,
in the Newton Ian world, which
is still the academic gospel of
of the universities. The the
universe is a clockwork, and
it's a it's a purposeless
machine which moves. Was by
chance, a necessity and
mathematical precision. But in
the quantum world, where we
pivoted in the 1930s we're in a
very, very different universe,
where intentionality saturates,
the world where there is a
simultaneity fields of knowledge
underlying discrete existence.
This is very much, very
compatible with the world that
psychedelics are showing us, so
that as the intellectual
community really internalize and
absorbs what is truly the
cutting edge of science. It's
less it's more open to the type
of experiences that are that
emerge spontaneously in working
with psychedelics. So I think
that there is a shift taking
place at a very deep cognitive
level among leading thinkers,
which is going to open more and
more doorways to psychedelics in
the future, and I think we can
look forward to a time in the
future when you will be able to
work with psychedelics. If you
choose to have a therapeutic if
you choose to incorporate
psychedelics into your
therapeutic regimen, you'll be
able to do so. If you choose to
incorporate psychedelics into
your spiritual regimen, you'll
be able to do so there have been
a couple of communities in the
United States, Ayahuasca
communities, who have taken
their case all the way to the
Supreme Court and have won the
right to use Ayahuasca as part
of their spiritual practice. So
we already are opening up the
legal doors. So I see it moving
in a very positive and a very
exciting direction. To me,
psychedelics are one of the just
as a philosopher, I cannot over
emphasize how important they are
to opening to facilitating this
intellectual paradigm that's
that's taking place because,
classically, historically, it
took decades, decades of
spiritual practice before one
could have access to these
Transpersonal dimensions of
existence, but psychedelics can
give even a modest individual
short term exposure to the
deeper these deeper textures of
reality, and they allow you to
change your thinking, even if
you can't abide in those
realities. They allow you to
change your understanding of the
world we live in, so that
they're tremendous door openers,
and I think that we won't be
able to turn down the
invitations that they are
extending into us, and that they
will be very much part of this
vast cultural awakening taking
place.
Cybele: Yes, it seems like the
the paradigm we live in, you
know, the Newton Ian physics,
the mechanical clockwork ness of
it. And people have lost the
ability to find new questions,
you know, and it sounds like
psychedelics. It gives the
chance the fish, the chance to
observe the water. And then you
have whole new possibilities of
questions,
Unknown: yes, yes, and
absolutely, new questions, new
opportunities, and it may take
you Once the door is open. It
may take you, not necessarily,
to continued psychedelic
experience, but it may take you
to more traditional spiritual
practices of meditation, yoga,
whatever, but it's a tremendous
door opener. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I
think if you live in the
Newtonian universe, I have
witnessed for decades What a
terrible, terrible, damaging
gospel secular humanism is for
our students. I mean, the vision
is that existence is an
accident. It's a fluke. It
proceeds by chance. There is no
deeper intentionality behind
your life. If you live in a
beautiful, healthy body, you're
lucky. If you live in a in a
body plagued by illness, you're
just not so lucky. The universe
isn't conscious. It isn't paying
attention to you. I mean, how
could, how could that universe,
that vision of reality not breed
all sorts of various types of
personal and social pathology.
And if the universe is
essentially dead, and if we are
essentially just material
beings, then materialism makes
sense. We just try to have as
many experiences and as consume
as many material things as we
can before we die. Because when
we die, we're going to cease to
exist anyway, so who cares? And
that is the gospel which we've
been giving our brightest, most
creative minds for generations.
And now that's beginning to
shift. Now, with the emergence
of an understanding of the way
in which the universe is
actually alive. We can document
its livingness in our
laboratories, and we can have
facilitated experiential
immersion in that aliveness,
then that opens up a profoundly
expanded vision of ourselves,
and it gives us a kind of
leverage to take us away from
this blind consumerism, so that
we can begin to draw our
resources from a deeper
immersion in the universal, in
the universe itself.
Cybele: So for people who have a
crisis of of lack of meaning in
in the world. This could be a
really beneficial Avenue.
Unknown: I think it can be very
beneficial. I think just
reading, of course, is
enormously beneficial. I mean, I
do a workshop sometimes called
no fear of death. And here My
contention is, if you read the
right dozen books, it should
completely dissolve any fear of
death. It should open up the
possibilities of really
understanding the in a new way,
what the meaning of life is,
what the possibilities are, the
potentials are, if you look at
reincarnation research, near
death episode research, if you
look at life between life
therapy of Michael Newton and
where we're regressing people
back, not only to their former
life memories, but to their
awareness of their life between
their incarnations. If you
combine that with research and
psychedelics, I mean this, this
just creates an intellectual
context that opens up all new
sorts of avenues for
understanding the meaning of
life and the purpose of
Cybele: life. That's fabulous.
Thank you,
Susan: Chris, before we bring
this symposium to a close, I'd
like to read something you wrote
in dark night, early dawn, okay,
and you said, I believe that
this divine marriage of
individuality and essential
ground of the masculine and
feminine of Samsara and nirvana
is the dawn that humanity's dark
night is driving toward. This is
the dawn that, if successfully
navigated, will unite humankind
and elevate us into a form that
has never before walked this
earth, a humanity healed of the
scars of history, its ancient
partitions, re absorbed a people
with new capacities born in the
chaos of near extinction. Only
when we have made this pivot,
when our long labor has birthed
this future child, only then
will we fully understand what we
have accomplished, and when this
moment finally comes, I deeply
believe that like all mothers
before us, we will count our
pain as a small price. This
birth is our gift to the
Creator. Thank you for writing
this. Thank you so much for such
a wonderful conversation. We so
appreciate it.
Unknown: Thank you very much.
It's been an honor and a
privilege to spend this time
with you. Thank you.
Chipper: Can I just read a poem?
I may have read it before, I
motion as love's beauty is
moving, standing nakedly and
blushing in photonics, brightly
rushing as love's artistries
unbrushed time in silent
rhythms, crushing sped slowly,
long and in a hush to bring to
rip title lushness out as and of
coupling within flux. Namaste.
Unknown: It's beautiful. Thank
you.
Susan: Chris, could you tell us
the names of your books and
maybe just a brief synopsis
about them.
Chris Bache: The books are the
first one is called life cycles,
reincarnation and the web of
life. It's basically a book on
reincarnation. It looks at
reincarnation through the issue
of the empirical evidence. It
looks. At it as a psychological
and spiritual phenomenon, and
then it once it documents the
empirical evidence for
reincarnation, it then asks the
question, so what? What's the
difference if we see ourselves
as reincarnating beings versus
one time through beings? So it's
just one of the early attempts
to explore this, the universe as
a pulsing, throbbing
reincarnation universe. The
second one is dark, night, early
dawn, which is a book in the
philosophical study of
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, specifically
psychedelic states of
consciousness, but integrating
Psychedelic Studies with near
death episode research and out
of body research trying asking
the question is, the question is
the universe as it shows itself
in near death episode research,
in out of body research,
particularly Robert Monroe's
work at The Monroe Institute and
psychedelic research, are those
pictures cohering, or are they
fragmenting? And so exploring
that, and exploring the ways in
which our the collective psyche,
shows up in the work of
individuals, and the way the
individuals work influences and
contributes to our collective
evolution. That integrated part
and the third book is called the
living classroom. And all of
these are you can get them on
Amazon or other book sites. The
living classroom tells the story
of it's about fields of
consciousness, collective
consciousness, the subtler
background textures of
consciousness as they surface in
the classroom. Because what I
found over time was, while I I
kept my personal life, my quote,
personal spiritual practice, out
of the classroom, because it's
not appropriate to bring it into
the classroom. That was my
weekend work, what I found was
that the work I was doing in
these very deep states of
consciousness outside of the
classroom began to impact my
students in the classroom, and I
began to understand and had to
think about and theorize about
the collective the nature of
collective consciousness, not at
the species level, but actually
at a very intimate level, of the
students that I was working with
week in, week out, year after
year. So it's about teaching and
collective consciousness. So
those are the three. And now I'm
going back to the topic of of
psychedelic work and trying to
give some type of philosophical
description or exploration of
that 20 year psychedelic Odyssey
that I went On between 1979 And
1999 You You You You.