Margaret Hiller: Okay, okay,
Alrighty, welcome, welcome,
welcome, and for those of you
who don't know me, I'm Margaret
Hill around spiritual leader
here at Unity Christ Church.
Thank you. Be guided to here. We
are so welcome to unity, and we
are so happy and grateful that
Chris Bache has returned to
visit with us. I know it's not
just because Ann Marie, our
member and bookstore manager,
happens to be his mother in law.
We know he's here because He
loves us. And actually, I have
it on good authority from Chris
that he really does appreciate
this group. And so Chris, wow.
He comes to us with over 30
years of being a professor in
luminous studies and also a
former Director of Education at
Institute of Noetic Sciences.
He's written several books, and
most importantly, he's been here
before, and we all so respect
and honor you and your
presentation style and presence
and all that you bring to us. So
thank you for being here again.
Chris fish, thank you. Good
morning,
Chris Bache: everybody. Morning.
Everybody. How nice to be back
with you again.
Margaret Hiller: Now, let me
just ask Ross about, do we need
a mic? Because we can, like,
Yeah,
Chris Bache: good question. Do
we? Are we? Okay, noise wise,
how we doing? Everybody able to
hear? Don't be shy about that's
a good voice. Anything lower
than that, anything more
Margaret Hiller: than I can get
the mic, and that may help.
Okay, okay,
Chris Bache: I'd love to talk
about the things we're going to
talk about today, and I just got
oodles of information to share
with you, but the most important
thing I'm going to be trying to
do is interest you in reading
some of these books, some of
them you will already have read.
Some of them will be new to you,
but the richness is actually
going into the material and
reading it yourself firsthand,
because I'm just going to be
summarizing the categories and
touching on some of the things
that I won't be able to take you
to the richness of it, which is
really people's lives,
experiences, the actual
experiences. I teach at a state
university in Ohio, and you
know, the religion of the
university today is a secular
university. Today is secular
humanism. It's material
reductionism, it's flatland or
metaphysics, where the
conviction is that the physical
world is the only world that's
real, and anything, any talk of
a world behind the physical
world is just fanciful
speculation. But even in a more
progressive environment, there
is still this, this perception
that my students come in with
all the time, when we start to
look at this information, that
we really can't know what
happens to us when we die. We
can speculate it, think about
it. We can have theories about
it, and some of them are
suggestive, but we really can't
know what happens to us when we
die? That's beyond the pale of
knowledge. And I think up until
about 30 years ago, that was
probably true. That probably was
the case, maybe in Western
culture. But I don't think it's
true today. Today, I think we
have the emergence of
disciplines, new disciplines
that have sufficient momentum
behind them and a convergence of
their data that is really taking
the question of what happens to
us when we die and placing it in
a new context, an empirical
context, and We really are
beginning to get sustained
insight.
Unknown: Okay, all right, go
ahead and start talking.
Chris Bache: We all you haven't
worked the volume, sustained
insight into the
larger cycle of life, the larger
cycle of life, the larger
patterns of life, only part of
which is what happens to us when
we die. It's not just what
happens to us when we die, it's
what it's that cycle of life
where we keep coming back and
we're going to go into where we
go when we die, and where we're
coming from when we're born, and
what the larger pattern is. So
today is just a sort of a an
introduction to four areas of
research, which, if you the more
you read in this material, the
more it just your any residual
fear of death just evaporates.
And I've been watching students
taking them into this material
for decades, and I've watched
their lives be changed because
they be the more. More they
understand, the less they fear,
and then more they can
consciously participate in the
life process, rather than
feeling like a victim or feeling
like we really just don't know.
We're just kind of hopelessly
trapped in our ignorance here.
So the areas we're going to look
at today four areas of research,
each one of which is a whole
course unto itself.
Four Areas reincarnation
research topic I talked about
when I was here
Margaret Hiller: last time. Oh
Chris, hold it up next there. We
go.
Unknown: Figure out for the
library, why
Chris Bache: near death episode.
Research, people nearly die, or
they die and they come back life
between life therapy, which is a
sort of a subdivision of past
lives therapy, and it's very
specific kind of track within
the past lives therapy,
tradition and psychedelic
research, the research which our
government has made illegal in
1969 but before they did that,
it had about 1500 years of
history among Native American
traditions, among Brazilian
traditions. So there is a there
is a massive amount of data that
the anthropologists are
cultivating, and now psychedelic
research is starting, is
resuming again. There's a whole
new generation of young scholars
that are beginning, a whole new
wave of psychedelic research
now, each of these areas
contributes a certain piece to
the discussion. I think you'll
see that there's an overlap in
the material, but each of them
bring out a certain set of
concepts, which puts new pieces
of the puzzle on the table in
reincarnation research. Here,
the concept is the larger cycle
of life. It's it's not just that
we come back, but it is the
larger vision of the soul that
is implicit in the vision of
reincarnation. It really has to
do with how old are we and what
kind of time frame are we
looking at to understand life.
It's really a matter of the
fundamental understanding of how
life works at the nuts and bolts
level, in the second category,
the Near-Death Experience
category. Well, there's a lot to
learn here, but the main thing
first we're looking at is what's
it actually like to die from we
know what it's like from the
physical side. You know what
that exit looks like, but what's
it like in the interior side?
What is the experience of life
like? Of the experience of death
like? Because if reincarnation
is true, then there's a
revolving door, there's a birth
is the entrance, death is the
exit. But what's it really like
to die? And at least we get some
insight by looking at people who
have gotten closer than you and
I have, and then who have been
pulled back by technology and
sampling their experience. And
we're looking at now millions
and millions of human beings who
have had these experiences, and
we've been looking at them now
for 30 years, 35 years, and so
we're getting a lot of good
empirical studies with them in
the life between life therapy.
Here I say we're looking at the
community of heaven. Here we're
getting some insights into the
actual structure of the social
world that we enter when we what
are we doing in between death
and birth? How are we spending
our time? Who are we spending it
with? What's the structure of
reality that we enter? And we're
going to see Michael Newton's
work in life between life
therapy is giving us insights
into this reality, and it turns
out those insights are very
congruent with the insights of
our mystical traditions and deep
spiritual traditions, the
Tibetan embargo, the Book of the
Dead, and the studies of the
Bardo. There's actually a
convergence here between ancient
and modern. And lastly,
psychedelic research. We're
looking at Sacred medicine,
journey, work, sacred medicines
with cultures much wiser than
ours have long known that there
are certain substances, certain
chemicals, which are. Sacred.
They actually. They amplify
consciousness, they expand
consciousness. They give us the
opportunity to enter into a
conscious communion with the
larger world. And these go back
1000s of years, and this is a
lineage which is very important
to me, because my whole
professional life has been spent
really exploring this particular
territory. Even given the
legality in the legal issues,
makes it kind of complicated,
but it allows, it allows us to
push the philosophical questions
into new territory. And I think
you'll see that there is a
positive correlation between
what we're learning from the
sacred medicine work and what
we're learning from these other
non psychedelic areas of
investigation. So the primary
thing I'm going to be doing
today is going to be taking you
into a recommending for your
consideration 12 books. I've
tried. I've asked myself, What
are the three most important
books, the books that would be
the most enlightening for you to
read in each of these four
categories, and I've thrown in a
couple more around the edges,
just because I couldn't stand
it. I've tried to boil it down
to three books, which you can
pick up and work your way
through and understand them and
go into the material. So I'm
going to lab here. I'm supposed
to tell you the schedule. We're
going to go until about about an
hour from now, about 1115 take a
short break, 10 minute break,
we'll come back, we'll work
until about 1230 take lunch, and
then we'll not let lunch run too
long, and then we'll come back
and run the afternoon until
three o'clock. Okay? And if you
need to step out for the
bathroom all the way, just step
up. And I get excited. So if I
get overtime and I lose track of
time, someone in the time
binder, raise your hand. Let me
know where we are, and questions
are appropriate all the time,
anytime along the way, interrupt
me, because that's when it gets
the best. Okay? Ready to go?
Okay, we'll begin with
reincarnation research. Now, the
first two books I'm going to
tell you are not part of the
three, but I couldn't resist not
putting the first two is this
book by Ian Stevenson, who just
died recently, so he's watching
from the bleacher seats now.
Margaret Hiller: And Chris, I
understand you have the book
list for us as a handout this
okay,
Chris Bache: just going to make
your work easier. I don't want
to write down so much. Every
good book I mentioned today is
on this list, and so you can
just check off the ones you want
to read and bring the list. She
can order them for you, and some
of them we have in our books
tour already. Ian Stevenson,
university Virginia has
published over a dozen books on
reincarnation research, and he
specializes in studying small
children two to three years old,
who have spontaneous memories of
what appeared to be a former
life, and, of course,
documenting those memories,
verifying those memories,
excluding the situations where
the children might have learned
that information through natural
means, not through actual memory
of a previous existence. All
those things are where the
research comes in. But Stevenson
is a meticulous researcher, he
has documented hundreds of cases
of children from around the
world who, just when they start
to speak when they're two, three
years old, they just matter of
factly bring up their former
life and, you know, unfinished
business, people, they remember,
people they want to talk to. And
we can, we've gotten these
children back into the family of
the original personality, and
they can identify people, they
can name names, they can they
can recall details of family
history. There's infinite
details of the houses they live
in, of things that happen on a
particular event. It's just
extra ordinarily important body
of knowledge. And Stevenson, I
think, is the Charles Darwin of
reincarnation theory, really, as
reincarnation is an old idea,
like re evolution is an old
idea, but Darwin gave us
empirical facts to assess that
idea, and Stevenson has given us
empirical. Facts to look at
reincarnation. Yes, just how did
Unknown: he get into that? How
did he get
Chris Bache: started? You know,
he was a traditional academic at
University of Virginia. He's in
the medical school there. He
wrote a personality textbook. He
was very traditional stuff. And
then he started encountering
some of these cases. And he had,
I think he had, he's in the
hands and endowed chair head, an
endowed chair. And I think it's
Xerox money or coke money was
behind the chair. And he just,
he put his whole reputation
online. Just found this
fascinating subject. He
recognized that, you know, this
is true, that's just incredibly
important for us. And he just,
he just dug in. He started doing
his international travels.
Audience 2: And there was a
psychiatrist, I forget his name,
he's quite big. He's on Oprah a
few weeks ago, and he talked
about how he was treating
somebody, and she started to
tell the story of her past life,
and then he got into that.
Chris Bache: Brian Weiss, maybe,
yeah. Brian Weiss, yeah. He's
one of the therapists. Now he is
not a therapist. I'm going to
show you a therapist in just a
minute, but he Ian Stevenson, is
not a therapist. He considers
himself a researcher. He's a
psychiatrist. Actually, he
doesn't do therapy, and he
doesn't trust hypnosis as a
source of data. He only wants to
work with people who have
spontaneous memories of what
appear to be a former life.
Okay, a therapist and a woman
who I think is one of the great
danes she also is now beside
Stevenson on the bleacher seat.
She just died a few years ago,
Winifred Lucas, and among the
people like Ryan Weiss and other
past lives therapists who were
on the talk show circuit. They
probably were trained by
Winifred Lucas at some time in
their past. She is one of the
older generation. Got into this
work, very, very early, German
educated. She published a two
volume book regression therapy,
which is just they wanted to
take past lives therapy and
establish a clinical protocol
for training past lives
therapists. They wanted to
standardize the discipline. And
this two volume book is written.
It's, it's an anthology, two
anthologies. It's the who's who
of people doing past lives
therapy up to the time when it
was published in the mid 1990s
and it's just a wonderful
textbook. Now, both of these
books, they're aimed for
professionals. I mean, they're
really kind of aimed. They're
not easy reading. They're not
for popular press. They were
never intended for the popular
press. They're very manageable.
Stevenson is a bit of a bore to
read. When I've taken my
students into his books, they
say, I'm really glad I read it.
I'm never going to read it
again, because he thinks like a
lawyer. He writes like a lawyer,
but that's exactly the scientist
you want doing this type of work
between the two of them is just
extra ordinarily. It moves the
whole discussion of
reincarnation onto a much larger
landscape in every one of these
cases where people have spoken
the past life, what happened
with them that they can identify
with that and say, that was my
life that's I've often wondered
about that. Or are they picking
up something like Ireland to the
Akashic field, all that energy
that's always out there? Are
people tapping into that? Or is
it actually a form of
reincarnation? You know, some of
you know the work of urban
Laszlo and urban at one point,
came up with it because he was
working on the Akashic field and
really trying to establish a
dialog between quantum theory
and field theory and ancient
theory the Akashic field, the
mind of the, you know, the
memory of the human species. And
he proposed that what people
were doing when they tapped into
what appeared to be a former
life, they were actually tapping
into the Akashic field that they
weren't really remembering their
life. They were remembering
somebody's life because they
were tapping into the collective
psyche. And he published this at
the end of one of his books, and
I immediately jumped up and
said, No, no, urban, you're
wrong. And so he and I got the
conversation, and he said, write
it up. And so I wrote it up. And
so he published it. And there's
a dialog between urban and I,
and I argued that that's an
inadequate description of the.
Actual fact, when you get into
the cases, it's a nice theory,
but when you get into the cases,
the detail and precision and the
continuity of memory is specific
enough that I think it explains
more to hypothesize if there is
a continuity of individual
memory, rather than hypothesize
that we are tapping into some
impersonal, collective memory,
and I give all the reasons and
whatnot for the article. And
Urban is a wonderful thinker.
He's a great man. And in this
case, he was convinced. I
persuaded it. And so I don't
think it's an either or. I think
there is a species mind. There
is a collective mind to the
species. There is ways in which
we can tap into that mind in
various contexts, but there is
also an individuated mind that's
alive within the context of the
species mind. And I do think
that, to me, the universe seems
to want, wants to create the
opportunity and to enhance
individuality, we have two
truths that are operating here.
One is the truth of
connectivity, the truth that we
are all connected, the truth
that there are larger patterns
of knowing and there's a larger
connective tissue to the
universe. And we are discovering
that at all sorts of levels. But
the other truth is that the
truth that the universe seems to
want to seed and encourage
individuality. It's a both and
situation. I think reincarnation
speaks to the individuality side
of it, and in terms of why these
children remember and most of us
don't, that's an empirical
question, Stevenson says. And he
says, we don't know, we just
don't have enough research, but
he has a hypothesis. He finds
that about 60% of his cases, of
his children in their previous
life died violently, and the
symptoms of a violent death is a
traumatic ending of life. And
out of the remaining 40% of
majority of those died suddenly
within 24 hours of the onset of
an injury or an illness or they
died with an acute sense of
unfinished business. So a woman
who dies in childbirth, all her
energy is giving birth to this
child wanting to take care of a
child. Our business man has been
working on a corporate merger
for years and years, and is just
going through and suddenly he
dies. So either traumatically,
suddenly, or with an acute sense
of unfinished business. It seems
to create a kind of a pull to
finish that business, to stay
connected. We find that these
children reincarnate faster than
the population at large and
closer to home than the
population at large. Average
time interval between the death
of the first personality the
birth of the second personality
for these children two and a
half years. Average range is 50
miles from the birthplace of the
first personality to the
birthplace of the second
personality. When we do studies
in hypnosis with the larger
population, there have been
several studies studying
hundreds and up to 1000 people,
and we try to get a demographic
for people who don't remember
their previous lives
spontaneously. You have to you
would you have to evoke that
memory and bring it forward in
some way. We find that the cycle
time is much longer,
approximately one life per
century, right? One life a
century, nine to seven years, is
what one research team found.
And so it seems that we're
incarnating faster now than we
did in times past. And it seems
to me that part of that is
because they're sending more
opportunities to have varied
experiences. You know, if you
were alive in the 25th century
Egypt, and then not too much
going on, that's different in
the 24th century, you know, it's
just not a whole lot of change.
But now there's so much change,
so much variety. People are
coming back a little faster. But
if your person dies when they're
65 you know, average 3035, years
of birth time before they come
back into another lifetime. But
these children come back very
fast. Two and a half years. It's
almost like they bounce back.
And they've got an unusual
attachment between these two
lives. One other question, yeah,
are you going to be dealing with
channeling at all? Not really.
That's some of those variations
coming from Yeah, can you repeat
the question? Or at least, will
I be addressing channeling? And
I just hadn't intended to here.
It's just kind. Of it poses a
separate set of theoretical
issues that we'd have to
address. Yes, I just
Audience 2: had a question about
I just started reading your
book, and got about a third of
the way through it. And one of
the things that struck me, and I
haven't read anything else about
it first that I've started, it
struck me that one of the things
you were saying was that that
children, that children are the
ones that seem to be the most
believable, and because they
haven't had all the other input
in you know, so is that where
the research goes then, as I
know, I've read some of them
that you put in later that were
not children. Yeah, it just
seems so much more believable
with the children.
Chris Bache: Two bodies of
evidence, one body of evidence
that comes from Stevenson's
research is all focused on
children, and he likes them,
because some adults do suddenly
develop a spontaneous memory of
a former life. They travel
somewhere, they go to a city
they've never been in before,
and all of a sudden they know
their way around, and they have
that deja vu kind of feeling.
But the problem is that there's
so many opportunities where they
might have accumulated that
information. Normally, it's hard
to eliminate that. Two year old,
we got a better chance of
eliminating the possibility
because we monitor our children
carefully. We know who's had
access we know what information
they've had access to. So that's
a nice population. That's why
Stevenson focuses on that in
past lives, therapy, not always,
but most of the time. We're
dealing with adults, but that's
a different population, because
here we've done something to
awaken a memory, either massage
or meditation, more commonly
hypnosis. So there we're dealing
with a different population,
which generates a difference, a
different body of data, and we
have to sort of sift that data
using different criteria, and I
discuss the differences in those
two populations in life cycles,
yeah,
Audience 2: I just want to say
one other thing. This is just
kind of a funny thing that
happened to me when I was
reading your book, and I was
reading it last night, and it's
always been in my head that I
used to be an Indian. What you
know, but I went to sleep after
reading your book, and during
the night, I got to be an Indian
all night. I thought
Margaret Hiller: to myself, Oh,
is that? What
Chris Bache: was that? I'm sure
it was just a dream. Carnation,
yeah. True, then just think of,
look at everybody in this room.
Just imagine how many centuries,
millennia of experience are
tucked inside these bodies that
we have. And what's the most
natural thing in the world that
something might awaken a
particular memory. It's just the
most natural thing in the world.
Once you understand that inside
you, your consciousness and your
body, your habits of mind, are
grounded in 1000s and 1000s of
years of history, and when and
your relationships are grounded
in 1000s of years of history.
It's like just you start living
in a different time, saturated
universe, and you start giving
yourself permission to embrace
some of the things about your
life that have always been
there, but maybe you never
really embraced because our
current system, which said
you've only been alive as long
as this body has been alive,
didn't give you an explanation
for why it's there, like this
interest in Indian culture,
aptitudes, alright? So this is,
I'm not even talking these
aren't the two I want you to pay
attention. It's you're looking
for your first encounter with
this material. What the kind of
here are my favorite books on to
go into what is Roger Wilber,
who died just about two years
ago. He's now open to bleacher
seats. Hey, Roger. Roger was a
Jung Ian therapist. Jung Ian
therapist got involved in past
lives therapy. He became one of
the great past lives therapists.
He's trained hundreds and
hundreds of therapists, and if
you are looking for one book by
one therapist who takes you into
the methodology of past lives
therapy takes you into cases,
discusses those cases in a very
intelligent fashion, gives you
historical background. He's a
good historian. He's a wonderful
therapist. This. Is my favorite
book. I mean, there's a number
of very good authors writing
people who are past lives
therapists. Brian Weiss is a
very popular one many of you
have read. But to me, Roger is
he's just one of my favorite
authors. In this way, he just,
he gives you cases, he helps you
understand because what's really
important about reincarnation is
not just the fact of it, but
it's the other concept karma,
cause and effect, that there is
a cause and effect relationship
that links us, and it's all
cause and effect. I mean,
there's we know our world is
saturated physically with cause
and effect. And Roger is showing
that details the way our psyches
are also part of a larger cause
and effect process that we are
constantly drawing upon a matrix
of causation which creates
conditions within which we
experience life, how we think,
how we Feel, whether we're
introvert or extrovert, whether
we're attracted to sports,
whether we like mental games,
physical games, whether we like
bonds or brunettes, whether we
are we have to create a will
die, or whether we're kind of a
goal on kind of guy. These
things, everything has cause.
Everything has history behind
it, so much so. But by the time
you read enough cases, you begin
to realize everything comes from
somewhere. Nothing comes from
nowhere. You like cooking, if
you like Carl, if you like
adventure, if you are a home
body, if you're a foreign body,
everything comes from somewhere.
Things which you were naturally
good at, they started somewhere
in a small experience, which
then was cultivated and then was
cultivated until eventually it
manifest in the life as a
natural aptitude. Mozart started
writing his music when he was
three years old. If you ever
listen to his first concerto,
when this is written by four or
five year old child, you know,
how does that kind of knowledge
present itself in this genius?
Well, in one time true, we have
no real way to explain that. We
hypothesize genetics, but in
reincarnational framework, it
said, This is not his first time
with music. He's worked music
before. His aptitudes are there,
and we find this is true with
people who are, for example,
good with guns. There'll be a
case somebody's good with guns,
always had an interest in guns,
always been a good shot. Well,
turns out that, you know, he's
got history with guns. He was a
marshal of a previous life. He
did this or that the other So
Roger Wilber is just one of my
favorite authors. It's an easy
read, and Anne Marie has this
one in the bookstore. Yeah, I
just
Unknown: want to ask, since you
mentioned karma, the definition
that I keep hearing over and
over recently is much more like
retribution. It's like you did
this, and this gets that the
original definition that I that
I knew of was that you hate
getting opportunities to learn
something, and if you don't
learn it, you get another
opportunity to learn it. Would
you clarify for us,
Chris Bache: karma has a bad
reputation when it's put into
Puritan cultures and there's a
vengeful God in the background.
And karma is like Whitman shape,
you know. And all karma means is
that which causes. It means a
volitional Act, a chosen Act,
which which causes the pair is
actually karma, the pop up,
cause and effect. So cause and
effect. It's just cause. It's,
it's totally neutral. It's,
there are some causes, but if
you die by being thrown off a
horse and you have a phobia of
horses in your next lifetime,
that's cause and effect. It's
not because you did anything
wrong and you're being punished.
It's just neutral cause and
effect. If you cheated somebody
in business, and your next
lifetime, you find yourself
being cheated in business.
That's karma, cause and effect,
which has a moral quality, but
perspective. That's why, in life
cycles, it's going to come up on
the screen in a minute. I
differentiate between moral
karma and non moral karma, you
know, it's just karma. Is karma.
It's just cause and effect. We
have had a tendency to interpret
karma in terms of punishment,
but punishment, you know? So my
view of the universe is the
universe is not interested in
punishment. The universe is only
interested in growth. Growth is
like, you know, if you fail a
student on a test, you're not
punishing them, you're just
giving them feedback on what and
they haven't learned certain
things, and you give them
opportunities to learn it again.
So anything which is not learned
in one lifetime, you'll have
opportunities, not necessarily
in your immediate life, but in
sub subsequent life, to learn.
We also have a very linear
concept of reincarnation, so
life a leads to life B, which
leads to life C, which leads to
life E. Turns out it's not
nearly that simple to me. Life
is like playing cards. You got
52 cards in the deck, but your
hand only has five or seven
whatever card depending on what
you're playing. You may have 100
lifetimes behind you, but in one
life, not all of those 100
lifetimes are equally relevant.
Only some of those lives are
relevant to this particular
life. So they are the major
lives for this life. What's
going on with all your other
lives? They're kind of like in
the background. They're kind of
like in the choir, waiting. You
know, they're just kind of
quiescent. So in one lifetime,
in the 21st Century, the threads
of your what you're dealing with
may, may come from your most
recent life, but not
necessarily, it may come from
the life of the 17th century, a
life in the 14th century, a life
in the 10th century, and those
threads kind of come together
and are woven into the issues
that you're challenging yourself
with in this lifetime. And I
also tell my students it's a
wrong formula to think
reincarnation gives you an
opportunity to get it right.
That's too short a time frame.
The universe isn't interested in
just you getting it right. The
universe is interested in
building galaxies, building
solar systems. It's interested
in, I mean, the universe thinks
in time frames of billions of
years. Why should the universe
be only concerned in a very
small 100,000 year time frames.
The universe is creating giants,
giants of soul, and so it's not
getting it right. That may be a
short term. It's really about
the open ended development of
our capacity over vast stretches
of time. It's about creating
genius. It's about just creating
more and more and more potential
inside the human form. So it's
much more open ended than we've
had a tendency to think in the
past.
Margaret Hiller: I love the
phrase you use last time you're
here, that reincarnation is the
universe's way to roll forward
information and intelligence. Am
I remembering?
Chris Bache: The universe is
like ecology. It wastes nothing.
Everything we learn is rolled
forward into future learning. It
just keeps somehow, the way I
see it, you know, evolution is
up to a time the universe is
learning expresses itself in
creating a whole new species.
You know, species evolve
together somewhere along the
line, sufficient consciousness
is concretized to produce
individuals, and then evolution
can evolve not only whole
species, but it can evolve
individuals within the species.
But the principle is the same in
both. It folds forward the
learning of the group, or the
learning of individuals, into
future manifestation. So
basically, nature recycles. It
always is folding out. Holding
our learning forward, taking it
someplace we haven't been
before.
Audience 3: It saves everything.
I've been hearing a lot about
empirical knowledge and data
collecting. Where do you place
the concept of all right, a lot
of people's journey right now is
getting to a higher level of
consciousness, developing
yourself spiritually. Where do
you place? Intuitive knowing you
know not anything gathered from
books, but an intuitive knowing
and a feeling of rightness. This
is right, and it rings true, you
know, and it may go against the
mainstream of modern thought,
you know, and even
reincarnation. And then your
inner knowing says this is what
I believe. Regardless of what's
out there, there's an inner
knowing that's telling you this
that
Chris Bache: is one of the many
qualities which we're
developing. Up, and you know
what? Our consciousness faces
out and consciousness faces in,
right? So we're learning a whole
lot about what's out there, and
then other people seem to be
more, kind of more concentrated
on learning to trust what's in
here, going deeper within, and
learning to listen and learning
to affirm the voice that rises
from within. Creative artist,
you know, intuitive scientist,
good parents, just learning to
trust the voice which rises from
within in their circumstance,
our culture doesn't support that
very much right now, because we
are so oriented towards external
verification. But if knowledge
phase is in and certainly the
memories of your previous lives,
which give you the texture of
what you perceive to be true,
what you feel to be true, then I
think developing that inner
intuition. You know, it's
critically important, really
important. I'm going to put the
other two books up here, just to
keep us a little on track,
Carl Bohm and Anne Marie has her
work. She has two books, and
this is her first book. Carl
Bohm is an interesting woman,
very grounded, very matter of
fact, a nurse got into this kind
of only because her own child,
she had a child. She wasn't
really interested in
reincarnation, but she had a
child who started having
nightmares, started having
nightmares and night traumas,
and like any mother you know,
want to take care of her child.
And she began to pay attention.
She began to read. She began to
understand Stevenson's work and
reincarnation, and she was eight
long story short, she was able
to help her child uncover the
trauma that was disturbing his
sleep and helped him make that
conscious and remember enough of
it, and then it washed through
him, and it left him alone, and
it healed him. And she began to
realize that if this is true for
her child, there must be other
children out there. Stevenson is
not interested in healing
children. He's interested in
documenting the cases, but there
are other children who are
living unresolved issues from
their most usually, their most
recent life, and she began to
help put things up on the web.
And when she put things up on
the web, she started getting
hundreds of people writing her,
saying, My child is like this.
Can you help me? And to make a
long story short, she kind of
became a clearing house for
cases and information of work
from parents who were concerned
to help their children deal with
memories that were disturbing
them in some form or another.
And I find her a very grounded
person. She's really she's well
read. She documents her sources.
Well, it's an easy read. It's a
very inspiring read, because her
cases are just so provocative.
She wrote a second book. What
was the name of it? Do you
remember Andrew read it?
Children from heaven, or
something from heaven? Memories
of heaven, something I uh, she
became eventually, you know, she
now, this is what she does
professionally. But I love cases
where people just come out of
the from the bottom up, where
they didn't, weren't trained in
this, but they kind of just come
out of the circumstances of
their life. If you read this
book, I think you'll see that
kind of woman. She just is a
compassionate, competent she's a
nurse, and she has one story
after another of children and
she has and she's speaking to
parents. She says, What? How do
you how do you treat a child who
has a spontaneous nightmare?
What's the best way to do and
her advice is, attend, listen,
encourage, and you don't have to
worry about it. You can trust
that the system is going to work
itself out. If you push it away,
it'll stay. If you let it into
the room, it will resolve
itself. It will come forward and
resolve itself. And it's not
injurious for children to have
these memories. You don't have
to worry that they're going to
be overwhelmed with something
that they cannot handle. The
system is self regulating in a
very wise and profound way. And
life cycles is the first. First
book I wrote. Now this is, I
guess that's was published in
1990 so it's, it's been around
for a while. It's over 20, close
to 25 years old. As a young
academic, I found Stevenson's
cases really important, really
powerful. So this book,
basically, there's a chapter on
the evidence. And I summarize
some of Stevenson's cases, and I
try to make them more reader
friendly than Stevenson does.
And I summarize about, I think,
four or five of his cases, and I
summarize about four or five
cases from past lives therapy,
and draw from different people,
but basically my position after
we get past the evidence
chapter, my position is there is
overwhelming empirical evidence
that reincarnation is a fact of
life. What do we do now? What's
it tell us? What's it say about
what difference does it make how
we live our life? What does it
tell us about our identity? What
does it tell us about our
relationships? Turns out, the
biggest chapter in the book is a
chapter on reincarnation in
Christianity, and because it's
because most of my students were
in my classes, they were coming
out of a Christian background.
They read Stevenson's book. They
were convinced by the cases, but
their religion told them that
they couldn't accept these
cases, and they were caught
between a rock and a hard place.
And so I wanted to sort of say,
well, you know, do you think
Christianity could ever
incorporate this evidence?
Christianity first rejected
evolution, but now, you know,
all sorts of thinkers are
showing us how you can integrate
evolutionary theory with
Christian principles. Could
Christianity ever incorporate
reincarnation evidence, and what
would it look like? What would a
reincarnation affirming
reincarnation Christianity look
like? So I outline what I
consider the minimum and a
maximum option that's available
for people who come out of a
Christian background. And
there's a chapter on the family,
you know, how it changes our
thinking about having children
and the children who come to us,
because from this perspective,
we don't create our children,
you know, and the qualities that
are in them are not simply the
sum of the qualities of the
parents or our
grandparents absolve. They are
whole and complete unto
themselves. They bring the
lineage unto themselves. Our job
is simply to help them unfold
their potential and help them
actualize the being that they
already are. And if you approach
children in that way, I think
you get better results than if
you expect them to stay close to
the root of your family
tradition, it gives us more
permission. So there's just all
sorts of topics that I try to I
also address. There's a chapter
on what's the Did Jesus teach
reincarnation? There are some
people, you know, Jesus did
teach reincarnation. My first
love, academically, was in New
Testament research, and I
learned Greek and Hebrew. I
mean, I really want to get close
to the original sources, and I
don't think there is sufficient
evidence right now that compels
the conclusion that Jesus taught
reincarnation, but there are
some very interesting,
provocative possibilities. And
of course, in many of the
Gnostic Gospels, it has Jesus
teaching reincarnation, and in
many of the early communities of
the first 200 years of the
church's life, reincarnation is
a very common idea in some of
these communities. So are women?
The role of women as equal to
the role of men in the church?
But we know what happened to
that one. You know, that went
out by the fourth century, and
the reincarnation belief was
that went out in the sixth
century, the second Council
Constantinople, they kind of put
the kibosh on that one. So I
asked the question, Why? Why did
reincarnation? Why did
Christianity reject
reincarnation when it was
circulating, that's a version of
the gospel in the early church.
Was it? Is it because it's
incompatible with anything Jesus
really taught? And I rely on a
man named Gettys McGregor, who's
a Scottish theologian who's
written numerous books on
Christianity and reincarnation,
and his position is Christianity
rejected reincarnation for
political reasons, not for
metaphysical reasons. In a
nutshell, in the context of the
fourth century, the Roman Empire
is falling apart. The Visigoths
are at the gate. Everything is
collapsing. The church has just
barely gotten a foothold in the
culture of the Roman. Empire
that just been welcomed on
footing with the pagan
religions. Things are just
beginning to look up. By the
fourth century, and all of a
sudden, the Roman Empire is
falling apart and society is
fragmenting. We're on the eve of
the Dark Ages. In that context,
the church, I think they were
doing, trying to do a good job.
I think they were asking the
right questions. They asked,
What would Jesus want us to do?
What does Jesus want us to do?
And they became convinced that a
secret to the survival of the
church lay in a highly
centralized authority, and they
create model on Roman
government. So you had the
Emperor, you had the Senate,
Carl, bishops, and so on, so
forth, down to the people. So it
was a vertical, top down system,
highly centralized authority,
Grace flow through these
channels you couldn't have it
wasn't coming up. It was coming
down through a narrow set of
channels. In that context,
reincarnation, you can see
threatened that centralized
authority, because if
reincarnation and karma are
true, everybody is ultimately
responsible for their own
salvation. You do not need
priests, you do not need
bishops, and you do not need the
Pope. Everybody is working it
out on their own. They thought
that was just too it threatened,
if we went this way, would be
weakened and diluted. And they
basically said, we're not going
to go that way. We're going to
keep it highly centralized.
Okay, if that worked for the
fifth, sixth century. But does
that work now? Right now, I
think that's holding us back,
because, to my way of thinking,
the belief that we only live one
lifetime is actually
reincarnation. Is the missing
piece living in an intelligent
universe. If you believe that
God is intelligent, if you
believe that there is wisdom in
existence, if you believe that
there is compassion in
existence, but you believe that
we only live one time, and you
can't see it. You can't see the
intelligence of life. If you
believe we only live one time,
you can't really see the
compassion of existence. If you
don't understand the fact of
reincarnation, once you kind of
open up to that possibility,
then you can look at these
pictures that we saw at the
beginning of the talk of these
galaxies and Nebula this vast
expanse, and you can begin to
see the causal matrix where the
intelligence is expressing
itself inside Our lives and
inside the circumstances we find
ourselves in. And so if
Christianity had a reason for
rejecting rebirth, for its
survival at one point, now, I
think if we reject rebirth, it
undermines their teaching of a
compassionate, loving God. And I
personally, I think
Christianity, I think this
community is a symptom. It's a
sample of Christianity pivoting
on that past and opening up to a
new a new understanding, a
deeper understanding of the
gospel. So if you read these
three books, and you can always
go back to Stevenson and
Winifred Lucas, but if you read
these three books, the vision
that opens is that life is a
cycle, and the way I like to
think of it is expansion and
contraction. When we die, we
expand into soul awareness. When
we're born, we contract into
individual egoic awareness. The
ego egoic awareness evolves. It
changes over time, but the
rhythm of life is this expansion
and contraction. So you want to
do a quick exercise. This is
what I call the yoga of
reincarnation. Stand up for a
second.
We'll close our eyes in a
minute. But this is what I'd
like you to do. Put your hands
together and picture in the
middle of your hands light now
when you breathe out and expand
our arms, like open them up, and
then bring them back together.
And then just keep it up when
you're ready, close your eyes
and this picture every time you
open your hands and bring them
together. It's 100 years of
time. When you die, you move
into the soul condition. You
remember who you are, what you
are, you. When you're born, you
become small and focused
and picture yourself every time
you bring your hands together, a
different sex, different gender,
a different color, a different
country. Different
language, we die, we expand.
We're born. We contrary, we
you might find that this ball of
light in the center of your
closing hands is actually
getting brighter, because every
time you do this, the knowledge
of the center is growing
stronger, the knowledge base,
the conscious base, is getting
stronger. And if we stay doing
this for about an hour and a
half.
Audience 3: Just imagine how
much light we would be bringing
Chris Bache: into that center.
Now open up your Listen, really,
really fortunately, stretch and
then born into this center. Move
your arms in different
directions. Really open it up,
knock your neighbors.
The Yoga of rebirth, expansion
and contraction.
Unknown: All right?
Chris Bache: Why can't you
remember our former lives as so
great? Why do we forget what is
the purpose of forgetting our
previous lives? Why go through
all that written to die to
remember who we are? The
reincarnation is true, and I
think it has to do, actually,
with it's critical at a certain
point in our in human evolution,
forgetfulness is necessary to
reduce the discontinuity that is
responsible for exponential
change.
Unknown: Say that again,
Chris Bache: forgetting, is
responsible for producing
discontinuity, and the
discontinuity is responsible for
exponential change. So imagine
your God, which is not difficult
for some of you, right? You got
you're creating a system, and
what you want to do is evolve
life into more complex forms as
fast as possible. You could
create a human being and give
them 100,000 years of life,
harvest them and then see how
much he or she has burned. Or
you could create a human being,
give them 100 years, get the
same 100,000 years, but break it
up into 100 year increments, and
every 100 years, change places
on the board. You are a man now
you're a woman. You're a
soldier. Now you're a poet. You
were rich now you're poor. You
keep changing positions in life.
At the end of the same 100,000
years, which one of those two
options is going to produce a
more complex, textured
individual most of us would
choose, I think the 100 year
increments. Why? Because variety
is the spice of life. Variety
causes us to grow in ways that
sameness doesn't How do you
create variety? You have to
create discontinuity. You have
to forget who you were, what you
knew in one life, and begin anew
in a new set of circumstances.
If you didn't remember what,
there would be no learning in
the end, you have to remember
your former lives sooner or
later. But the time to remember
isn't necessarily right here
right now. It's when you die,
then you remember when you're
born, you forget. So it's kind
of like I tell my students, you
know? So if you have a fight
with your boyfriend or your
girlfriend right before you come
to class, you can't pay
attention to what I'm saying.
Your mind is still out in that
fight. You're just not here. I
think you have to forget your
life in order to learn something
new as fast as we wanted you to
learn at a university classroom,
so this forgetting is important
in order to create the
conditions for accelerated
learning.
Unknown: I was wondering I
recently heard a constant of
that of perception. So do we
bring something about our
perception, not necessarily
memories for all of us, but our
perception from our past lives,
like someone was saying that we
have our five senses through
which we see the out of the
world, then we have our mind
integrates the information, then
we take action, but that the
Joker in the deck is our
perception. We all have a
different perception. And could
that perception kind of be what
we bring in from our past life,
even though we forget the life?
I mean, I have no clue, but I
know I have perception that's
been a joker in the deck many
times, and that when I start to,
when I start to see that that
perception is distorted, then
I'm learning, yeah,
Chris Bache: sometimes they're
distorted, it's distorted and
needs to be tweaked, and
sometimes it's accurate and
doesn't need to be tweaked. But,
yeah, I mean, basically you're
pointing to like, what you were
talking about with intuition,
perceptions, gut, hunches,
feelings, all of those things
carry through. We may not
remember the details of our
previous life. I mean, I don't
remember the details of my
previous life this. I didn't
until I started digging in the
basement with hypnosis and
whatnot, but I but they were
still those perceptions, those
aptitudes, those affinities were
still present. Now here's one
other last thought. I don't
think we're going to keep
forgetting our former lives when
we incarnate. I think if you do
this exercise and it's just try
this at home and do this yoga
reincarnation for 1520, minutes,
sooner or later, it seems to me,
if we reincarnate long enough,
often enough, the consciousness
that we incarnate into is
getting stronger, stronger,
brighter, clearer, sooner or
later, it seems to me that the
soul, which is the consciousness
that integrates all of our
lives, that's waiting for us,
that We return to when we die,
that soul is going to incarnate
on Earth, intact, without
amnesia, without loss of memory.
That I think, is the next step
in human evolution, is the birth
of the soul in history. And we
know that the soul we take on
more qualities, more soul
qualities, the older we get.
That's why we talk about
someone's an old soul, someone's
a young soul. We know what we're
talking toward, but sooner or
later, I think we're going to
see we'll look back and we'll
see that this forgetfulness was
actually part of the design. But
that doesn't mean we're trapped
in it forever and ever. See the
way the system, the way
reincarnation is believe now is
that once you achieve
enlightenment, once you achieve
some type of spiritual
breakthrough, once you wake up
to the divine being that you are
and we all are, then what
happens you leave the system.
The Hindu first Hindu concept,
of reading of enlightenment was
Moshe. Moshe means escape,
escape the physical world,
escape Samsara, escape into the
spiritual world. But to me,
that's that's just the first
approximation. That's a first
understanding the ultimate goal
is not to escape. It's to wake
up here, so that heaven becomes
the condition on Earth, so that
eventually we will be born and
we will not forget. We will have
complete knowledge of our entire
history, and we will have a
deeper communion with the
spiritual universe. We won't be
estranged from the physical,
from the spiritual reality. So
just because we forget now
doesn't mean we forget forever.
Audience 3: Yeah, going along
with this is a quote from Thomas
a campus. The Ring. If one knew
all, one would forgive all.
Chris Bache: The past, if one
knew all, one would forgive all.
Yes, what you just
Unknown: said about the ultimate
goal was that we would remember
everything.
Audience 2: How does it? It does
not fly in face of what we were
just talking about then about
it's good that it's like that
because we don't remember, and
we have all these different
hundreds of newer experiences,
being different people, being
different things, and we put
those all together, and all of a
sudden you've got this wonderful
universe of knowledge. However,
what happens then, if we become
people that can remember all of
it all
Unknown: the time? Does that
what happens
Margaret Hiller: next? Yeah,
does that kind of limit our I
having
Unknown: all the different
experiences and being have the
massive knowledge. You
Chris Bache: see the question,
if there is a reason for
forgetting, then what happens if
we don't have to forget anymore?
And it's very clear, all of a
sudden, we're playing a
different game. The game has
changed. It's a different system
with different rules. We don't
really know what that those
rules are going to be like, but
I think the system differs that
we will be playing a different
game. And I think, personally, I
think that the system is, we all
know we're in a global systems
crisis. We're all know that
we're at a dead end in history.
We all know that we can't keep
going the way we have been
going, or we're going to go
extinct as a species. You know?
I mean, I hope that's not news
to anybody here. This culture,
this culture was created by the
ego, which means this culture
was created by a fragmented
psyche, a piece of knowledge
that's the only reason why
people can be happy themselves,
personally, why so many other
people are suffering is because
they only experience a very
narrow portion of the mind. They
don't experience other people's
pain. It's their pain. But if
we, if we were to become fully
conscious and fully in communion
with this deeper underlying
connective tissue, we would
create a different world, we
would create a different
culture. And I think there's a
tremendous psychic pressure
building, just as economic,
ecologically, economically,
politically, we know we need to
create a different world.
Spiritually, I think we are
growing into a different
identity, and I think these two
are reinforcing each other, so
that I think if we don't wake up
at a soul level, we probably
will go extinct at an ego level.
If we were to wake up at the
soul level, we would become a
different species. We would
become a species of Buddhas and
Christ, we would become awakened
being. And then ask yourself,
what could the human species
accomplish if we truly were
awake, as Christ was awake, as
the Buddha was awake, what could
we accomplish clearly we changed
the planet. There'd be nothing
that we couldn't do if that
happens. So I think we are in
the process. I think the design
is to push us into this deeper
sense of identity, so that we
have a deeper sense of
inclusiveness, so that we can
create a world as one author put
it a world that works for all
this, what I call the birth of
the diamond soul. I think we are
in the process of birthing the
diamond soul in history. And the
diamond soul is simply my way of
languaging the identity which we
have been cultivating for
hundreds of 1000s, possibly
millions of years the soul
identity, but the soul identity
conscious inside time and space.
And I think some of our great
saints and sages were prototypes
of that consciousness. That's
why they they teach radical
terms. They teach about the
family of humanity and the
oneness of God and the oneness
of life, those don't make sense
to egos that awakens in us, this
intuition that we know is true
because our soul knows it's
true.
Unknown: Yeah. Just reminds me
of a son who I call an idealist,
but he's got a lot of anger out
there about the psych guys, that
conspiracy thing, but he's
really saying what you just
said. He thinks you shouldn't
have to have money. You should
be able to create a world that
works for all. But instead of
being in a peaceful place like a
Buddha monkey, he's Yeah,
Buddha,
Chris Bache: well, I think all
of us have felt that anger. You
know, we feel that anger at
different times. That's,
there's, there's great truth
expressing itself in that anger.
There really is anger is tricky,
isn't it? It'll eat you up. It
really will just eat you up. And
on the one hand, you don't want
to eliminate the truth that
that's in it. On the other hand,
there is, there is, I mean, I
get angry. I get angry at things
like this, but it's not a place
you want to live from. It's not
a place you want to stay from,
and it requires, I think, an
understanding of a larger
landscape in order to put that
give that anger a creative
outlet, give that anger a place
to go, because anger ultimately
has to be tempered with
compassion so that it can mature
into wisdom, so it'll be wise
action, not destructive action.
But it's a tricky thing, because
it's there's a truth there
Unknown: to other people about
what the conspiracy part and
disputing that anger to others.
And I, you know, I see what I
learned for unity is quite the
opposite. What you just said was
so profound because it really
brought tonight. I'm not talking
about the son of something. Me.
I really wish I could inspire
him to be wise.
Chris Bache: He'll find his way
to it. Sometimes it's very
useful sometimes, I mean, I
value deep, introspective work,
so sometimes it's useful to
follow something like that to
its source, to really go into
history, to get at the very
roots of that anger. Because
sometimes, even though, if it's
true, it's an accurate
perception in the world, but
sometimes there's a there's a
cause for that deeper in our
personal history, which when we
get as a cause and clear the
cause of that anger at a
personal level, sometimes it
gives us a little we don't have
to let go of the truth, but we
can let go of the anger, you
know. So there's lots of ways
moving into it.
Unknown: I was thinking that
couldn't not just be anger,
but an elective frustration at
what is and what can be, and
that more people don't get it or
not making enough progress in
the in that direction, and, you
know, and being, you know,
unable to do anything about it,
yeah, and then it just turns
inward, yeah,
Chris Bache: my students are
angry, you know, they're trying
To make their way in the world,
and they know it's not working,
and it's getting worse. The sea
level is rising, the jobs are
moving. They're angry. But how
do you how do you use that
perception in a way that doesn't
eat you alive? So shall we call
the close to the first segment
and Take 10 minutes be back
here? 1130 okay, I'm just
Margaret Hiller: Oh, yeah, what
happened? What time did you get
here?
Unknown: I had to do an
interview, three articles due
today for natural week. Oh.
Audience 3: You okay, and then I
told Mary to be a little bit
late.
Unknown: Looks like they're
recording it. Yeah, be nice to
Yeah,
hopefully make an audio or
something, yeah, yeah.
Good to see you. Yeah,
continuously embarrassed now i.