Unknown: Imminent experiences in
class yet, of when mind and body
and heart and spirit come
together, and I, on a personal
level, feel really lucky and
happy that he's with us this
week. I only know a little bit
about your history of your
life's work. So I'll just let
you speak. Okay?
Come on, people, let it
Chris Bache: rip. Feel how that
changed the energy. Just that
little bit I
don't have time to fuck around
anymore. We don't have time to
fuck around anymore. There's
just not time. There's just only
time to get down to the serious
stuff. So let's get down to it.
Rick asked me to talk about
teaching, like I've picked up
some incalculable secret
knowledge from teaching in Ohio
for 30 years, I don't know, so
I'll just tell you what I got,
and then you can decide whether
it was a good thing. But we're
going to have fun tonight, no
matter what. And you know, I
don't think you wouldn't mind if
we kind of finished before 10
o'clock would you? It's been a
long day. You people have been
working hard. And for me, a talk
is simply an excuse to get to
the discussion, right? Because
that's where the juice is.
That's really where the where
the good stuff is. So I'm just
going to kind of lay out some
bullets, throw out some
material, to sort of focus our
discussion, but I'm really
hoping we can move quickly
enough into some discussion, and
if that goes really well, we'll
still be out of here before 10
o'clock. All right. Yeah, okay.
Is Robert here yet? He's coming.
Here he is fly away among his
many illustrious publications he
did he one of the ones that you
may not come across too often is
his beautiful introduction, his
Prolog preface to the living
classroom, which is a great
honor. And he, he really made me
look pretty good, very good. It
was just an honor. So this is
kind of PCC certified, you know.
And how many people have read
this? Okay, all right, well, I'm
going to hit some bullet points
on it, but I'm going to put it
in a larger context. I'm going
to give you some of the back
story to it, alright, and I'm
just going to talk a little bit
about how I came to write this,
and kind of what happened during
it and what's it about. But this
is like my second Saturn Return
book. I mean, I started teaching
in 79 and this was published in
2008 that's pretty much exactly
29 years and before I was coming
up on sabbatical, because the
only time I can this is a little
loud, doesn't it sound a little
loud? Maybe, no, okay, all
right, the only time I can write
books is when I'm on sabbatical.
I can write essays before, but
takes a lot of time to get in
deep so before I came up on my
last sabbatical. There were two
books that I was thinking about,
a book on psychedelics and the
living classroom. And so I went
into session space, what I
usually do when I have an
important question. And after I
was done with the various
things, I said, What should I
write? And it said, definitely
the living classroom. Because by
the time you write the
psychedelic book, you're going
to be so far out in left field
that you know you're going to be
beyond the mainstream pale. And
now where you are the living
classroom, you can do it in a
mainstream fashion. So I said,
Okay, and as soon as I said
okay, and soon as I agreed to
that, and kind of made the
mental intention, all sorts of
wonderful things began to
happen. I got some grant money
that allowed me to spend more
time writing the book, and just
a lot of wonderful things
happened. And the living
classroom has been published, or
there have been six excerpts, or
excerpts or chapters that have
been published in five different
anthologies. It's gotten more
AirPlay than any other single
thing that I've written, and I
think it's because of Robert
McDermott's Preface. I think
it's because consciousness,
collective fields of
consciousness, is an idea that's
kind of it's bubbling up. Its
time has come. We're ripe for
it. So as the second Saturn
Return, this is a book that the
universe wanted to be written,
and it's basically a summation
of the most important things I
learned about teaching from my
30 years of teaching at young
sound. Now another little
background, when I had my second
Saturn Return and I came to
Youngstown, it broke my heart. I
really didn't want to be here. I
mean, I didn't go to seven years
of graduate school in order to
teach at an open enrollment
undergraduate college about
12,000 13,000 students in a rust
belt town in Ohio, no graduate
students. It wasn't my ideal,
and I tried, like anyone with a
grain of sense, tried
desperately to leave for several
years. Because you know, when
you get out of graduate school
and you come to good graduate
school, you have a few years
when you might jump out into
something. And I tried jumping.
Problem was I had also
encountered Stan's work, and I
started my own psychedelic work
in 79 a year after I started
teaching, my mind got very
quickly radicalized. I mean, one
year I was writing essays on
towards a unified theory of
metaphor. Two years later, I'm
writing essays on the emergence
of perinatal symptoms and
Buddhist meditations like, what
happened? You know, my
department was wondering what
the hell happened to him? They
hired a traditional analytic
philosopher of religion and
linguistic discourse, and
suddenly I'm really saying, Hey,
this guy is onto something
seriously good. Well, it wasn't
happening. You know, Religious
Studies is a very conservative
discipline, and by the way, did
you appreciate our just up for
you. This is just for you. Yeah,
it wasn't happening. And so this
came to a head four years after
I was there four years and there
was a the only job that it had
opened in five years, opened
that year, and they decided to
go with the very traditional
philosophical, theological type.
And I thought, and you know,
when you teach at a teaching
university where you really in
the classroom a lot, you're
teaching three courses a
quarter, nine courses a year,
plus teaching in the summer.
This just pounding, ly difficult
teaching. And I just said, Okay,
I give up. This is not what I
wanted, but it seems to be what
life wants. So I surrendered,
and I said, I'm going to become
the best teacher I can possibly
become. I'm not going to fight
it. I want to work with it.
Let's see what happens. Let's
see where it goes. And it went
in some very interesting places.
And the result of what happened,
basically, I was able to put
down in this book. And 1/3 of
this book is my students, 1/3 of
it, the back third of it, really
it's a second book, are essays
that my students have written
over the years, and just
beautiful, beautiful essays. And
there were hidden reasons I
learned later for why I was in
Youngstown, and I'll get to
those in a bit. And there were
some benefits of being there,
because if you don't have a lot
of graduate students, and you
don't have a lot of
responsibility for that level.
You can do a lot of exploration.
You can do a lot of things. So
if I ever wanted to learn
something, I just said, I'll
teach a seminar on it. And I was
teaching a lot of courses and
things that lay outside my
discipline. I just kind of
learned. I learned a lot of
things, and as I went through
and I was able to do a lot of
innovation in the in our
curriculum, I taught a lot of
what I call Transpersonal
studies. You know, near death
episode research, reincarnation
research, out of body research.
I taught Transpersonal
psychology of religion. I taught
lots of seminars and Stan grofs
work. So, you know, there's a
certain there were some
benefits, there were some trade
offs. And one of the great
benefits was non traditionally
aged students. About 40% of our
students are non traditionally
aged, and that was a nice
compensation for not having
graduate students, because they
were, you know, they were much
more seriously engaging in their
studies than the 1819, year old
kind of might be. But the other
thing that Youngstown gave me
was an opportunity for deep,
spiritual practice. It's
something, you know, there's not
much to do in Ohio. It's kind of
boring, you know, it, you know,
watch the corn and watch the
corn, you know. So it's just
kind of a nice, contemplative,
smooth environment if you want
to do deep, serious work. And so
I wanted, I found out I wanted
to do deep, serious work. So I
started my psychedelic work
right when I started my career.
And I did four intense years,
and then I stopped for six
years, and then I did another in
10 years after that. Now I.
Loved teaching. I've always
loved teaching. I've always
liked to gab, but I'll tell you,
teaching open enrollment
University, it's front line
teaching. I mean, it's the kids
who didn't this first time that
anyone in their family has gone
to college, lot of people
pulling them down, telling what
do you want to go to college
for? You know, just get a job at
GM Lordstown, make cars. You
know, it's what I you have to do
what I call full contact
teaching. This is take no
prisoners. Full Contact
teaching. You have to provide
the motivation. You have to kick
them in the butt. You have to
slap them around. It is like
when I come here to teach them,
and you guys are so easy, you're
so motivated you're already, you
know, it's like you want to
learn these things. You're there
in Ohio. It's a different game.
And so they make you work for
it, and I work for it. I'm
willing to work for it. And
eventually my classroom became,
I began to think of it like a
dojo. You know, it's like,
you're on my mat. No one's going
to get hurt, but you're going to
hit the floor a few times, and
it's like, I don't have time to
fuck around. Let's get down to
it. So 30% of my students who
sign up the first day, they drop
out by the end of the first
week. And I make it real clear,
just to get credits in the
humanities is a perfectly good
reason to be here the first day.
It's not a good reason to be
here the second day, because
it's easier place ways to get
the credit. But I also then try
to show them what we can do,
show them a sense of where we
can go if you're willing to
work, and I find that they're
willing to work, if you give
them a quality product, they're
willing to work with you because
they're they really they've been
damaged often in their high
school. They've been hurt.
They've been crimped. They don't
have high expectations. They,
you know, they're not at
Oberlin, they're not at Yale.
They have kind of low
expectations. If you give them
the promise of something
substantive, they'll work their
ass off for you, and they'll
open their heart if you allow
them to and go there. But when
you start to psychedelics, and
you make the choice to work with
psychedelics, you kind of have
to make some adjustments in your
professional life. I had to
split my life in two. I had a
professional life where I did
the things that you had do as a
professor, and you do all the
traditional things. You serve on
the committees, you do this, you
do that, you publish. And then I
had my personal life where I was
doing the Grof Ian deep
psychotherapeutic work. And you
can't let those two blend in the
classroom. This is not cis All
right, the good people of Ohio
do not like to hear that their
professors are dropping massive
quantities of acid. So you keep
those two separate so I didn't
talk about my work in front of
my to my classes. I mean, my own
faculty members, it was like 10
years before they really got a
an idea of what was going on. I
mean, every when I would do a
session, I was kind of so poor
as a beginning faculty member, I
had to borrow the tape player
from one of my colleagues. He
began to get a sense of what was
going on. But you don't talk
about it. You just I didn't talk
about it for years. I it,
because these were kept separate
in the physical world, it ended
up producing some very
interesting complications or
consequences that taught me a
great deal about the nature of
consciousness, because, as we're
going to see, consciousness did
not split itself, even though I
split my world, the world of
mind is not dividable in that
way. And there were some things
that happened that began to make
those things be connected, but
there are also some personal
consequences. I'll come back
around later about when you
split yourself like this and you
won't you cannot be your whole
and complete self in every
circumstance, and you kind of
know what you're doing going in,
but I didn't really understand
what the some of the long term
ramifications of that would be
down the way. So this is what
began to happen early in my
teaching, student asked me a
question. You know, after you've
taught a course three or four
years, you pretty much have
heard most of the questions that
undergraduates are going to ask.
So soon as they ask a question,
your mind starts running with an
answer. This time, I just
stopped, and I thought among all
the possible answers that I
could give, which what could I
say that would be most in tune
to this student, and my mind
kind of stopped. I. It, and
suddenly I had an image of a
door in the back of my mind, and
a piece of paper passed through
it, and I read the piece of
paper, and it was an idea. It
was an idea, an answer that I'd
never given to that particular
question. So I just Okay, let's
try this. I ran with it, and it
had the magic happened. Teaching
happened. The student's eyes lit
up. Other people's eyes lit up.
The energy went up in the room.
Something good happened. So I
thought, okay, and I really
prepare. I mean, I bring it
look. I even brought notes to
esslyn. I prepare my classes. I
have a lot of notes. I really
work them through, and I keep on
track with my syllabus. I know
where I'm going to be in the
12th week in a course, you know,
because I otherwise anyway, I
really prepare for it, but that
little door in the back of my
mind gave me a teaching about
integrating improvisational
intuition with data with my
prepared work. So I began to pay
attention to that door in the
back of my mind and to work with
it. And when I did, you know,
something happened in the room
that didn't happen when I just
kind of stayed in my prepared
script. And then time passed, I
kept on doing my psychedelic
work. And if you've read, those
of you have read dark net, early
dawn, you kind of know it. You
know, I dropped into some pretty
deep stuff pretty quickly. And
really was engaging deep, deep
collective dynamics and entering
hell realms and the ocean of
suffering I'd talk about. So it
was pretty intense. But wherever
I was on Saturday, Monday
morning, I was back in the
classroom, doing my job. It was
really that was a commitment. I
would not let my personal work
get in the way of my
professional work. I had a major
commitment for my students. And
then one day, when it was just
an ordinary day, I'd been doing
my ordinary thing, teaching
intro Eastern intro world,
teaching psychology, religion or
Transpersonal studies. This was
actually an intro Eastern
course. A student came up after
class, after he was sure that
the room was empty and no one
would hear what he had to say.
And he said, It's funny that you
would use that example that you
used in class today, because
that's exactly what happened to
me this week. And he told me a
story, and it was right, it's
like I quoted his life story. So
that's interesting, you know.
Okay, little synchronistic, you
know, but I never thought of
myself as being psychically
sensitive. I always sort of
think of myself as being kind of
brick ish in that way, I'm a
psychic brick. I don't have
those type of things some people
do. Always envy those people who
have like I was 12 years old
when I had my first mystical
experience, I said, Oh, lucky
you, but it's not me. So I kind
of, you know, I was trained to
brush this stuff off. But then a
few weeks later, it happened
again. Somebody came up and
said, you know, that's exactly
what happened to my mother. And
to make a long story short, the
deeper my psychedelic work
progressed, the more frequently
this began to happen. People
were finding pieces of their
personal life showing up in my
lectures, and I wasn't intending
it, and I wasn't conscious of
doing it. I would just be
reaching for an example to
illustrate a point, and
something was connecting me to
them, and I was like reaching
into their life and putting it
forward. Now, if you're in a
room just looking for three
credits or four credits in the
humanities, and you're in the
back of the room with your
baseball cap on backwards, and
you're just kind of passing
time, and all of a sudden the
professor is using your life to
illustrate a point being made.
How could you not take that as a
personal invitation? How could
you not have yourself snapped to
attention? This began to happen,
not a lot, but often enough that
it kind of became a pretty semi
regular thing in my classroom.
And then the plot deepened when
I began to go into deeper and
deeper territory, when I got
into the deep ocean of
suffering, Death-Rebirth at the
collective level, where you're
just dealing with massive
currents. It's like you're not
dealing with the near shore
currents. You're dealing with
the big tidal flows in the
collective psyche, and you're
getting into deep, deep
collective Death-Rebirth
meltdowns. I found that my
students were being drawn deep.
Deeper and deeper into deep
existential crises in their own
lives. It was like we were all
part of one giant, massive co X
meltdown system. Addictions were
bottoming out bad marriages or
weak marriages were being forced
into, you know, grow or die
situations people were having
suddenly unearthing sexual
abuse, and I don't talk about
sexual abuse, but something was
bringing to the surface deep
pains in their life. I so I
can't emphasize enough that this
was not my intention. In fact,
as this thing began to happen, I
began to even try to slow it
down, because it did not feel
like I didn't understand it. So
I couldn't control it. It was
happening. How do you ensure
informed consent in a process
which is so involuntary? I even
put on my syllabus one time. I
even put caution taking this
course may be dangerous to your
psychological equilibrium. The
students thought I was being
cute.
Unknown: You.
Chris Bache: This thing, I
called it the magic, you know,
the magic happened. I'd come
home and I'd say to my wife, the
magic happened today. You know,
I was just doing my stuff, and
bam, all of a sudden, this
lightning bolt came out of
nowhere and blasted somebody
apart, and all of a sudden,
we're having this intense
conversation after class, and
they're like, they're moving.
Something's moving in their
life, I began to sort of
function like a lightning rod,
you know, there was something
sparking, and at that time, I
didn't understand really what
was going on. I knew it had
something to do with my
psychedelic work, but I really
wasn't prepared for the enormity
of the implications of the
paradigm shift that I was going
to have to make, and eventually
did make, to understand how this
happened. And by the way,
everything that's in the living
classroom, I mean, I had been
thinking about it and wrestling
with it some, but it all dropped
in, intact, complete, in one
psychedelic session, all the
fundamental structure, and it's
what gave me seeing it clearly
in that space, is what gave me
the courage of my convictions to
articulate it, so that it
because if it's happening to me,
I knew it had to be happening to
other people. And it's not
really about psychedelics. If I
were using any type of spiritual
practice that had the capacity
or any that to drop you deep
into the collective psyche and
into that territory. If you open
up at that level, then you're
naturally going to generate a
kind of an energetic shock wave,
which is going to touch the
lives of people that you have
karmic connection to. And I'm a
teacher, so I have a lot of
karmic connections to my
students, this is just if you're
a business person, if you're a
researcher, if you're a
choreographer, if you're working
in the world and you're embedded
in a network of relationships,
and you go deep into that level,
the mind, the universe doesn't
necessarily from one
perspective. It doesn't
recognize individuals. It's like
the weather, it doesn't really
recognize individual atoms or
molecules of, you know, oxygen
and whatnot. It's like, there's
that side of it going, it just
goes. So I began to realize that
I was teaching on two levels at
campus, there was something that
began to happen at one level,
and for the most of the
students, I was just an ordinary
professor. I was teaching the
stuff, and they came and our
relationship was about
information exchange, and they
mostly left pretty happy. But
there was a second group of
students who began to take
pretty much all the courses I
would teach. And they were here
because just being in my classes
began to be a source of
transformation in their lives.
They were here for the energy or
something. They knew that
something was positively moving
in their life. When we came
together to work and again, it
wasn't my intention. Eventually
I this, I began to realize that
there is an energetic resonance.
This is just, it's nothing.
Anything supernatural or
paranormal, it's just normal.
It's just natural. Life is like
that. Consciousness is like
that. Minds are like that. We
it's just an illusion of the
physical senses that our minds
are fundamentally separate.
Well, they are. But there's that
other side, where the, you know,
individual minds emerge out of a
unified field of mind. And when
you come together and you focus
intention, there is a natural
sharing that takes place. And if
one of you is working at a very
deep level, then the universe
seizes that opportunity to
awaken and to heal other beings.
It's not something I was doing.
It was something that the
universe was doing, almost in
spite of me.
Teaching is information transfer
and all that magic that you do,
you know, in the dance of the
dance, but underneath that,
teaching involves the direct
engagement of mind and mind in
the unified field of mind.
Clarified states of
consciousness are contagious.
You cannot help it. It cannot
help it. It just happens.
Negative states are also
contagious, but clarified states
of consciousness are contagious.
Our spiritual ecology simply
does not allow private
realization. If you're beginning
to wake up, there's an energetic
quality component of waking up.
People around you begin to wake
up. And if you're a teacher, or
you're in anything that works,
people where you're working with
groups, you have to be prepared
for that consequence, for that
implication. In fact, you cannot
stop it. There may be a reason
why people do this work in
monasteries, on mountains far
away, because it kind of
buffers, you know, but if you're
going to do this work in the
world, you have to be prepared
to handle the implications of
the consequences of this natural
process. And here's the thing,
by the way, the better teacher
you are, the more powerful this
will, this will happen, because
teaching is that magical
mystery. You know, it's that
resonance. I mean, you're really
you're working communication,
you're trying to organize
intention, you're in the dance.
And if you're good at that, well
then that just makes it easier
for this stuff to happen. You
Yes, so eventually I had no
recourse, but I had to learn
what was happening. I had to
understand what it means to
teach at this level. What time
is it? Okay? Wow, okay. What
does it mean to teach when your
person has kind of become the
ADD, some kind of added catalyst
into the room. It's not just the
ideas that are the catalyst, but
your person has become the
catalyst. I had to learn how to
manage, not control, but to
manage the energies that were
involved, how to make it more
efficient, how to protect the
students, how to how to just how
to choreography, how to
choreograph. It a little bit.
Then I began to realize it
wasn't just what was happening
in the room was really too big
to be understood simply in terms
of an energetic resonance
between my spiritual practice
and my students. That was part
of what was going on. But then I
began to realize there was
something else going on.
Students were beginning to show
up in each other's dreams. There
was something happening socially
in the room. What what was
happening was simply I began to
understand what it was, too big
and too powerful, simply to be
explainable in terms of some
just a one on one, resonance
between me and them. There was a
second dynamic that was moving
on, moving in the room. Now I
had read Rupert Sheldrake, you
know, his books, a new science
of life and the presence of the
past and the rebirth of nature.
I'd read his books. I understood
the concept of morphogenetic
resonance and Morphic fields,
but Rupert is working in very,
very big fields, long, you know,
historical evolutionary fields.
And I didn't see the relevance
of those giant fields to what
was happening in my classroom,
because we were together for 15
weeks at a time. That's not a
whole lot of time. But then I
again in this one particular
psychedelic session, suddenly I
saw, Oh, you mean short term
groups have generate, feel.
Fields feels are generated
whenever people gather together,
and the more focused they are in
intention. And if they're
together long enough and deeply
engaged enough, and it's very
important if the if the group is
repeated, if it's a repetition
that goes on, these fields
emerge now. They emerge out of
the Unified nature of
consciousness, that
consciousness is a inherently
unified field. So it's not like
an erector set where you're
connecting, you're putting two
pieces that are really separate,
linking them together. It's kind
of like that, but, but at a
deeper level, what's happening
is an underlying potential is
being is being brought, is being
sparked into form, group feels,
group mind. Phil Jackson, not a
very mystical guy, as far as I
know, but Coach of the Los
Angeles Lakers, right? He sees
it. He says we see this a lot in
critical situations, when
players are totally focused on
the team goal, their effort can
create chain reactions. It's as
if they become totally connected
to one another, in sync with one
another, like five fingers on
one hand. Now Howard Bloom,
great author, wonderful book,
the global brain. He wrote, In
other words, without knowing it,
individuals form a team. Even in
our most casual moments, we
pulse in synchrony. Isn't that a
wonderful phrase, repulse and
synchrony, other symptoms of
this being a field phenomenon. I
began to realize that there was,
just like Rupert Sheldrake
theory predicts, there was a
change in the learning curve
taking place in my classes. It's
kind of like it. This is too
simple, but it's almost as if
one class was starting where the
last class stopped. It wasn't
quite like that. But, you know,
you got a course scripted, you
have it kind of worked out. You
know, it's a winner. You've
refined it. You spent several
years polishing it. You know,
you're taking them A to B to C
to D. You walk in the class the
first day, and all of a sudden
they're giving you the cues that
they're already in B, they're
already in C. And you've got to
rearrange your entire syllabus,
or you've got to make you've got
to step up, because something
has shifted. They've moved. I
began to realize there was a
learning that was taking place
in one class between semesters,
there was some kind of
developmental process, and you
go through certain turning
points, all of a sudden, things
are stable, and then something
triggers, and every class in
that subject after that, you're
working in a different context,
and that's a pain in the ass to
have to rearrange your syllabus.
So once in a while it's like,
I'm not going to do that. I'm
going to we're going to stay
with the tried and true. That's
bad news. That doesn't work,
because the students get bored
and the energy in the room, and
then you spend so much time
trying to lift up the energy,
and it's like, no, it's better
to go with it. Find where they
are, because if you find them,
it's not just that you'll do a
better job teaching, but
there's, there's something that
they're giving you in where they
are, they're going to take you
places that you haven't been
before yourself. I began to
differentiate two different
levels of these fields. So
there's the class field I call
and then the course field. The
class field is created by the
energy of the people who are in
the room today. All right, it's
kind of like in a tree. If there
are many, many rings of a tree,
the the outer ring. What did the
not the cambium ring? What's the
outer ring of the of the tree
called, I'm blanking on it,
sorry, having a brain fart. You
know, the living outer edge of
the tree, not the bark, right
underneath the bark, pardon?
Cambium? Okay, that's the class
field, right? The course field
is a much older, bigger field.
It's the energy. It's a kind of
a residual arc in the learning
of the field, which has been
contributed to by every student
who has ever taken this course
with this particular professor?
Now I'm going to kind of
restrict it to that with this
particular professor. I think
it's more than that. But in the
beginning, the class field may
be the stronger field, but over
time. The course field. When
you've been teaching 2030, more
years, the course field gets
very strong. So here you've got
three systems, the individual
student, whose consciousness is
being affected by the class
field, whose consciousness is
being affected by the course
field. So here you've got the
universal mind, the individual.
And what we're suggesting is
that this organic relationship
between universal mind and
individual mind has these
intermediate fields, which, when
those fields are get strong, and
when they are skillfully
focused, as you can then it
triggers, it animates, it
empowers, it makes more
creative, more adventuresome,
the learning of the individual
mind. If you were a coach, we'd
be talking about performance
feels. If we were physicians,
we'd be talking about healing
fields. I'm a teacher, so we're
talking about learning feels but
feels is, feels okay, old, feels
young, feels present, feels
past, feels I learned that you
could work with these fields. I
learned some tricks. I start
working with the fields of a
class before the class begins.
There are certain practices that
I do because to me, the field is
the unregistered student in the
room, right? It's a tangible
thing. I even will so far go so
far as when I'm looking at which
books to assign a semester from
now, I sometimes try to tune
into the field that's emerging
around this course to determine
whether I should you go to a or
go with B. I do certain kinds of
practices, spiritual practices,
because I don't want a lot of
old karma screwing things up in
the classroom. I don't want a
bad vibe from you me, because,
you know, I'm a
reincarnationist. I believe in
reincarnation. You we I think
you know
life being what it is. I'm
assuming I've got former lives
with some of my students. I'm
assuming that sometimes it
worked out well and we got
something good that came out of
it. Sometimes maybe it didn't
work out too well. We got some
bruises or some pain that's
going to come up. We I don't
have any time for the bad stuff,
so I do these practices. It's
like, I'm sorry if I hurt you,
without the students knowing
this is something you don't do
to them. I'm sorry if I hurt
you. Please forgive me. If you
hurt me, I forgive you. Let's
just go. Let's just get on with
it. And there are practices you
can do. Every spiritual
tradition has practices for
cutting the cords of karma,
karma. I used to use a Hawaiian
Kuhn, a practice called
hooponopono, which means
cutting. And then later, when I
learned Chud, which is a Tibetan
practice, which also means
cutting, I would do that
practice. So before class
begins, when I get a roster,
which usually comes in about a
month before the class begins,
I'm doing Chud with this roster
with the students in front of
me. I've often wondered what my
faculty colleagues would think
if they came in and I'm doing a
bell and ringing and I'm singing
a Tibetan prayer for students in
a class that hasn't even begun
yet. But once you understand
fields, this is simply just
being efficient. It's just being
efficient. You're working with
the energy before there are
physical beings present. Once
the class begins, then you get
to see the beings that are
physically the embodiment of the
energy that you've been picking
up on. And you can work with
fields during the class. You can
do it behind the scenes, and
there are ways in which you can
do it in the class.
Visualization exercises can
empower fields. Various types of
Cafe conversations can cross
fertilize fields. One of the
other things that's important to
do is to close the field at the
end of the semester. Now, by
closing the field, I don't mean
like you dissolve the field, but
there's a sense in which every
class has a beginning, a middle
and an end. It's important if
you're going to empower fields.
And if you're going to work with
fields, and you're you're going
to invite that type of dynamic
into the room, it's important at
the end of the semester to close
the field and help students
detach from the field, to re
empower them as individual
learners, and then send them on
their way where they will. On to
new fields and connect with new
groups, and then go on to new
fields and connect to new you
don't want to encourage an
attachment to the field, but if
you don't close the field,
sometimes students get stuck.
They'll show up at your office
two weeks after a course is
over, kind of wanting to talk
and what's I began to realize
there was something wrong here.
Wasn't just that they liked the
course, but they were still
psychically attached to the
energy of the class, but they
didn't have a place to take it,
and so you have to do things
both shamanically and
strategically pedagogically to
close the field so that, like a
final exam, is a good way to
help close the field, let them
demonstrate their learning.
Whenever you have a kind of a
beer or pizza that the local
student union at the end of a
course, you're always are
asking, what's what are you
going to do next? Where are you
going next? What's next on the
agenda? You're you're focusing.
You collect information on the
course, you get student feedback
in the course, and you tell
them, I'm going to use your
feedback to make this better for
the next class. You're
reinforcing the sense that they
are part of a lineage of
learning and their time is over,
and that's okay, everybody. Our
time together is finite,
waking up in the classroom,
waking up, right? We're talking
about, you know, some type of
spiritual awakening. What do we
mean? What is that? Waking up
simply is in one perspective,
it's simply waking up to the
simple fact that nobody holds
their own being in and of
itself, the beginnings and
ending of our being lie outside
of ourselves. There's just,
there is no it's It's waking up
to the tangible fact that we our
lives, are deeply intertwined
and woven together. And if you
can stand in a certain way, you
can feel that weave. And when
you feel that weave strongly,
that chronic sense of tightness
of the self relaxes, and the
wind blows through the trees and
the leaves dance. It's just
waking up, waking up to
something that has always been
there. It didn't start. It
doesn't stop. You don't make it
happen. It's just the natural
condition of being, the bubble
pops Shunyata, right? Emptiness,
emptiness of self, but the
translation of Shunyata that I
like the best is transparency.
Transparency. It's like I am
here, but everyone is here, but
we become transparent to the
ground condition. We become
transparent to the true
condition of things. People wake
up in all sorts of
circumstances, in all sorts of
activities with all sorts of
context and what outside of my
own psychedelic work, one of the
places where I've experienced
this simple, simple truth very
deeply is in the classroom. You
know, when something uses my
mind or uses me, and there is
this wind that blows invisibly
between the students and myself,
or between us together, and that
and that delicious feeling of
being used, where you just kind
of relax, and something happens
which is bigger than you. Oh,
there's no self here. There's no
self in bit in it. This is
something which is inherently
trans self phenomena. And when
you when you just appreciate the
trans self nature of this
exchange,
the joy of discovering that the
life that is alive in you, the
life that's moving in this room,
is actually the life of all
things. It is the life of all
things, your life and their
life, your life. It's the life
of all things relaxing into that
you it, even when we forget,
even when I forget, life doesn't
forget. Life is still one the
transparency is still there,
whether or not I'm remembering
it or not, whether I'm paying
attention to or not, it's always
there. It. Just there waking up.
You can wake up in any
circumstance, in any condition,
and it's lovely to wake up when
you're working, as in the
classroom, it's just, why not?
The Circle of Learning. I had
the had the experience many
times. I'm sure you have to. You
go through an exercise, you go
through an experience. You read
a book, you learn something very
quickly. A few days later, a
week later, somebody asks you a
question in class. If they had
asked you two weeks before, you
wouldn't have anything to say
because you don't didn't know
that, but because they asked
you. Now you have something to
say, and you you give it to them
and that it's important to them,
and you think, Wow, isn't that
cool? Something is alive in the
universe. It's able to use
something that I learned in
order to help somebody, somebody
else that is just got to be damn
cool. That's neat. But then I
began to realize, you know, I
don't quite I hadn't seen this
all work out yet. It's much more
complicated than that. It's not
simply that something that I
learned is being used by the
universe to facilitate a
learning in somebody else. It's
actually often the reason I
learned this in the first place,
the reason I had this experience
in the first place is because
there was a need to know coming
at me, and my system picked up
the need to know, and I had the
ability to learn, so that when
this happened, when this need
came forward, the exchange took
place, the Circle of Learning.
And when I began to realize that
this was happening all the time,
it was all it had been happening
for decades before I even
understood it. That's when you
really have to let go big time,
because you don't even own your
career. You don't even own your
own academic ideas, your own
academic passions, your passion
and your student's passion are
intertwined right from the very
beginning, and that's when you
either clutch and get real tight
on it and try to get back in
control of it, or you let go
very, very deeply and you begin
to just this. The beginnings and
endings of your life did not
start and stop with you. The
reason you want, the things you
want, the reasons you love the
things you love, the reasons
that you just have, the hungers
that you have, are not
independent of the loves and
hungers and the wishes that
other people have. We're just
constantly processing these
things at multiple levels all at
the same time. Now that's a
dance, isn't that? It's just a
dance?
Well, I kept doing the
psychedelic work. I kept going
deeper and deeper I began to get
into, you know, things I haven't
written about publicly yet. You
know, dark night, early dawn,
takes the first 10 years, but
there's a second 10 years,
deep stuff, stuff that many of
you have touched and worked in
to experience reincarnation, not
as an in, not at the soul level,
not at the individual level, but
at the aggregate level, to
experience what it's like to be
In a species that's
reincarnating so that every
individual is like sloughing
cells off of skin this massive,
magnificent, beautiful organism,
learning, the learning of the
species mind, generation by
generation, billions of people
beginning to be drawn into the
larger story of humanity's
evolutionary pivot, going into
vast tracks of time, being drawn
into the crisis as fermenting
underneath history, bringing us
into this boiling point, going
beyond The boiling point to see
what's what's being generated,
what has been being in the works
for 100,000 years from and this
crescendo that we're moving to,
in some ways, can you imagine
what it would be like to go
through pregnant. See in labor
and not know what what a child
was, in some ways, what we're
going through. Only really for
me, began to make sense when I
began to get a taste of the
human that's coming, the human
that we're all in the process of
gestating through history. I
degree, and then to be enter
into some of the domains that
I've called the domain of
diamond Luminosity, or the
Buddhists call it sambhogakaya,
as best as I can determine, this
deep, deep intimacies with the
divine intimacy so deep they
eventually become, became, for
me, too painful to leave. Just
too painful. I couldn't keep
going back into them. I could
not share this knowledge with my
students. I didn't talk about my
work, but I was always teaching
Stan stuff, so there was a sense
in which I could teach through
Stan. But eventually my work
reached and tapped into
territory. I could not bring
that to them, even though they
were willing, they just didn't
have sufficient preparation.
They were undergraduate students
in Ohio. They were not graduate
students in California. You I
could not bring that to them.
And something began to happen
inside my body, because my
natural being is to share, but I
could not share these things
that meant so deep to me. I had
knowledge that I could not bring
forward. I had to stop myself
from bringing it forward. I
began to lose control of my
voice. I began to there was so
much tension in my voice,
because someone would ask a
question, and inside me, there
would come this knowing that
would naturally want to reach
out and share, but I couldn't,
so I'd clutch, and I'd lose
control of my voice, and there'd
be kind of a bark. It's kind of
embarrassing. It's kind of a
bark, and I'd stop. It was
getting pretty intense. This was
one of my work was really
getting to the peak stages in
9798 99 I stopped it in 99 I
really didn't know how to where
this was going to go. And then a
number of things happened in my
personal life. My marriage
ended, dark night, early dawn
was published, and then I was
given an opportunity to come to
be the Director of Education at
ions. And so I thought, okay,
took care of my family. I mean,
the worst experience of my life
was going through that divorce,
taking care of my former wife,
taking care of my children,
moving them, getting everything
situated, working that beginning
of that healing process. But
then I went to California, and I
thought, Ah, this will be the
new platform. This will give me
out. I'm out of Ohio, I'm out of
teaching undergraduates. I'm
going to be able to work with
more people who are already
through class, A, B and C. We
can start at D. You know, this
is going to be a new platform
for me. And it was kind of
initially, but two years later,
it didn't work out for a variety
of reasons. Don't need to go
into really did not want to stay
there. And I came back to Ohio
and I resumed my teaching
career, which is a hard
transition to go through.
I knew I didn't belong at YSU
anymore, in Youngstown anymore,
but this is where I had to be,
because I had to get my kids
through college. I had college
tuitions to go. I really
couldn't step away until my
youngest graduated from college,
and that was still a number of
years off. So I kind of, you
know, adjusted. I had stopped
the intense psychedelic work. My
system was beginning to slow
down, but I knew that something
wasn't right. I mean, I was
really ungrounded. I was really
I had developed an over
attachment to marijuana, you
know, I just, I began to realize
part of me just was not willing
to come down off the mountain,
and my smoking was keeping me
from coming all the way down,
all the way down off the
mountain, and I realized I had
to come completely down off the
mountain. And that took that
took some time.
It took. So five to 10 years
after I stopped my work, before
my whole system kind of
recalibrated down to the new
baseline. Soon as my daughter
graduated from college, I
resigned from YSU, and then the
question becomes, how do not?
How do I share what I know now?
And so I it's by writing. You
know, it's by writing and
wonderful opportunity to spend
some time with you. I mean, it's
just, well, you are such a
blessing to me. Really, such a
blessing. Your hearts and your
minds are so beautiful. Damn.
How do I contribute to the
resurgence, the renewal of the
psychedelic Renaissance? How do
I personally contribute to my
discipline? How do I help them
realize the potential of
psychedelics, for philosophy,
for my original discipline? How
do I bring that forward? How can
I help others tap into the
cosmology, the cosmological
depths that they are already
deeply part of without exposing
themselves to some of the risk
and making some of the mistakes
that I made along the way? I
Yeah, knowing when to pull back,
knowing when to stop, knowing
when the students whom you love,
and I love being with the
students, I love being in the
classroom, but knowing when
those are not my students
anymore. I can't keep doing
this, pulling back and then
writing, you know, writing, and
then seeing what happens, seeing
what comes from there. So the
book now I'm working on is
stealing diamonds from heaven,
which is this whole story. And
then I have another one I want
to work on, called The Birth of
the diamond soul, which is
really about my sense of what's
happening in history and in
nature.
Unknown: Okay,
not bad. Nine o'clock right on,
pretty damn good, huh? Okay, I'm
done. Let's stand up, un kink
your ankles and Your knees.
Okay, do reference here, Chris,
Robert McDermott: you I'll say
something okay. I think you can
see why I was so delighted to
write the forward to Chris's
book and how easy it was. So
thank you for those, any of you
who are interested in continuing
this conversation with Chris,
with me, with various parts of
what, what you're doing, and
it's important to see us, I
would be happy to participate,
maybe even while we're here, if
we could figure that out. Okay,
that's good. Okay, that's
possible. Pull up a cushion.
Okay. I don't know if any of you
gonna be leaving. I have a
really be breaking the mood,
wouldn't it? We'll save it for
later. Okay, I do have an
announcement for later, but
let's save it till the
discussion. Okay, okay, anybody
who wants to leave at any time?
Yeah, please do Yeah. But I
mean, I'm very moved by first,
as you can tell. And if you read
the forward, you'll see that it
was, it was an easy affirmation
to make.
Chris Bache: Now, what most of
you don't know is that I was
Robert sitter in a Holotropic
Breathwork session right down at
the big house when we and he was
my sitter, we got down together.
Okay, floor is open. Let's talk.
Robert McDermott: So maybe I'll
begin with a little explanation
why I jumped up here. Okay, so
you said you did young for 30
years, 3333 Yeah, I had a very
similar experience for 20 years
at Baruch College. Yeah, right.
Taught all my students were
first generation. Yeah. I. So I
taught for I never had fewer
than 40 students. I never taught
the same student twice. I taught
40 students three times a year,
three times a day, each semester
for 20 years. Yeah, so it's a
little something. Then I come to
Paradise, not as a faculty
member initially, but I've been
out with a faculty member for 14
years, all the time, looking for
the kind of experience that you
described. And either i Well,
I'm the brick that you said you
were to have. All those things.
I also didn't have a whole
psychedelic practice. We can fix
that.
There's no shortage of people in
this room to get me. To get
me that said, I want to say that
in this psychedelic inspired
community, neither Has it ever
happened that a person pressured
me,
Unknown: not at once. Yeah,
that's the way it's
Robert McDermott: supposed to be
always in life, yeah. But it is
the case. Yeah. Okay, so, so I'm
always looking for the kind of,
what I call the etheric body,
yeah, to be experienced and
shared with language and
examples and whatever. And I'm
not saying it doesn't happen or
it hasn't happened. It certainly
has not happened at the level
that you described in the living
classroom, which I think is
quite an amazing document. If
you haven't read it, it's an
amazing document. So I just
wanted to take I jumped up here
very spontaneously, or you feel
right. So I actually had a
pretty hard trip, if you
remember. Yeah, in fact,
everybody was out of the room. I
don't know why I'm talking about
this. Everybody was out of the
room, and Stan relieved you.
Yeah, and when I came out of
this experience, I assisted to
insisted to Chris that it was
about 10 minutes. It was
actually three hours, and there
was a hand that I recall
experiencing, something like a
baseball glove, which was Stan's
hand on my face, that went from
this giant of a mountain of a
man with exquisite, gentle,
compassionate quality, Right? I
almost I had this opportunity to
talk at the conference. I almost
said that, but I said, No, it's
not really what it's about, but
it's in my mind, because we just
had this great experience of, of
Chris, of sorry, Stan, so
anyway, we had that together. I
sat with you. So it's a very
bonding experience to have this.
The other dive I did, it was in
my house and Ashbery street with
will keep it
Unknown: well, he's good. You're
in Cherry hands. Good hands.
Robert McDermott: I went to the
mountain twice, yeah. But
anyway, getting back to you and
your work and your relationship
to our students, which is quite
intense, considering that you
don't teach that often, yeah,
right. It's quite intense. I
hear, get him here, keep him
here, that kind of thing, which
I listen to and remember and try
to be, you know, do what we can,
but keep it up. Keep it up.
Chris Bache: Let me mention
something about the etheric
field. Yeah, this comes at the
very end of the living
classroom, because the living
classroom was written in,
published in 2008 written in
2006 seven and I stopped the
heavy duty psychedelic work in
99 over time, this energetic
resonance calmed down. It didn't
go away entirely. But instead of
kind of being like a lightning
rod, where it was happening
around me without my being, you
know, now, I had to kind of
cooperate with it. I had to kind
of let it happen, not like I
could control it. But there was
a sense of it's a it was a
subtler thing, and that kind of
teaches us something about the
etheric level, that the practice
empowers the system. You open
up, you bringing in heavy duty
energy. You move from 110 volts
to 240 volts, naturally you're
going to activate these inherent
circuits. But then, if you. If
the system calms down, it's not
like the circuits, the network
is there, but you're not.
There's not as much energy
driving it. And that's there's a
wisdom in the kind of the pace
of evolution. There is a
certain, not a risk, I think. I
mean potentially. But there is a
certain if you over, if you
drive the system hard, things
are going to happen. Then you
calm down. Things calm down, you
know. So I don't have that
transparency today that I did at
the peak in the living
classroom, and now it's kind of
a subtler thing than it was
then.
Unknown: Rules are rules. You
know, the period of the greatest
transparency, as you described
it was that whole period of the
iranis Neptune conjunction,
which was indeed a field, a
collective field, that did
exactly that, you know,
dissolving of boundaries, the
creation of transparent fields.
It's perfect expression of it in
a very creative way. And it was,
you know, it basically, you
know, started coming in in the
mid to late 80s, and then was
just totally cooking all through
the 90s. And then, you know,
once it got to 2001 it reached
the 15 degree mark and and, you
know, that pulse that, you know,
PCC was born under, and many
other, I mean, now we've got the
Uranus Pluto and a whole nother
kind of driving intensity is
here. But what you are
describing of the living
classroom and the Morphic field
that was taken in, and these,
these fields, these course
fields, these class fields, etc,
it's, it's larger, both the
perception and the capacity to
cultivate it and the capacity to
name it and articulate it, very
much, I think, is an expression
of that, that larger Uranus
Neptune very the privilege that
we all had come to have had That
going all during those years.
Robert McDermott: Yeah, yeah.
Thank you. Where are we going?
Chris, Richard.
Unknown: Chris, I just want to
express my deepest gratitude for
some of us that have experienced
you in the classroom and see the
living embodiment of your
written word in person, it is
unbelievable to be in the
presence, and I feel every time
I leave the classroom, I feel
I'm just a little bit more
dignified and connected to a
larger purpose in life. And on a
personal note, like five or six
weeks ago, I started teaching
poetry to sixth and seventh
graders, and I was terrified in
front of those kids. I felt like
I didn't even know how to speak
to kids. And if it wasn't for
for your book, I think I would
have fallen apart, because I had
this distinct feeling, with the
help of your book that not all
responsibility laid on my, my
shoulders, and I could actually
just allow the field to create
the class. And sure enough, it
happened, and I saw it in in
living action. Yeah, so I do, I
do have a question that I want
to add to this little note, and
that is what, cosmological
implications do you see from the
field experience that you have
made in your life, that the
whole universe seems to relate
in that potential to create
fields everywhere we look, As a
galaxy, a kind of field like,
yeah, and
Chris Bache: any thoughts. Well,
the nice thing about it is it
was working just fine for 100
it's been working this way for
billions of years before we even
began to understand what was
going on. So whatever is going
on, it's been going on for a
hell of a long time. The fact
that we're beginning to
understand some of these
dynamics and maybe can
participate in them more
consciously. Some people,
actually, some of my colleagues,
have said, you know, well, this
is kind of like, it undermines
your individuality, you know,
all this kind of ego, fear kind
of stuff. But it's like, look,
we're just beginning to play
with something that's been
playing with us for a long time.
So I don't know. I don't know
how it all works, you know, I
don't know the full
ramifications of all these
dynamics. It's just that look,
when we just kind of work
together, we synchronize
ourselves, we work with guided
intention. We want focus to.
Intention. We do these exercise
together. What do you know?
There's a little bit of bleed
through that comes together, a
little reinforcement that takes
place. Hey, then it gets scary.
You think about, well, there's a
field around the Pentagon,
there's a field around shopping
malls, there's a field around
the New York Times. There's a
field around all you know,
there's so fields are
everywhere. There's they're not
good or bad, they're not moral,
just moral things. There's
negative. There's a field around
the Ku Klux Klan. There's in the
field around the NRA and all the
chapters of the NRA. But it's
been going on for a long time.
It's just the connective tissue
of consciousness. Meant you're
reaching sort of threshold
proportion. But once you
understand that, then you kind
of begin to be a little bit more
sensitive to your own psychic
hygiene. You don't want to put
yourself in certain psychic
fields, because, yeah, you know,
it's like, I used to take my
kids to karate matches and
little Lance like, Ooh, you
know, it's kind of, you know,
but going to an art museums
that's kind of a nice field, you
know. So it's,
Robert McDermott: why did you
say, as I think you did, that
they're not good or bad, but you
just, you just indicated that
some fields really are pretty
negative and difficult.
Chris Bache: By good or bad, I
mean, nature isn't making is
doesn't seem to be. At least, I
don't think of nature as re in
as in this particular respect,
reinforcing morally good fields
and undermining morally
injurious fields or negative
fields. Now I, as an evolving
consciousness, want, I choose to
cultivate certain energy in my
life. And by choosing, if I want
to cultivate that energy, then I
kind of want to detach from this
energy so I may make moral
distinctions, and I may want to
associate myself with fields of
compassion, intelligence,
creativity and and not put
myself in in the context of
intense competition, You know,
corrosive, vitriolic fields. But
it's kind of like, you know, the
ocean has currents, the ocean
has riptides, the ocean moves
one way or the other. We drowned
or we float, but they're not
moral.
Robert McDermott: So we have two
differences in our worldview.
Okay, I've surfaced in the last
few minutes. Okay, you might be
interested. One is for me, this
entire discussion takes place in
a comprehensive evolution of
consciousness. Yes, if we, since
we all here, mostly all here for
Rick's talk. Just remember what
he was saying about the
uniqueness of the modern Western
consciousness. Well, that what
that fact that Rick is so good
at articulating, but he and I
both influenced by Owen
Barfield, saving the appearances
and many books like that, leads
me to say that to you for Your
comment that something like the
etheric was immediately evident
without the separation came
about in the modern West, and so
now we are in a situation where
we have to learn, I think, by
Love, to reconnect with our our
etheric and the etheric that
surrounds us in a way that we we
do try to discern etheric
fields, which may be synonymous,
tautological, okay, that are
working against love, and we
have to know that they are and
do what we can to transform
them.
Chris Bache: I'll go even
further than that. I agree with
you, right? I think, I think the
universe, you know, Jung said
the universe tilts towards
growth, right, right? So I think
there are ways and levels of the
universe that's actually
encouraging the forces of
compassion and tilting it
towards growth. But when I say
that the fields themselves are a
natural phenomena that are not
in. Themselves, good or bad,
they just are. That doesn't mean
that there aren't other dynamics
that are at play, which are
encouraging the emergence or
strengthening in subtle ways,
perhaps fields of compassion,
which are fields of oneness,
which are fields of growth and
kind of not giving as much
support to fields which are
inherently divisive and
inherently destructive of the
Unified Fabric of life.
Robert McDermott: I think I, I
think I would want to revise
your language just a little bit
okay, because I'm not. I don't
often talk about anything
inherently without adding it's
really it's multiple
relationships, yes. So I don't
think that fields are negative
all by themselves. They're
negative in relation to
something that the universe
needs to accomplish.
Chris Bache: That's interesting
language. I have to sit with
that for a bit.
Unknown: Okay, let me sit with
that for a bit. In relationship
that they have to accomplish
something. Let me
Robert McDermott: sit with that
for a bit Jung sense growth or
talks about the universe, to try
and evolve towards love and
freedom. Actually think it's
towards love and freedom is only
the only is the condition which
makes love possible.
Chris Bache: Yeah, to me, love
is, is an expression of the
inherent oneness of life. And it
is, it is it fosters it. It
expresses it. And that's why
it's so powerful. It's, it is
the experience of the inherent
unified nature of reality, you
know,
Robert McDermott: yeah, and
therefore those fields that are
emphasizing and militating on
behalf of disunity and fear,
hatred and delusion, I consider
to be negative and to be and
that it's part of my life to try
to transform those fields which
I also advance against what I
think of myself.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I certainly
agree with you on that. I mean,
you know, just a little side
note, Youngstown, one of the
reasons I learned that I was in
Youngstown, particularly short,
very quick bullet. My it was my
soul's choice to do the work
with the ocean of suffering that
I ended up doing for all those
years in the psychedelic work.
San Francisco is not a very good
environment in which to deal
with those kind of negative
fields. Youngstown is a very,
very good environment to deal
with those kind of negative
fields. Youngstown has made the
cut the cover of Time magazine
twice as Mobtown, USA had the
highest murder per capita rate
in the country for a number of
years. And it goes the mafia
dominated Youngstown politics
for many years. Lots of gangland
executions. And it goes all the
way back the Native Americans,
where some terrible massacres
took place there. So there's a
field, a huge kind of psychic
feel, a lot of Eastern European
immigration, a lot of
patriarchy, a lot of abuse of
women. It's really kind of,
it's, it's a place where bad
karma comes to work itself out.
And so I, I believe in working
to lift those fields, lift those
energies out of the collective
psyche. And I, you know, so I
affirm that very, very deeply.
But when I So, when I say that
the fields themselves mean the
aggregation of that negativity
is a natural phenomenon, I don't
mean it's a I don't mean to
affirm it as a natural therefore
good. It's it's an aggregation
of energy, which is
Robert McDermott: natural. How
about intelligible?
Unknown: Intelligible, okay,
Robert McDermott: how'd you like
a job? Oh, yeah,
Unknown: to be into somersault
from now on. Yeah. I Yeah.
Thank you, Chris, for coming and
sharing with us. It was
beautiful to see you speak so
freely and express everything
you want to express and
articulate. It very well. Thank
you. My question, my curiosity
in working with fields is comes
with the idea of, I, I think
about the the form of an atom
and how the electron jumps from
ring to ring with no time taken,
yeah, and, and with that idea as
kind of a. Model for how the
universe is structured? Yeah, I
was curious to hear what you
would have to say about
conscious the evolution of
consciousness in a relational
field and quantum leaps in that
field.
Chris Bache: I don't know. I
mean, we know about emergence.
We know that, you know, things
happen, things jump. We hit
tipping points. We think we're
coming to a tipping point, an
evolutionary tipping point. When
people have near death
experiences, they go through
these exponential increases in
awareness in a very short period
of time. And more than one
author has suggested that the
human race is coming to a
collective Near-Death
Experience, a potential jumping
point. If fields come to tipping
points in small groups, you
know, in dark net, early dawn. I
suggest that we have a long way
to go and very little time to
get there. And I suggest that
the only way we could possibly
make it as far evolutionary wise
as we have to go, is if we
understand field dynamics,
because from field dynamics,
we're not trying to change 7
billion minds. We're only trying
to change one mind, and the 7
billion experiences are being
processed at an integral level.
And so if we understand non
linear systems. And if we
hypothesize that the human
collective unconscious is a
system and it can be thrown into
non linear dynamics or far from
equilibrium conditions, perhaps
non linear conditions can
emerge. And Brian help me out
here. But you know, when a
system goes into beyond far or
far from equilibrium conditions,
things happen fast, and things
can jump. And I really think
that some dynamic like that is
underlies the potential that
human beings have to make a
quantum step change. It's not
simply an aggregate of a lot of
individuals, but there is a kind
of a deeper summation coming
forward in all those
individuals. Does that
Robert McDermott: following on
Brian again, okay, I'll let
other people talk, but I
remember what I was thinking.
Sama, your job. Yeah? Thank
Unknown: you. I was just saying,
Sami, that it'd be really cool
if you somersaulted, and I could
tell you didn't understand. Man,
I felt so bad. I thought he
thinks I didn't like his
somersaulting. I loved it.
That's fantastic. Good. Okay,
great, great. So I actually
didn't want the microphone,
yeah, but Robert does, and so
here we are,
Robert McDermott: Jesse's all
the way back and Aaron Lydia,
thanks.
Unknown: I have a question about
working with fields. Yeah.
I have two questions, but they
might have this some very
similar answer, okay, one is
that I could see how working
with fields goes can be almost
applicable in kind of any
relational situation? Yes, so
I'm I'm inquiring if you could
share something specific about a
practice in working with fields.
And I guess my second question
is about a lot of us do work in
relationship to being aware of
the crisis that's happening in
the world and the level of
destruction and chaos that a lot
of people are experiencing. And
I guess whether it's a person
we're trying to sort through
something with or or being
present with and wanting to be
strong and and good and and
used, in the face of also
knowing that we're going to live
our lives being very aware and
maybe really Close to levels of
destruction that are scary and
and processing and being with
lots of fear and anger and
delusion. So do you have
specific practice that you'd
like to share, or does that what
make you think of that we
something? For us to maybe
digest on I
Chris Bache: uh, compassion
practices. That's what comes to
mind. First of all, you're
already doing what you're
describing. You're already doing
it. You, each one of you has
made a choice to radically
insert yourself into an
evolutionary process to bring
about a fundamental shift and an
improvement in the condition of
the planet. You really you have
traveled across the country, you
have aligned yourself with a
very, very distinctive
institution, and many of you are
just like following pure gut
instinct somewhere that you
can't see because it's not a
traditional track. You're
already doing it. You're already
plugged into the dynamics that
are building. Pressure wise,
you're already taking in massive
quantities of information.
You're already watching a
Cooking taking place. You're
already reaching for becoming
the embodiment of the solution.
So everything you're doing,
you're that you're talking
about, you're already doing. So
how can you do that better, is
what you're really asking, just
a little bit, just a little bit
better. And I think it's really
important to take care of
yourself, because there's a lot
of wear and tear and burn out,
because this is not over. This
is not going to be fixed soon.
This is you're going to die and
still be in process. Your
children will die and will still
be in process. So it's, it's a
long it's a marathon type of
thing. How do you keep yourself
perpetually replenished in a
long term like that? How do you,
how do you kind of stay attuned
to the opportunities? There's
several things that come to
mind, but I guess the one that
comes most deeply are compassion
practices. And every tradition
has compassion practices where
whether it's exchanging self for
other, or some type of practice
where you just voluntarily
expand your heart into deep
beauty, into deep pain into
broad horizons, and just hold
that and then bring it back down
again, and then take up your
individual day's work. Every
tradition has practices like
that, because compassion is the
is the recognition of the
inherent oneness of life. And so
if we're talking about a
revitalized contact between the
individual, the highly refined,
highly evolved, historically
beautiful individuality, but
reconnecting into the larger
context of the larger field of
life, compassion is that
expression of that celebration
of that oneness. It's
encouraging that oneness. There
is clarity practices. If you
need clarity, there are clarity
practices. There are all sorts
of different they're antidote
practices, but compassion
practices seem to me to really
most deeply address what you're
what you're talking about.
Thanks.
Unknown: Thank you so much for
this. Chris, yeah, so my
question is about coming down
off the mountain. I was really
struck by that part. And I'm
curious if you could speak a
little bit more towards it, both
your decision. I mean, you had
your own natural waves and
evolution in terms of your use
with sacred medicine. And then
also, something I personally
wrestled with was an over
attachment to marijuana. And I
also felt like it was really for
many years, in a very beautiful
way, keeping me connected to the
mountain, to the Numinous, to
the archetypal realm. And I had
to find an am still finding my
own relationship to it, in order
to live my truth in this world,
in the way that I want to and
how I want to bring do my work.
And it's very alive and true for
me and also for a lot of my
friends in different
communities. Yeah. So I'm just.
Curious if you could, you know,
speak a little more to that, and
also something around the
intimacy with the Divine and how
you feel. You said that the veil
or something shifted, slowed
down or calmed down, yeah, and
I'm wondering where you are with
that now, and why it's felt
important for you to move in
that direction at this point. I
Chris Bache: you. Thank you for
the very heartfelt question that
you're asking. I'll do my best
to speak to the same depth from
which it comes.
I'm Neptune, first house square
sun in the 10th house. Addiction
is the shadow of Neptune, right?
And Neptune is what allows me to
open up into deep fields with
kind of relatively ease. But
this the shadow, and it's what
gives me kind of a sensitivity
to collective dynamics. But the
downside is, you know, there the
shadow side of it is taking the
lower form of unity rather than
the higher form of unity, and
that's been an issue for me,
addiction of that not alcohol,
death, but marijuana has been an
issue for me, and I really had
to learn and grow it and and
know when to let it go. I
i stopped the high dose work for
two reasons, one because I was
running into a lot of physical
and subtle energy system
complications, and I kept
thinking that these
complications would stop if I
kind of went through another
enough dying experiences. And
then eventually I realized no,
they were actually happening,
because I had gone through so
many dying experiences, and they
were only going to get worse if
I kept on plunging myself into
these huge fires. And I just, I
had to let the system. And I was
doing a lot of purification
practice, I was doing a lot of
yoga, I was doing a lot of
Tibetan deity practices. So I
was really getting a lot of
support, but I was still running
so much energy that I just, my
body was telling me, you you
just got to let that energy calm
down. You've got to let it
soothe out. But the main on top
of that, there was another
reason, and so there's a
cautionary note I'm saying, you
know, you normal. I speak deeply
and positively about
psychedelics, but it's a tricky
path, and even when you do it
really well, and I tried to do
it really carefully and really
well, it's still tricky. And the
main reason I stopped is because
I literally, I just could not
take coming back anymore. The
intimacy with the divine. The
places that I eventually learned
how to move into were so
beautiful and so extraordinary,
and so home and so light that
coming back was so painful. Now,
there are beings who can live in
those places. I know they are. I
read them. You know, all honor
to the Great mahasiddhas. I'm
not one of those beings who can
sustain that yet, and going in
and out of that condition, and
we're not talking about
enlightenment. This is something
different. This is kind of more
like the mahasiddha, something
that in that lineage, coming
back out of it was just becoming
too painful. And eventually, I
asked the universe never to
bring me back into this reality
until I wouldn't have to leave.
I couldn't take it anymore. I
learned that it's possible to
have too much God, and that's
not I didn't even you know, but
it is. You can just take on more
than is healthy to if you're
going to stay with your feet on
the earth, you can open yourself
too deeply for it. When I
stopped that deep work, I went
into a sadness that was just
excruciating. Them, because I
knew when I left, I was never in
my lifetime, I would never be
able to go back into that
territory again, because it
takes, it's like Olympic
training. You can't get I can't
get back to it by dropping a
huge amount of acid today, I
would take years of work to be
able to get back into this
territory. It's a momentum
thing. I knew I was leaving this
forever until I died. And I
believe when I die, I'm there. I
you know, the universe would not
be so cruel to not allow me to
go back. And if I can get to
there. It's an even deal. Coming
back down. Marijuana allowed me
to, not to, sought to, not
because of all this work. When I
would smoke, I would open up
pretty big, none of the
intermediate kind of stuff. It
was just like opening up to the
sun. And it was a way of not
getting really back down with my
feet completely on the ground.
It was just and it was a
deepening of my commitment to
the mother, to give up this
particular because marijuana is
a tricky thing. It's a mild
psychedelic, but it's also a
euphoric, right? And so it gets
that little positive glow, you
know? And if you're, if you're
receptive to it and comfortable
with it, it's but it was keeping
me literally off the ground. It
was keeping me just little off
and I began to realize that I
couldn't finish my life's work
in that condition. That was just
not good enough. I had to get
all the way down into the
ground. I had to get all the way
down in my body. So I continue
to do practice. I, you know, I
do Vajrayana practice, I do
Dzogchen practice. I do my
thing, and I take teachings, and
I sit with the beings who, you
know, can give the teachings I
beings, but the diamond
Luminosity domain is it's not
the same as the state of
transparency, the state of
Shunyata. It's a different
reality. There are beings who
can live there. I know there
are. I'm just not one of them
yet. Thank you.
Unknown: Thanks, Chris. I have
two questions. One, I'd love to
hear more about the human that
we're moving towards as a
species, or as you know,
and the diamond soul and and
also, I'm, I'm just curious
about you mentioned
the moment that you reach when
your students are no longer your
students, and that doesn't seem
to happen here. And so I'm
curious what how we might relate
to that in a place where we are
always invited back in as
continuing the learning fields.
And I don't know whether we're
not closing the fields or
whether we're closing them in
certain ways, but leaving parts
open, or what? How that's
working? But, yeah,
okay, that's an interesting
question.
Chris Bache: I think your own,
your your I'm okay, your full
time faculty probably have a
better answer to them than I'm
going to suggest, but I don't
what I'm seeing is not a failure
to close the field. That doesn't
mean maybe we could close the
field better. But you know, from
what I see from a distance and
what I've seen from Christina,
who was the program coordinator
for a while, and she used to
write these poems for
graduation. Graduation is a
tremendous celebration of
accomplishment. And you seem to
graduate well. You seem to
celebrate accomplishments. Well.
You celebrate your
dissertations, well, and you
celebrate your master's thesis.
Well. It seems to me that you
you do have closure built into
your community. You honor your
graduates, and bringing
graduates back in doesn't mean
that the fields haven't been
well closed. Now, if there's any
fine tuning to do well, that's
you know, but I don't think just
having an extended Q. Community,
because, again, you're an
unusual community. Really, you
see much more than most people
see. No wonder you get lonely
out there. You know, there's not
too many people who see what you
see, and they're not too many
people who are willing to put
their lives on the line the way
you have put your lives on the
line. So naturally. What would
be more natural than to have a
community that nourishes itself
through your various levels of
re entering the world? Kind of
you know, and engaging?
Robert McDermott: Extremely good
answer, Chris and thanks for the
question. Great question.
The way, the way I tend to think
about us, us PCC, faculty and
students and alumni, not so much
in terms of field. So it's
helpful. It's a good concept. I
think of it much more in terms
of individual and somewhat
temporary, karmic joining of
will and mind and affect. And
for some people that joining has
great longevity,
and for some people it doesn't
that seems to me
perfectly fine, that some people
really come into this community
with heart and mind and will In
a way that is transformative of
for those persons and for the
community and other people are
in more lightly and thereafter,
are held in a way that's
proportionate to that
commitment. And so some of our
alums, in a certain sense,
haven't left the community, no
matter where they are. And
others, I think I want to say
will hardly hear there is that
huge range that seems to me
right. It's perfectly fine for
each person to be as in in many
different ways as he or she
wishes for that time in their
life, given their karmic task
and opportunity. And so I don't
think of a single field. I think
Unknown: it's a
Robert McDermott: it's a
community of many levels, and
some of us are trying to operate
on all the levels. Some of us
are doing just have other
commitments, and it will be
influential in some respect, and
not others and not all. And for
some people, no, it's really
major, comprehensively
transformative. And I think we
sort of know who we are, the way
we talk to each other. And so
when, when Chris comes in with
his very profound and
fascinating and to my mind, very
mysterious, as well as inspiring
biography, it seems to me that
he touches very deep places in
our community psyche. But I
don't for a moment think expect
that Chris touches all of the
members of our community, many
of whom are working on a
different problem and have
different different tasks,
different opportunities, or just
blocked from something that
Chris could give or they already
have moved on to something else.
So I'm very impressed by the
when I think of all the reasons
I'm impressed by PCC and I'm
very impressed by our the
capacity of the entire community
to sustain and encourage very
impressive plurality. A variety
of ways of participation. And so
for me, field is a little too
singular. Yes, it is. For who we
are as we just look around,
we're really different from each
other, and it's great that we
can come together as deeply and
as creatively as we do, given
how different we are and will
continue to be. This is not a
psychological philosophical boot
camp. This is a place where you
come through and go out and
something very deep or not so
deep, will have happened, and I
hope you have gratitude and ways
of continuing to participate.
But the field, I'm not even
going to use the word, the
community, is constantly
evolving thanks to the many,
entirely different, highly
unique individuals who come and
and stir it up and lift it up to
new possibilities the way I
think about it.
At some point we probably
should, and Huh, okay, I'm not
in charge. I was only
Chris Bache: asking, how about
if I ask you answer your second
question, because I suspect to
me, and maybe that's, maybe
that's a good place to stop. No.
I mean, the hot tubs are waiting
for you, not for us.
Robert McDermott: Unfortunately,
I have a really low level Toby
one day gone from I think about
Plato, who wrote the fabulous
symposium and the Republic, and
then he had it write the laws
three times as long as the
Republic. And so what I'm about
to say has to do with law. Has
to do it. I'm glad we live in a
country of law, but it's also
sometimes, okay, sometimes sort
of a low, a low, a minimal
level. So you heard the night
that Rick said, Where, because
we're in a we're not only here
in this culture, but we're part
of a larger legal culture,
institutional, CIS, et cetera,
we have to observe expectations
that institutions and our whole
legal system requires us to
observe. And so there are three
groups here. There's faculty,
including two adjunct faculty.
There are students and alums. We
could make three different
suggestions, but I'd like to
suggest that we make two faculty
time and student time. Try to
remember this faculty time in
the lower tubs is only 815, to
915, in the morning, and
students, therefore, and
students and alumni are not
invited in the tubs at that
time. On the upper tub, which
some of you perhaps don't even
know about. It's actually a
square handicap tub. It's not
quite as beautiful, but it's
sometimes very, very quiet, not
always that tub. There are two
times when you can't go. One is
the same as the other, 815, to
915 in the morning, and also 10
to 11 at night. In other words,
right now, but if I could get
there, shouldn't go to the upper
cup. Should go to one of the
threads. But
already there. Did you say,
Sean, yeah, I hope, I hope
Robert doesn't change this rule.
Is it clear? And can you
remember? It Clear and
remembered? Thank you very much,
because you don't want to keep
talking about it, and we and I'm
really glad you have 23 hours,
All right? One hour.
Unknown: Yeah, that's true.
Robert McDermott: The others
have we've all been here 25
years, 30 years. Don't worry,
you're here. It's a special
thing for you. It's we want you
to have as much as possible. We
also want to thank Chris first
to his wonderful Well, his
wonderful work, his inspiring,
deep, profound, transformative
work, his wonderful writings.
And for this extra conversation,
which I thought was even more
disclosing. So we do thank you
and applaud you.
Chris Bache: You are wonderful.
Really, I can't tell you how
wonderful it is when I get to
come here and spend time with
you and to mix it up with you,
and to listen to what you have
to say and what you do. Really,
you're just an extraordinary
group of people. My heart is
really deeply touched
Unknown: about the question,
okay, this has been something,
it's it's been a
Chris Bache: reoccurring and
deepening theme of my
psychedelic work went on for
many, many years, and a big hunk
of it was, I put it down in the
chapter in the in dark night,
early dawn on the Great
Awakening chapter. But it kept
on going after that and the in
the last three sessions of the C
I didn't know it was ending, but
it was about to end. The
universe gave me three last
installments, three last pieces,
and one of them was the capstone
of a series of installments
around the evolutionary project
and the future human. And it'll
be in, you know, this book, and
maybe I'll make this particular
session available to the the PCC
group, and I'll give it to Rick
or Robert and let it go out. It
was the most Absolutely,
profoundly disorienting death
dismember not just reality
ripped apart. I mean, really, 70
sessions in, you wouldn't think
that you could go through
something like this. I mean, you
would think it would be used up,
you know. But it was just an
absolute ripped down, total
shattering of reality. In order
to give me one last piece in
order to finish this installment
on what's coming forward. And
this is something that's taking
place at the at the deep level
of the collective psyche. This.
This is, you know, we all live
our lives, and we die and
reborn. We die and reborn, and
we do it within a certain
cradle, and that cradle is the
archetype of the human species
that we are at this point in
history. And what's happening is
that cradle is about to shift.
The fundamental under lying
structure of the human psyche is
about to shift, and so the
entire baseline of what we're
dying and being reborn into is
about to change. You.
When we make this transition,
and we will all be there in some
way, shape or form, we will we
will feel it will be part of it.
It's going to be multiple
generations, but we will all be
part of it. And when it happens,
and as it happens, and as this
exquisite creature comes out of
our historical womb and walks
the earth, we will look back on
all the pain from Homo erectus,
all the terrible suffering, all
the things we've done to each
other, all the horrendous things
we've done to each other, all
the loneliness and all the
terrible things, we will look
back on it and say, it was worth
it. It was worth it, because
this being is the most
exquisite, beautiful being.
Picture humanity with its heart
completely healed of all the
wars and of all the rapes and of
all the just completely whole
again in a new way. Picture the
mind just radiantly strong, not
fragmented, not torn apart and
no conflict within the psyche.
No. Push, pull, chest,
completely transparent on the
earth of the earth green to its
roots, and yet at the same time,
in easy communion with the
surrounding intelligence of the
universe. Heaven on Earth, for
such a species as this. It was
one of the greatest blessings of
all the work, just to be able to
see what history is making, what
is in the process of emerging
and and the sessions told me you
have to start writing more about
the future human, because when
it's it gets dark, and we're
going into the darkness. If you
don't have a vision of what's
coming, if you don't understand
what's being birthed by the pain
it's you're going to get lost in
the pain. The humans will get
lost, and it'll but if you have
a vision again, and you all
know, you all have the intuition
you were you had it before you
were born. You took it into this
incarnation. You feel it, and
it's important to hold on to
that. It's important to really,
really deeply in your bones,
know that everything that you're
investing in, you are working
with the universe to bring this
forward, and it will come
forward. It's taking us right up
to the edge of extinction.
Really, the old has to die in
order to give birth to this
magnificent creature. This is,
this is a, you know, a species
of Buddhas, a species of Christ,
a species of Prophets. This is
when the feminine is completely
healed and reconciled with the
masculine, giving complete
unprecedented access to the
blessings of cosmic
intelligence, and it is
absolutely embodied. No up and
out cosmology, no escapist
theologies anymore, and no
Bardo. The Bardo is in the
process of emptying itself. In
this process, the Bardo is a
fragment of is a condition of a
temporary condition in the
evolutionary saga. We are in the
process, by becoming more
integrated. We are in the
process of emptying the Bardo.
This species will not need that
type of buffer. This is what
we're working this is one
person's poor grasp at what we
are working for. But I think we
all feel it. We know it. I mean,
this is not this is just a piece
of one person seeing something.
What it is is much bigger than
any one person can see. Yeah.
Thank you. Thank you.
Unknown: I.