Unknown: Good morning, so I now
have the joy of introducing to
you our first speaker this
morning, and also, I have to
say, one of my most influential
teachers, Christopher Bache.
Chris is professor emeritus in
the Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he
taught for over 30 years in
psychology of religion,
Transpersonal studies, Buddhism
and Eastern religions. For two
years, Chris was the director of
transformative learning at the
Institute of Noetic Sciences in
Petaluma, and he is also adjunct
faculty at CIS where each of his
classes feels like one is being
held and participating in a
transformative sacred container.
His publications include life
cycles, the living classroom and
his groundbreaking work, dark
night, early dawn this morning,
Chris will be speaking on
exploring the boundaries of
death and rebirth in LSD
psychotherapy. Please join me in
welcoming Chris Bache. You
Chris Bache: Good morning,
everyone. It's a true joy to
join you this morning in the
continuing celebration of Stan
Grof, extraordinary lifetime
accomplishment as a scholar, a
healer and a pioneer, like many
others in this room, Stan has
had a profound influence on my
life. He changed the direction
of my professional and personal
life. The turning point for me
came in 1978 I just finished
graduate school in philosophy of
religion, which left me an
atheistically inclined agnostic
and begun my career as a young
academic. I was in a time of
transition, and I didn't know it
at the time, but I was in a
Saturn Return, and I read realms
of the human unconscious, and in
that one reading, I found my
life's work. I was convinced
that the people who would make
the most substantial
contribution to my field and
philosophy of religion, would
soon be writing out of an
experiential basis, not simply a
conceptual basis. And here was a
man who was opening up a
methodology for exploring the
deep psyche that was more had so
much extraordinary potential and
with such solid scholarship
behind it, that I knew I could
trust this man. So I made the
choice to begin what turned out
to be a 20 year journey, working
with high doses of LSD that
lasted between 1979 and 1999 and
what I'm going to talk about
today basically comes out of my
attempts to understand my
experiences on that journey and
after this journey, my life has
never been the same. How do you
thank someone for such a gift as
that? The experience of dying
and being reborn is one of the
central dynamics of Holotropic
and psychedelic work, and at the
same time, it's deeply puzzling.
This morning, I'd like to share
with you my attempts to address
three basic questions about the
Death-Rebirth dynamic. First
question, why does death become
as large as it sometimes does in
psychedelic therapy. Secondly,
why does death repeat itself so
many times in this long process?
And third, and perhaps most
difficultly, why what is
actually dying in the
Death-Rebirth process along the
way, I'd like to also revise the
discussion of Death-Rebirth that
I presented in my book Dark
Night early dawn, which I now
find to be incomplete. Now I'm
just going to be giving you
quick bullet points this morning
of an article that discusses
this in greater length. This
article will appear. There we
go. Okay. Well, back, back.
Okay. This is the book that Tom
Roberts mentioned yesterday,
edited by Harold Abram Evans.
Evans is Harold here. Raise your
hand. This is a wonderful two
volume book. Many of the
speakers who are presenting here
today are included in this two
volume work, and you'll find a
more complete discussion of what
I'm going to be presenting today
here. So let's jump into it. Why
does death become as large as it
sometimes does in LSD
psychotherapy? I wrote dark
night, early dawn, in part to
answer this. Question, so I need
to give you a little bit of
background. My first two years
of psychedelic work were focused
on the perinatal level of
consciousness. For two years, my
sessions were filled with the
usual perinatal symptomology,
extreme existential
confrontations, convulsive
seizures and various forms of
fetal experiences, and then this
eventually culminated in a
Death-Rebirth experience that
turned my life inside out and
snapped my identity like a twig.
I began the day as a white
middle class, fresh out of the
Ivy League, philosopher obsessed
with the meaning of life, and I
was forced to become women,
hundreds of women of color,
women with no educational
background, women with no
philosophical horizons. And it
was frightening. The inversion
of my values, and particularly
the loss of my sexual identity
was shattering. It was the
perfect hell for a male
academic. When I lost the
distinctions that had defined my
life, I died and I was reborn
into a new world, the world, the
extraordinarily beautiful world
of the feminine explored under
the arm of the great mother.
Immediately after this, a new
cycle began, in which I was
repeatedly immersed in
experiences of collective
anguish that dwarfed these early
sessions and shattered all my
previous frames of reference. In
this second phase, I entered an
ocean of suffering that expanded
session by session until it
eventually encompassed the
entire history of the human
race. The dying in these
sessions was vast and elemental
in scale and intensity. One
excerpt will give the flavor the
anguish thickened into a
terrible horror acted out around
me on all sides. The forms of
the horror were so many that
there was no way to describe it.
Disembowelings by the score, the
mauling of lives, deaths in the
1000s, swirling forms so
complex, multi dimensional and
multi thematic that isolated
images barely stand out. It was
war, savagery, destruction,
killing and anguish. It lasted
hours. I know many in this room
have had similar experiences.
This phase of work lasted four
years and 28 sessions, one year
of active work, then a six year
break, followed by three years
of active work. My first
interpretation of these
experiences was to see them as
leading to a deepening of ego
death, as leading to a more
complete ego death. My
assumption was that if any form
of death were taking place in a
session, there had to be pieces
of dying in somewhere in the
mix, pieces of ego dying
somewhere in the mix. What did
the sensation of dying attach
to, if not to an ego Eventually,
however, this assumption was
overwhelmed by the sheer volume
and intensity of the collective
suffering involved. These
episodes went on for too many
years and were too extreme in
their content for me to continue
seeing them as being drawn in
through resonance to a core of
unfinished ego death. This
forced me to reassess the
boundaries and the goal of the
entire therapeutic enterprise.
The conclusion I eventually came
to was that these collective
episodes were not primarily
aimed at the transformation of
my personal consciousness, but
rather they were aimed at the
transformation and healing of
the species mind as a whole. In
dark night, early dawn, I
abandoned the person centered
narrative I had been assuming
that the goal of therapy was the
healing of the individual, and
adopted a larger narrative by
integrating Rupert sheldrakes
concept of Morphic fields into
Stan's paradigm, the way open to
viewing these collective ordeals
as part of A larger process
aimed at healing the scars that
humanity still carried in its
collective memory. I think that
in these highly energized
states, the field of the
collective psyche is sometimes
activated so intensely that it
triggers a collective healing
process through some fractal
flip that I had not even thought
possible at the time, the
patient in My Sessions had
stopped being me and had become
humanity itself, or some part of
humanity. So I want to show you
a couple of slides. But to do
this, I have to sort of show you
the vocabulary. First. Stan's
perinatal matrices organized as
a cycle, and then drawing upon
Rick and Stan's work on the
correlations between the
planetary archetypes and the
perinatal matrices, changing
this into the glyphs where one
Neptune, Saturn, Pluto and
Uranus, and then this image
simply an image to suggest the
relationship between ego,
represented as the little drop
at the bottom and the vast
expanse of tart, of perinatal,
of the Transpersonal territory
and the Death-Rebirth cycle at
the perinatal level, at the
interface between personal
consciousness and Transpersonal
consciousness
in dark, night, early dawn, I
kept the perinatal vocabulary to
describe these collective
ordeals, but I tried to stretch
the rationale for their
appearance. I proposed that a
person's experience of the
perinatal domain could tilt or
slant towards either the
personal or the Transpersonal
side of that interface. If your
parent if your perinatal
experience tilted in the
personal side, you might
experience the loss of your
physical identity intertwined
with reliving your biological
birth. But I hypothesize that if
your perinatal experience tilted
towards the Transpersonal side
of the interface, then you might
experience your death and
rebirth in a state of profound
fusion with the human species,
in which case the birth canal
would become the birth canal of
history. I also suggested that
there were two tiers of death
and rebirth operating here, one
tier aimed at personal ego
death, and another tier aimed at
collective ego death, trying to
hold these two together. At the
present time, however, I've
shifted to what I think is a
simpler and more elegant way to
understanding these episodes. My
current thinking emphasizes that
death and rebirth is an
archetypal cycle that repeats
itself many times as we move
through deeper stages of
psychedelic unfolding. It is a
wheel that, like the wheel of
Buddha, Dharma, turns multiple
times being an archetypal wheel
any single Death-Rebirth
experience can draw in elements
from multiple levels of reality,
but being a cycle, it repeats
itself in different forms as one
moves into deeper dimensions of
consciousness. So the essence of
my revision of dark night, early
dawn is this, rather than seeing
these episodes of collective
suffering, at least in my
experience, as a protracted
first turning of the wheel of
death and rebirth, now I see
them as a second turning of that
wheel. They are the second
movement of a larger symphony, a
movement taking place at the
subtle level of consciousness, a
movement whose dynamics are
inherently collective, focused
on the collective patient and
aimed at a collective
transformation in a personal
Exchange. Exchange with Stan on
this topic, he supported this
revision. He wrote me quote, I
feel that for clarity, we should
change the terminology and make
it clear that the term perinatal
should be used only for fetal
experiences and not for
experiences of death and rebirth
on higher levels of the
Transpersonal spectrum with no
relation to biological birth. So
that brings us now to the next
question. The second question,
why does dying repeat itself so
many times in psychedelic
therapy? Let me return to my
personal story. When this long
phase of collective dying and
being reborn had ended. It was
followed by a series of five
overwhelming positive sense
sessions that seemed to
constitute a mega rebirth. I
felt overwhelmed by grace and
filled with blessings. I had a
deep sense that I had
accomplished the primary purpose
of my entire incarnation. At
this point, I didn't know what
to expect after all these years,
I hoped that the dying, the
ordeal of dying, would stop
sooner or later. I thought the
transition to Transpersonal
reality would become easier, and
it would have, I think, if I had
stayed within the boundaries of
Transpersonal experience that I
had been initiated into thus
far. But for better or for
worse, the method of exploration
I was you I had chosen to use
was so powerful that it kept
pushing me beyond my
experiential limits, and I was
working with five, 600
micrograms in of LSD in totally
internalized sessions that are.
You know, the whole works. So
another image, I don't have any
interest, vested interest in how
many cycles of Death-Rebirth,
and how you describe the
multiple levels of reality. I'm
going to be using the language
of psychic, subtle, causal
levels of reality. But we may
have many different maps for
mapping the vast expanse of
Transpersonal territory. It's
just the principle that I'm
trying to illustrate with this
graphic. Over the next six years
and 35 sessions, a third phase
opened in the work in which I
was propelled through a series
of Death-Rebirth experiences
that drew me ever more deeply
into the divine. I was spun into
the radiance of what the
Buddhists call sambhogakaya, and
what I came to call the domain
of diamond Luminosity. I had
known light many times before
this, but this was an
exceptionally pure light. It was
a different order of reality
altogether. Its clarity was so
overwhelming and its energy so
pure that returning to it became
my only goal, and it completely
extinguished any residual
interest I had in exploring
dimensions of archetypal reality
that had previously fascinated
me. This is something different.
When this phase was over, I
counted six cycles of death and
rebirth. There were many deaths,
of course, but six seminal
breakthroughs. And it's the
pattern of experience that's
important to the point I'd like
to make here, that death and
rebirth is a cycle that repeats
itself at successive levels of
initiation into the cosmos, no
matter how complete and
satisfying each rebirth was, it
was in time followed by more
experiences of dying as the
spiral continued to turn. Death
repeats itself, not because it
has failed to hit the mark and
ego has survived, but rather
because the Divine is an
infinite landscape with
countless levels to explore each
death is a gateway to what lies
beyond. In his beautiful book,
the ultimate journey. Stan
describes some of the forms that
death can take at these
Transpersonal levels. He writes,
we may identify with our
ancestors or people from
different countries and
historical periods who are dying
or whose lives are threatened.
Such sequences from the
Collective Unconscious can
sometimes be associated with a
sense of personal remembering,
which characterizes them as past
incarnational memories. Death
can even be experienced in full
identification with an animal or
plant. Death is also powerfully
represented in the collective
unconscious as mythological
motifs of death and rebirth and
as various eschatological
themes, including specific death
gods and underworlds of various
cultures, the archetype of death
astral or Bardo realms, the post
humanist journey of the soul and
abodes of the beyond. Only Stan,
I think, could write a sentence
like that, really. And you know,
he knows what he's talking
about. That's what gives that's
what's so amazing. I really, I
wouldn't, I don't think I would
have had the courage to go some
of the places I went if I had
not known that he had gone there
before me and lived to tell the
tale. At whatever level it takes
place the core of dying is
always the same, complete loss
of control, absolute surrender,
a disorientation so deep that it
dissolves reality as we have
known it. And rebirth is always
the same, the experience of
awakening inside a new and
unanticipated dimension of
reality, the birth of a new
identity with new capacities,
the experience of absolute grace
of having been given infinitely
more than one has given up. But
within this basic structure, the
details of dying and being
reborn reflect the specific
level of consciousness at which
one is dying at which one is
working, the experiential
texture of each death, its
flavor, focus and function and
even I'd suggest, what is dying
changes as the work progresses.
After one has died and been
reborn many times, eventually,
the very concept of death loses
its meaning. One learns through
repetition that at the deepest
level of one's being it's
impossible to die. The form that
you are can die. Reality as you
have known it can be destroyed
multiple times, but the
innermost essence of your being
always. Re emerges. The Phoenix
always rises. Death becomes
simply a measure of the degree
of purification being enacted
when purification reaches so
deeply that it dissolves the
form that you are then dying has
returned to grace you, and this
is what I mean by calling it
purification unto death. It was
during this third phase that I
surrendered one more assumption
about the Death-Rebirth process,
namely, that there is an
ultimate end to this cycle, a
final death. I no longer believe
that this is the case.
I believe that the progression
is endless. The dying stops when
one's capacity for discovery is
exhausted and one simply can
take no more. Now let me qualify
this carefully, because I know
it goes against the notion that
a complete death is a final
death when one's private
existence has been dissolved,
one can enter a state of oneness
that is completely and utterly
satisfying. One rests in the
source of existence. One with
all that is you cannot imagine
anything more satisfying. And
yet my experience has been that
with repeated immersion in this
condition, new dimensions of
oneness eventually reveal
themselves, and new levels of
joy are associated with each of
these levels, the one exists in
many modalities, and therefore
can be known in many modalities,
always one, but in different
depths of expression. So then
that brings us to, what is it
that's actually dying? And here
I want to affirm a delicate both
and balance. It's the individual
who undergoes these deaths and
absorbs them. They become part
of his or her life story, and so
they belong to the individual.
On the other hand, I think that
these deaths also belong to the
universe in ways that transcend
the individual. It is something
it is doing. The Universe uses
these opportunities to heal
itself and commune with itself
in ways that reach beyond the
individual. I think both these
perspectives are true and need
to be affirmed. So what is
dying? Well, first in the early
deaths, particularly the ego, is
dying, the constrictions and
wounds, the illusions, the
habits that are created by our
earthly history. But in the
later sessions, after ego has
surrendered its grip on our
consciousness, what exactly is
dying? Then there is often an
acute sensation of dying. But
what does it attach to? Well, I
think part of the answer is some
aspect of the species ego is
dying when the wheel of death
and rebirth is turning at the
subtle level of reality, where
the deaths are largely
collective. What is dying, I
think, is some part of the
species ego that is some
collective nodule of pain and
suffering that's living inside
the collective unconscious. When
the patient shifts from being
the individual to being the
species. Mind, the pulse of life
we are living in those hours is
the pulse of human history. We
may participate in this death
and rebirth, but we do so less
as an individual and more as a
fractal member of the entire
species. The Coex systems that
are resolving themselves are not
personal correct systems at this
point, but collective coexist
systems in the collective
unconscious, what I call the
meta matrices of the collective
unconscious. But there's another
level I think that we can move
to what's dying at these levels,
and it's what I named the
shamanic persona. Now, all of us
have had the experience after a
session has ended that we
sometimes can't hold on to all
the knowledge and all the
experience and all the insights
we had during a session. And
yet, when we re enter the
psychedelic state, we find that
this missing knowledge is there
waiting for us, and we resume
our psychedelic identity when
the next session opens. Now,
this common experience suggests
that the psyche retains and
integrates our psychedelic
experiences at levels deeper
than our conscious awareness,
ego, ego state. Psychology has
demonstrated that this
compartmentalization of
experience is actually a common
feature of our psychological
makeup. And I'm thinking here of
the work of Gordon Emerson, John
Rowan and Tom Zinser. I think
ego state psychology can throw
important light on how our
psyche manages the extreme
fluctuations that take place in
awareness and psych. Psychedelic
therapy. Specifically, I want to
suggest that in the repeated
opening and closing of awareness
in psychedelic sessions, a semi
autonomous state specific
consciousness is formed that
retains and integrates and
preserves the knowledge and the
capacities that we had acquired
in our sessions. I call this
psychedelically generated entity
the shamanic persona. It can be
thought of as a state specific
Alter Ego. There are many
variables which affect the
integrity of the shamanic
persona, but basically, as a
general rule of thumb, the
better run the session, the
tighter and more coherent will
be the shamanic persona that
emerges now, returning to an
earlier slide, when one system
begins to open to levels of
Transpersonal reality that are
deeper than the levels that you
have previously been exposed to.
Our earlier psychedelic history
must yield to this deeper
territory, our previous
psychedelic knowledge and the
identity based on that knowledge
must surrender control before a
deeper mode of Transpersonal
knowing can emerge and
stabilize. In essence, then what
I think is dying in these
sessions is sometimes the
shamanic persona, its death may
feel like a personal death, but
it's not the ego that's dying
here, but rather a deeper
individual identity that has
been birthed inside one's
previous sessions. One shamanic
persona may die and be reborn
multiple times after one
shamanic persona dies and one's
experiences stabilizes at a
deeper level of Transpersonal
reality, the second shamanic
persona will retain the memories
of the first Persona and then
will add to it the memories of
the Knowledge and the
experiences from this deeper
level down the road, when a
still deeper level of
Transpersonal reality opens the
second persona will have to die
and yield surrender in order for
Transpersonal experience to be
stabilized at these deeper
levels. I'd like to suggest
maybe one more layer of the
answer to this question, what is
it that's actually dying? I
think it's actually a dimension
of the cosmos itself. And here I
am thinking primarily about
those deaths that take place at
what we might some have
described as causal level of
reality. First, we might pause
to ask, What could possibly die
at these sublime levels of
reality? What need do causal
level reality? Levels of causal
levels of reality have of
rebirth at all? I don't know the
final answer to these questions.
I can only share some intuitions
that I've formed over the years,
and to do so, I need to very
quickly invoke Sri Aurobindo
involutionary evolutionary
cosmology, because his vision
resonates so deeply with the
cosmology that emerges in
psychedelic states, as Stan has
described so beautifully in his
book, The cosmic game.
Aurobindo, vision is of a
cascading involution of the
Divine, generating multiple
levels of reality, all of the
all divine, but with, but within
those multiple levels, a
descending scale of self
awareness of divinity like a
series of one way mirrors, the
divine looking down sees all,
but the divine looking up sees
less. Now at the end of dark
night, early dawn in the last
chapter, I made the point that
in such a multi level cosmology,
a Death-Rebirth Event can
function simultaneously as a
liberation from below to the
above and an infusion of above
to the below. You can often
stand at that threshold, and you
can feel the energy moving in
both directions. So a
Death-Rebirth can function as
ascent and also as descent. So
assume for a moment that we have
managed to stabilize experience
at the low causal level for a
few precious hours inside our
sessions, we exist as a life
form that breathes the rarefied
air of causal reality, bathing
in Divine oneness. When through
further exercises, a doorway
opens to still deeper levels of
causal reality. It allows a
cosmic communion to take place,
deep communes with deep a.
Bringing different levels of
Transpersonal reality into
conscious communion with each
other, even if only for a few
hours, seems to nourish and
bring joy to the weave of
existence as the below remembers
the above and the blessings of
above pour themselves into the
below. It is a cosmic dance
taking place between deep levels
of the Divine. It is God
communing with God.
So what dies and is reborn at
these deeper cycles of death and
rebirth, beyond the ego, beyond
the species ego, beyond a series
of shamanic persona. I think
what dies and is reborn is
something of truly cosmic
proportions, some dimension God
is calling, some dimension that
is extraordinarily vast,
surrenders and in that
surrendering awakens more
completely to itself, and much
to our surprise, the divine
appears to genuinely appreciate
our help in facilitating this
communion. Stan, thank you from
the bottom of my heart, thank
you. You
Unknown: i.