Chris Bache: Special rise in in
geistest
Unknown: universe petition I
Chris Bache: ch Marcus, I want
to thank you very much for the
opportunity to be here today and
for the opportunity to address
the time waiver community, which
is certainly such a progressive
and wonderful community. Martin
mentioned Stanislav Grof. He's
the one of the co founders with
Abraham Maslow of Transpersonal
psychology, and he's the
foremost authority of
integrating LSD and other
psychedelic substances into the
therapeutic process. When I
first read realms of the human
unconscious. His first book, I
read it in 1979 I was a brand
new young junior faculty member
at the University. As soon as I
read that book, I realized that
psychedelics would represent a
turning point, a pivot point,
not only in psychology, but also
in philosophy, and I was trained
as a philosopher of religion, so
I made the decision to begin a
psychedelic voyage. I was
convinced that the most
important work which would be
done in the near future would be
be done by people writing out of
an experiential basis, not
simply an intellectual basis,
and so I began the process of
doing that experiential work.
Now I have to assume a certain
familiarity with Stan Grof work.
I won't try to describe the
methodology of working with
psychedelics. It's a very
intense methodology. It's not
tripping and going to a concert.
It's working in very
contemplative, isolated
circumstances, isolated from the
world, with eye shades going
deeply within. I did this work
over 20 years. Over 20 years, I
did 73 high dose LSD sessions
using Stan Grof paradigm. I
worked for four years, and then
I stopped for six years, which
are not part of the story, and
then I worked very intensely for
another 10 years now. To do this
work, I had to split my life in
half. On the outside, I
continued to be a university
professor. I gave my lectures. I
did the things that university
professors do in my inner life,
I began this very intense
journey, and I kept them
separate. I kept a firewall
between the two. I You could I
could not talk about my
psychedelic work with Well, I
talked with my friends at the
university, but I never brought
them into my classes. I never
brought it to my students, it's
only after I've retired from the
university and after I'm passed
the statute of limitations for
doing this work, because I
stopped this work in 1999 that
I'm able to really bring forward
the philosophical work, the
philosophical significance of
these experiences. And this is
what I'd like to share with you
tonight. I am just finishing a
book that I'm calling diamonds
from heaven. I don't know
whether this is what it will
look like, because it's still
being considered by a publisher,
but in my mind, this is how I've
imagined it. Irvin Laszlo has
contributed the forward to the
book, and what I would like to
do is just basically take you
through some of the highlights
of this journey, just little
touches, little scenarios here
and there along the way. And I'd
like to emphasize that I did
this work as a philosopher, not
as a therapist. I wasn't
primarily seeking healing. I was
seeking knowledge of how the
universe works. I saw myself as
pursuing a new philosophical
method, a method that was
pioneered by William James in
the varieties of religious
experience. And this method
consists of basically three
steps, three stages, first to
enter, to structurally push the
boundaries of your experience in
carefully structured psychedelic
sessions. Second, to come back
and make a phenomenologically
complete and accurate record of
your experiences within 24 hours
after every session, and third,
to critically analyze your
experience, to bring it into
dialog with other fields of
knowledge, and to compare it
with the experiences of other
psychedelic explorers. So this
is what happened. Now. This. Is
only the third time that I've
tried to speak about these
things in public. So you'll have
to forgive me if I follow my
notes maybe a little more
closely than I might otherwise
do. A few comments about method,
and then we'll go to the
content. Oh, interesting. The
spacing is different than on my
computer. Most of you are aware
of the difference between low
dose psychely therapy and high
dose psychedelic therapy. When I
was doing this work, I saw
myself doing basically an
extended series of high dose
psychedelic therapy. The
original protocol in Spring
Grove Hospital restricted
psychedelic sessions to a
maximum of three sessions. What
they were trying to do was to
trigger a near death type
experience for people who are
approaching their own physical
death. And so I saw, I thought,
whatever could be done three
times safely could be done more
times safely. What I learned,
however, was that while I my
work always stayed within the
bounds of safety, working with
multiple sessions with high
doses of LSD opened up
challenges and opportunities
that weren't really considered
in the first early stages of
psychedelic therapy. And so
looking back over the course of
my work, I figured I had to have
a different name. I had to find
a different name for it. So I
call it psychedelic exploration.
The method is the method of
psychedelic therapy, complete
isolation, working with
eyeshades, with a sitter, always
with a sitter, carefully
calibrated music to pace the
stages of the opening and
closing of a session. The
difference is the number of
sessions involved. For me, 73
sessions. Over 20 years, I kept
detailed records of all of my
sessions. I even tracked the
astral, logical variables of my
sessions, looking at the
correlations between transits
and my session experiences. I
kept meticulous notes over these
years, about 400 pages of raw
experiential data and the story
I'm telling in diamonds from
heaven. And I call it diamonds
from heaven, by the way, because
I wanted to start at the end of
the story. I thought put the
title that indicates where it
ends, but it took a long time
before the diamonds came in. It
isn't really a personal story. I
mean, it is a personal story,
but it's not primarily a
personal story. This diagram
represents kind of a series of
sessions, and they're drawn
overlapping, to emphasize that
one session pretty much starts
where the second session
stopped. And I found that my
personal experiences, the
healing experiences and insights
into my personal life, tended to
take place at the beginning and
the end of these sessions, when
I was leaving and coming back
into time and space, but when I
was in the peak of the
experiences indicated by these
large circles, after about the
first 12 or 15 sessions, I was
operating in a state of
consciousness that was far
beyond personal states of
consciousness, and that's the
story that I'm trying to tell in
diamonds From heaven. That's the
philosophically significant
story, because that's, I think,
the story that in some way we
all share. It's all part of our
collective inherence and
inheritance. It's the
cosmological story which is the
important story. When one does
this work, one goes through many
cycles, many iterations of death
and rebirth, not just ego.
Death, the first circle this
drop everything below the cross
line takes place below time and
space reality. That bottom line
kind of represents ego and the
first Death-Rebirth cycle, which
I've marked with the
astrological glyphs, kind of in
recognition of Rick Tarnas and
Stan Grof insights into the
correlations between
astrological transits and one's
experiences in Non-ordinary
states, which I only partly
affirm, my experiences affirm
and then don't confirm, but that
first Death-Rebirth takes place
at what Stan calls the perinatal
level of consciousness, And one
moves into deeper states of
consciousness, and then death
and rebirth repeats itself in a
deeper formulation, taking you
into a deeper level of reality
and a deeper level of reality.
Stan Grof follows Ken Wilber in
describing these levels in terms
of psychic, subtle, causal level
reality. I don't have any vested
interest in what scale you use,
and certainly to differentiate
only three dimensions of
consciousness, Transpersonal
consciousness is elementary,
because there are 1000s and
1000s dimensions of
consciousness that one moves
into. But basically, just to
give a suggestion that there are
many levels of. Consciousness
and Transpersonal consciousness,
and one enters these levels of
consciousness in stages. And at
every stage there is a cost
which is exacted. There is a
depth of surrender that takes
place. In the beginning, what's
asked is for you to surrender
your ego. But there are other
types of surrender that take
place at deeper levels of the
journey.
To draw only one circle is to
oversimplify. Sometimes these
indicate numbers of sessions
entering deeper and deeper into
causal reality. There are cycles
within cycles within cycles. So
you can mark of these all as one
cycle. But in fact, there were
cycles within cycles within
cycles as the journey continues.
So the easiest way now is just
to give you the chapters, to
show you the chapters of the
book, and maybe share a few
comments on each of the
chapters. So here are the
chapters of diamonds from Heaven
crossing the perinatal plane,
the ocean of suffering, deep
time in the soul, initiation
into the universe, the greater
real of archetypal reality, a
benediction of Blessings, the
birth of the future human and
diamond Luminosity. Now there
are some missing chapters.
There's a methodology chapter
and there's a chapter where I
give a typical introduce to a
typical session day. But these
are the chapters that carry the
content of the sessions, the
content of the experiences.
Yes, the first crossing the
perinatal plane is the easiest
to summarize, because it's the
one most people are most
familiar with from reading Stani
grofs work. One goes through
many fetal experiences. One
relives one's experience in the
womb. One's relives one's own
birth. One goes through many
variations of the death and
rebirth process. My going
through this level took about
two years and 10 sessions, and
in the end, in the ninth and
10th session, the universe, in
my version of ego death, it just
snapped me like a twig. The ego
is on the end, not very
difficult to take apart. It
snapped me like a twig by
turning me into the exact
opposite of everything I had
known myself to be. I entered
the day as a white, middle
class, highly educated
philosopher concerned with the
meaning of existence, and it
just took all of those variables
and reverse them. I went in for
hours and hours experiencing the
lives of women and women of
color from multiple cultures
around the world, women who were
poor, women who had no interest
in philosophy whatsoever. And
yet I was all of these things. I
was all of these beings lives.
It was terribly frightening for
it. It was just scared me to
death. It was the perfect hell
for a male philosopher. There's
nothing wrong with being a
woman, of course, and there's
nothing wrong with being poor,
and there's nothing being wrong
with being not interested in
philosophy. The issue is, it was
my identification with my
maleness, my identification with
my middle class, whatever,
whatever, which was the problem
is what the universe had to
break in me. And the message was
not simply recover your lives as
women, because I know I've had
former lives as women, this was
different. This was where you're
going. Gender does not exist,
let go. So as part of my entry
into deeper states of
consciousness, my identity as a
male was taken from me, and when
I surrendered and when it was
taken from me, I entered into
the most glorious experience of
womanhood. I experienced
hundreds and hundreds of women.
I experienced all the aspects of
female experiences that I could
imagine. I conceived, I gave
birth, I laughed at my husband's
I wish every man could have the
experience of having such a deep
experience of women's lives when
I went into the next phase, the
next two years of work, I
entered a domain of
extraordinary collective
suffering. I entered
systematically deeper and deeper
and deeper. I was taken into
just an orgy of pain and
suffering. It seemed to comprise
all the wars of history, all the
droughts, all the famines. It
was just it was a true ordeal.
In the beginning, I thought that
this represented a deepening of
ego death. I thought that
somehow pieces of my ego. It
slipped through the first death.
And this was somehow a
collective this collective
suffering represented a
deepening of ego death. But
eventually this went on for so
long and it involved so many
1000s and hundreds of 1000s of
beings that I came to a
different conclusion. The
conclusion I came to was that
somehow these sessions were
using something. Was using my
sessions not to heal my private
person. It wasn't about healing
my private life. It was about
trying to heal the collective
psyche of the human race that
somehow all the trauma of all
those wars and all that violence
through history has lodged
itself into the collective
psyche. And at least in this
particular context, one of the
ways that the universe was
trying to heal the human species
was in these expanded states of
consciousness beginning to
siphon and draw out of it
through this awareness, the pain
of the human species, and
transform that pain and bring it
into the light. Now, psychedelic
sessions have two halves. There
is the first half, which is the
cleansing half, where I was
experiencing this ocean of
suffering, and then there's the
second half. You go through a
certain amount of work, and the
suffering comes to a
culmination, and after that, the
rest of the session, you're spun
into positive, ecstatic,
Transpersonal spaces. The ocean
of suffering lasted two years,
but actually there was one year
of work. Then I took a six year
break, and then I started
another 10 years of work and the
ocean of suffering, when I
resumed my work six years later,
started exactly where it had
stopped six years before, which
I think is an indication of the
precision and the intentionality
of the intelligence that we are
engaging In these deep states of
consciousness when I came
through the ocean of suffering
in the first half the first
year, I entered into what I call
deep time in the soul. I had a
series of experiences in which I
experienced my entire life, from
beginning to end, complete. I
experienced the distilled
essence of everything that I was
in the process of becoming, and
everything that I had become. It
was my entire life complete,
start to finish. And I kept
coming back to it again and
again and again the same system
field, opening up layers more
and more layers, I began to have
insights into the people I was
related to, to my wife, to the
family members. The first time I
entered this state, when I came
out of it, I couldn't remember
any of it. It was the most
meaningful experience of my
life, but I couldn't remember it
when I went back into it, a
second and a third and a fourth
time, however, I began to
remember more and more I could
hold on to more and more of the
experiences. And this is an
important epistemological point.
When you enter these states of
consciousness, you, in the
beginning, will enter into new
states of consciousness which
are so cognitively original you
can't hold on to it. And this is
where I think people talk about
ineffability. But if you keep
going back to the same state of
consciousness again and again
and again, you will remember
more and more. You literally
have to teach yourself how to
stay conscious in these deep
states of consciousness. And you
can teach yourself to stay
conscious in these deep states
of consciousness, it involves
tremendous purification. You go
through one level of
purification after another, but
you can go through and remain
conscious. Six years later, when
the ocean, when I entered my
work again and the ocean of
suffering resumed that time,
when I went into the ecstatic
portion of the experiences, I It
started in a completely
different space with no
explanation, I entered into what
I call the initiation into the
universe, a series of sessions
that took me deeper and deeper
into the universe and gave me a
carefully calibrated series of
instructions. It was like going
to course, except in this case,
the professor was the universe
itself. Now I give my sessions
names to help me remember them.
When I try to give them a name
that represents the pith of each
session, and I break my sessions
down into bullet points, I'm
trying to remember the entire
session and the entire journey.
And so these are the names of
the sessions that I'm addressing
in initiation into the universe.
Whoop. Sorry. Final visions,
forgot that one. Okay, all
right, initiation into the
universe you and I creating. So
it's taken back into the
original point, point of
creation, the cosmic tour. Some
of these are represented you, if
you. Heard these names before
they're in dark night, early
dawn. The Council of Elders
dying into oneness was a session
of repeatedly dying deeper and
deeper and deeper into oneness.
The master plan was the first of
a series of visions that took
place over many years in which I
was being shown what the
universe's agenda was for the
human race. I know it sounds
arrogant. It sounds like ego run
amok to say that, but in my
experience, what I was being
shown was what the evolutionary
trajectory was of humanity and
what the evolutionary agenda was
for humanity. Eventually, the
ocean of suffering reached a
level of intensity it's hard to
describe. It culminated in what
I call healing, the collective
wound, just a massive, huge
purification process of
collective healing. And when
that finish, it spun me into an
unprecedented a new level of
reality, a level of reality that
I call archetypal reality, the
greater real of archetype of
reality.
When I first entered archetypal
reality, my identity as a human
being began to fall away from
me. I found that there is an
identity that we have as a human
being that is deeper than the
identity we have as a specific
human being, and to enter into
archetypal reality, I literally
had to leave behind the entire
history of human race and the
not just my personal history,
but I had to leave behind the
conditions of human
consciousness images. It imaged
like being in the space station
orbiting above the earth. I
entered a state of consciousness
that was beyond the collective
psyche, and I was being worked
with for months, being taught
how to experience how reality
works at that level, beyond
archetype, beyond the collective
psyche. In my experience, there
were two levels of reality that
I experienced at that archetypal
level, one of them at the high
subtle level, one of them at the
low subtle level. At the high
subtle level, which I think of
as kind of the Platonic level. I
encountered living forms that
were responsible for creating
space time and the core
structures of space time, they
were vast. They were huge. My
mind imaged them like galaxies,
billions of light years across.
They were just enormous. I could
not wrap my mind around them.
They were like they were
archetypes, but they were not
like Plato's archetypes. They
were not eternal ideas in the
mind of an unchanging God. They
were living forms that were
changing, but over vast tracks
of time. Subsequently, I went
into lower, subtle level
reality, which is more of a
Jungian kind of level, I entered
into the living tissue of the
collective psyche. I had many
experiences over and over again,
of the wholeness that the human
psyche represents, that it is
even the human body. I had
experiences of the archetype of
the body, that all of us are
fractal manifestations of
aspects of and I experienced how
each of us in healing our
individual diseases is
contributing to the archetypal
structure of our human body as
it becomes stronger and stronger
through history, I began to have
experiences of reincarnation,
but as a collective process, I
had always imaged reincarnation
as an individual process, where
we individually are developing
our soul's journey. But I began
to have experiences of vast of
the human race as a single
organism, incarnating
intelligently, creatively,
intentionally, generation by
generation I was in working in
deep time experiencing the pulse
of humanity's self evolution
through incarnation of billions
and billions of beings every
century, just moving. It was
both simultaneously a Numinous
experience and an absolutely
devastating experience at the
same time to experience all of
humanity with all the
experiences that all of us are
going through in every
generation, to experience that
from the perspective of the
Unified intelligence that was
manifesting as the species and
evolving the species farther and
farther through time, it was
one. No, it gave me a completely
expanded horizon of the
intelligence of the universe.
After spending 18 months
exploring archetypal reality,
which is not long, and I went
through it with very big step.
So what my description is very
incomplete of the totality of
that reality. I entered a year
of extraordinary blessings. It
was, I called it the benediction
of blessings. It was one
blessing after another for an
entire year. These are the names
of the sessions. Oh, I've got to
keep up with my notes a little
bit more. These are the sessions
I dealt with in archetype of
reality. Let me jump back there
for just a second notice how
much cleansing is involved, even
when you're working at such a
deep level of consciousness.
Session 28 was an
extraordinarily positive
blessing. It was my first
contact with causal reality. I
touched this extraordinarily
beautiful, ecstatic state of
consciousness. I was only there
for 30 minutes, but the next
three sessions over six months
were just grueling Ordeals of
detoxification and purification.
What I came to understand is
each deeper state of
consciousness is a higher level
of energy. And when you enter a
deeper state of consciousness,
you you have to acclimate to
that higher level of energy.
Otherwise, your your experiences
there will be fragmented. You'll
be chaotically confused. And so
just that one touch of causal
reality, it took three sessions,
hours and hours of physical
psychological detoxification in
order for me to be able to
return to that state of
consciousness, so I could return
to it more clearly, so I could
stay more cognitively coherent
in that state. This is a pattern
that repeats itself over and
over and over again as you go
deeper and deeper into the
universe, so much so that I
began to dread the session.
After every major breakthrough,
there was a carrying out the
garbage quality every time I
broke through into a new
Luminous state of consciousness,
the next sessions were just just
terribly difficult. Now, now I
can go into the benediction of
blessings. I present four
sessions in the book. Each of
these was different. The forest
was an experience of oneness,
Shunyata, emptiness. It was like
no present, no self present in
me, no self present any in the
world. It's an absolute
transparency to the totality of
life as a living singularity. It
was a deep entry into causal
reality, singing the universe
away, jumping over, singing the
universe away, was an enter into
the primal void. It was an
entering into the Buddha womb,
Satchitananda. It was the
primal, fertile void that
underlies all manifest
existence. Jesus' blood was an
experience of overwhelming
experience of cosmic love. It's
just being drenched in you've
never been loved until you've
been loved like God. You know.
It's just just overwhelming
experience of love deeper than
anything I'd ever experienced
before. Let me mention the birth
of the diamond sole just a
little bit longer, because it
will come up again later in the
sessions. 11 years previous, I
had had the experience of my
life as a completed whole start
to finish. But in the 40th
session, I began to experience
the integration of all my former
lives they were coming in. It
was like winding A string and
around a kite spool. All my
former lives were coming in fast
and furious, and it was like
winding a string of white light
on a kite spool, and when it hit
a certain critical mass, it
exploded. All those individual
lives fused into one life and
they exploded. It was my first
contact with what I would call
diamond Luminosity. My heart
just ruptured and exploded. My
consciousness jumped far beyond
any consciousness of any
individual life. And I think
what I experienced at that day
was where reincarnation is
taking humanity. Reincarnation
is not adding a little bit
lifetime by lifetime, adding a
few more qualities, a few more
capacities, lifetime by
lifetime, reincarnation is
taking us into, I think,
eventually taking us into a
point where all of our former.
Lives, all of our history, all
of our learning, will fuse, and
when it fuses, it lifts us into
the next step in human
evolution, the soul literally
will wake up on earth. Because I
think reincarnation, we die. Our
mind gets large. We are born. We
contract to a small
consciousness. We go from the
soul to the ego, the soul to the
ego. But if we keep this up for
1000s of years, sooner or later,
sooner or later, the soul is
going to wake up on Earth, and
when that happens, everything
changes, because the soul
experiences life differently
than the ego does. The soul
experiences a depth of
connection with other beings,
because we've all we've been in
each other's lives for centuries
and centuries, the soul has a
different relationship to the
earth, because the soul knows
that the earth that it leaves
will be the earth it's going to
inherit in its next incarnation.
So it has a whole different
relationship to the issues of
ecology and care taking of the
Earth,
where the sessions went next
chronologically was into the
diamond Luminosity work. But
before I go into that, I need to
backtrack a little bit and talk
about the birth of the future
human. When I started this work,
I never imagined that what I'm
about to describe to you would
become part of it. I was
thinking that this I was doing
this work for my personal
healing, for my personal
transformation, my personal
enlightenment, whatever. But
what happened was I started in
the 23rd session, and in
multiple sessions over the
course of the years, I started
to have repeated visions of the
human race, the what was
happening to the human race. And
I think this is a natural
progression, because when you
die as an individual, when you
die as an ego and your
consciousness opens, it doesn't
just open into the oneness of
God. It opens up into the
species that you are, into the
life of the species. And just
like we have a feeling of our
individual age, you enter into
the age of your species. And I
was repeatedly shown that the
human species is coming into a
time of a tremendous exponential
explosion in its capacity. We
were coming into a time of great
awakening. So in this chapter, I
present what are six visions
that I call the visions of
awakening, visions that I pull
out of all these other sessions
that I've already presented, and
I just kind of weave them
together to tell, to show, the
coherent story, the story of
this great awakening, the story
of this birth that we are coming
into. And I had seen over four
years this story, but it never
showed me how it was going to
pull it off. I never saw how we
were going to make this jump in
consciousness. And then in 1995
a week before Christmas, I went
into I was expecting to go I was
in the diamond Luminosity work.
I was expecting to go one more
time into the diamond Luminosity
state. But instead, the universe
threw me far into deep time, far
into humanity's future, and it
gave me the experience of the
death and rebirth of our species
at a collective level, there was
nothing personal about my
experience. I I was the human
species. I was the psyche of the
planet as a whole. I had
dissolved into the collective
psyche, and I experienced a
death that took place at that
level. It was a Near-Death
Experience. But for the species,
there was a time we were
overtaken by conditions. It was
a loss of control. It was a loss
of deconstruction. It was a time
of great suffering. I think the
21st Century is going to be the
beginning of the dark night of
our collective soul. It is going
to be the time of the great
undoing. We're going to lose
control. We've postponed making
the important environmental,
ecological, cultural decisions
so many times that I think
there's no avoiding the fact
that we are coming to a time of
a great global systems crisis.
And just when it had reached its
worst, just when it was at its
worst, it passed. The storm
passed like a hurricane going
over an island. And when we
began to collect ourselves, to
pick ourselves off of the
ground, there was an exponential
growth. Growth of light within
the human species, an
exponential growth in
intelligence, in ideas, in
creativity, in social
formulations, in social formats,
new families, we're springing
up. I think that this process
that we are going through is
leading us not simply to
recreate our culture and
recreate society and to create a
new technology and a new
economy. It's literally a
transformation that is taking
place at the core of the
collective psyche. Our
collective psyche is going to
make a shift into a new
foundation, and after that
point, everyone born a human
being is going to be operating
out of a new foundation. I think
we truly are becoming a species
of Buddhas, a species of Christ
and prophets.
You, after the benediction of
blessings, I was completely
content. I mean, I the universe
had asked me to give something
in the ocean of suffering, and I
gave it, and it rewarded me with
more joy than I could ever
imagine. It was just an
overwhelming joy. I had known
God. I had known the fertile
void. It was, it was a
philosopher's dream come true. I
had no idea where things would
go, but there were still five
years ahead on the journey and
where it went. It took me into
after one more death and rebirth
cycle, it took me into an
extraordinarily hyper, clear
state of consciousness. It took
me into the light that I came to
call diamond Luminosity. It's
what the Buddhists call
Dharmakaya, the absolute clear
light of being. Now I had known
light many times before. Light
comes in, light had come in at
the subtle level of
consciousness. Light had come in
in many different dimensions,
but this is a different order of
light when I call it the diamond
light. I'm not simply using a
metaphor to describe the light.
I'm trying to describe a
particular quality of light, an
ultra clear, super luminescent,
just clear, beyond imagination.
I entered the diamond Luminosity
four times in the next four
years. Out of 25 sessions, only
four times did I enter the
diamond Luminosity. These are
the names that I gave these
sessions in between each entry
into the diamond Luminosity, as
you can imagine, tremendous
purification, tremendous
detoxification, healing the
system just but then I would get
spun into another experience of
this diamond light. There were
two movements in this process.
There was a progressive entering
deeper and deeper into the
diamond Luminosity into the 50th
session was the deepest I ever
went into the diamond Luminosity
I was in. I was in a state of
deep absorption into pure light.
I was light. My boundaries were
lost entirely. I was as I was as
happy as you can imagine a
person being. And just at that
moment, something happened that
changed my entire understanding
of life. My visual field pivoted
90 degrees, and in the far
distance I saw reality that was
as far beyond where I was as
where I was in the diamond light
was beyond Earth, time, space,
and in that reality, I saw
light, and I was hit by a ray of
light from that reality. It hit
me and it just shattered me. I
call it the absolute light, just
to give it a name. And that's
when I understood that it's an
infinite progression. There is
no end to the journey. There is
no reaching the end of God, the
end of the Divine. Like many of
us, I had adopted the belief
that there was an end to this
journey. It had been described
differently by different people,
oneness with God, or the super
cosmic void, entering the super
cosmic void. But I had entered
the Divine oneness many times,
and I had learned that there
were dimensions. Of oneness.
There are different variations
within there are depths of one
to oneness. And I had entered
the primal void, but I learned
that there are even depths of
void within void. But I had
always assumed that there was
still an end. I could get to an
end that would be the destinies
the final or stopping point. And
this taught me it's an infinite
progression, that there, there
is no stopping point. The Divine
is infinitely large, and that's
why, if I were doing it over
again, I wouldn't use the same
method that I'd used before. I
would be gentler with myself. I
would not push myself so hard to
enter so deep, so fast. Even
though 20 years may not be very
fast, I would be gentler with
myself, because now I know that
the goal of this work is not to
try to reach some state, some
condition. The goal of this work
is to open up and to let in as
much of the Divine into you as
you possibly can, and to allow
it to transform your life and to
transform your existence and
everything that you can do with
that awareness in life.
The last year's work is final
visions. These are the sessions
that I address in the book, the
last two visions. The last two
sessions were what I call the
goodbye sessions. I didn't know
I was stopping this work. I was
thought I was going to continue
to do it, but the consciousness
that had always guided my
sessions, it choreographed the
ending of our time together
before I knew what was
happening. It gave me an
overview of my entire life's
work. It showed me, in the end,
in this fruits of my labor, how
all of my work fit together,
what the correlations were. And
I used the experiences in that
session to actually organize the
telling of the story in diamonds
from heaven. And then it gave me
a series of last instructions
before we parted. But before
that happened, there was one
serious piece of work to do,
Chapter Seven, seven, session
70. On that session, the
universe put me through a strip
down which was one of the
hardest, most deepest, one of
the deepest, most demanding
strip downs that I had ever been
anywhere on the journey I would
not have believed it would have
been possible to go through so
many layers of dying and death
and just complete loose loss of
all reality as I went through in
this session, and after going
through this for an hour and a
half or Two hours that spun me
out into a condition of very
clear state of consciousness,
and it, to make a long story
short, since I'm already at the
end of my time, I'm past time.
I'm sorry. It took me deeper
into deep time than it had ever
taken me before. It took me
deep, deep into a time frame
somewhere on the order of 100
200,000 years. And it gave me a
series of experiences that were
the culmination of the birth of
the future human. It gave me the
capstone of the story of the
master story of where we're
going. It gave me the deepest
experience that I had of the
being that we are becoming, it
was as if I was taken into the
future and allowed to try on for
size, the being that the
creative intelligence of the
universe is bringing forward on
our planet, such a magnificent
being, just an extraordinary
being. It's so important that we
hold a vision of where we're
going, of what is actually
happening. Because as the Dark
Shadows gather in this century
and the century ahead, we could
lose ourselves in despair. We
could lose ourselves in
hopelessness if we don't
understand that we are in labor,
we are in labor, and we are
giving birth. And we're not
simply giving birth to a
slightly improved version of
ourselves. We are giving birth
to an extraordinary child, a
child that has never existed as
a species on this planet before.
One of the other things this
experience it taught me was it
gave me a series of lessons, and
it taught me something that was
a missing piece to everything
that I had been given before
about the birth of the future
human it told me that. It showed
me that we are built for speed.
Our species is built for speed.
We have a tendency to think of
human nature, you know, kind of
as a staff thing, human nature,
this. Human nature that but
really, if you step back into an
expanded time frame, and if you
think in terms of reincarnation,
you think in terms of all the
lives that we are winding
around, and then this gathering
of knowledge which is taking
place in the center, in the
archetypal center, when this
center shifts, there. An
exponential jump. And when you
look at the whole evolutionary
dynamic, that evolution, that
reincarnation, makes possible,
it becomes clear that we are
carrying our history on our
backs in much smaller packs than
we had, than we might think, if
we didn't take this large
perspective. We are built for
speed. The human species is
built for speed. We are built
for evolutionary acceleration,
and we are in a tremendously
accelerated time of history
right now and before any of us
were born, before we were born,
we knew what we were getting
into. We knew we chose. We knew
what was happening to the human
race. We knew what a hard time
this century was going to be,
and we made a choice to
participate in this time in
history, to be part of this
exciting and dynamic, if
difficult, but this important
progression. Now I'm done. My
time is done. I can't go on
further. I will just very
quickly say when I stopped, I
stopped my sessions for two
reasons, for pain, because my
subtle energy system was over
excited. Was kind of I was
running too much energy, even
though I had done I took a lot
of yoga, did meditation, did all
the things you try to do to take
care of yourself. But the main
reason I stopped was heartache.
I literally reached a point
where I could not take coming
back. I could not take coming
back out of the Divine once you
have dissolved completely into
light, once you have known the
joy of being light of
experiencing reality as light
time, space, reality can begin
to feel kind of dried up. And in
fact, when I stopped my
sessions, I entered a period of
deep, deep sadness. I did a good
job integrating my sessions as I
went, I really worked hard on
integrating my sessions, but
when I stopped my sessions, I
entered a deep, deep existential
sadness. And I know that near
death episode people have this
experience. I knew that Carl
Jung had this experience in the
hospital. I knew I was not alone
in this but I had entered so
deeply into the divine expanse
that my wound was particularly
deep. Eventually I reached a
point where I knew I was just
waiting to die. I was just
waiting. I was taking care of my
family. I was doing my lectures.
I was, you know, I was doing my
taking care of my
responsibilities, but in my
heart of hearts, I was just
waiting to die so that I could
return to my beloved.
Eventually, I began to realize
that's that's not right. This is
not a good way to live. It's not
not the way this work is
supposed to go. It's not good to
be living your life waiting to
die. So I made a determined
effort to bring myself into my
historical existence again, to
ground myself into time and
space. I learned that somewhere
along the way, I made a mistake.
The mistake I made was that I
had lost the balance between
Transcendence and immanence. I
had thrown myself so deeply into
divine Transcendence that I lost
my footing inside the imminent
divine, inside the body of God,
inside the physical presence of
God that we all are. It took me
about 10 years to get myself
fully grounded back in time and
space and fully kind of
comfortable back in time and
space again. And in this
respect, my experience on this
journey is a cautionary tale.
It's not simply like, you know,
the hero's journey, where you go
and you have an adventure and
you bring back with good news.
It's a cautionary tale. It's
Transcendence is a it's a
complicated, paradoxical thing.
A little bit of Transcendence is
good. It's healing. It can, it
can help us understand who we
are and what we are and where we
are and what here is. But too
much Transcendence can cause you
to lose sight of an equally
important fact, the fact that
the physical world is the
manifest body of the Divine. So
thank you very much for letting
me tell my story to you. You
Unknown: Ian.