Iain McNay: So hello and welcome
again to conscious TV. I'm Ian
Mcnay, and my guest today is
Chris Bache, Hi, Chris. Hi, Ian,
and we found Chris quite
recently. He was doing a lecture
in London, and I read his short
bio that came along with the
details for the lecture, and I
thought, What a fascinating
chap. So I invited him, and he
very kindly agreed to come along
and talk with us today. Chris
has written three books. I only
have two here, but one is
lifestyles, a study of
reincarnation in light of
contemporary consciousness
research. And then this one
here, dark night, early dawn,
Steps to a deep ecology of mind.
And then the living classroom
teaching and collective
consciousness. And then he has a
new book, which isn't published
yet, which is going to be called
diamonds from heaven, a 20 year
journey into the mind of the
universe. So Chris, let's start
with you had these questions,
didn't you? You worked for many
years lecturing in comparative
religions, psychology, I think,
to some degree and then. But
there's the how you had these
questions that were burning
inside you.
Chris Bache: Well, I was trained
as a philosopher of religion.
And philosophers of religion are
concerned with, you know,
exploring the deeper questions
of existence, the meaning of
life and the structure of the
universe and the limits of human
consciousness. And I had been,
these are the questions I had
been trained as pursue in
graduate school. And then I came
to my university, Youngstown
State University, and just as I
came there, I encountered the
work of Stanislav Grof in
psychedelic research in his
book, realms of the human
unconscious. This was 7819 78
and as soon as I read that book,
I was so deeply impressed with
the caliber of the of the
research that he had done, and
the caliber of his mind that I
knew that I wanted to do this
Iain McNay: work. And the
questions you had were, were
questions with a variation about
consciousness, what are is? What
are its potentials and patterns?
What are its are its boundaries?
These are slightly different
from the not the usual. Who am
I? What am I type questions?
Yeah. So these have been
obviously working in you for a
time,
Chris Bache: for a time, yeah,
yeah. When I, when I there were
two people that I met my first
year of teaching. One was Ian
Stevenson and his work on
reincarnation research, which
opened up a whole world for me
because I had never I finished
graduate school as an
atheistically inclined agnostic.
You know, Ian Steven opened up
reincarnation. Stan opened up
the opportunity to actually
experience deeper dimensions of
consciousness, and by entering
those dimensions, experiencing
deeper dimensions of existence
itself, and that felt like the
opportunity of a lifetime. What
philosopher would want to do
that? Yes, the problem, of
course, is this was 78 and they
had been made illegal in the
United States. The first
generation of work was over, and
we were 40 years away from the
renaissance of psychedelics
that's taking place now. So I
made a difficult choice. I
decided to split my life, on my
public life. In my public life,
I became, I was a university
professor. I did all the things
professors do. I taught and
published and served on
committees, but in my private
life, I began a private 20 year
journey in using Grof methods of
for me, high dose LSD therapy,
73 sessions over 20 years. I
worked for four years. I stopped
for six years, and then I worked
very intensely for 10 years. So
overall, from 77 to 79 to 99 I
did this work, but because it
was illegal, and because, if I
had, because, if I had talked
about this work, I would have
lost my job. I had to keep quiet
about it, and it wasn't until
after I retired and after I was
passed the statute of
limitations, because I don't do
this work now, that I was able
to begin to talk openly about
what one can learn. About
consciousness and about the
universe by following this
particular method of
exploration.
Iain McNay: I think the
interesting thing is, you went
into it as an adventure, but you
went into it in a quite a
disciplined way, an organized
way, and the sessions were all
laid out. I think your first
wife was supporting you in the
sessions. And from what, again,
I've learned by talking to you
and reading is that also the
sessions, in themselves, were
organized, but not by you
insofar as they were sequential.
And it's like I didn't know so
much about psychedelics. I know
lots of people that have been on
LSD trips, but it tended to be a
trip and another trip, and it
was for an adventure, and it
wasn't a serious study, and you
approached it as a serious
study, yeah? And I think you
talk about a big difference
between doing that and doing it
for a recreational purpose,
yeah,
Chris Bache: I've never taken
LSD and gone to a concert. I've
never stayed up and talking with
friends. This is a very specific
methodology. It's completely
internalized. It's Stan Grof
psychedelic therapy, as he
describes in his book
psychedelic LSD therapy, you're
totally isolated, you're cut off
from the world. You're in a
private space, you're lying
down, you're wearing eye shades,
you're listening to very
carefully selected music. My
first wife was, was and is a
clinical psychologist, and she
was my sitter. And you take the
medicine, and then you
completely surrender and let it
take you where it will take you.
And I did this work in contrast
to current research, with the
renaissance of psychedelic
research, which is very focused
on healing, which is important
work, very important. Much
smaller doses as well as much
lower doses, yeah, very low and
gentler substances. I did this
work as a philosopher. I wanted
to explore the deep structure of
consciousness that Stan had
shown in his early work, and the
structure of the universe
itself. And I found that if you,
if you are willing to submit to
this intense destructuring of
consciousness, you go through
not just one death and rebirth,
but over time, you go through a
series of deaths and rebirths
and deaths and rebirth that take
you deeper and deeper and deeper
into what do we call it? The
mind of the universe, the mind
of the cosmos, the mind of God.
And in my experience, I never
controlled what was happening in
the sessions. I would try to set
intentions. But working at
levels this high, which I don't
recommend,
Iain McNay: I really because it
was 500 600 I
Chris Bache: was working at five
to 600 micrograms, which, now
that I'm through it and looking
back, I really don't recommend
working in a sustained manner
with levels that high. I would
be much gentler on myself if I
were doing it again. But at the
time, I didn't, you know, I was
young, and I took good care of
myself. I really very good care.
And everything was very
methodical. I kept detailed
records within 24 hours of every
session, making a complete
phenomenological record, keeping
track of all the variables, of
all the dates. And then, and I
studied the sessions over years,
because these are complex
experiences. What I found was
that if you open yourself
deeply, you enter into a
conversation with the universe,
and the universe is interested
in deepening your experience of
it, and so the universe takes
you in and teaches you and and
trains you and and softens what
needs to be softened, breaks
what needs to be broken in order
to allow you to enter more and
more intimately into the deep
structure of reality.
Iain McNay: But you see, doesn't
it take a certain courage from
you as a human being, to allow
that to happen because you've
got no idea where it really
leads.
Chris Bache: Yeah, it does. And
this is one of the great gifts
that Stan Grof gave me in
reading his work. One of the
deep gifts he gave me was to
trust the process. If you submit
to it, if you let it take you
where it will take you, no
matter how terrible it becomes,
no matter how inscrutable the
process, if you surrender to it,
it will always culminate. It
will take you through a breaking
point, and then it will catch
you. You will die, and then you
will awaken into. A different
condition, a different reality,
as a different being in a
different dimension of
existence.
Iain McNay: So what do you mean
that you will die? What would it
actually mean in a tangible way,
Chris Bache: in order to
experience intimately the deep
nature of reality, you can't
take your ego into that reality
and have a Transpersonal
experience. The only way to have
these to enter into these
realities, is to become a
citizen of those realities. And
our time space identity, just by
the conditioning of time and
space is keeps us small, and in
order to enter into vast
expanses of reality, we have to
let go of that which keeps us
small. So literally, you go
through a psychological death,
the ego death is very common.
Iain McNay: So ego death, so
it's a death of a construction
of who we think we are, yeah,
who we've become through our
conditioning. Yeah.
Chris Bache: So I, I was a white
male, highly educated
philosopher concerned with the
meaning of existence. The
Universe broke me by turning
into the exact opposite of all
of those. It for hours and hours
I experienced being female,
being poor, being women of
color, and being women who had
no interest in philosophy
whatsoever, which is perfectly
fine, except it completely
negated my sense of who I was
and when I finally yielded and
let it, let that happen and
allowed myself to become a woman
it took me, in the most
marvelous Experience of hundreds
and hundreds of women's lives,
showing me just giving me the
experience of being feminine
that I wish every man had the
opportunity to experience women
as deeply as it gave it to me.
Iain McNay: And when you say you
during these adventures, let's
call them, what is the you?
Because if the ego is dissolved,
what is the you that's having
this experience?
Chris Bache: Yeah, that's that's
one of the linguistic puzzles
that kind of every mystic also
always has to address, that I is
not this I, but it is continuous
with this eye, but it's not this
eye. And so the first death is
the death of ego. There is
continuity of awareness, there's
Kant, there's continuity of
memory, but discontinuity of
capacity. So when you die and
wake up in a different reality,
you remember who you are, but
you are not who you were when
you were a human, a time, space
human being. You literally have
become a different kind of being
for six to eight hours at a time
I wasn't. I mean, Chris Bache
gets shattered, and you
literally learn how to be a
different kind of being. And
then once you stabilize
consciousness at this post egoic
level, and you go through
various purification and
transformative processes,
eventually, if you keep pushing,
keep going deeper, it will ask
you to surrender even more
deeply, and it will you have to
give up something more
fundamental than your personal
identity. And when you do, and
you wake up in that next
reality, you're not Chris Bache,
you're not even who you died,
who Chris Bache died into you
are a different entity. When you
come back, there is a thread of
a memory, but you are literally
remembering having been
different beings or different
dimensions of being,
Iain McNay: you see, so is the
transformation happening within
the trip, or is it happening
after you come back, or is it
both?
Chris Bache: It's both. It's
certainly both. And I want to
say this, you know, there's a
lot of discussion of
psychedelics and enlightenment,
and does psychedelics lead to
enlightenment? And what's the
relationship? And is it counter
productive, or is it productive
and and these adventures were
not aimed at enlightenment. I
mean, they started that way. The
I started because I was
interested in enlightenment, and
I thought I could do these
sessions, and ego would die, and
I would get to enlightenment
faster. But that turned out, it
changed very quickly, because
after I went through my first
ego death. Instead of personal
transformation, the story opened
up into a story of deep
collective transformation. I
began to enter into what I call
the ocean of suffering, where I
began to enter into what the
Buddhists would call the hell
realms, just the. A deep, deep
suffering that still lives
within the collective psyche.
And this went on for two years
and so many sessions and so many
years it involved so many people
that it eventually shattered my
perception of what was going on.
It wasn't aimed at my personal
transformation. It was aimed at
the some transformation of some
aspect of the collective
unconscious of humanity. And
then after that, after I went
through that. And after that
culminated, I entered into
archetypal reality. And when I
entered into archetypal reality,
I went through a phase where I
had to cease to be a human
being, and I discovered that
there, there is a human identity
which is deeper than your
individual human identity. And
just as I had had to die as
Chris Bache in order to become
something larger, I had to die
as a human being, per se, I had
to go completely outside any
frame of reference of humanity
to move into best as I could
determine was archetypal
reality, different dimensions of
archetypal reality, and each of
those, every step deeper is a
step into a much more intense
modality of energy. So every
step deeper is a step into a
very, very intense energy field,
so intense that in the beginning
it can be shattering and very
hard to maintain coherent
awareness. But I found that if,
if I went back again, and I went
back again over a year, I went
back again systematically about
five times a year that you go
through a purification process
and a clarification process that
you're you learn how to stay
conscious in levels of reality
that at the beginning you could
not stay conscious in that you
have to practice.
Iain McNay: Yeah, I think, to
give it some context, you did 73
trips, yeah, over 20 years. I
would never say trips good. So
what you would use the word
sessions, 73 sessions over 20
years, and then each session, no
matter how long the gap was
sequential, yeah? So what would
happen is, at the end of one
session, the next session, you
would start where you left off
the previous one,
Chris Bache: proximally,
there's, you know, sometimes you
have to sort of see the whole
sequence before you understand
the logic of the flow. Yeah, it
wasn't. It was kind of like a
keeping a dream journal. It it's
there is a logical flow that you
can identify, but sometimes you
have to kind of go several
layers down before you can see
the overarching story.
Iain McNay: Yeah, yes, no, I
understand. And you took the
time in between to kind of to
integrate, absorb what had
happened. And also, you were
saying last night when we had
dinner that the also, your body
had to not as if it was
recovering as such, but the body
was adapting, because the energy
you're in, yeah, when you're in
the session, it's such a
powerful energy. And you've got
this, you've got the absolute
coming into some finite vessel
which has to be able to
accommodate that energy and
that, that was, that was quite a
big thing, wasn't it huge?
Chris Bache: Yeah, because every
step deeper is more intense, and
you, when you go into these
states, you open up into vast
fields of consciousness, and the
energy is just huge, and it's
running through your system, and
you have to prepare your body to
go into those states, and then
after your system shrinks down,
after the session, you have to
then continue to work with your
body to help it absorb the
experiences health in a healthy
manner, you really have to stay
clean in your in your heart
habits and in your meditation
and your in your yoga practice
and in all the structural
aspects of your body. And I, I
found out my system had kind of
a natural capacity to let go,
and I never had any trouble
coming back. There was a natural
congealing, but you have to
monitor your system very
carefully throughout. And I
would have a session, I would
write it all up, and I would
have two or three months to
think about it, absorb it, to
ponder, it to follow its
teachings, because it gives you
teachings, yes, and then I would
open up again, and the process
would repeat itself in this
manner,
Iain McNay: because you also
talked about, there's layers of
conditioning, yeah, that you're
letting go of, yeah, and it's
not like you are saying I'm
letting go. Yeah, in the
sessions, the letting go is
happening, yeah? Because you're
there's an allowance there,
yeah,
Chris Bache: I surrender it. The
universe, or this creative
intelligence takes me in.
Usually, what happens in a
session is the first half of the
session is spent in some form of
intense purification, and then
it reaches a peak, and you're
drawn then into the second half
of the session, which is some
type of ecstatic experience,
some deeper immersion into the
divine, and then a series of
teachings. And then the system
slowly closes
Iain McNay: down. And do you
remember all those teachings
when you come back? I do, wow.
Chris Bache: Now it have to
qualify that just a little bit,
many layers. And you go through
this Death-Rebirth cycle,
Death-Rebirth. And if you, if
you stop there. You stay at that
level. But if you keep pushing
and driving, and that's one of
the things I found about the
high dose LSD work. It's just
huge power. It keeps pushing you
to your edges, to your outer
limits when you break into a new
level, when you first break into
a new level, it's a different
system, different rules. It
works by a different process,
and when you first break
through, often recall is hard,
and you may you get pieces, you
get aspects, but they don't
always cohere in a way that
makes sense to you. So your your
account will have sessions will
have gaps. But if you go back
again and you go back again and
you go back again, you train
yourself how to stay conscious
in that level of reality. You go
through purification and more
purification, and eventually
you're able to maintain coherent
cognition at that level of
reality. At that point, the
pieces begin to cohere. You get
a more coherent map of what's
going on. You get a clear,
stabilized vision. And this is
one of the differences between
therapeutic work and tripping
it. If you trip, you may touch
these places here, there, but if
you want to have sustained
conscious experience at various
levels of reality, you have to
pay your dues, and you have to
work, to be conscious at that
level. When you do that, you
come back, I am able to bring it
all back. And when I write my
account, I found that I there's
a technique I used, which was
the day after a session, you're
kind of a horse. I would play
the music that was used in the
session in exactly the same
order in which it was played.
And I would write the session up
listening to the music that I
had used in the session. So it
kind of put me one foot in, one
foot out, and I would I could
get back into the space, and it
would help me remember, and help
me remember, and I would get it
down in print always, and
pushing it, but with work, with
careful attention in the
session, and afterwards you can
retain it.
Iain McNay: I think one of the
things that I particularly liked
when I when I it was in, I was
thinking it was in The Dark
Knight book was that you, you
kind of, you stressed that you
cannot waken fully awaken
individually, because you had
the realization that at the
absolute level which you were,
you were visiting certainly,
certainly part of the time, that
it is all one. So when you come
back to the human vessel, it
makes the it makes a real myth
that someone can awaken
individually when the next
person isn't fully awake. How
can that be that an individual
awakes, yeah, another individual
doesn't awake, yeah?
Chris Bache: You know, the
metaphor that I like to use when
I'm teaching this with my
students is the metaphor of the
leaf, leaves and the trees
leaves, if you imagine leaves
being individually conscious,
and yet they are manifestations
of the consciousness of the
tree. It's a both. And so we are
both individually conscious. And
there is a story of the
individual evolution. But if you
really kind of dig deep and you
ask, well, what is an
individual? Then you encounter
the collective psyche. You know,
the consciousness of the planet,
the consciousness of the galaxy
and from and then deeper into,
as you say, the absolute, what I
call my belovedness. In it,
individual awakening is really
kind of, it's a, it's just a.
Mistaken inference. It's true
that if you don't, if you don't
work individually, you don't
make progress. And yet, when you
make progress, you are actually
drawing into your work. I think
you would touch the
consciousness of many people,
and many people's consciousness
are represented in your work. So
it's impossible to put a
boundary on awakening, and the
universe doesn't, in this sense,
doesn't even think in terms of
individuals. I mean, it does,
but it also thinks in terms it's
interested in awakening the
entire species. It's not
interested in awakening this
religion and that religion, or
this planet, this this
continent, that continent, it's
interested in taking the whole
of the human family into its
evolutionary progression. And
that's so that's I began to
realize I wasn't doing these
sessions for my personal work. I
wasn't doing it to, you know,
for my personal healing or my
personal transformation?
Iain McNay: Yeah, it started
with the questions, but the
adventure led you far beyond
those initial questions,
Chris Bache: and then beyond
even collective transformation.
It just became an adventure in
knowing the universe, just an
adventure in being drawn deep
into intimacy with the creative
intelligence and drawn into
causal reality, into oneness,
into Shunyata emptiness and into
the fertile void, into the
Satchitananda you know, the
existence before existence. Just
one adventure after another,
deeper and deeper. And there I
have an acute sense of that the
universe loves to be known. I
mean the universe wants to be
known. So any part we are the
universe we we are part of its
knowing. And when we when we
return to source, when we begin
that journey back to point of
origin, we are met with the what
do you call it again? We are met
by this massive supreme
intelligence, this extraordinary
compassion and loving beyond
imagination. And it's so happy
that part of it has come back to
experience it and to know it.
And it wants to show you
creation. It wants to show you
what has been going on because
we're it's been working for
billions and billions and
billions of years, and we are
just getting to where, in the
last few 1000 years, we can
begin to open up deeply enough
to consciously participate and
to see the creative process. And
it's so happy when we do that.
Iain McNay: And do you have a
view on so your your adventure
took you to these, this
knowledge, this experience, and
yet, there's other people that
go the path of contemplation and
meditation that have very
similar experiences. Yeah, do
you? Do you feel that your way
was slightly different. I know
in terms of substance it was.
But do you feel that
realizations and the knowledge
of your way was that different
from from the way of
contemplation and meditation?
Chris Bache: No, I think that
the cosmology that came out of
this work is not different than
the cosmology that you see in
the great contemplative
traditions, the great spiritual
traditions, you know, all honor
to the great masters who have
done this under the very power
of their own daily practice. I
mean, I taught courses in
mysticism and meditation, and
the great spiritual sages were
always my teachers, always my
masters, and they kept me, but
what they describe and what I
experienced seemed to fit hand
in glove, so I don't There's
nothing new there. The only
thing new is that we have a
different method. Who could let
someone of modest spiritual
capacity, if they have
sufficient determination and
courage to submit to the
regimen, even someone of modest
spiritual capacity like me might
have temporary experience of
these things. Now, as Huston
Smith said, a mystical
experience does not a mystic
make so you can't take these
experiences in and use them to
maintain that consciousness
permanently. It would be so good
if you could, but by going back
and forth and back and forth and
doing the practice and doing
your work in the daily way,
hopefully more. More and more of
it internalizes itself in your
being and and you grow.
Iain McNay: You grow. Yeah, I
think one of the interesting
thing was that you, midway
through, through this event,
you, you wrote this book, yes,
the living classroom, yeah,
which was about the about what
was happening with you, with
your students, yeah? And you
don't mention psychedelic, yeah,
psychedelic experiments at all
in this Yeah. And yet, something
very special was happening
between you and your students.
Yeah. Do you want to talk
briefly about that?
Chris Bache: I wrote living
classroom towards the end of my
teaching career and and I don't
mention psychedelics at all,
because it's not about
psychedelics. It's about
consciousness. But the back
story to it is I was teaching,
and I was doing my private work,
and I never talked about my
psychedelic experiences to my
students, I never, you know, I
just kept a firewall between my
professional life and my
personal work. But what I found
over time was that my students
were being activated by my
private work, that when I would
go into deeper states of
consciousness or go through some
Death-Rebirth process, they were
spontaneously being activated in
their own life, in ways that I
began to recognize were parallel
to what was happening in my
practice. And another thing
began to happen when I was
lecturing on something, and I
would just need an example to
make a point about, and I would
just pause and wait, and I would
think of an example, and I would
use the example. And students
began to come up to me after
class, and they began to say,
you know, it's funny that you
used that example, because
that's exactly what happened to
me this week. And first this
happened. I thought, Well, okay,
coincidence, but it kept
happening. It kept happening.
And the deeper I went in my
work, these synchronicities
began to touch very, very deep
pieces of their life. And it was
like there was a radar operating
that was connecting me to where
they were hurt, what they needed
to hear some healing that they
needed, some idea that they
needed. And when they would hear
them their life being suddenly
in the room, they could not help
but get involved deeply. And
when I began to see that this
was happening pretty regularly,
I began to realize I have to
understand this. I have to, not
only do I have to understand it,
but I have to figure out how, as
an educator, how to work with
it. Do I need to protect them
from what's happening? Do I need
to build barriers? Or, how can
I, how can I be myself and teach
in a way that's safe for them
and yet also allows me to just
be who I am, what I am, and
that's what the living classroom
is about. It's about
consciousness, in its natural
condition, is boundless and
endless and doesn't have firm
membranes and edges. There is a
private consciousness of a sort,
but in its end, consciousness is
like a lake. You throw in a
stone, the RIP will spread out.
And so I developed a strategy, a
set of strategies, for how to
work with consciousness in the
context of rooms of people,
groups of people. And I also
found out that there is a field
energy. I mean, I'd read Rupert
Sheldrake and his work in
Morphic fields, but I'd always
thought of Morphic fields in
terms of species, whole species.
But what I found is that there
are fields that congeal around
courses. There are fields that
congeal around students in a
room. And if you teach the same
course year after year after
year, there's a field that
congeals and gets stronger that
reflects the learning of all the
students who've taken that
course with you. And that field
accelerates the student the
learning of students who take
the course five or 10 years down
the road. And so once you know
that that's happening, you can
begin to work cooperatively,
strategically with those fields.
So there's just it's a whole
different modality of pedagogy.
You might call it, instead of a
Newtonian pedagogy, it's a
quantum pedagogy. So for
example, I found it's important
to close those fields at the end
of a course. So if you open the
room into kind of the collective
energy of these fields, students
get very deeply touched. I mean,
they get deeply activated. I.
Yeah, but at the end of the
course, I found that, I found
that students were kind of
showing up in my office after a
course was over, and they just
kind of wanted to talk or and at
first I thought, Oh, that's
nice. They had a good course.
But then I began to realize, now
something's wrong. They were
caught. They were still stuck.
They were still connected to the
field, but they didn't have any
place to take it. So I began to
realize, not only do you open
these fields and work with them
skillfully, you have to close
them skillfully. So you have to
go through a process, both
socially in the room and sort of
shamanically in spiritual
practice, to close the fields,
because you don't want to
encourage that type of
dependence. I want my students
to be independent. I want them
to take the learning, go to
their next course, integrate
what their next professor has,
to find their own field and find
their own field, and I want them
free in the world. And so it's
just lots of you know, there was
a lot of learning.
Iain McNay: I think there was
one interesting example you used
in the living classroom about
how you found that when a
student would ask you a
question, if you didn't reply
straight away, you just open for
a few seconds, you'd see, like
this door open, and a whole new
dimension to the answer to the
question would come,
Chris Bache: yeah. Well, it's
like I found if I stopped, and
instead of saying the first
thing that came to my mind,
because, you know, pretty much
every question they ask is
something you've already heard
before, but if I stopped, I
visualized suddenly I saw a
little blank door in the back of
my mind, and a piece of paper
came through that door, and I
read the paper and it was a
different answer. And so when,
if I, if I tried it, all of a
sudden the eyes would light up,
and the energy of the room would
light up, and we would, we would
go in a new and novel direction.
And and so my teaching began to
be a dialog between organized, I
organized. I do a lot of notes
and really thoroughly organized,
but then this improvisation, and
my understanding is the
improvisation that was coming
through this deeper
consciousness connection was
what happened when my mind was
put into the context of our
collective mind, and the
teaching came out of A dialog
between the minds who were there
and my mind who is there.
Iain McNay: And you also talked
about how the students were
changing you. Oh, yeah. Felt
that any talk about as a quote
from the book, over the years,
the students broke me down and
rebuilt me. Yeah, that's quite
radical to say. The students
broke you down and rebuilt you.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I've always,
was always blessed with really
good students. They were willing
to engage deeply the questions
that I asked, and we danced, we
danced together, and in that
process, they they opened up my
heart. They they invited me into
the room, and they let me into
their lives, you know, not in a
counseling kind of way, but in
an intellectual in a
philosophical inquiry kind of
way. And we worked together, and
in that process, they taught me
about this hidden territory in
the room. They taught me what
could happen when good people of
good hearts came together in
this adventure and and they did.
They broke me down. I learned,
for example, at first I thought,
you know, I would a student
would ask a question, and I
would have an answer only
because of an experience that
had recently happened to me, or
a book I had just recently read,
or a session I just had, and I
thought, Oh, that's interesting.
I do the work, and suddenly the
universe has this capacity to
use my knowledge to seed
knowledge in somebody else's
life. Then I began to realize I
had it all backwards, that
sometimes I was having the
experiences I was having and
reading the books that I was
having. Was reading because
there was a questioning student
who was coming to me in the
future, so that my learning was
actually being seeded by their
desire to know. And once you let
go at that level, once you stop
thinking that you were the
orchestrator of this entire
enterprise, that it's really a
collaborative enterprise right
from the start then, and you
realize that your learning and
teaching is so deeply embedded
in their learning and teaching,
then where is the self in that,
you know, where are the
boundaries of the self? You
know, it just becomes a dance of
presences in the room, and when
life uses you in that way, when
life kind of you. Uses you in
that delicious way to when that
cross fertilization takes place,
it's The Sweetest feeling in the
world to me. You know, you're
just part of something larger.
You release to it, and they
release and they release to it.
And they took me there. I could
not I could not go there by
myself. They took me there.
Iain McNay: And then at some
point, a great sadness came upon
you on your adventure, you talk
about, yeah, As years passed,
you found yourself entering a
deep sadness. Your enthusiasm
for life was fading, you began
to feel separated and marooned.
Reached a point where you
realize you was just waiting to
die, to return to your beloved.
Chris Bache: Yeah, that was
after I stopped the journey.
Yes, so I have to kind of fill
in a little bit of a blank, and
then I can say what happened
after the journey. In the book,
I tell the story in diamonds
from heaven. I tell the story of
ego death, moving into the ocean
of suffering, and then moving
into archetype of reality and
and then moving into causal
reality. And it's having these
wonderful unitive experiences
and and I, I was completely
satisfied at that point. I mean,
you know, to merge so deeply.
But there were still five years
in the journey ahead. And what
happened is, I went through yet
another cycle of death and
rebirth, and I was taken into a
domain of light that was so
clear, so exquisitely just
clear, clear beyond imagination.
Buddhism calls it Dharmakaya,
the absolute reality of clear
light. And over five years and
26 sessions, I was taken into
this reality four times, just
four times. And in between those
four sessions, there was
tremendous purification, you
know, and and so it was you,
literally in these states of
awareness, you become light. You
just dissolve completely into
light and you, and you have the
qualities of light and the
boundlessness of light and the
you just dissolved in the in the
in the crystalline nature of the
Divine. Now I don't mean divine
in any theistic sense or in any
conventional sense, but I don't
know how else to what other
vocabulary to give to it. In
each of those four adventures
going deeper into the divine,
there were a series of things
that happened. And then the
divine began to come deeper into
my body. But then I reached a
point after being handled very
carefully and broken down, but
handled carefully. And then this
consciousness came brought me to
the end of my work. It just it
brought me to the end. It gave
me an overview of all of my
sessions from the beginning to
the end, to show me the whole
pattern to put all the pieces
together. And then it gave me a
last set of instructions as I
was about to leave. I didn't
know it was over, but it called
it. And so I knew, I knew I had
to stop my work. And the primary
reason I stopped the work was
because it became too difficult
to come back from the light. It
became so painful to come back
into time and space after having
dissolved so completely into
this infinite light. And of
course, light comes in many,
many little it comes in early
on. It has layers and layers and
layers. But the diamond light is
what I call the diamond light is
a particularly, it's a
particular advanced form of the
light. It's a very, very deep
expression of light. So I
stopped my sessions, and I had
always been integrating my
sessions carefully all the way
through. But what I found was
when I stopped my sessions, and
I thought I would now, because
I'd done this work carefully, I
would be able to just enjoy the
fruits of that labor. But what I
found over time is that a deep
sadness settled in over me, and
over time, I began to realize I
was suffering from a loss of
communion. I just there. Such a
longing for that light, and I
did not have the spiritual
maturity or the spiritual
capacity to incarnate that light
in my physical existence. And I
reached a point where I began to
realize I was just waiting to
die. I was taking care of my
students, taking care of my
family. I was doing the things
that I would do, but in my heart
of hearts, I was waiting to die
so I could return to the light.
And I began, over the years, I
began to realize that this is
not right. This is not the way
it's supposed to go. Somewhere
along the way, I made a mistake.
I must have made a mistake,
because this is not the way it's
supposed to be. So I really went
back and re examined the whole
process, and I began to realize
that you could say I was
suffering from too much God. But
since the physical universe is a
man is the divine as well, I'd
say I had lost balance, a
balance between Transcendence
and immanence. I had plunged so
deeply into the transcendent
divine that I lost my foothold,
my place in the immanent divine.
And that's that's incredibly
valuable. The immanent Divine is
so valuable. So I had to make a
concerted effort to congeal my
life, and to come to terms with
being where I was, as I was, and
to continue the process of doing
my spiritual practice so that I
could let the divine, the the
light, enter more deeply into my
body and into my consciousness.
So it's a, it's an ongoing
process. I mean, it's, it's a
work still in process,
Iain McNay: yes, but you, you
also talk about in the book, the
books not published yet, the
diamonds from heaven. Yeah, that
it's it, the fact the human
things like the family, yeah,
was so important to you in
helping you sort of refine the
ground and finding pleasure
again in human things, because,
yes, you are almost blown away
by what was there. But there's
so much beauty also in the human
realms that somehow these are my
words rather than yours, which
been taken out of significance,
but in themselves, they're
wonderful,
Chris Bache: absolutely. I mean,
my family was always the my
rock, my students and my family.
I have three children, and just
always coming back wherever I
was on Saturday, Monday, I was
with my classes, and I was
always with my children, like
these flowers on the table. What
magnificent expressions of
creation there are, and the
diamond Luminosity, the light is
magnificent. We have a huge,
tremendous hunger to touch these
realms and return to them. But
the physical world is the
manifestation of that reality in
tangible form. And so nature has
been a tremendous balm for me.
It just just nature, the starry
sky, being in the woods, being
in nature, being with people.
This is another aspect of that
sadness. The sadness wasn't just
loss of communion, the other
isolation, the other sadness is
in our culture, I wasn't allowed
to talk about these things. You
know, in traditional culture,
you bring your visions back to
the elders who help you
understand them, and because
your visions were are not meant
for you, they're always
collective. But in my culture, I
wasn't allowed to talk about my
sessions. I couldn't bring these
visions back. I couldn't teach
from them. I couldn't share them
with my colleagues, and that
sickness of silence just added
to my sadness. It just isolated
me, and it makes you sick
inside. Living in a psychedelic
closet is just as injurious as
living in any other closet,
where you have to deny yourself
in order to live in your
culture. Writing diamonds from
Heaven was really my step back
to the world and sharing these
visions doing what I was
designed to do to be a teacher,
I find I share, just to just
bring them forward, just to let
hopefully they'll be of use to
people. Hopefully they'll find
them helpful in some way, and to
be able to begin to share them,
to bring them back, to be able
to speak without reservation of
about my experiences and and
it's my experiences are not
important in that what's
important is all of our
experiences. I mean, I What's
important is that all of our
experiences of the transcendent
reality, or these realities, be
put on the table. We look at
them together and we find out
what's important what's not
important. So I don't have any.
Attachment to my I don't own
these experiences,
Iain McNay: yeah, but it took
you says. You also saying in one
of the books that at the end of
the 20 years, yeah, you were
told, or you felt it would take
20 years of integration, yeah.
And actually, the 20 years is up
next year.
Chris Bache: It's getting close.
Yeah,
Iain McNay: it might take 20
lifetime
Chris Bache: Yeah, at first
when, after I'd done the
sessions, and when my meditation
Spirit told me 20 years in 20
years out, that it would take 20
years to absorb them. Now I'm
coming close to those 20 years
that I'm thinking that might
have been optimistic, because
these things are so deep that
sometimes it feels like it will
take many lifetimes to absorb
them, and that really, I have
really basic questions, how do
you experience? How do you
integrate infinity into finite
structures? You know, some of my
experiences involved going far
into deep, what I call deep
time, outside of time and space,
deep into the future, deep into
different dimensions of time.
How do you integrate those
breadths of time into Monday,
Tuesday, Wednesday,
consciousness, you know, and in
the end, where I am now, I don't
think you can, the only thing we
can do is integrate our finite
existence into the infinite. So
we do our practice, we
surrender, we make ourselves
available. We do everything we
can to respond to the needs of
the present, and if we do that
consistently, hopefully, then
the infinite becomes a deeper
and deeper living reality in our
conscious awareness.
Iain McNay: Yes, and again, I
was saying to last night that
it's not so much just the
experiences you had, which are
amazing experiences I find for
myself. It just I get to
understand something, or have an
experience or have a
realization, and it can take me
years to properly integrate
that. Yeah, I realize it's still
hanging around in a form that
isn't totally something I can
absorb. And I just think, I just
feel more and more on the kind
of the spiritual journey. People
often give themselves too much
of a hard time, because they
think, Well, yeah, I kind of got
that. I must move on, and now I
must get something else. Or I
should be clear, no, you do your
best, but as you found out, it's
a process. It takes time. You
cannot force these things. You
can be available. You can do the
you can do the meditation and
look after yourself and any
other supportive work. But it
happens in its own time.
Chris Bache: It does. It's a
slow and gradual process. You
you can't cheat nature. It takes
time. You can kind of push it,
but in the end, you have to let
nature take its course. Yes,
yeah,
Iain McNay: okay, Chris, I'm
looking at the clock, and
nature's taken its course, and
time is very up.
Chris Bache: Thank you so much.
Ian, it's been so good to have
this conversation with you.
Thank you for it.
Iain McNay: Thank you for coming
along to conscious TV. And I'm
going to mention your new book,
which should be out sometime
next year, next year, diamonds
from heaven, a 20 year journey
into the mind of the universe.
And then the three books already
out, dark night, early dawn,
living classroom, which we
touched on about halfway through
the interview about Chris's
teaching, and the first book,
which I haven't actually life
cycles. Life cycles a study of
reincarnation in light of
contemporary consciousness
research. So if you're
interested in Chris, there's a
lot to read. There's also, I
think, on your you haven't got a
website yet, but there is soon,
there is a lecture you did in
Prague, which is about an hour
long, which I found very useful
for picking up the details of
Chris's psychedelic adventure
the
Chris Bache: international
Transpersonal conference last
September in Prague, right?
Iain McNay: Yeah, okay, yeah. So
there's a lot to follow, and I
think I'd like to explore this
more on conscious TV. So if
you've got any ideas of people
that we should look at
interviewing them, then get in
contact. Okay, thanks again,
Chris, thank you. Ian, thank you
for watching, and I hope we see
you again soon. Goodbye. You.