Chris Bache: The good news, do I
have a mic? Yeah, the good news
is that after me, it's lunch, so
I'm the end of your day. Now.
I'm a professor. I've been at
this game for a long time, so I
know a tired audience when I see
one. It's been a long morning
and a lot of wonderful ideas. So
I'd like to take real quick.
Everybody stand up. Just stand
up and stretch your arms up.
Bring in that more good energy.
Bring it in. Okay, okay, now sit
down.
If the most important
philosophical question one can
ask in life is, do we survive
the death of our body, which Dr
Van Lommel is asking, I think
the second most important
question is, do we live once, or
do we live more than once? And
it all hinges on time. The
problem the significances of
time as a teacher, if I give a
quiz, I have a right to expect a
certain performance from the
students. If I give an hour
exam, I have a right to expect a
higher level of performance. And
if I give a take home research
paper, I expect a higher level
of performance because they have
more time. If this universe, if
this magnificent universe that
we are in, has a purpose, then
as a philosopher, we can, we
have to measure the purpose of
the universe proportionate to
the time. We have to fulfill
that purpose. If we only live
one time, then we might
extrapolate or estimate or
calculate the purpose of
existence to be but if we live
100 times, if we live 1000
times, if we live 10,000 times,
if our participation in this
magnificent universe is truly
open ended, then we have a very
different relationship with the
universe, and then we have a
reason to think about the
possible purpose of existence in
a completely different
framework. And the religions of
the last 4000 years have had a
tendency to not value physical
existence. They've had a
tendency to say, well, you
achieve realization, you achieve
enlightenment, and then you
leave Nirvana, Samsara, you
escape. Samsara, moksha, escape
or you achieve salvation, and
then you leave. But that leaves
the fundamental question, what
is the purpose of the universe
unanswered? What is the purpose
of my physical existence in the
universe? But if we come back,
if we come back to this life
many times, then we have a
different story that begins to
unfold, and it doesn't. I think
it. I think our understanding of
reincarnation is completely
incomplete at this point, just
as we've begun to understand the
true depth and breadth of the
universe that we are part of,
likewise, when we begin to
understand that we participate,
we're dancing with this universe
for extended period of time,
then we have a deeper
understanding of what the
universe might actually be
trying to accomplish in us, and
what might be our gift to the
universe in the continual
refinement and compounding of
our talent over time. So what
I'd like to do today is talk
about the evidence for
reincarnation, and I've been
thinking about this and been in
this game for a long time. The
first book I wrote, it was, is
life cycles. And notice how long
ago I wrote it. It was the first
book I wrote as an academic. And
that is a signal of how
important I think this topic is,
and that there is good, critical
empirical evidence that allows
us to decide this topic. If
there weren't critical evidence,
then it would just be a wasted
exercise. And I think this
evidence did not exist 50 years
ago, and the theologians used to
debate about reincarnation go
round and round. But today we
have a different body of
physical of empirical evidence
on reincarnation that has moved
the topic from the theologians
table to the psychologist table
to the philosopher's table to
the to the psychiatrist table,
and that's what I'd like to take
you through some today. Now when
looking at the evidence for
reincarnation, we can either
look at go small or go large.
Large, we either look at the
detailed cases in or we look at
the larger body of literature.
The Beauty and the real joy is
in the detailed cases. But in 45
minutes, I've chosen to go
large. What I would really like
to do is encourage you today to
read one book on reincarnation
that you haven't read yet, and
so I want to take you into some
of the literature on
reincarnation and show you some
of the patterns that are
emerging in the literature in
rebirth. Okay, ready to go?
Let's go 20 cases suggestive of
reincarnation by Ian Stevenson.
This is a book that changed my
life, because, like many people,
when I finished graduate school
in 1978 I was an atheistically
inclined agnostic. I was trained
in philosophy of religion, but
all that training basically made
me an atheist. But when I
encountered this book right
after finishing graduate school.
He turned my life around because
he convinced me that there was
evidence that we live on life
more than once. He is the Ah,
okay. Oh, good. Steven. Steve
Stevenson is the Carlson
professor. Was the Carlson
Professor the University of
Virginia between 1967 and 2001
he has written 11 books on
reincarnation. Some of the most
important are these cases of
reincarnation, type written over
a seven year period from 73 to
84 unlearn language, languages
by children about children who
have an ability to speak a
language which no one in their
family speaks, no one in their
entire town speaks, sometimes an
ancient language, children who
remember previous lives. And his
last book, his Monu mopis, a
1000 page, two volume work, a
study of 187 cases of children
who not only have detailed
memories of their most previous
of their immediate life, but
actually carry the scars in
their body which relate to the
death wounds of the body in
their previous personality. And
that, of course, really upsets
academics. I mean, it's one
thing to have continuity of
memory that's bad enough, but to
suggest that a wound of death
can actually be transferred into
the physical body of a
subsequent personality that
drives my colleagues right up a
wall. But 187 cases, well
documented case histories. It's
a magnificent book. What are we
looking at with Stevenson? We're
looking at cases of children
from around the world who have
detailed recall of their most
immediate recent life. They know
their way around towns that
they've never been in before.
They can recognize persons when
they're brought into the life
place of the previous
personality. They can recognize
persons that they have never met
before. They know the personal
history, their personal history
with that person. They have the
appropriate emotional responses
with that person. Husbands. For
wives, children, you have cases
of a five year old child who is
showing all the feelings of the
husband of a 35 year old woman
with all the emotional
responses. There is one case of
a child called parmed When he
was reunited with the family of
the previous personality. He was
very shy around the wife of the
previous personality. He
wouldn't identify her until she
left the room, but then he
identified her, and then later
he took her aside and he said
two things to her. He said, I've
come but you have not fixed
bindi, which is the spot that
Indian women wear on their Ford,
is an indication that they're
married. And he also criticized
her for wearing a white sari
instead of a colorful sari. And
the tradition in India is when
you become a widow, you don't
wear color from the rest of your
life, you wear only white.
Essentially, this five year old
boy was saying to this 35 year
old woman, I've come but you're
acting like you're not married.
They know the inner architecture
of homes that they've never been
in. They know people who owed
them money when they died and
the debt had not been collected.
In one case, this little child
was brought back to the home of
the previous personality, and
the wife of the previous
personality said, Okay, if
you're my husband, where did you
put the will? We couldn't. Find
the will. The little boy walked
over to a floorboard in the
kitchen, pulled up the
floorboard and pulled the will
out of this little secret place
that only he knew about in the
floor of the kitchen. Cases like
that drive my philosophical
colleagues at the University
right up a wall. They don't know
what to do with it. It's hard
for them deny it, but there it
is. Some patterns in the data,
the average time interval
between the death of the first
personality and the birth of the
second personality. Stevens
finds about two and a half years
the average distance between the
life place of the first
personality and the life place
of the second personality, 50
miles. And these children tend
to lose their memories around
the year, around eight years
old, when they become begins to
get into school and in a more
complex social environment, they
basically forget. They lose
their memories. So we're looking
at a small time window from
research, from about three years
old to eight years old, a five
minute time window to get to
these children and document
their memories. The remaining
90% forget them by the time
they're eight. The remaining 10%
the vast majority of those,
forget them when they hit
puberty, when they hit puberty.
You know, all hell breaks loose,
and they forget their subtle
traces of their former lives.
Stevenson asked, why do these
children remember what most of
us forget? And his answer is, he
doesn't know we need more
research. It's all research. He
has a hypothesis. He points out
that about 60% of these children
died violently in their previous
life. The remaining 40% died
either early, suddenly or with
an acute sense of unfinished
business, like a mother who dies
shortly after the birth of her
baby. His hypothesis is maybe
there's something about the
trauma of being wrenched from
life violently, suddenly with an
acute sense of unfinished
business that encodes the
consciousness in a way that
draws them back faster than
usual and closer than usual,
because this time, I don't have
time to give all the evidence,
but this two and a half and 52
and a half years 50 miles, is
faster than the population at
large and closer to home than
the population at large.
In reviewing 20 cases suggestive
of reincarnation, the Journal of
American Medical Association,
wrote Stevenson has
painstakingly and unemotionally
collected a detailed series of
cases in which the evidence for
reincarnation is difficult to
understand on other grounds. Two
years later, the Journal of
Nervous and Mental disease, a
major psychiatric journal in the
United States, published an
entire journal devoted to
Stevenson's cases. And that it
was such an unusual move that
they published an editorial to
justify or to explain their
rationale, and in the editorial
they wrote, Our decision to
publish this material recognizes
the legitimacy of his research
methods and the conformity of
his reasoning to the usual
canons of rational thought.
That's the way an academic
qualifies their endorsement. Now
the philosophical institution,
the guardians of Orthodoxy, are
not going to let Stevenson get
away with this, not without a
fight. And he has had his
critics, and the most important
critic is a man named Paul
Edwards. And I promise you, this
is the best picture I could find
of Paul Edwards online. His book
reincarnation, a critical
examination. Paul Edwards was a
major American philosopher. He
taught at the New School for
Social Research. He's best known
for having been the editor in
chief of the eight volume
Encyclopedia of Philosophy. So
he's a major heavyweight in the
philosophical tradition. He
wrote a series of articles in
1986 to 87 a four part article
on reincarnation. And eventually
he published these articles in a
later form, in this book
reincarnation and his he is the
harshest critic of Stevenson. He
accuses Stevenson of fraud. He
accuses Stevenson of not being
sufficiently rigorous in his
analysis of the data. He accuses
Stevenson of not not. Actually
verifying that he thinks that
there could have been contact
between the two families, that
Stevenson isn't really critical
in proving that these families,
the first and second
personality, have never had
contact. But there's actually a
deeper you know, to accuse
someone of bad research and to
prove bad research two different
things. And if you go through
Stevenson's arguments very
carefully, I'm sorry, Edwards
arguments very carefully, you
see that there's kind of a
deeper logic operating in his
work. He says reincarnation
would represent a crucifixion of
our understanding. And by our
understanding he means secular
humanism, the philosophical
scientific tradition, the
Newtonian, Cartesian
philosophical tradition. He
says, If you believe in
reincarnation, you must accept
what he calls six collateral
assumptions. And these
collateral assumptions are that
materialism is false, that that
mind is not reducible to brain,
that our identity is more than
our personality, that there is a
domain other than space time,
that death is an illusion, that
there may be a deeper logic to
our lives. Edwards says these
assumptions are surely
fantastic, if not indeed
nonsense, and even in the
absence of a demonstration of
specific flaws, a rational
person will conclude either that
Stevenson's reports are
seriously defective, or that his
alleged facts can be explained
without bringing in
reincarnation. Well, I won't go
over Edwards arguments more
carefully, because Robert Robert
almeter has done this for us.
Robert almiter is another major
American philosopher. He is
Professor Emeritus at Georgia
State University. He has
authored, or co authored 24
books. He wrote this book in
which he is evaluating five
categories of evidence for
survival of death, the major
analysis he's doing in this book
is the debate between Stevenson
and Edwards. And what he shows
by analyzing Edwards argument is
that Edwards does not refute
Stevenson's argument. What he
does is refuse to even look at
it seriously, because he is so
convinced that it must be false.
He says his argument constitutes
a blatant bit of question
begging, because he always
assumes precisely what is in
contention. What is in
contention is, Can consciousness
exist without a brain? And
because he believes that science
has proven that consciousness
can exist without a brain,
therefore we know that there
must be something wrong with the
evidence. Albert says if you
have a very commanding argument
that you can that you cannot
refute, then not to accept the
argument is to act irrationally.
Stevenson's tradition continues,
even though he's passed on, he's
now looking from the bleacher
seats, watching us from there
this book by Tom Schroeder, old
souls. Tom Schroeder wins the
definitely wins for having the
award for having the worst cover
of any book in reincarnation
research. But Tom Schroeder is
an interesting guy. He's a
reporter. He's a Pulitzer Prize
winning reporter. He's also one
of the editors for The
Washington Post, a major
American newspaper, and he was
interested in whether
Stevenson's research could stand
up to a critical reporter's eye.
So he went with Stevenson on one
of his trips around the world,
studying these small children.
He looked over his shoulder, and
he came away convinced, as the
subtitle shows, compelling
evidence from children who
remember past lives, convinced
that this Stevenson's methods
were good, the data would stand
up. These children were real.
This is a compelling case for
reincarnation, and at the
University of Virginia,
Stevenson's work continues in
the person of Jim Tucker, who
has now inherited Stevenson's
chair. This book is a wonderful
book, very much in the Stevenson
tradition, continuing to look in
detail, the detail cases, and
explaining why these cases
cannot be attributed to weaker
hypotheses like super psi or
something like this. I. Might
mention that Jim Tucker's book
is a lot easier to read than
Stevenson's book. Stevenson
writes and thinks like a lawyer.
It's very good, but it's very,
very detailed, very dry. Jim
Tucker brings a little more life
to the subject matter. Now
everything we've been looking at
so far has to do with what I
would call the evidence from
spontaneous memories, just
children who spontaneously have
memories of previous life. But
there's another body of evidence
you have to approach it with a
different framework. It's evoked
memories, memories which have
been evoked in some way,
different techniques, even
massage, can evoke a former life
memory, but the most common one
that we're familiar with is
hypnotherapy, some type of
hypnosis. The following cases,
the following books are
representative titles of people
who have worked in the field of
past life therapy. My favorite
book written by a single
therapist who has worked in the
area of past life therapy and
has thought about it a great
deal. Is this book by Roger
Wilber. Notice the date an
earlier book, other lives, other
cells, started as a Jungian,
ended up in past life therapy,
doing past life's work, even
though Carl Jung, I don't know
whether you probably know, he
himself, believed in
reincarnation towards the later
years of his life, but he kind
of kept it quiet. This is a
wonderful book, intellectually,
totally competent, a wonderful
review of detailed cases and a
discussion of the implications
of these cases. Past life
therapy began to really explode
in the 70s, 80s, and there were
a lot of therapists who were
concerned that there was not a
graduate school, there was no
curriculum, there was no agreed
upon curriculum for how to
establish the credentials for
people who wanted to do past
life therapy. And this task was
taken on by Winifred Lucas, who
wrote a magnificent two volume
anthology, which is a compendium
of essays and articles of the
best of the best of the people
working at that time in past
life therapy. So if you wanted
to read a single book, I would
read Wilbers book by one author.
But if you wanted to see an
overview of multiple people
writing in the field, I would go
to Winifred Lucas' book
regression therapy, a handbook
for professionals.
Carol Bowman was a social
worker. She wasn't interested in
past life therapy. She got into
it because her son started
having nightmares. He started
waking up with very disturbing
nightmares, and she approached
him. She tried to work with him,
took him to therapist, tried to
do conventional things, but it
didn't work. And then she began
to do her homework. She began to
look into past life therapy. She
began to learn the field, and
she began to help her own child
solve his own trauma carried
over from a previous life that
was both spontaneously bubbling
up in his life, she began to
attract other people, with other
children who are also having
problems, and eventually she
wrote this beautiful book,
specifically a therapeutic book
for parents who have children
who are having traumatic memory
surface that they're having
difficulty dealing with was very
successful, very persuasive. It
really made, had a lot of
impact. She got more business
coming in, she wrote a second
book. She gets the award for the
second worst title, a cover on
reincarnation book, return from
heaven. She's looking
specifically at relatives who
have been reincarnated within
their own families. Now, as a
philosopher, that's a weaker
body of evidence, right? Because
there's so much potential for
contamination if you're
remembering your grandfather.
But as a father, this is
interesting. It's interesting,
because reincarnation simply
doesn't happen where it works
well for the researchers, across
great distances and great
families, but inside families is
a very common occurrence, and
therefore it deserves to be
looked at and next. Michael
Newton, two wonderful books, and
I must confess a special
partiality if you want to read
some, if you wanted to just pick
out one or two books out of this
entire list, I can't help but
wish that you would read Michael
Newton's work. Michael Newton
was a hip. Therapist who got
into past life therapy and was
doing past life therapy, and
then he accidentally discovered
that his clients in deep
hypnosis had the ability not
only to remember their previous
life, but to remember what
happened to them after they
died. They could remember
basically his clients were
beginning to describe the
afterlife, and he thought, he
didn't think this was possible,
but he followed his clients,
good therapist that he is, and
he took hundreds of people into
deep hypnotic regressions, and
he followed them when they would
go through their former life and
they would go through the death
experience, he would follow them
into their memories, continuing
on, and then he would ask them
questions. And he kept detailed
notes. He would ask questions
about, what was this? What was
going on, what was it like? And
what he found was, regardless of
what background people came
from, whatever their cultural
enculturation was fundamentalist
Baptist, Carl, Marxist, atheist,
hard core, scientific
reductionist, whatever their
background was, people were
describing the same fundamental
reality in the after death
state. They were describing a
world that had order, that had
structure that had logic. There
was actually a social structure.
It was a world in which older
learners taught younger
learners. And it was also a
world where people made the
choice to reincarnate as a
conscious, careful decision.
It's one of the most important
choices you make if you go to
college, what courses you sign
up for, that's an important
choice, because once you sign up
for a course, you're committed
for the entire semester. When
you incarnate, what life you
take on is an important choice.
And Michael Newton found that,
in fact, in the spiritual world,
the choice of what life to take
is a consciously taken choice,
made under the guidance of your
spiritual helpers and made in
cooperation with the other
persons that you're going to be
incarnating with. So before we
knew, before we were born, when
we knew more than we know now,
when we were aware of more than
we are aware now, we chose the
life that we are living now,
that fact alone just bears deep
meditation. Two last examples,
not from professionals, they're
from amateurs, but that's what
makes them interesting. The
first is this book looking for
Carol Beckwith, and what makes
it interesting is the man who
wrote it, Robert snow. Because
Robert snow is the commander of
the homicide division of the
Indianapolis Police Department.
All right, so he's Chief of
Detectives of he investigates
murders. His opinion is very
important. It must stand up in
court. He would be the last
person that you would think
would be doing research on a
former life. But it happened
that he kind of, he did a hypno
a hypnotic session not oriented
towards past lives. He just kind
of on a lark, he did the
hypnotic session, and in this
hypnotic session, he was hit in
the face with a life that
appeared to be his life, but it
was it scared him to death, and
he literally ran out of the
room. But he was curious, and so
he brought all of his detective
skills to the systematic search
to see if he could identify and
track down whether there was
such a person. And the story of
his experience and the story of
his detective work is told in
this short book, looking for
Carol Beckwith. And lastly, this
book Sole Survivor, which you
may have seen it because they
did some news clips, decent news
clips on it, written by Bruce
and Andrew leininga about their
son, James. And this is a case
of a child, three years old, two
years old, who started having
spontaneous memories and trauma,
waking up crying in the middle
of the night, spontaneous
memories of appear, apparently
dying in World War Two as an
airplane pilot over the over the
coast of Japan. And his father
was a fundamentalist Baptist,
and he was absolutely,
vehemently opposed to his son
reincarnating. Mother was a
little more receptive. So they
got involved in first they
wanted to help their son, but he
got involved in the the inquiry
because he wanted to disprove
reincarnation, whatever was
going on with James. He wanted
to disprove reincarnation to
protect his faith. In the end,
they tracked down this pilot.
They tracked down the story.
They were able to reunite James
with the people at a military
reunion, with the people who had
served with this pilot. And
James was able to identify
people out of this group. The
father became convinced that, in
fact, his son was a
reincarnation of this pilot, and
reincarnation is true. Now I'd
like to just finish with two,
two observations. Quick
observation says lunch awaits.
I'd like to emphasize what we
don't know about reincarnation.
The evidence for reincarnation
may be compelling. However, we
don't really know a lot about
how reincarnation takes place,
or what the physics of rebirth
is. We're still beginners in
this at this point, we can't say
what the soul is, or what it's
made of. How does it come and go
from the physical body? How does
it interface with our biology
and our genetic makeup? How does
it encode its previous learning
into our present body? And how
does it leave with its learning
intact after we die, these
things right now are beyond our
present grasp. I'm sure we'll
make progress in the future, but
before we do, we're going to
have to start we're going to
have to stop reducing mind to
brain, and we're going to be
have to approach this research
with a more multi dimensional
metaphysical cosmology. And
lastly, I'd like to point to a
certain paradox in the evidence.
And to do this paradox, I need
to really go back to Ian
Stevenson. Stevenson's evidence,
I think, is the most powerful
evidence for reincarnation, and
his evidence liberates our
thinking at one level, but it
also constricts our thinking at
another. Because the strongest
evidence for reincarnation comes
from lives that show the
tightest connection, the
tightest correlation. But the
correlation can be so tight it
can lead, if you just study
Stevenson's evidence, it can
lead to a
anemic an under developed vision
of what life is like when we
die, when most of us die. In
that respect, we must remember
that Stevenson's cases are not
typical cases. These children
are coming back very fast and
very close to home. Most people
spend much more quote time in
the timeless condition of the
spirit world. They have a much
wider breadth of experiences. So
Stevenson's evidence liberates
us to thinking about the soul
and thinking about our lives and
thinking about our existence in
a much larger, expanded
framework. But in order to
actually fill in that Canvas, in
order to actually explore more
deeply what happens to us when
we die, and what the larger
circle of life is like, from
expanded consciousness to
contracted consciousness and
back into expanded
consciousness, we need to look
at other bodies of data. I think
Michael Newton's work is an
important body of data that
gives us a larger vision. And
this afternoon, when I talk
about psychedelic research, I'll
look at another body of data,
which I think can give us an
expanded vision of our life in
this universe. Thank you very
much. Applause.
Unknown: Again, Chris, again.
Thank you so much. This was,
again a real experience to
listen to you, and I so much
like how you how you make clear
that this is the knowledge which
makes really such a difference
how we live our life, which
makes such a difference how we
approach every minute in our
life. If this is true or not,
makes the real difference. Like,
I think all the three speakers
of this session fitted together
so well. It's, I think it's so
much arranged, and it's really
the core of the Institute for
existential consciousness,
because these are the real
existential questions. And there
is a scientific basis, and we
have to bring it to society to
make a shift in consciousness
again. So thank you very much,
and I'm so much looking forward
to your next lecture. You.