Chris Bache: Okay, testing one
two, testing one two, yeah,
you're great.
James Jesso: I'm also great.
Audio wise,
Chris Bache: hey, good. How you
doing? Squared image, okay, it
looks good, yeah, yeah. How you
doing today? I'm doing well.
Looking forward to our
conversation. You you
James Jesso: foreign. Hello,
everyone. Welcome back to
adventures through the mind I am
your host, as always. James W
Jesso, I'm going to start this
episode off with a big thanks to
the spirit plant medicine
conference in Vancouver,
happening November 2 to the
fourth. You've probably noticed
they've sponsored a few episodes
over the last couple months. And
yeah, that's very exciting. The
guest today, Chris Bache, is one
of the presenters at the
conference, and I will be one of
the attendees. So if you want to
come check me out, or check out
the conference in general, or
come check out Chris at that
conference, follow the link
contained in the description to
this episode. Jump over there.
If you buy a ticket, then I get
a little bit of commission from
that, which goes towards my
costs to fly to Vancouver to
attend this so it's and you get
to go to a great concert or
concert Jesus conference. Yes,
win, win. Okay, today's guest is
Christopher M Bache. Bache is
professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at young
Youngstown State University,
where he taught for 33 years. He
is also adjunct faculty at the
California Institute of integral
studies and a fellow at the
Institute of Noetic Sciences, an
award winning teacher and
international speaker. Chris
work explores the philosophical
implications of Non-ordinary
states of consciousness,
especially psychedelic states.
He has written three books,
translated into six languages,
life cycles, a study of
reincarnation in light of
contemporary consciousness.
Research. Dark Knight early
dawn, a pioneering work into
psychedelic philosophy and
collective consciousness and the
living classroom, an exploration
of teaching and collective
fields of consciousness. He has
a new book being released from
inner traditions in 2019
diamonds for from heaven, a 20
year journey into the mind of
the universe. So let me just
give you a little bit more
detail as to Christopher and
what he's been up to. At some
point about 40 years ago, he
decided it would be a good idea
for him to take high doses of
LSD regularly with the
intention, I guess, to map
consciousness as a metaphysical
philosopher. And then proceeded
to do so 76 I believe, 76 times
over the course of 20 years, 20
years after his last journey in
that specific structure, he is
about to release his book
diamonds from heaven, and he is
on the show today to talk about
basically, what drove him to do
this, what it was like, and what
did he learn. And furthermore,
not just what did he learn about
the nature of consciousness and
the psychedelic experience. But
what did he learn about what can
we do as human beings to make
sense of experiences that are as
massive as the ones you're going
to hear him describe in this
episode, we also had a great
post credits talk that with his
permission, I am going to be
releasing as well, exclusively
to the patrons at first, but
after a few weeks, you will be
able to get access to it on
YouTube. So if you're not
already subscribed to YouTube,
please head over there. Do so
hit the little bell so that you
get notifications. Because these
sort of extra episodes the post
credit sequence only get
notified to patrons, and then
once they're public, they only
get notified basically out
through those who are subscribed
on my YouTube channel, so head
over there and do that if you're
not already watching this on
YouTube. And if you want to
become a patron, that would be
amazing, because it is thanks to
my Patrons on Patreon that I am
able to give my time into
building this podcast in the
larger domain of my work for you
the psychedelic culture. Big
thanks to the patrons whose
names are listed in the upper
corner of this episode on
YouTube, and to tempoic massage
and Lola for the excellent and
very generous PayPal donations.
Okay, got a little bit of noise
happening in my environment now,
so I'm gonna end this quick if
you want to support the show.
Becoming a patron or by leaving
a donation. The links to do so
are contained in the description
to this episode on YouTube at
James W gesso.com, and whatever
pod catcher you are listening to
it. Enjoy this episode with
Christopher Bache on adventures
through the mind. Just because
of a the context of my of my
work and my travel, I didn't get
a chance to really look into
what you do until yesterday.
Other than, you know, Stevens,
you know, what's the word I'm
looking for, shining
recommendation, definitely put
you on the map. And then I was,
I was really blown away. I found
it. I found it to be, yeah,
yeah. That's just really blown
away. It's interesting, yeah,
interesting stuff you had going
on there,
Chris Bache: yeah? Well, I've
been sort of on the side of the
psychedelic community, but been
there for a long time doing my
own thing.
James Jesso: Yeah, it makes
sense, because you had to
protect your your career for
some time.
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah. All
right. So okay,
James Jesso: why don't, why
don't we start it off here? Just
easing in, give me a sense of of
where you're coming from. When
you start this work, you were
doing high dose LSD experiences
for 20 years. You stopped about
10 years ago, which means that
you started doing this 3030,
years ago at that point, I
believe LSD was already illegal.
Can you sort of like draw or
paint us a picture of the
context that you were entering
into the decision to do this.
And while, while doing that, can
you also explain the difference
between what you were doing and
what was popular at the time in
so far as psychedelic therapy or
psycholytic therapy?
Chris Bache: Yeah. Well, I came
out of graduate school in 1978 I
was trained as a philosopher of
religion, and I came to
Youngstown State University in
Northeast Ohio to begin my
teaching career. And at the
time, I was an atheistically
inclined agnostic. But that
first year, I read Stan Grof
first book, realms of the human
unconscious, and I immediately
connected with it. I felt I had
found my life's work. This was
1978 the Controlled Substances
Act had been passed in 1970 the
early era of psychedelic
research was over, and of
course, we were had entered that
blackout between 1970 and when
Scientific American had
published its front page
editorial recommending that we
end the ban on psychedelic
research in 2017 2014, but there
was this blackout. No one was
allowed to do this work anymore.
I was convinced that it could be
done safely. And Stan Gross was
very work was very important me
in that respect, and I was
convinced that the people who
would be making the most
important contributions in
philosophy of religion would
soon be being people who are
writing out of an experiential
basis. So I made the decision to
divide my life in half and my
public life. I continued my work
as a academic, Professor,
traditional professor, teaching
my courses, doing all the things
professors do. But in my private
life, I began a 20 year journey
working with high levels of
psychedelics of LSD, 73 sessions
extending over 20 years between
1979 and 1999 I chose to work
with high doses first because it
was complicated to arrange time
for sessions when you have a
dual career marriage to
professional people, and I
wanted to make the most out of
every session. But then, after
the process got started, I found
that I thought it would get me
to my goal of enlightenment
faster, basically breaking off
larger pieces of karma, chewing
up larger pieces of karma in
every session after that model
of personal enlightenment
dissolved along the way, I
continued to work with high
doses of LSD, because it took me
where I wanted to go, and then
It took me farther than I ever
dreamed was possible.
James Jesso: Now I'm just going
to take a quick pause to clarify
something, because high dose LSD
is not very clear for the
listeners, how high of a dose?
What was the what was the
metric?
Chris Bache: Metric was 500 to
600 micrograms, which is kind of
a maximum high dose Stan's work,
Stan differentiates between
psychedelic or low dose therapy
averaging about 200 micrograms
up to 300 psychedelic therapy is
high dose between 315 100, more
typically 300 to 500 but in the
early work. He did at Spring
Grove Hospital. It was
deliberately limited to a
maximum of three sessions. The
idea was to trigger an
experience of Transcendence that
would help people come to terms
with their impending death. I
thought, if you could do this
safely three times, you could do
it safely more frequently, and
that's so I saw myself, at the
time, simply doing an extended
dose of high dose therapy. When
I got to the end of this
journey, however, and was
looking back, I realized that
what unfolded on this journey
was more radical and more
challenging than what had
emerged in the early psychedelic
therapy work, and so I had to
coin a new term, a new phrase
for it, so the way I would
describe my work now that that
psychedelic period is
psychedelic exploration, the
method is psychedelic therapy,
with totally internalized
sessions, strong, evocative
music, working with a sitter,
always in a protected, isolated
environment, classic set and
setting. The difference is the
high number of sessions, seven
for me, turned out to be 73
sessions.
James Jesso: Some of the
conclusions that you, that you
drew are, I just remember having
recently listened to some of
your lectures, and just being so
moved by it, and I'm noticing
myself now wanting excitedly to
ask you basically what you
learned in the end. But I know
that this, I'm just like, kind
of suppressing that urge a
little bit and to maybe deepen
into, you know, what? What
exactly was happening? What? And
I want to ask that question
couched in very specific
phenomenon that you observed,
which was multiple layers of
death and and rebirth and like
an increasing expansion into,
and I'm kind of, I guess, using
my own, my own words here, but
like of higher levels of
reality. Can you sort of couch
in this idea of, what do you
mean by multiple death and
rebirth? Can you give us an
outline of, I mean, what the
hell was happening in there
after 70 something? Or, you
know, progressively through 70
something sessions of 500 Mikes
of LSD?
Chris Bache: Well, that is the
question. And it is, it's, it's,
it's hard to summarize. I mean,
it's taken me about 300 pages
just to tell the story of what
happened. It's hard to jump into
it quickly, because there were
so many layers. But basically,
my experience has been that the
universe, or the mind of the
universe, or the mind of Divine
is an infinite ocean of
potential, and when we drop our
individual mind into that ocean,
it catalyzes a set of
experiences out of that infinite
potential. And as we are changed
and influenced and healed and
purified by that exchange, the
seed crystal of our mind
changes, and then later, when we
drop that same mind, now
transformed into the ocean, it
catalyzes a deeper set of
experiences out of that infinite
potential. So my experience was
that there were a series of
initiations that took place over
many years, a series of deaths,
followed by a rebirth into a
deeper level of reality, and
then a gradually acclimating to
that level of reality, adjusting
to its conditions, going through
a purification process, because,
as I experienced it, leads every
deeper level of reality, or
every deeper state of
consciousness that gave us
access to a deeper level of
reality was a higher level of
energy. So to stabilize
consciousness at that deeper
level of consciousness, so that
your experience of that deeper
level of reality would be
coherent and not fragmented, you
had to go through a very intense
purification process, but if you
continue to work at a particular
level, if you can continue to
stay internalized and push my
experience was you would go back
to the same level, and you would
I would acclimate to that level.
I would begin to have more
coherent experiences at that
level. And eventually I would
come to a point where the
Death-Rebirth process would
repeat itself. I would go
through some agonizing, complete
loss of control, and then I
would collapse, and be an
internal collapse, and then I
would be reborn into a yet
deeper level of consciousness,
which gave me access to a deeper
level of reality. And this went
on systematically, periodically
for 20 years. So to describe the
levels of consciousness that I
entered into, it's a that's it's
a longer story.
James Jesso: Absolutely, yeah,
and I was thinking at some point
I might ask you a couple like,
what does this mean? In so far
as like, why is the chapter
titled this? And, yeah, but
maybe because all of this, you
know, having listened to the
longer story, you know, all of
this is very descriptive, but
for someone who's just entering
into this for the first time, it
can be kind of abstract. So
maybe you can, you can talk
about what this looks like,
because I got one description
from you that seemed to make a
lot of sense to me, which was
something like, you know, in the
early sessions, you were working
through your own personal stuff,
and that eventually you needed
to die to who you were, to
become, you know, yeah, beyond
your personality into a greater,
a greater sense of like, the
underlying human consciousness,
and then even at some point to
die from that underlying human
consciousness into something
beyond it. Can you give maybe a
step by step in the early
stages, what that looked like?
Chris Bache: Yeah, for about the
first two years, I worked at
what Stan Grof describes as the
perinatal level of
consciousness, which is the
interface between your personal
reality, your egoic reality in
space time, and early
Transpersonal consciousness. So
I went through many experiences
of reliving my own birth, of
experiences of death and dying,
until eventually, after about
two and a half years, my
personal reality was just
shattered. I was just crushed
and extinguished. I died as the
person I had known myself to be.
And then I was reborn into a
level of reality that
transcended, radically
transcended, Chris bacheous
reality. And I was working, at
that point, at a deep within the
collective unconscious, and then
the entire process began again.
And in my experience, there are
two phases of every session.
There's a cleansing phase, which
lasts usually a couple of hours,
and then there's an ecstatic
phase. So if you enter into the
cleansing phase and let it take
you wherever it wants to take
you, you reach. It reaches a
peak. You go through some type
of crisis, some type of
transition, and then the
remainder of the session is
spent in ecstatic reality, where
you receive teachings and
experiences. So in the cleansing
phase of phase two, I entered
into what I call the ocean of
suffering, just domains of pain
and suffering that were vast,
encompassing large swaths of
human history and hundreds of
1000s of persons. It took about
two years to go through all of
that material at the personal
side, on the ecstatic side, I
was experiencing for about a
year, I experienced my life as a
completed whole, start to
finish, all the time, moments of
my life as a simultaneous
present. I just kind of
experienced my life as a
complete totality. And then in
the second phase, I went through
a series of initiations in which
I was taken deep into the mind
of the universe and just given a
series of teachings and given a
series of experiences, it
basically grounded me in a
larger cosmological vision of
reality. After about two years
of that process, I went through
another death and rebirth cycle
and was spun beyond, not only
beyond my individual reality,
but also beyond my reality as a
human species, altogether,
beyond the collective psyche
into what I identified as
archetypal reality. But it
wasn't the archetypes described
by either Plato or Carl Jung. It
was both, I mean, it had certain
features similar to Plato's
description and certain features
of Jung's description, but it
really had other features that
did not fit in their
description. The realities that
I encountered there at the high
archetypal level were not
eternal, unchanging ideas in the
mind of God, as Plato describes
it, but vast, living cosmic
forces, giant beings being so
vast, my mind literally could
not wrap itself around it. I
could only get approximations of
the scale of their dimensions at
the slightly beneath that, at
the Jungian level, I entered
deep into the collective psyche,
and then for a couple of years,
had all sorts of experiences of
how our species functions as a
single organism, was taken deep
into the sort of meta neural
networks of the species mind,
and also began to have
experiences of reincarnation,
but not as an individual, not
from the perspective of
individual souls, but from the
spectrum of an entire species
that was incarnating every
generation, a whole generation
of its beings, and experiencing
the centralized intelligence
that was kind of orchestrating
or collaborating with the
individual souls to. Facilitate
not just an individual journey
of transformation, but to
facilitate a species journey of
transformation. And I went
through another round of death
and rebirth. I'm skipping over,
of course, a lot of things,
right, right? And then I was
catapulted into what some people
call causal reality, into non
dual reality, and where the
entire universe began to
function as a single totality.
And had a number of experiences
of what the Buddhists call
Shunyata, emptiness, of self,
oneness, cosmic love,
experiences of the primal void,
the fertile void, you know, the
formlessness that is the source
of all existence. After that,
then I went, I was coming into
the last five years of work, and
the last five years catapulted
me after again, more rounds of
purification, death and rebirth,
into a cosmic light that was so
intense and so clear and so
pure. I called it the diamond
Luminosity, and that's where the
title of the book comes from.
Diamonds from heaven. Buddhism
calls this the absolute clear
light. It associates it with its
concept of Dharmakaya, the
fundamental reality that is the
source of all existence. Now let
me back up. Light entered into
the experiences. There are many,
many levels of light, many
gradations of light, in my
experience there, I had
experienced light many times in
earlier Death-Rebirth processes.
So when I talk about the diamond
light, I'm not simply talking
using metaphor to describe that
light, I'm trying to describe a
particularly intense,
exceptionally clear state of
awareness of crystalline light
that becomes so clear,
eventually becomes transparent
to itself. And in those last
five years, in the last 26
sessions, which was actually
about 1/3 of all of my work, I
entered that reality four times
and just four times. So about
once a year, I would be
catapulted into this reality,
and then I would go through more
detoxification, more
purification, and about a year
later would enter into this
reality one more time. That's
the kind of larger overview,
James Jesso: right, right, good,
and I'm glad that you stopped
there, because there's some your
closing experiences. I want to
get to near the end, but I want
to maybe jump back a little bit
and focus on what you're talking
about here with this
purification and also with this
idea of of becoming more
coherent. Now, when you say
purification, what exactly do
you mean? Because I my immediate
assumption is something akin to,
you know, what the Ayahuasca
culture calls purging, where
you're basically putting,
pushing out or releasing or
letting go or discharging,
suffering, pain, you know,
hardships, whatever, through the
active metabolic process of
feeling them so that you can
having let Those go, enter into
a state that a state of being
that exists without them. Is
that what you mean when you're
saying purification,
Chris Bache: that's a good
description. It is that it's
physiological. I mean, you know,
people throw up a lot on
Ayahuasca. They don't tend to
think of LSD as something that
causes throwing up. But to me, I
I was working with such high
levels, I threw up a lot on LSD,
and that's part of this whole
releasing of physical toxins,
biochemical toxins,
psychological toxins, just
letting them come through your
system and offload in very rapid
sequences. When you move into
deeper levels, it takes
different forms. I mean to sort
of it, if you want to become, to
enter it, to enter into very,
very deep states of
consciousness where you enter
into unitive consciousness with
the divine or different
dimensions of existence, or
different dimensions of the
cosmos, you have to completely
let go of everything in your
life which keeps you small. So
it's not just negative
experiences, it's not just pain,
it's every thought form, every
emotional derivative that
constellates around smallness.
But you you have to sort of
allow your system to step up to
handle the enormous waves of
energy that move through you in
these very deep states of
consciousness. So purification
begins at the personal level.
You're purifying all sorts of
pieces of your personal history,
including your former life
history. You. Hmm, but as you go
deeper and deeper, the forms of
purification become harder to
identify with anything personal
they become and eventually you
literally are transcending time
and space. And there is a sense
in which you have to empty
yourself of everything
associated with your entire
history of being a time and
space, being to enter into
realities beyond time and space,
but it is exactly as the
Ayahuasca, the Santo Daime
tradition, describes it. It is a
port ego. It's a letting go.
It's a manifesting and letting
go of those realities.
James Jesso: I'm, you know,
given that we're talking about
transcending time and space. I'm
gonna assume that it, you know,
it's Transcendence linguistic
form as well. But I'm just
curious, like, what, what does
it feel like to, I like, I know
what it feels like to, you know,
purify or discharge, sadness.
Yeah, I know what it feels like
to, to feel like the grief and
the fear, you know, particularly
the grief of of letting go, of
who I think I am, or who I who I
thought I was, yeah, but it
really, it's, it's mind blowing.
Really, is there a way that you
could describe in language what
it's like to purify let go of
your very essence of being bound
by time and space.
Chris Bache: Your question
really penetrates right to the
some very heart of some very
thorny issues. Let me, let me,
let me mention before we jump
into it, you know, ineffability
is taken as one of the signature
qualities of a genuine mystical
experience. William James first
brought it in, and it's been
incorporated into some of the
diagnostic questionnaires to
assess the depth of one's
mystical experience. Personally,
I think ineffability is
overrated. So these things are
hard to put into words. They are
hard to define ways of
expressing experiences that you
enter into in these realities.
But my experience is, when you
first break into a new level of
reality, it is hard to get it
down on paper. It is hard to
find words, and there are some
tricks that I learned in order
to concretize by recall of these
experiences. But what I found
is, if you keep going back to
the same level of reality over
and over again, if you go
through this purification
process and consciousness
stabilizes at that level of
reality, your cognition becomes
clear, you begin to understand
how this works, the pieces begin
to cohere, and it becomes easier
and easier to find the right
words to describe it. Then when
you break into a new level of
reality, the same dynamic
repeats itself that you're kind
of overwhelmed by the enormity
of something different, but if
you keep going back with focus,
you will be able to stabilize it
the particular experience that
you're talking about, of letting
go all of your experience in
time and space. Well, partly,
partly, I experience it as a
matter of fear. You're becoming
something so large that it's
swallowing everything you've
ever known. Not only swallowing
everything you've ever known as
an individual, but there's a
sense in which when you're
working at that level, even to
even to push that particular
boundary, you are no longer an
individual. Having gotten to
that level, there's a sense in
which you're you're functioning
as a species. You're functioning
as a as a fractal member of an
entire human species. And then
at a deeper level, you're not
even a species. You're somehow a
fractal embodiment of an entire
evolutionary impulse that's been
manifesting galaxies and solar
systems and planets and evolving
life. So you literally have
already dissolved into those
deeper patterns. So you're not
an individual having a
Transpersonal experience. You
have surrendered into that part
of the universe that lives as a
galaxy that lives effort as an
evolutionary thrust. So when it
comes to the point of letting go
of that and entering into
something which is where the Big
Bang came from, entering in the
domain of formlessness itself,
it's it feels less like a
personal crisis. It feels like
an almost an evolutionary
crisis, or a species anxiety.
But if you let go, the universe
takes you in, and can you just
lose all frames of reference?
Yeah, and then suddenly you're
alive within a different
reality. I mean, what you It's
hard to describe, because I say
you're alive, but you're not who
you were before. But there is a
thread of memory that connects
who you were inside time and
space to who you are in this
reality, which is outside time
and space. But what you are
experiencing it's not you're
literally adrift in the mind of
God, so to speak, you're,
you're, you're in the in the
cosmos as part of the title,
currents of the cosmos,
James Jesso: like part of but
also as the title currents,
like, there, is there? Like,
it's not just like, Oh, I am in
the universe. Is there? Like, a
sense of being all of that as
well?
Chris Bache: Yes. I mean,
basically, in each deeper and
deeper level, I experience it as
a remembering I wasn't entering
a reality that I was not. I was
remembering a dimension of my
own existence that I had
forgotten about. So becoming one
with God is not a matter of
confronting an external deity,
which you then merge with,
becoming one with God. Or I
don't even like to use the word
God, because of all the you
know, historical associations,
the baggage that comes with it.
But to become one with that
reality, with that fundamental
reality, you it's a matter of
remembering. It's a remembering
the fundamental truth that
that's what you are. You are a
manifestation. You are a fractal
embodiment of an aspect of this
divine impulse. So the whole
experience is as you become
larger, you remember more. As
you remember more, you become
clear. As you become clearer,
you enter deeper and deeper into
into these ocean currents, but
always the sense of waking up.
You're waking up. It's not
really about dying and being
reborn. It's just a matter of
waking up to something that is
your true and natural condition.
James Jesso: So I might, I might
be jumping the gun here, as they
say, but I feel like this might
be a good time to ask something
that I wanted to save till
later, and then I'll jump back
afterwards. Okay, I'm, I'm
assuming that you're familiar
with with the the anecdotal
reports of five Meo DMT that
have been really growing a lot
over the last 10 years or so.
Yeah, and a lot of the people
who are, we'll say the people of
the five, you know, they they
experience, and then claim that
what happens is like, this is
the ultimate non dual
experience. And you enter into,
you become like the apex of
consciousness, in some way, like
the God. And in your experience,
you at one point even got to
what could be described as this
apex, maybe this, this is this
diamond Luminosity. And then at
some point, realized that there
was something even further
beyond that as well. I'm
curious, given your experiences
like your you know, your deep
experiences with high dose LSD
over such a long time, and
these, this, these entrances
into into different levels of
consciousness. How do you feel
about the sort of the larger
cosmological or metaphysical
claim that's being made by
people who are experiencing five
Meo DMT?
Chris Bache: Yeah, first, I'm
really comfortable with the five
Meo DMT discussion. I mean, I
think it's a fascinating
substance. It has this capacity
to just catapult us through so
many layers and give us a short
immersion into those deep, deep,
cosmic territories. But in some
ways, the situation is similar,
I think, to people who have near
death episodes, you know, who
just walking down the street,
they have a heart attack, and
they they they almost die, and
they're knocked out of their
body, and they have a powerful,
transcendental experience, which
lasts minutes, hours, and then
they come back in their body,
and they're trying to understand
what it is they experienced. And
if you have fleeting contact
with these realities at one
level. You know what they are.
You can feel what they are. You
know, there is a sense in which
you are immersed in the ultimate
but it may be because they are
so short term and so singular. I
think sometimes we draw
premature conclusions about what
they imply for the nature of the
universe itself. So at least
here's why. I suspect that when
I was doing this work, and I got
to the point where I was in
those last five years, and I was
in that series of immersions
into what I call the diamond
Luminosity, past oneness past.
You know, merging with the
divine into some level that felt
even beyond calls or reality.
I'd gone into it once. I went
into it a second time. This is
my 50th session. And then
towards the end of that session,
I had an unusual experience. I
was as as far out as I'd ever
gone, I was totally, absolutely
peace, floating, merged with
this light, and then suddenly
everything pivoted 90 degrees,
and I saw a reality that was
far, far removed, and this
reality was light soaked, and a
beam of light came out of that
reality and hit me, and it just
absolutely shattered me. It was
a completely different order of
light, beyond even the diamond
Luminosity that it had taken me
15 years to get to. And that's
when I realized I called it the
absolute light, just to give it
a name. But that's when I
realized that it's an infinite
progression. And I completely
gave up to the the idea that we
could ever get to the end of it.
See, when I had started this
work, I thought there was an end
state. You did this work, and
you you reach some definitive
end of the process. And some
people talked about us becoming
one with God, or becoming one
with the universe. Some people
talked about entering the primal
void, or the super, meta, cosmic
void. And I had entered those
states of oneness, and I
discovered that there are
actually many gradations of
oneness, and I had entered
formlessness, but I discovered
that there are actually
gradations of formlessness, and
this experience convinced me
that even using this very
powerful method, the universe
was just much, much larger than
I had imagined it to be, and
that there was no way I was
going to ever be able to come to
the end some end. And I just
realized that was a false, a
false expectation on my part.
And then what happened in the
sessions is that the session
stopped taking me farther out,
and the diamond Luminosity began
to crunch itself deeper, more
and more deeply into my physical
body. The next year, two years
of work were all about being
having that diamond light crunch
into my physiology, into my
psychology, into my neural
anatomy. So I understand, I
really do understand those
senses of ultimacy that emerge
in these experiences. I think
that's a phenomenologically
accurate description, but kind
of, as a metaphysician, I would
bracket discussions of ultimacy,
because I'm not, I really not
sure that we are in a position
as a species even using these
very, very powerful substances
to make safe claims about what
is ultimate or not.
James Jesso: Yes, cool. Thank
you very much. Now we're going
to put a pin in that and jump
back, okay, and talk a little
bit more about purification and
coherency. You make a comment,
you've made the comment multiple
times, and maybe you could just
sort of clarify it a bit now
that you you have to effort at
some point, and get familiar
with certain states of
consciousness at which point you
become coherent. There you're
you hold a cog coherent
cognition while in these higher
energy states of consciousness.
Can you maybe just explain that
a little bit more deeper, and
possibly you know, how, how it
is that you do that?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, this
was a learn as you go process.
You know, I didn't, I wasn't
part of a psychedelic culture. I
never, didn't have a shaman,
kind of helping me through this
process. I was really having to
figure it out as I went and I
was using a medicine that didn't
have a lot of history. It didn't
have and it didn't have
psychedelics, didn't have fields
associated with it, the way that
mushrooms do and the way that
Ayahuasca does. It's really a
relatively new medicine, and
therefore it's very much was
taking me to an edge my
experience. You know, when, when
I read the literature of
people's psychedelic
experiences, particularly their
experiences with with LSD or
other very powerful
psychedelics, I saw that the the
different ways that they were
touching all sorts of different
levels of reality, but I also
saw a lot of confusion and a lot
of fragmentation in their
experience. They were getting,
it was as if they were getting
bits and pieces. And I found
that when I when they were
describing multiple sessions, it
was as if they were always
starting over again. They were
they were always getting to this
space where they were having
these experiences, but there
wasn't a progressive
development. Mental sequence, my
experience was different than
that. I experienced myself as
being engaged in a long
sustained conversation which
deepened into a communion with a
consciousness which never took
any form. It never took a
particular symbolic form. It
never but it always was there.
And it was orchestrating my
sessions. It was determining
what happened in the sessions.
All I had to do was show up, let
it take me where it would take
me, and then make sense of what
would happen. And making sense
of what happened involved
methodically recording the
session, thinking about it
extensively after the session.
It wasn't simply just a matter
of having a clean context
environment. So good set, good
setting, good preparation, all
those things. It was a matter of
thoroughly thinking about
processing, trying to integrate
intellectually as well as
personally, emotionally and
physically, the experiences that
you were having. So I mean, I
was trained as a philosopher. I
was trained as an analytic
philosophy philosopher. So when
I would enter these states, I
would try to enter into it as
clearly as I could and take in
as much as I possibly could and
understand as much as I could
and retain as much as I could.
And I found that if you meet the
universe, or if you meet these
states with that kind of
devotion to engagement, it will
orchestrate your experience and
take you as deep as you have the
capacity to go, but you have to
hold the posture at your end.
You have to do your work. You
have to do your side. And your
side for me, involved paying
attention, surrendering, having
the courage to let it take me
where it would take me, having
the courage to die again and
again in this process, but then
writing it down, thinking about
it, trying to figure it out, put
the pieces all together and let
it unfold.
James Jesso: Hmm, interesting.
Yeah, that's great. And later,
before we end, I'd like to ask
you a bit about your your
thoughts and advice on on
integration. But you having said
that, and when I first heard it,
really, it echoed something that
I hadn't been able to give words
to before I wrote a book on on
working with Psilocybin
mushrooms. And that is exactly
what happened to me over the
course of an extended period of
time, of using it monthly. It
was like, each time I used it, I
got with this, like pay
attention, surrender and trust
the process. I just got a
greater level of cognitive
coherency so that I could come
back, I would do all the
writing, I'd explore it that I
could, you know, accurately
articulate. This is exactly
what's happening, and here's how
it comes about, and here's Well,
for me anyways, at these dose
levels. So that was a really,
that's a really cool language,
and unless you want to
particularly comment on that, I
have a I have another question
here
Chris Bache: for you. Now, I
completely understand our it's
interesting how our experiences
are so congruent with different
psychedelics. Each psychedelic
has its own quality, but the the
phenomenon of engagement is the
same in all of them,
James Jesso: you definitely went
much deeper than I, much deeper
than I did actually. Let's just,
let's Okay, we're gonna just put
everything on hold for a second
because you said something else
one time that I thought was very
interesting. And I'll just ask
you outright, because I get this
question of a lot. What is the
difference between LSD and
Psilocybin? Yeah. Well, I mean
this phenomenologically, not,
yeah, phenomenologically,
Chris Bache: I think of
Psilocybin as very much of a
kind of a body grounded
psychedelic. I feel it very
strongly in my body. It really
when I'm in a Psilocybin state,
this intelligence. It almost as
if it enters into my body. It
sweeps through my body, checks
it out, can identify what's
going on here, there touches,
the emotional feels, and it's a
very it's my whole body hums and
glows when I'm with Psilocybin,
something very similar with
Ayahuasca. It feels very your it
takes your whole body into the
experience. My experience
working again with high doses of
LSD and different lower doses,
but with high doses of LSD, it
is such an enormous
acceleration, such an enormous
catapulting into deep, deep
states of consciousness. It
almost as if this isn't really
quite true, but in certain ways,
it almost as if it tends to
leave the body behind. And
there's a way in which
integrating the body into those
states of consciousness. Ness
takes time and comes later.
There's a tendency to that's not
a dissociative psychedelic like
ketamine is, but it tends to
sort of drive to what I would
call the high cosmological
ceiling. It tends to throw you
into the high cosmological
ceiling, and it doesn't give
you, for example, in least in my
experience, it didn't give me
contact with the elemental
spirits, with the earth spirits,
with the with the the totem
ancestors of the animal or
vegetable kingdom. It just
wasn't working at that level. It
tends to be kind of drive
towards the cosmological
ceiling, so to speak, so it
would drive me beyond my
personal ego, and then it drove
me into the species
consciousness, and then it drove
me into Earth consciousness, and
then it started taking me even
beyond that territory. Cool.
Thank you. I found later that
using Psilocybin actually kind
of helped me integrate some of
my LSD experiences precisely
because it tended to open up my
body and allowed some of that
high cosmological energy to
enter more easily into my
physical form.
James Jesso: Now were you
taking, were you taking higher
doses of Psilocybin, or more
average, say, five dried grams
of mushrooms, or were you
entering into uh kilinde e
territory, where you're at 2030,
grams, 4050, grams of mushrooms.
Chris Bache: I was probably
working in more standardized
doses with Psilocybin. I wasn't
really trying, and much of the
work I did with Psilocybin was
after I had stopped the LSD
work. I did some intermittently
along the way, but after I
stopped the LSD work, I worked
with Psilocybin and some with
Ayahuasca, and what I found is
that it was very helpful towards
integration. I didn't feel like
I was breaking new territory,
and I wasn't trying to break new
territory I was trying to
recover from the territory I'd
already broken into. I was
trying to basically learn how to
walk on the earth again after
having so many transcendental
experiences.
James Jesso: Well, I would be
very curious to see you and
Kalin de compare notes of ultra
high dose tryptophan. But let's,
let's, let's, let's go back now
that we're okay, we've explored
that. Okay, increasing, you
know, cognitive coherency at
increasing levels of high energy
consciousness, yeah, mixing this
with purification. Okay, so what
I'm curious about, like, did it
get easier, or did it stay about
the same as you progressed? And
what I mean by this was, is
okay, so in the early phases,
you're just, you're struggling
with all the pain and grief of
just letting go of being a, you
know, a white, you know, highly
educated philosopher, a male
This is one of your stories into
becoming something else, you
know, like the entire female
side of our species. You know,
over time, yeah, you're
struggling with that, the pain
and grief of that, maybe pain
and grief of past traumas or
whatever it is. And then, you
know, fast forward 15 years, and
you're, you're, you're facing
the fear and the discomfort and
the challenge of letting go of
all time and space, and
somewhere in the middle of that,
you're in a would you call the
sea of suffering? You know, when
you're experiencing the
suffering of the entire species
of humanity, you know over all
time, simultaneously, you know
is it is what you were
experiencing in those later
phases. Was that about the same
level of challenge with a
greater psychic magnitude, or
did it get easier? Did it stay
this? This is what I'm curious
about, really. Yeah, yeah,
Chris Bache: the ocean of
suffering was much harder, much
more demanding to experience
than the dissolution of my
private ego is different, a
different order of magnitude.
Let me have to go back to think
of something I thought while you
were asking the question, I'm
beginning to lose it now. Okay,
I don't I want to be careful not
to over emphasize the negative,
because there's a steady rhythm,
you know, there's the the clear,
the the purification phase of a
session, and then there, there
the ecstatic phase. And to me,
the only thing that makes it
possible to endure the
purification phase are the
blessings that you're giving in
the ecstatic phase. So when I
was processing the ocean of
suffering after a session, it
wasn't just the ocean of
suffering that I was processing.
I was also processing the
enormous gift of my early
unitive experiences, my early
experiences of being taken on
what I call. The cosmic tour, my
early experience of being taken
back to the beginning of
creation. So it's it's all sorts
of wonderful ecstatic
experiences are part of that.
And this rhythm kept up all the
way through. There was a rhythm
of purification and a rhythm of
blessing. And the blessings
always kept pace with this, the
magnitude and the scale of the
purification. So the deeper the
purification went, the deeper
the blessings became, until
eventually, once you learn that
rhythm, once you learn that all
you have to do is follow the
purification as deeply as it
goes, and there will be
blessings waiting for you at the
end. At that point, you
literally begin to not avoid
purification. You seek it out.
You want to go as deeply into
that muck as you can, not
because you're a glutton for
pain and suffering. Your your
glutton for what lies on the
other side of that pain and
suffering. Now, in some ways,
the rhythm itself gets easier
once you know that that is the
rhythm, it gets easier because
there is less fear associated
with it. The ordeal may be
intense, but it does not
frighten you as deeply you may
get transiently terrified, but
you trust the process. You keep
going deeper into it, one of the
worst in the sense,
experientially, most demanding
sessions I ever had, actually,
was the 70th session. It was the
last great vision. I was given a
series of what I would call the
great visions in my work over
the years. But the 70th session
put me through a tear down, a
rip down that was worse than
anything I'd ever gone through
before. So it in some ways, it
gets easier, but then, if the
universe wants to take you very,
very deep, in order to get to
that depth, it's got to put you
through a process that you need
in order to stabilize
consciousness in that depth. And
in this case, it took me deeper
into what I call deep time than
it had ever taken me before I
use I coined the term deep time
to describe a particular
experience with respect to time
and transcending time, you can
go outside of time altogether
into eternity and escape the
envelope of space time
altogether. But I had many
experiences of experiencing
certain units of time, certain
spans of time, as an organic
whole. So this began early on by
experiencing my complete life as
a totality, start to finish, and
then I began to experience
evolution, the evolution of the
universe and the evolution of
humanity in terms of a time
frame of 10s of 1000s, hundreds
of 1000s of years. So there was
like my consciousness was
extended to 100,000 years, and I
could experience how the
universe experiences that
100,000 years, not how Chris
Bache might experience that so
deep time became a term that I
used to describe different
modalities of time, and
eventually I became convinced
that these modalities weren't
simply projections, and they
weren't simply, you know,
playing, shuffling the cards of
how Chris Bache experiences
time, but somehow I was being
taken into how the universe
experiences time, and the
universe as you move more
towards the edge of space, time,
time itself begins to be more
porous this last session. Well,
let me back up one of the things
we haven't talked about yet is
many experiences that I had,
which eventually became a story
of the evolution of the human
race and where we are in our
evolutionary story, and the
particular crisis that we are
coming into As I think our
entire species is trying to
outgrow the egoic psychology of
the past and move into a much
deeper archetypal No, a much
deeper experience of being a
human which is much more soul
oriented, much More transparent
to each other and to the divine.
The 70th session that I
referenced was my deepest
excursion into deep time, which
took me deep into humanity's
future and gave me one of my
clearest experiences of what I
call the future human, the the
human being that humanity is in
the process of becoming our next
evolutionary type. So it gets
easier, but you never know when
you know it can come up and slap
you hard if it wants to take you
somewhere especially,
James Jesso: yeah, that's
something, something I learned
all too. Well, and is definitely
shared amongst the other deep
explorers that I know it's just
like, just be careful, because
as soon as you get brazen, it'll
teach you a lesson. All comes,
no matter how competent you
feel. So maybe now is a good
time to to move into some
closing because we're just about
the hour mark here, pretty
quick,
you stop doing this Yes, and,
and I kind of already have a
sense of where the answer is
going, so I'm curious how to ask
the question, because I I'm
simultaneously wondering, Why
did you stop? Yeah, while also
wondering, you know, what did
these experiences? How did they
change your relationship to
dying like your your physical
death as a as human now. Yeah,
that's, that's sort of like the
large, open ended question,
yeah, well, let
Chris Bache: me take that last
question first, because it's the
easiest. I'm so looking forward,
not necessarily, to the process
of dying, but I am so looking
forward to being dead with
absolute and complete
confidence, because I know where
I'm going. I've died. I've made
that transition so many times in
my sessions, I feel very
comfortable with what's going to
be happening after this body
falls away. I stopped these
sessions. It's not that I
stopped sessions altogether, but
I stopped this particular series
of sessions. I stopped working
with high doses of LSD for two
reasons. One was pain, and the
other was heartache. When you're
working with such extremely high
doses of LSD, there's just an
enormous demands. It places
enormous demands on your body
and on your subtle energy
system. And what I found, and
this I talk about, in diamonds
from heaven, what I found is
that, after many years, my
energy was just running so hot.
I was carrying too much energy.
It was like I was almost never
comfortable in my body. I wasn't
having flashbacks or anything
like that, but literally, my
subtle energy system was so
taxed by entering in and out of
these states and a rhythmic even
just five times a year that I
had to stop to let my whole
system Calm down, cool down, and
find its new equilibrium. But
the main reason I stopped is
different. The main reason I
stopped was heartache. I
literally could not take the
heartache of being separated
from the Divine anymore. I had
entered and was entering so
deeply into the diamond
Luminosity, so deeply into the
crystalline nature of whatever
you want to call it, the divine
or the absolute, or I had
dissolved and lost my body, my
boundaries, and entered and
become light so many times, and
with such exquisite joy that
coming back into time space
became just a terrible
heartache. And eventually I
reached a point where I decided
better not to go back at all
than to have to go and leave.
And so I made a kind of an
agreement with I call the
absolute, my words for the
absolute, or my beloved, because
it was a love relationship that
unfolded. So I made a deal with
my beloved to never take me back
that deeply again until I would
not have to leave. And that's
really why I stopped my
sessions. I thought that I
could, just because I really
paid a lot of attention to
integration all the way through
the process, you know, I really
tried to do it right, do all the
things you do to really solidly
integrate each individual
session. And I thought that I
could therefore stop my
sessions, and then I would be
able to harvest the insights and
the experiences that I had been
blessed with on during those
years. What I found was,
however, that in the years
following, really a number of
years, I began to enter into
what I call the deep sadness. I
began to enter into a sense of
existential loneliness. I just,
I was so I was missing the
divine so deeply back now in
time and space that basically
life had began to feel all dried
up. I really, I really wasn't
that interested in being here,
and I found that I was just
waiting. Waiting to die. I was
just waiting to die so I could
return to the light in years
past. And I began to realize
slowly that this isn't good.
This is not the way it's
supposed to be. I knew that this
was not the way it was supposed
to end up, and I didn't
understand what had happened
because I had been so careful
with integration all the way
through I It wasn't clear to me
where I had where had gone
wrong, but my life was telling
me was screaming, failure to
integrate, failure to integrate.
In time I began to realize that
what had happened was I had lost
a balance between Transcendence
and immanence between letting go
and going beyond all time space
reality and being grounded
solidly within time and space.
Reality. Time and space is the
manifest body of the Divine. I
know it's the divine. I've
experienced it as the manifest
being of the Divine. It's not
that there are two divines.
There's just the you know,
transcendent divine and the
immanent divine. But I had
plunged so deeply into the
transcendent divine that I kind
of lost my foothold. I lost my
grounding in the imminent
divine, and I made a it took
about 10 years, but I made a
determined commitment to
reground myself into physical
existence, to temper my memories
of Transcendence with my
appreciation and enjoyment of
the manifest divine around me
continuously. And that took a
long time, but eventually I did,
and eventually I became more
comfortable being here. One of
the problems, one of the things
I ran into in going through this
process, one of the challenges,
wasn't simply withdrawing from
this intimate communion, it was
living in the silence that had
been imposed on me by our
psychedelic phobic culture. I
wasn't allowed to speak about my
experiences. I couldn't teach
from them. I could not bring
them to my colleagues. I could
not really write in complete
abandon. I could not do what I
had been trained to do as a
philosopher of religion. I
couldn't philosophize based on
these experiences. I wasn't part
of a psychedelic subset in Ohio,
and I knew that if I began this
conversation, I would be fired.
You know, I would just and I
love to teach. I love being with
my students. So this beat, this
split between my public life and
my private life, became
increasingly burdensome. And
then when I stopped the
sessions, it became even more
burdensome that I I didn't have
a place to process my
experiences. So what I found is
that there's, there's a level of
integration that could take
place privately,
psychologically, before I
started to speak, and then when
I began working on diamonds from
heaven, and I began to give the
talks as i This book was coming
to its conclusion, and I began
to share with people what it
actually what I had actually
done, and where it had gone. So
I could not only share what I
had experienced, but take in
what they had experienced. I
found that the integration of
those experiences began to
deepen. They began to live in me
differently than they had lived
before. I began to speak about
them, and that's that's begun a
process that's still continuing
to unfold. I don't know where
it's going to go, but somehow
the transcendent divine and the
imminent divine seem to be
reaching a deeper merging, a
deeper synthesis in my life now
that I finally, you know, shared
the conversation, I've opened
the conversation.
James Jesso: There's, there's a
couple more questions I have for
you, if you've got the time,
yeah, this one might be a bit
quick. You were just, you were
uncomfortable physically because
of this, you know, high subtle
energy. Were you doing any
physical spiritual practices,
yoga, tai chi, anything like
that?
Chris Bache: Yes, I was doing,
first, I was doing meditation
and Vajra during all of my
years, and in the last five
years, I was really doing formal
Vajrayana practices. I was
taking good care of my body. I
was doing yoga. I was really
maintaining a very careful at
that time, a vegetarian diet. I
was really taking a lot of care
of my body. I was doing
chiropractic care. I was doing
massages. I was really taking
care of the instrument.
James Jesso: Okay, cool. That
was I was curious about, because
that might be an area where it's
like, oh, maybe if you were
doing yoga, blah, blah, blah,
yeah. Cool. So this other
question is very personal. Why?
I mean, everything you've shared
is obviously very personal, but
this is the kind of personal
that a lot of people hesitate
to. To share. So you certainly
don't have to answer this. No
pressure, which is, what kind of
a toll did these experiences
take on your capacity to be
intimate with other people?
Because I know for myself, when
I was it's less now, but when I
was going regularly, very deep
into my mushroom experiences.
Yeah, I often felt very
existentially alone and like I
couldn't relate to other people
and I couldn't relate to I
didn't I felt like there was
this vital area of relationship
in my romantic partnerships that
was always missing because they
didn't go there as well, and so
I always felt alone in those
explorations. Yeah, so I'm just
curious what kind of because I'm
assuming that your intimate
partners weren't going as like
regularly, deep as yourself. You
know, what kind of impact did
that have on your ability to be
at the human level and be
intimately relating with other
people or with lovers?
Chris Bache: Yeah, I know
exactly what you're referring
to. I understand that
loneliness, and that loneliness
was the unexpected cost of doing
this work. I Of all the things I
had anticipated entering into
this essentially a shamanic
path, the loneliness and
separation from other people was
the most unexpected. And it's
kind of curious, because because
of the experiences, my capacity
to enter into other people's
lives, to empathically enter
into their experience, had
deepened enormously, but unless
they were psychedelic and Italy
initiated themselves, they had
no capacity to understand what
were, to me, the most important
experiences of my life. And so
naturally, a certain distance
grew up between myself and my
social relationships and this
anyway, so there is and there is
a sense the world. There's a
place in Carlos castaneda's book
where Don Juan is talking to Don
Genaro, and Don and Gennaro says
the world is only real when I'm
with him, meaning Don Juan,
which means there's a sense in
which, if you take up the
psychedelic path, or any
practice which really opens up
deeper and deeper levels of
experience. It does inadvertent
it inevitably separates you.
You're on a different road than
the people around you who are
interested only in physical,
tangible things. And so there is
a loneliness that comes with
that. I find that this
loneliness is for me is easing
as I become more public and I
enter into conversations with
people like yourself, who have
had their own experiences, and
we can share these things, and
it's easier now. In terms of my
most intimate relationships,
I've been very blessed in that
respect. I've been married
twice. Carol was a my first
wife. We were married for 24
years. She was my wife during
all the years when I was doing
this work. She was my sitter in
all of this work. She is a very
mystically inclined person.
She's a deep Buddhist
practitioner. She never was
interested in doing sessions.
They just wasn't she was they
always seemed too violent for
her, and she really was
meditator everything she needed
she found on her meditation
cushion. And in some ways, it
wasn't until I began at very
advanced levels of this
conversation, this engagement,
when I was moving into the
diamond Luminosity, that I felt
like I began to understand her
for the first time. So she was a
highly developed spiritual being
after we have separated, and she
has remarried, and I have
remarried, she has gone on to
complete her Vajrayana training.
She's done her three year, three
month retreat with her teacher
in Santa Fe, New Mexico to go
Sonic. So she's a serious
practitioner, and so I didn't
experience lack of headroom in
my conversation with her. I
always felt like, in some ways,
even though the experiences were
different, but in some ways, the
more I did this work, the closer
we were coming existentially in
that way, and after, after I
stopped my sessions, we came to
a point where we separated with
for reasons that don't have to
do with the sessions themselves.
We just came to a parting of our
ways, and we're still friends
and but then I was blessed with
a second marriage that with
Christina Hardy. And Christina
Hardy is also a journeyer, so
she understood experientially
the dimensions that I had
entered into. She understood
them from her own experience.
She's also an astrologer, so and
she's very deeply a daughter of
the earth. Than a daughter of
the stars. So she kind of lives
deeply grounded in the reality,
in the text, in the textures of
time and space and in the
rhythms of time and space. So
that in my most intimate
relationships, I've been blessed
to be with two women who were
able to understand the unique
experiences that I was going
through, it would have been very
lonely to be with people who
where you experience intimacy at
one level, but you don't
experience that intimacy at
another level.
James Jesso: Yeah, the final
question that I have, I want to
hold on it for a second, because
you said something, and I just
want to make sure I understand,
because if, if I understand, I
think it's an important point.
You said that your first wife
never she did not want to do
what you were doing because she
found it too violent. And you
said, at a certain point, you
began to understand her. Is that
what you mean? You started to
understand why she wouldn't
choose to do what you were
doing.
Chris Bache: No, it wasn't that
particularly I, I shouldn't say
focus just on the violence she
really. She's a very gentle and
a naturally mystical, oriented
person, and she found the
vehemence of the cleansing
portion of the sessions very
hard for her to relate to. She
also found the temporary nature
that you would have these deep,
temporary experiences, but then
you would come back and you
couldn't hold on. You could
remember them, but you couldn't
embody them. And she was more
attracted to a path where you
basically could hold on to more
of your experiences. It was a
slower path of initiation, but
you could hold on to more of
your experiences. What I mean
was by when I say I began to be
able to understand her more
deeply. There is a sense in
which her natural way of tuning
into the universe, and the
universe that she tuned into
that is what I began to
appreciate more deeply, that
when, when I began to touch into
the diamond Luminosity, I
touched into a reality that was
so absorbing and so powerful for
me that basically nothing else
in my sessions mattered except
reconnecting with that reality.
And I began to appreciate how
her entire life, ever since she
had been a girl, had been
oriented towards accessing and
stabilizing this deep
participation in the universe.
James Jesso: Okay, that's what
it was. Yes, I got you i I'm
glad for the clarification,
because I might have
misunderstood as, as you know,
you've said in your talks
elsewhere, that that you
wouldn't recommend this path for
other people, and that, you
know, if you could go back, you
would be, you know, quote,
easier on yourself, and so I
wondered if that's, if that's
what you were leaning towards,
Chris Bache: I would be gentler
for a number of reasons. One is
because I learned that it's not
a matter of getting to an end
destination. It's a matter of
becoming open living as much of
the infinite enter into your
being as you can absorb. And if
that's the approach. If it's
really about grounding the
transcendent experiences here
and now in this body, then that
is often served better by
working with lower doses that
allow you to hold on to more of
what you experience. So I really
don't recommend what I did. I
mean, I really think I pushed
myself. It It took a great deal
of concentration, a great deal
of commitment to do, to go some
of the places I went. And I
don't think it's necessary in
order to spiritually wake up, to
have the to go where I went. I'm
I just have more compassion for
myself, and I wouldn't want some
people, anybody to to undergo
some of the things I went
through.
James Jesso: Okay, thank you.
So, the final question before
the, you know, the
understandable opportunity to
promote your new book and get
people more connected with you,
yeah, is about integration,
maybe a fuller understanding for
us, like what it means to
integrate, because there are,
there's, you know, one thing
about, you know, writing the
stuff down. I remember you had
explained that the next day, you
would write it down, like
narrativize it, listening to the
same music you listen to during
the session, and that you would
name each session so that as
soon as you looked at the name,
you would have a sense of what
that session contained, which is
brilliant. Thank you. On behalf
of all psychedelic explorers,
thank you for that. And you've
also mentioned the vital
importance of relationship in
the integration process in other
talks. And so. Those two things
sort of laid out. How do you
integrate something as profound
and massive as the things that
you had gone through?
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think some
of the challenges, the personal
challenges that I faced around
integration, is one of the
reasons I precisely would
recommend that people don't do
what I did, precisely because it
with these substances. We can
project ourselves. We can
dissolve so deeply into these
vast territories that it truly
becomes mind boggling. How does
how do you integrate them? In
fact, I mean, as long as you're
staying inside time and space
and you're uncovering your pains
of your past and your oncoming
trauma for this life or former
lives, we have therapeutic
models for what integration
looks like and how to do it. And
if you go deeper and you
experience the intelligence that
runs through all things, and you
experience, you know, the
certainty of continuity of life
after death, we still have
spiritual models for what it
means to integrate those
experiences into our life. And
when you look at the near death
episode research, people have
very deep one time experiences
of Transcendence. We have a
sense of how to integrate that
material, but it truly is one of
the leftover questions of my
life is, what does integration
mean when you when you're going
so deep into deep time? How do
you integrate 100,000 Year
swaths of time into Monday,
Tuesday, Wednesday,
consciousness? How do you
integrate becoming one when you
are, you know, just one among
many again. How do you
integrate, you know, going so
deep into the future that you're
looking at the next evolutionary
stage of the human process. How
do you integrate that with
coming back and going back to
work in the morning after I
finished my session, shortly
thereafter, in my morning
meditation, Spirit said to me,
20 years in, 20 years out. And I
thought, okay, I understood what
that meant. It would take me at
least 20 years to integrate the
experiences that I'd cultivated
over those 20 years, and I
thought that sounds about right,
but now dark matter, the
diamonds from heaven, will be
published 20 years after I
stopped my session. So I really
have been looking at how much
I've been able to hold on to
during those 20 years and where
it's taken me. And as I
mentioned, the depth of the
loneliness that I experienced
was not because of a failure in
my sessions. It was actually
because of success. The success
that you have entering into the
universe becomes the challenge
of integration when you come
back again, I found that as long
as I was keeping silent, as long
as I was really not
communicating from my center
about these experiences,
immigration could only take us,
could only proceed to a certain
level when I wrote dark night,
early dawn, where I first began
to unpack some of these
experiences that allowed me to
enter into some conversations
that allowed this integration,
this deeper integration, to
manifest. But it wasn't really
until I began to write diamonds
from heaven that I began to
experience a deeper level of
integration manifest. And I
guess the way I would put it is
like this, I don't think you can
integrate the infinite into the
finite. It's very definition.
Almost you can't integrate
infinity into finite existence.
The only thing you can do is
integrate your finite existence
into infinity. You must
surrender to the infinite,
moment to moment, day to day,
opportunity to opportunity. You
must kind of become a servant of
the infinite, surrender
completely to that involutionary
process that Sri Aurobindo talks
about. And I think that, I mean,
I'm I'm a teacher. My natural
instinct is to learn and to
share. And the laws around
psychedelics interrupted my own
natural way of being in the
world. Now that I'm retired, now
that I've passed my statute of
limitations for my psychedelic
crimes, now that I can speak
about these things now that I
can those two different sides of
my life are coming together. And
really, for the first time in my
adult life, I feel like I'm
beginning to be a whole person
again, as I'm beginning to be a
whole person, something is
happening in my relationship,
within myself, in the universe,
and also something is happening
in my relationship with other
people, because the depth of the
consciousness which is alive in
me is also the depth of the
consciousness that's alive in
you. And so when we come
together, this deeper kind of,
you know, fluctuation surfaces
underneath both of us, and I
find this when I'm teaching and
when I'm working in workshops or
with groups. Which is a deeper
aliveness that in earlier years
I had to hold at bay, I had to
kind of tamp down. Now it's
beginning. Now I can let it come
through. Now it comes forward. I
don't know where this deeper
integration is going to go. I
don't know where it's going to
take me. It's taking me places
that I have not been before,
except in the sessions, but in
times of my physical
consciousness, my time space
consciousness, there is a
certain transparency that
catches me up, that's fresh, and
there is a certain wholeness
that arises when I'm with people
that is fresh and I don't know
where it's going to go another
20 years of this, it's I have no
idea where it's going to lead
me, but I like it. It feels
natural, and it feels like
integration is continuing to
take place. So I don't consider
myself finished with this
integration process at all.
Cool.
James Jesso: Well, thank you
very much for that, Chris and
thank you so much for this whole
conversation today. Me too, give
maybe you could end us off with
letting the listeners know where
they can find out more about
you, where they could get your
your I'm not sure if your
diamonds from Heaven is released
yet, but your three books what
their names are, as well as your
social media handles.
Chris Bache: Well, actually, my
website is still in the process
of being made, so can't go there
yet, but soon, diamonds from
heaven, the book that we've been
talking about will be released
from inner traditions in 2019
probably next summer, in this
it'll be in the second half of
2019 my three earlier books was
first life cycles, which is a
book on reincarnation research.
Second book was dark night,
early dawn, where I basically am
integrating psychedelic research
and incorporating my own
experiences with near death
episode research and out of body
research. So it's an extensive,
unfortunately kind of
academically dense, if rigorous
but dense discussion of some of
these issues. The third book is
called the living classroom. All
of these are available on
Amazon. The living classroom
basically is describing
something that was happening in
my classroom while I was doing
my psychedelic work in the
backside. I don't talk about
psychedelics there at all, but
it's about fields of
consciousness. It's about the
contagious nature of states of
consciousness. Because what I
found was that when I was doing
this work and keeping it private
from all my students,
nevertheless, some of my
students started to be activated
by my own work. And so I, you
know, it was like I began to
understand and have to work with
the contagious quality of states
of consciousness, and then
diamonds from heaven, is the
book just finished, where I
basically go back to the very
beginning and simply take people
through layer by layer, the
entire sequence of events,
because I found that you can't
even begin the philosophical
conversation about psychedelic
states, unless people, in this
case, editors of professional
journals and things, unless
they're convinced that these are
legitimate experiences. And the
only two ways to be convinced
that these are legitimate
experiences is to either have
the experiences yourself or to
be to undergo a secondary
initiation by reading other
people's accounts of their
experiences and kind of picking
up on it through kind of
osmosis, and that's what I'm
hoping that diamonds from
heaven. I don't think my
experiences are special or
unique in any way. They may have
pushed a little harder than some
people, but I think they fall
within the broad range of
experiences that people have.
I'm just trying to lay them out
in an organized fashion so that
people can become more familiar
with these states. And I hope,
maybe, hopefully, it'll, it'll
help people in their own
psychedelic work, but I also
hope it will be useful to people
who never take a psychedelic,
because it's what's important is
not the method, but what the
method teaches us about the
universe itself, and as a
philosopher, that's what my
interest in, is letting people
see the universe as the universe
showed it to me in these
sessions.
James Jesso: Yeah, beautiful.
Thanks. Thanks so much. Chris.
Are you on social media
anywhere?
Chris Bache: I'm on Facebook,
but I really, I'm not really
well grounded in social media.
I'll have my website up
hopefully within just a couple
of months, and I'll be
collecting, I mean, my talks are
scattered all over the web. You
know, if you Google me, you'll
come up with a whole bunch of
videos and talk. Books, but I
haven't consolidated them and
presented them in a in one
place.
James Jesso: Cool. Well, I will
make a little bit of an effort
to consolidate some stuff,
including links to all your
books where people can buy them,
and your website once it's live
at James W jesso.com under the
page that has the show notes to
this episode. Christopher, thank
you very much for being on the
show
Chris Bache: today, James, my
pleasure. It was a great
conversation. Really appreciate
your probing questions. Really
excellent.
James Jesso: And cut while Thank
you very much for tuning in to
that episode of adventures
through the mind. If you liked
it, please give it a share on
social media. Additionally, if
you are enjoying the show in the
larger body of content that you
access to the adventures through
the mind gateway, please
consider becoming a financial
supporter of the show by
becoming my patron on Patreon or
by leaving a one time PayPal or
cryptocurrency donation links to
doing so are contained in the
description to this Episode on
YouTube at James W gesso Comm,
or in the description can take,
I'm getting a bit lost in
whatever pod catcher you might
be listening to this on. Okay,
great, so that that finalizes us
up. Please follow me on social
media at James W gesso and I
will see you on the Next episode
of adventures through the mind.
Take care. You.
Unknown: You.