Marc Caron: Mark, Hello and good
afternoon. My name is Mark Kron.
I'm here with my co host for the
spirit plant medicine
conference, Steve, Mr. Steven
Gray, good friend. Glad to be
here. And today we have a very
special guest on our little talk
about our speakers for the
upcoming conference. We have Mr.
Chris Bache. Now. Chris is a
professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he
taught for 33 years. He is also
a junked faculty at the
California Institute of integral
studies and a fellow at the
Institute of Noetic Sciences.
He's an award winning teacher,
and Chris's work explores the
philosophical implications of
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, especially
psychedelic states. Chris has
also written three books. One is
called lifestyles. Another dark
night, sorry, life cycles, dark
night, early dawn and the living
classroom. And his new book is
LSD in the mind of the universe,
which is actually the title of
his talk as well for the
conference. Coming up in
actually a month tomorrow. We
start in four weeks. So welcome
Chris, pleasure to see you
again. Have a conversation. It's
always great to hear what you
have to say, and we look forward
to having you at the conference
again. But as we get started,
maybe you can introduce yourself
and let our viewers you know,
know a little bit about your
story and the work that you've
done in terms of, I think we're
just talking about, you know, 73
high dosage LSD journeys to as a
mind in the mind of a
psychologist or philosopher, if
I remember correctly, from last
Chris Bache: year. Yeah, well, I
was actually a professor of
religious studies, and I taught
in a philosophy of Religious
Studies program at the
University, which is part of the
Ohio State system, up in the
northeast corner of the state.
And I'm really excited about the
conference. I'm very, very
pleased that the book is
actually being released for the
first time anywhere at the
conference, and after all the
years of research and all the
years of writing, finally, it's
coming out and allowing me to
have a conversation that I've
been waiting to have for a long
time. Because basically, in
order to do psychedelic work
myself, to explore the
philosophical potential of
psychedelic states, I had to do
all this work underground, so it
was hidden from my colleagues. I
couldn't really talk about it.
I'm on my day job. I was a
conventional, you know, maybe
not so conventional, but I was a
religious studies professor.
None of my students knew about
my work. So this is a
conversation that I've been
waiting for a long time. I had
to wait until after I retired to
have it. I had to wait until
after I was passed the statute
of limitations for my
psychedelic crimes, and I've
been I'm just delighted to begin
this conversation here at the
conference and in the workshop
we'll do following The weekend
after the conference.
Stephen Gray: Great. Wow. Yeah.
So, oh gosh, you know, we could
all ask all kinds of questions.
Marc Caron: Just that
introduction gave me about 10 of
them right now,
Stephen Gray: why don't you fire
one out then mark, oh, I
Marc Caron: just, you know,
might not even be a question now
that I think about it. But the
big part that struck me there,
Chris was talking about how you
had to hide the work from your
colleagues, doing it
underground, and even the
consideration of the statue of
limitations running out before
you can talk about these things,
you know, it's a really
profoundly thought out process
in terms of What you had to deal
with, even to do your research,
so I wanted to acknowledge that.
And I guess the question is,
what was the biggest challenge
in terms of keeping it all kind
of contained into yourself?
Chris Bache: Well, I knew that
silence was going to be the
prerequisite that would allow me
to do this work, so I took that
responsibility when I did the
work, but over the long term, I
did not appreciate that. First
of all, the loneliness would
become the issue that it became
the kind of the inability to
share your experiences, the
inability to engage in
conversations like that. If I
lived in San Francisco, where
there's you know are in
Vancouver, where there's an
active psychedelic community. It
would have been different, but I
lived in Ohio, and so there
really wasn't an active
psychedelic community here to
share my experiences with and to
have the conversation. But I
found actually that in the long
term, after that, I'd finished
the work. I did this work. I did
73 high dose sessions between
1979 and 1999 and so I waited 20
years, you know, to write the
book, to tell the full story
I've written about, you know, my
story in dark night, early dawn,
but I really didn't tell the
full story until now. What I
found was that. So not being
able to talk about your
experiences actually inhibits or
compromises your ability to
fully integrate your experiences
into your life. So I was able to
integrate them at one level, at
a sort of a personal
psychological level, but I
wasn't able to integrate them
into my full person. I'm a
teacher. I love to learn
knowledge and to share that
knowledge with students. I could
not teach from these
experiences. I could not draw
upon the things I had learned,
and I found that that
cumulatively made me sick. It
literally kind of made me
psychologically sick, like
living in a closet is just
sickness making for anybody
whether keeping them in the
closet. So being in a
psychedelic closet was really
burden. And now that the first
level of the burden is off by
writing the book and going
public, and the second level has
been lifting, as I have begun to
talk about this material, and I
hope this will continue to
deepen in the years ahead, as I
have the give and take of
conversation.
Stephen Gray: Well, that's quite
understandable. Thank you for
sharing that with us. That was a
good question, I think, Mark.
But now let's talk about the
material itself.
Marc Caron: Even, can I make one
comment about that, because I
think it's a really important
part of what we're seeing in our
community here now as well,
especially in the past year
since the last conference, is
integration being the biggest,
you know, kind of buzzword now,
and you talked about that in
terms of your isolation and
being alone in that and how
important that is, and that's
what we're seeing in terms of
the community that we're
creating, and not even really
creating we're bringing people
together because, you know,
we're all out there. We're just
kind of, you know, pulling it
together, like hub. And so I
think it was really important
that you talk about that, and
that's the big part, is so
people can talk about their
experiences, which is a big part
of what our conference is.
Because it's not just for, you
know, doctors and practitioners,
naturopaths and things. It's for
people who are looking to, you
know, connect with people, so
they can actually share, talk
about their experiences and go
even deeper with their own work.
So thank you really for touching
on that, and I think it's really
important, especially
considering you know that 20
years of doing it in the closet,
Chris Bache: I think that I'm
really, really pleased to see
integration being discussed
more. There's an anthology
that's going to be coming out in
London within a year, all about
integration finding, of course,
with the technology that we have
with this, with the session
material and the sacred
medicines we have, we can blow
out the system, you know,
increasingly easy, but
integrating those experiences
and integrating, you know, we
can't stay in these states,
that's clear. But learning how
to live with the memories of
deep immersion in the universe,
using those memories skillfully
as part of your daily meditation
practice and your social
integration. That's really
important. And another aspect
for me has been I wrote the
living classroom because I found
that while my students never
learned about never knew about
my psychedelic work, they were
actually being activated by my
private work. You know, because
consciousness is not private,
it's an open field. And the
deeper I went, the more deeply
my students are being drawn
implicitly into my work. And
that's what really led me to
address this in dark and early
dawn, and then to write this
small book the living classroom
about fields of consciousness in
groups.
Stephen Gray: Well, I was going
to try to lead you into some of
the content of the material that
you learned. But as long as
we're on integration, maybe we
should follow up a little bit
more on that. So with this
question, what do you think are
the most important aspects of
integration for, you know,
typical person who's doing, say,
you know, couple of Ayahuasca,
two, three Ayahuasca session, or
weekends a year, or something
like that. Maybe working with
Psilocybin mushrooms a bit, and
then they're living in, you
know, Vancouver, you know, or
some urban center you know,
what. What do you think are the
most helpful things that those
people can do to make sure that
they try to keep that they keep
those channels open and keep
themselves grounded properly?
Chris Bache: Yeah, good
question. I mean, I don't think
I have a pat answer for that.
I'd like me more dialog around
it. But basically, the things
that spring to mind is, first in
your sessions, emphasizing clean
contact, controlling the
variables, controlling the
isolation, so that you have
clean contact with these
realities, not smudgy contract,
any confusion, clean contact,
and then first step is
remembering your session, so
writing up a detailed
description. Question within 24
hours, because these memories
fade over time. And then once,
personally, once I write up a
session, I never change it. I've
learned that trying to edit it,
clean it up, you can lose some
things. Yeah, and I actually
when I'm course, this is more
relevant, perhaps when you're
pushing way, way deep beyond
conventional reality. Just to
write a good session up, I
listen to the music that I
played during the session while
I'm writing up my account,
because it allows me to get
deeper into my memories and get
them down on paper. So I think
the other thing I think is
important is a daily spiritual
practice, whatever form, yoga,
meditation, rule of thumb is,
the deeper you're going into
Non-ordinary states, the
stronger should be your daily
practice. Well, that's a good
one. And then just, you know,
people use art to to bring their
sessions, hold on to their
sessions. For me, I've been
given lots of teachings in my
sessions, and I've been giving
meditation. I've been given
practices, so my responsibility
is to try to live by that
teaching as best I can, and to
cultivate those practices, to
actually do the assignments that
I was given. And then I think
sharing with other people is
really critical to to listen to
their experiences and to share
your experiences. That's is this
nothing that can replace that
Stephen Gray: wonderful so now,
can we get into some
Marc Caron: of the Steve, it's
your turn.
Stephen Gray: No, it's not that
wise. I'm not looking for my
turn. I'm looking for the
material. You know, it's
actually not about, it's not
about any of us, really.
Marc Caron: And that's I just
like having fun
Stephen Gray: with you, my
friend. That's all indeed, yeah.
So it's all good. Well, okay, so
from my point of view, you know,
you know, I've read this book,
and I've also read dark night,
early dawn, and what stands out
to me there's, there's so many
amazing things that that have
happened, that happened to you
during that 20 year period that
people would find stunning, like
the whole time when you, you
know, experienced all your past
lives, the time when they where
they grabbed you by the Ball, so
to speak, and made you become
like just about every different
kind of woman on the planet. But
the ultimate for from my point
of view, is is what most affects
everybody on this planet, which
is what you've called the Great
death and the Great Awakening.
And I wonder if you could
elaborate on that somewhat.
Chris Bache: Well, let me back
up just a little bit to give a
context, and then you bring me
back. If I don't get back to it
in time, you bring me back to
this, the birth of the future
human. Okay, yes, I found that
in when I was working with these
very high levels of LSD. And
again, this is a protocol that I
honestly, sincerely do not
recommend that people follow
doing individual high dose LSD
sessions is fine, but doing such
a relentless, long, really,
completely rigorous, nothing but
high dose LSD sessions is not
something that I would
recommend. I would balance high
dose, low dose. That balance
Psilocybin in Ayahuasca with
LSD, but I did this work
starting 40 years ago, so I
didn't understand it as well as
I understand now. Basically,
when by working with these very
high doses, you can blow open
consciousness and enter into a
deeper level of reality, go
through a Death-Rebirth process.
And what I found was that by
going back again and again and
again, not only does your
experience stabilize at this
deeper level of reality, but if
you keep going back and if you
keep pushing your own limits,
you will go through a
Death-Rebirth cycle again and
enter a deeper level of reality.
And if you keep pushing, you'll
go through another Death-Rebirth
and go through a deeper level of
reality. And it's not ego that
is simply dying over and over
again, but it does really become
a question, what is dying in
these advanced deaths and
rebirth? And I actually have an
appendix, which is in the book,
which is asking the question,
what dies? What's actually
dying? But when I was charting
the overall levels of the
development in my journey, I
identified five core fundamental
cycles of death and rebirth, and
this is something I'll be
talking about at the conference.
First was going beyond physical
identity, the death of self,
ego, death. The second was going
into collective mind, the ocean
of suffering and some of the
lower levels of subtle level
reality. The third level going
into archetypal mind, really
moving deep into archetype of
reality, both in terms of this
collective unconscious, the
species mind, and also into
cosmic, logical archetype of
reality. Fourth Level was going
into oneness, the fundamental
condition of oneness. And the
fifth level is what I call
diamond Luminosity. Going into
the diamond Luminosity, what
Buddhism calls Dharmakaya, or
the clear light of absolute
reality. So all of my sessions
kind of can fall into these
categories. And but then, while
there's this deepening process
and going into collective
dimensions, archetypal
dimensions, causal oneness, and
going into diamond Luminosity, I
began to have rhythmic,
systematic initiations into a
series of ideas that had to do
with the entire human species.
In fact, the entire trajectory
of my experiences were was not
personal. It really wasn't
primarily about my personal
healing or my personal
development or my personal
enlightenment. Everything seemed
to be converging around the
theme of humanity's collective
transformation, that seemed to
be the work of the hour. That's
what we're here for. That's what
we're about. We're at a life and
death moment for the species.
And my work and all of our work
seem to be part of this
convergence that's taking place
in history, taking us through
this transition that we're going
through. And this is what I came
to call the birth of the future
human, leaving it open ended,
what the form of this future
human will take. I have my own
experience of it and my own
theory of it, in a way. And I
think it is a combination of the
reincarnation project process it
will take us into a different
level of our species evolution.
It's a shift that takes place, I
think, at the fundamental
archetype of level of the core
blueprint of the human species,
we're really work doing some
work that's going to influence
and trigger a pivot in the
blueprint of the human psyche.
And I don't think we're going to
make this jump into this new
psychological awareness of the
heart and mind without going
through a tremendously painful
transformation process, the dark
night of our collective soul,
and which is essentially time of
purification, a time of letting
go of the past, a time of
basically coming to terms with
the choices we've been making
historically in the past, making
new choices, choices that do not
re force reinforce the stories
of Hate or stories of class
division, racial division,
religious division, the
nationalisms which tear our
planet apart, the economic
divisions which have done, which
cause so much damage, literally,
I think we have to consume the
karma that those choices have
brought us, and we've been
making those choices. I mean,
you know, we reincarnate
generation by generation. So
we're carrying the entire
history of the human planet, in
our history, in our souls, in
our stories. And as we change
those stories, we contribute to
a change in the in the playing
field of humanity. And so in my
work, I've been taken into that
process, gone through tremendous
exercises of purification and
healing, of the collective
psyche, of the war is that we've
fought and all the things,
terrible things we've done to
each other and have been taken
into what I Call deep time, into
dimensions of time where the
future becomes available,
becomes as available as the
present, and been given glimpses
into the culmination of this
death and rebirth process
experienced at a collective
level, and then the
transformation of our species
into this higher order of
humanity that's coming forward
that, to me, is the most
important theme of the
Stephen Gray: work, because,
yeah, all of us are involved,
all of our children, all of our
grandchildren. I think where
we're going with this is that
it's, you know, it's, I don't
know what the timeline is, but
you know, in some relatively
near future, it is going to be
clear to the whole planet that
this is job number one, as Ford.
Ford used to call it. So how
about this question related to
that? Then you know, you listed
off the kind of ways in which
the sort of human enterprises,
you know, off track. Work like
nationalism, racism, religion,
divisions, and perhaps, you
know, right up there at the top,
you know, materialist illusion
of that promotes 50 families
having half the the wealth on
the planet, or whatever that is.
So given that it appears that we
are as a species so far away,
you know, I mean, lots of people
are making inroads into the
transformation, of course, but
it's, you know, in total
numbers, out of 878, billion
people, it's a minuscule number
of people. So that, given that,
you know, 98 or 9% of the planet
is not getting, not even aware
of this possibility, let alone
doing anything to move in that
direction. What's what is it
going to take? It seems to me,
it's going to take terrible
disasters of some kind to open
up a crack. What do you think?
Chris Bache: How can we get as
far as we need to get in as
little time as we have, as the
global crisis triggers a cascade
of a series of economic,
political, social crises that
we're seeing.
Marc Caron: Not even mentioned
environmental, oh, yeah, yes,
yeah,
Chris Bache: I sort of, I don't
have any, any secret, any inside
information of the how, when and
why, of what's happening. You
know, just that we're going into
a global systems crisis, which
is being driven by global
ecological crisis and other
imbalances in the world. But
then, after years of being shown
this very, very positive,
optimistic fulfilling our
evolutionary destiny, it didn't.
It had never shown me how, how
could we possibly make this
transition? And you're asking
that question, Steven, exactly.
And then one particular session,
what I call the Great Awakening
session, session 55 took me into
that process and into this
trauma, and it also gave me a
set of teachings around how we
could actually how we will make
this transition, and it has to
do with understanding the
dynamics of the collective
psyche that all of our
individual psyches feed into and
are part of. We are fractal
embodiments of our collective
psyche and all of our
experience, as Rupert Sheldrake
talks about in Morphic field
theory, all of our experience is
being processed, collected and
processed at a collective level.
And we know something well. The
basic formula is this, our
collective psyche is a field.
Fields have behaved in certain
predictable ways. There's a
correlation between the way the
collective psychic field of
humanity will behave as it
enters into extreme crisis, and
the way in the future, and the
way that other physical systems
behave when they go into what
are called non linear systems
are far from equilibrium state.
The basic vision is this, when
we are go deeper into this
century. We are going to go into
a period of tremendous pain. I
mean, just, I don't see any way
around it. We're going to suffer
terribly. And in contrast to
anything that's happened before,
this pain will not be restricted
to one continent or one part.
It's going to be global. It's
going to be massive, and all of
this pain that we are going to
experience individually is going
to be feeding into the
collective psyche, so that the
collective psyche itself will be
moving into increasingly non
linear conditions when a field,
when the psychic field of
humanity, moves into these non
linear conditions, several if we
can extrapolate lessons from
physical fields, we can
hypothesize that several things
will be begin to happen. First,
small perturbations can produce
very large effects. So the
impact, or the effects of
individuals on the outcome of
history will increase good one
individual people can have a
larger trigger on the future.
Stephen Gray: Yeah, I could I
interrupt for a sec. I think I
understand what you mean by non
linear conditions, but perhaps
it needs a little more clear
clarification. Can you go into
that a wee bit more
Chris Bache: basically? And
here, I'm not a scientist, so my
apologies to those who really
could answer this question much
better. But basically, when you
have a system, it develops a
balance between energy in and
energy out. And if you keep
pouring more and more energy
into that system, it becomes
increasingly unstable. And when
it becomes unstable, it shows
characteristics which are not
like it was when it was a stable
system. When it becomes so
unstable, we find that in
nature, it can respond to this
instability to draw out new
levels of creativity out of
nature itself. So non linear
systems are highly creative
systems. They produce things
which we wouldn't have predicted
pre. Obviously, and it's fast.
Things changes can take place
very fast when they're in non
linear conditions. So it's just
and individuals can have
disproportionate effects on the
outcome in non linear
conditions. So technically, the
term would be in systems that
are in the far from equilibrium
state. Yeah. So creativity,
spontaneity, fast speed and
individuals having larger
influence, right?
Stephen Gray: So obviously,
that's a pretty scary, you know,
prognostication for the for the
decades coming. But it also
suggests that when you know
that, you know, as Leonard Cohen
said, there's a crack in
everything, that's how the light
gets. And so what might that
look like? You know? And I think
it might be useful for people
watching this to to imagine what
conditions or what the new human
might be like, so that we can
recognize the the inklings of
that awakening in ourselves. Can
you elaborate on that?
Chris Bache: Yeah, let's remind
ourselves that the human beings
that this will be happening to
are 1000s and 10s of 1000s of
years old, because we're it will
be happening to souls in human
bodies, not simply 200 year
beings, but 100,000 year old
beings who have this very
complex psychic history of their
former lives, all kind of
flowing within them as they as
they enter into time. So my
understanding of what has come
through my sessions repeatedly
is that, as without, so within,
so what is happening on the
planet, at the geopolitical
level, at the geophysical level,
as we are trying to become an
integrated planet and get past
this stage of evolution where we
are so fractured and divided, as
we are confronting our history
geopolitically, we are also
confronting our history inside
the history of the soul, and the
fragmentations within the soul.
And the sessions have shown me,
taught me that there seems to be
a synergistic relationship
between engaging a changing
world outside of us as we work
to create a future that is
fundamentally different than the
past, and a maturation which is
taking place where we kind of
integrate our former lives in a
way that leads to an arising of
an awareness that is an
intuitive and immediately
experienced awareness that my
mind And my heart are not the
age of my body. My mind and my
heart are much older than my
body and my relationships are
much older than my present
body's relationships. I am
living in time as time as a
manifestation of creative
energy. Everyone around me is
doing this. We've been doing it
for generations. I think that
what we're witnessing the only
way put it a different way, the
ego created this global crisis.
The ego cannot solve it. Soul is
the only thing that can solve
it. I think we're making a
transition from ego
consciousness, individual body
mind consciousness, to soul
consciousness. And by soul
consciousness, I don't mean
simply a disembodied ego. I mean
what I call the diamond soul all
of our history integrated in a
way that generates a higher
level of functioning, so that we
begin to live out of a larger
platform. And I think we can see
this happening around us when
people take up projects that
they know they won't finish in
their lifetime, when they are
willing to die so that others
can live when they when they
just when their commitments are
not to their own individual
private enhancement, but to the
enhancement of larger numbers of
people. I think what we're
seeing is the soul. Those are
the symptoms of the soul
emerging in our psychological
awareness. We just don't know
what to call it. We just think,
Oh, this is a great being. This
is a Gandhi. This is a Martin
Luther King. But really, what
we're seeing is the maturation
of the soul within our
individual lives.
Stephen Gray: And do you think,
go ahead? Do you see a lot of
that happening?
Chris Bache: Well, just look
around us, because there are a
lot of people doing a lot of
injurious things, but there are
a lot of people doing some
magnificent things. You know,
they are committing themselves
to projects that they'll never
see realized in their lifetime.
And I think we're going to see
more and more of that as we
really come to terms with the
fact that the way we're living
just isn't working. You know,
the way we've organized our
culture isn't working. We need
to be experimenting with new and
different ways of creating an
economy, creating social,
family, so on, so forth. I think
now, here's the thing. It. It's
there's no guarantees in
evolution, right? There's no
guarantee that we're going to
come through this. There's no
guarantee that the next form of
the human being will be born
successfully. But the more we
experience the intelligence of
the universe when we work in our
sessions, the more we experience
the profound wisdom that's
behind the formation of galaxies
and the formation of solar
systems and the emergence of
light, that intelligence seems
to think that humanity is ready
for this transition. Gestation
is a long process, right? But
birth is very short, very fast
and convulsive. I think we have
been maturing through 1000s and
1000s of years. The soul has
been now Nature says it's time
to give birth to the to the soul
inside history, not just when we
die inside history. This is hard
work. This is what we're coming
into. I think
Stephen Gray: what a beautiful
vision. It's, you know, you
know, it's this idea of, you
know, having a vision and having
hope that's going to kind of
keep people going. I think, as
things collapse that way, I'm
just curious. It may not even be
all that relevant to the
discussion at hand, but I want
to ask you anyway, I, you know,
I gather from reading, you know,
the books that the teachings you
are receiving are about humanity
and about our journey. But you
know, just what you can see with
the naked eye, there are many,
many 1000s of bodies that are
much like our Sun, produce heat
and light. Did you ever get a
sense that there are other
planets, other species that have
that are going through similar
things, or have been through
them and have successfully come
through them, or any of that
sort of thing.
Chris Bache: You know, I've
never explored that particular
aspect of things, or it was
never put in front of me. I
mean, I never directed my
sessions. I've I tried to set
intentions, but a deeper
intelligence did all the lay all
the groundwork for what
happened? And essentially, it
never took me there, but it was
just the very nature of the
experiences that it took me
into. It was just assumed that
we are one speck in a much
larger, cosmic, logical process
with life emerging, life and
life and life and galaxies all
over the place that we are
incubating something taking
place on this planet, but it
parallels things which are
taking place elsewhere, because
nature is just vast, and it
works. It works in groups. You
know, it's evolved. You know,
these are the dynamics of
evolution. So to me, I just
assume, when I look up in the
night, tie in the sky and I see
all those stars, I just assume
that somewhere there, there is
life percolating and struggling
at all sorts of different levels
around the universe,
Stephen Gray: switching tax a
little. There's a segment of the
psychedelic community that's
very devoted to natural plants.
You know, the core of your work
was with a semi synthetic
substance. LSD, what? What's
your take on that? What do you
say to those people that say,
you know nature knows best?
Chris Bache: Somehow, I think
nature does know best in many
ways. I mean, I think natural
plants are very good plants to
work with, good ways to work.
Most of human history has taken
it been in dialog with natural,
sacred medicines. I don't think
to me to make too much of the
difference between a synthetic,
meaning a man made human, made
medicine and an organic
medicine. I don't know that I
would put quite the emphasis on
that that some people do. I do
think that around any work with
a medicine with any regularly
induced state of consciousness,
fields develop, so that there
are fields around Psilocybin
mushrooms, you know, psychic
fields that reflect humanity's
history with them. There are
fields around Ayahuasca. I think
maybe that's why people who have
never lived in the Amazon and
are doing Ayahuasca and Texas,
they encounter these giant
snakes in their first session.
It's somehow, there's a field
around these medicines. And so
when we open our mind, we don't
simply open our mind. We open up
through these fields, into these
fields, and they speak to us.
Now, LSD has a it doesn't have a
historical field associated with
it. You know, a few years in the
60s, it's nothing compared to
the fields associated with
Ayahuasca or or Mescaline, or
Peyote, so it's relatively Feel
free, and I think it has, of
course, it also tends to be a
high altitude psychedelic. So
many of the organic psychedelics
are much more sensitively tuned
to the nearby psychedelic world,
which. It's a very helpful and
relevant psychedelic world, the
world of spirit guides, the
world of Animal Collective
psyches of angelic figures, so
on and so forth. LSD tends to be
somewhat neutral. It doesn't
have a lot of history, and it
tends to drive into the high at
high levels. It tends to drive
into high cosmic, logical
territory. So I think it's good
for giving at least for me, I
think I I drilled a deep
borehole in the universe, and it
gave me a lot of overview, but
it didn't give me a lot of
experience up close with the
nearby territory that is
explored, and I've experienced
in Ayahuasca sessions or in
Psilocybin sessions that I did
after I completed my LSD work.
Stephen Gray: So you found those
to be a good adjunct. For you,
Chris Bache: they have been a
good adjunct. And I wish that I
hadn't been smart enough to be
using those adjuncts all the way
along during those 20 years. And
Marc Caron: that was my question
for you, Chris, is, what was it
that made to choose LSD in 1979
when you did, versus, say, the
magic mushroom back then?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, it's I
read Stan Grof work. You know
Stan Grof published realms of
the human unconscious in 1976 I
came out of graduate school in
78 I read that book, and very
quickly, LSD psychotherapy,
which came out in 1980 and this
is what Stan had done his early
research work on this was the
material. And in my case, I was
able to find a way to get high
quality, you know, laboratory
grade, LSD. And so it was a
combination of, I trusted Stan
grofs work his methodology was
really around LSD in the early
years, and it was only because
of his research that I trusted
my own mind into going through
this process, and it was the
substance that was available to
me.
Stephen Gray: What about what's
your take on five Meo, DMT, it's
becoming more and more popular,
and I think it needs to be
discussed more. Let me just put
it this way. I was on a panel
discussion on psychedelics and
their role in the future. Last
weekend at a small conference
here, and they we broke up into
groups, and the panelists were
asked to sit in with some of
these groups. And one of the
people in the little group I was
in said, You know her, her view
of psychedelic she'd, I think
she'd had a couple of
experiences with them, was she
thought they were a door that
shouldn't be opened. So I say
that in the context of five Meo
DMT, because I've had one full
on experience with it. And I
mean, it was absolutely stunning
at the moment, where I just
went, oh my god, this is what
I've been waiting to realize at
the gut level my whole life, but
since then, that's like three
months ago. I really have no
idea how that it's informing my
ongoing spiritual awakening
journey. So I don't know where
that fits into the Pantheon, as
it were, I don't do you have any
feelings thoughts about that?
Chris Bache: First of all, I
don't have a lot of experience
with five Meo DMT. I've only
done a couple of sessions. They
were ecstatically wonderful
sessions. They were luminous
sessions. I did this years after
doing the LSD work. So the mind
I brought to the to the five Meo
DMT experience, it's not the
mind that I had in the beginning
of my LSD work. It was the mind
that had been polished and
curated over all the years of
that work. So I yield, really,
to people who have more
experience with this substance
in the discussion, it is
striking how fast it can drop
you deep, deep into the
universe, but the speed within
it dropped within the speed with
which it drops you in, deep into
the universe, and your time
there is so short, and then
you're back, it makes
integration or healing, or it's
better for opening doors than it
is for really deeply
internalizing the experiences
that you've you've opened into,
which doesn't mean it's a bad
thing. I mean opening doors and
letting in the brush of fresh
air can be very helpful. But
there's something. One thing I
have learned about LSD, of
course, it's a long day, it's a
big commitment. It commits you
to a day before, at least all
day session, and a day after,
and on the day of a session,
it's an eight hour commitment.
And you know, usually about five
or six or seven hours you'd
like, Oh, come on. Now, let's
get this over. I'm ready to come
back. But one of the things that
it does is, by keeping you in
these states for long periods of
time, it allows the mind. Mind
that you are exploring to polish
the mind that is doing the
exploring. Because in this work,
you're always using the mind to
explore mind. So the length of
time that you expend gives the
universe more time to heal you.
It gives the universe more time
to show you things, to teach you
things, and it teaches me things
over and over and over again. It
really repeatedly will teach me
something until it's sure that
I've got it, and it'll keep this
up for several sessions in a
row. So I think there is a
certain polishing that takes
place in long sacred medicines
that doesn't take place in short
acting sacred medicines. Again,
that doesn't mean the short
acting sacred medicines are not
useful and they're not good.
It's just that it's different,
the Native American traditions,
the Brazilian traditions, they
have preferred, in many cases,
the longer acting sessions.
Peyote is longer acting.
Ayahuasca is longer acting. The
Psilocybin mushroom is not as
long as LSD, but it's a longer
acting substance. They consider
the length of time that we spend
in these conditions to be
special and sacred, you know.
And also, Rick Strassman, when
he was doing his work on five on
DMT, not five Meo DMT, but on
DMT, he was surprised to find
that while people had very deep
experiences in their five their
DMT session, he found that it
didn't really produce long
lasting results for the majority
of them. So it's something about
quick in, quick out, hard to
really convert that into a
transformational experience. I
can
Marc Caron: certainly, you know,
agree with, with that statement,
and kind of what you're talking
about Steven and the five Meo
with just the DMT. I was like,
it was, it was an experience,
all right. But I was like, okay,
so how does that? What's I
couldn't nail any kind of like
spiritual experience or
mysticism? Well, there's
certainly mysticism. I guess
that's not the word, but it was,
you know, it left me with more
questions, because what I saw
was just really, what was that?
What does it all these
hieroglyphics and things that I
was seeing and what his work I
trusted my DNA, and, you know,
my soul and spirit were getting
it all. But I was like, I still
look back at it
Stephen Gray: and go, what was
that? You know? So, yeah, that
brings up another related
question. I think this, like, I
don't know if this is quite an
exact, accurate assessment or,
you know, description, of the
journeys that you went on. But
the way I remember it correct
me, if I'm not quite getting the
exact nuance here, was that you
you had that you said there were
two parts to every journey.
First two hours or so, was a lot
of letting go. Sometimes, I
think I remember you use the
term exquisitely painful, before
you broke out into the living
intelligence of the universe. I
if I may say so, I think you're
perhaps unusual in that sense,
in that you were suited, perhaps
from your past, you know, lives
or whatever, your destiny, so to
speak, karma, in this lifetime,
to go to these places, but I and
correct me if I'm wrong. But I
think the majority of the you
know Psychonauts, as it were,
you know, the people that we're
going to be talking to at the
conference and so on, are not
likely to go there. And it's
more about having to get
ourselves out of our own way,
the healing that we need to do.
So, you know, do you have some
thoughts on that? You know,
where that's at for most people?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, I think
basically what I understand now
at the end is different than
what I understood at the
beginning, and it leads me to
approach working with
Non-ordinary states differently.
Now, I'm kind of much more
patient with the slow, gradual
developmental process, rather
than trying to accelerate the
process so far, because I
thought in my early in my work,
I thought, ah, the The goal was
to get someplace. I'd get to an
end destination. I'd get to
home. I'd go home, or become one
with God, or I dissolve into the
primordial void. And I had all
of those experiences, but what I
found was they didn't have as
long, lasting a penetrating
transformation on my person as I
thought they might in the
beginning. And I also found when
I went as deep as I ever went
into the diamond Luminosity, I
found that what I initially had
felt like after. Absolute
homecoming, the sweetest, most,
totally soul satisfying
homecoming. In that moment, I
was shown given a series of
experiences that showed me that
there is an infinite territory
beyond where I was, so that the
idea of getting to the end of a
journey was just I let it go. It
didn't work anymore. So now,
instead of trying to reach some
spiritually defined definition
or end state of enlightenment or
nirvana or oneness with God, now
I feel much more patient with
opening up, taking what's given
to you, healing, receive the
teaching, but keeping it within
a measure that's kind of more
practical, so that there may
come time when you want to go up
Periscope, you know, take a deep
look around. But a lot of the
really productive work, I think,
is done at a lower level, we
don't have to tear apart our
psyche as deeply as I did, or
other people do sometimes in
order to really remember who we
are, remember what's happening
in history. So I guess I would
counsel a gentler approach into
these things.
Stephen Gray: Good one. Yeah,
Chris Bache: now, as a
philosopher who had a deep
passion to understand how the
work world was put together, you
know that part of me, I wouldn't
trade this 73 days for anything
on earth. I mean, they just they
gave me an understanding of how
the world works, which has
changed my heart, changed my
life, yeah, and you know,
Stephen Gray: but and your work
for this, for this lifetime,
too, to share that right? So on
this notion of going gentler,
maybe you could share with
people a little bit about what
you hope to accomplish, or what
you hope people might walk away
with at the end of the workshop
you're going to do on the
following weekend after the
conference.
Chris Bache: You know, I really
don't know yet. I know what I've
experienced. I know what's
living inside me as living
memories. I'm trying to figure
out how I can make these useful
to other people. I know that
they're things that I know and
they're things that I
understand. I know that when I
begin to get into the memory of
these events, when I begin to
describe them or that they get
activated within me. I know that
my consciousness changes just in
the talking about them. I'm
still trying to figure out how I
can make this this living
experience, which is only mine
in a certain way. It's I didn't
give myself these experiences.
The Universe poured these
experiences in me. How can I
make these available to people
or whatever? Maybe it's not
making them available. How can I
be of use to people in their own
spiritual practice? Given the
history that I've gone through,
I'm now that I'm getting to do
the workshops. That's what I
want to explore. I want to
explore, for example, when we're
Can we go into guided
visualization exercises? When
people go kind of into deep
relaxation, or kind of a semi
hypnotic state. Can I work with
them in a way which will allow
them to enter more deeply into
their own inner being? Because
I've explored some of these
dimensions of my own inner
being, and therefore I have a
certain sense of some of the
ways maps can be drawn. Can I
convert that into something that
will be useful to people as they
explore their own inner being?
Stephen Gray: So, just so that
people understand who might be
interested in coming to this,
it's not going to be Chris Bache
yacking at you for two days,
right? You're going to do a lot
of exercises with people. But
what I what I sense from what
you're saying, and I, you know,
I have one
Marc Caron: thing, Steven, we're
not doing. LSD,
Stephen Gray: yeah, no, of
course not. No, no, no, no,
Unknown: but not doing anything,
any short, acting, nothing
there, yeah.
Stephen Gray: But you what I
hear you saying, and I I accept
it 100% because I know that you
know you're saying it from a
point, a place of humility. Is
that your energetic field, from
what you've accumulated in your
learning, could have an
influence energetically on the
room while they're doing that?
Is that a correct way of putting
it,
Chris Bache: I think so. I mean,
basically, this is what happened
with my students. What I wrote
about in the living classroom,
my so called individual,
experiencing my deeper
consciousness, with the larger
consciousness the mind of the
universe, had an effect on my
students, which was a.
Combination of healing and
liberating and kind of causing
them to face things in their
life that they may not were
initially wanting to face, but
when they did, it had a very
beneficial outcome. So that I
know that my being and their
beings are interconnected in
these very, very subtle ways. So
I would think that something
similar happens whenever people
gather in groups with a shared
intention, and they're engaged
in meaningful exercises which
everyone kind of chooses to
participate in, that our
energies interacts. Their energy
comes into me, my energy flows
into them, and the question then
becomes, well, what can we do
with our shared intention? How
deeply can we take this? What
insights can we, you know,
trigger and what healing I find
that when I teach in workshops,
people, the healings take place
without me intentionally doing
it or doing anything. It's just
when we get together, we open
our hearts and minds, things
happen
Stephen Gray: beautiful, you
know, just from the Department
of wild ideas, so to speak. Have
you ever considered doing
something like this with, say, a
very light dose of a psychedelic
to amplify or potentially deepen
that collective possibility
there.
Chris Bache: Well, that, of
course, is the way shamans
typically work. Will often work
their client or subject will be
using a sacred medicine, and
they will use the same sacred
medicine, perhaps a lighter
dose, to go into these states
together. That's, of course,
there's so much history behind
it, we know that that works.
Well, I've never done that.
First, I don't, I don't. I have
chosen not to be a therapist,
not to sort of work with people
going into psychedelic states.
That was a conscious choice on
my part. That's a different
skill set. You know, I'm
comfortable there, but I've
chosen to push my own limits
rather than help people push
their limits. But as a teacher
now, this is something different
when, because just opening our
minds and our hearts to these
Horizons has a very powerful
impact. I find now there may
come a time when I would do what
you're suggesting, that time is
not now. Now my time is to sort
of get the ideas out, to engage
in the psychedelic circle and
see where our discussion and
exercises can take us. And also
I, at the end of this work, I
don't want to go too deeply into
this, but basically at the end
of my work, there were energies
that were moving deeper and
deeper into my physical body,
into my psychological body, and
then deeper internalization
process. And I realized at the
end of my work that in order to
let this process mature and
complete itself, I had to not
alter my consciousness. I had to
not amplify it. I had to sit
still and let these energies
come into me rather than go out
to meet them.
Stephen Gray: You talked about
even having to stop using
cannabis for that reason, didn't
you? Well,
Chris Bache: a little bit
different with the cannabis. But
when I let me back up and tell a
different story around that when
I stopped my sessions in 99 I
had been given so many gifts,
and there were so many treasures
that I had been given. I thought
that stopping my sessions would
be a pretty straightforward
process. I could just stop, and
I would be able to remember and
be nurtured by these many
wonderful experiences. But what
I found was that it was more
complicated than that. What I
found is that I had entered so
deeply and so intimately into
dimensions of the Universe and
dimensions of the Divine. You
know that when I stepped back
into time, space, consciousness,
and I knew that I was my
journey, my psychedelic journey,
was heads over at least this
part of my journey was over.
Over the years, I entered into a
very kind of deep existential
sadness. I was literally
suffering from withdrawal of the
Divine, from the Divine. I just
I knew I would never have the
type of ecstatic joy that I had
had in my deepest sessions,
where coming light transformed
there, and I I got developed an
over attachment to marijuana
during this period, because I
was kind of self medicating, and
the marijuana allowed me to kind
of stay a little bit above the
earth and not come completely
off the mountain. And.
Eventually I had to address that
and to give that up in order to
come completely off the ground,
off the mountain, to get
completely grounded in time
space, in order to continue the
integration process that had
been taking place inside the
sessions themselves. So my work,
a lot of my work, and it's not
that I never touch it, or I
don't do psychedelics at all,
but my work is primarily a
contemplative work now, and one
of the things I'm experimenting
with is how to build, how to
take classical spiritual
practice, which for me, come out
of the Vadnais tradition, some
of these classic, you know,
deity exercises, Guru Yoga
exercises, meditation,
contemplation exercises, how to
empower those by drawing upon my
memories of these specific
states of consciousness which
are relevant to these outcomes.
So it's trying to develop forms
of spiritual practice which
consciously integrate
psychedelic experience without
trying to replicate
Stephen Gray: them. Sounds like
a good sort of long term plan
for people heading toward
eldership. Hey, Mark, it's been
an hour or more. What do you
think should
Marc Caron: we we're pretty much
ready to wrap it up. It's almost
an hour, because I feel like we
can dig in and go deep every
time we speak with you, Chris.
And of course, we want to leave
something for the guys who and
gals who come to the conference,
of course, and for the two day
workshop, which is the place to
really go into the deep dive,
but I just love so much of what
you shared today. There's some
things that really stuck with
me, and one was just about
gestation, birth and
convulsions. It really, really
kind of struck a chord with
what's kind of happening in the
future, as well as just some of
your other, you know, brilliant
insights in terms of your work.
So I personally thank you for
that, and I look forward to
meeting you again this year at
the conference. I don't know,
Steven, you got something else
you want to, you know, rabbit
hole you want to go down?
Stephen Gray: No, absolutely
not. No. I mean, that's a long
discussion, and a lot of great
stuff came out. I hope for
people. I just hope a lot of
people see this and then come
and see, you know, come to the
conference, if they're not
already, you know, signed up to
do that, and are you gonna do
your little FBl, 33 thing today?
Mark,
Marc Caron: you just did it.
Steve,
Stephen Gray: better explain
what it is. Then
Marc Caron: it's, no, it's no
it's not like some five Meo or
anything. FPL, 33 for anybody
watching this, or, you know,
wanting to come to the
conference, since the prices are
up, at regular price, it's just
a discount that we're offering
you for watching the video and
being part of our community,
being curious, looking for
answers, being on the path. And
yeah. So FBl, 33 is something
there for you there. And we're
just always happy to connect
with you. Chris. I look forward
to another great weekend,
another great VIP party. We look
forward to that one too. We had
a good time. We
Chris Bache: had a good time.
And I just, I'm really honored,
and looking forward to coming
back to Vancouver, coming into
the conference when I was there
last time, I had just finished
writing the book end stages, and
that was all about the book
that's going to come. And now
the book is out. The book will
be available in Vancouver for
the first time, and I'm just so
pleased to be able to bring it
to this particular audience,
because I was so moved by all
the participants in last year's
conference and the excellent
speakers that you had gathered.
It's a real, living vitality,
vital, vital community that
you've created there. It's just
a pleasure and an honor to be
back
Stephen Gray: there. Wonderful.
Hey, Mark, before we go, though,
maybe you should just say a wee
bit more about this workshop
that Chris is going to be doing,
because it sounds like it's
going to be amazing to me. I
actually can't go myself, or I
would definitely go.
Marc Caron: I'm going to post it
in the comments of this
interview, this conversation,
but it's really a talk on this
book, and Chris can tell us more
about the event, but it's going
to be on the Hang on. Let me
just pull up the date Chicago. I
Stephen Gray: think he already
explained it. I'm thinking more
they can get tickets and
whatnot.
Marc Caron: Put that link out
here, because it's right here. I
just didn't have it at my ready.
Stephen Gray: Sure.
Chris Bache: It's going to be
the Friday and Saturday, the
weekend after the conference,
and it's going to be two full
days with a meal provided, I
think, right, yep, lunches,
yeah, so it's going to lunches.
It's going to be an opportunity
to really settle down and sink
deep into the mystery, into this
material. But it's also it's a
dialog. It's about sharing our
experiences and processing them
together. And it's. Exploring
different exercises so that we
can not just absorb these ideas
intellectually, but absorb them
in our hearts and
psychologically into our souls.
Wonderful. I'm really looking
forward to it. It's a new it's a
new adventure for me, and I
think it's going to be a lot of
fun. Great.
Marc Caron: I've just shared it
in the comment section on on the
Facebook feed. So for anybody
interested, they can find it
there. It's on the spirit plant
medicine website, conscious
living Network website, it is
all out there. And it's in some
promotional materials and emails
going out with our pre and post
conference events as we get
geared up for a month leading up
to the conference, it's going to
be go time. It's kind of what
makes me thrive and go a little
crazy. And I enjoy the pressure
because it's the pressure seems
to be what it takes to get
things done for me. Thank God
for a deadline.
Stephen Gray: Yeah, you know,
and Mark deserves an immense
amount of credit, because you're
working really hard at this
mark.
Unknown: Yeah, there's a
conference like this.
Marc Caron: I'm just enjoying
the process learning new things
every time, because there's a
lot of, you know, moving parts.
And also, it's like Steve Steven
says to me today, you got that
on your list mark, and I go
list. I'm supposed to have a
list. Oh, no. So, yeah, it's
it's go time. We're four weeks
away, four weeks away tomorrow.
So anybody out there want to
come? Happy to have you there.
And we're looking to be a sold
out crowd. There might be one
day tickets available, but,
yeah, happy to see it all happen
for the ninth year. Thank you,
Chris again, for for being part
of it, a second year in a row.
My pleasure, awesome, Steven.
It's never a day without my fix
of Stephen Gray, so that's it
today. And thank you everyone
for watching any questions. You
can always comment, message us
and connect through our many
different social media feeds. So
thank you very much, and take
care of yourselves out there,
Happy journey.