Unknown: There is a door in your
head that no one told you about.
It is the door through which we
enter into life and pass out of
life again.
It is the door which separates
ordinary consciousness from
genius. It is the door that
separates time bound mind from
timeless mind, the door that
leads from Personal
consciousness to cosmic
consciousness, the mysterious
cultures that existed at the
very beginning of recorded
history, whose cultural and
technical accomplishments
demonstrate an almost
unfathomable genius took special
care to immortalize the
instructions that enable each
individual to access their own
hidden door. Ch,
you. Thank you so much, Chris
for being with us today. I
really appreciate you taking the
time to share this amazing
information with people. I want
to say that your book has been
one of the most revelatory that
I've read ever and the
information contained within it.
Sorry, darling.
I'm touched.
I'm touched honestly. I mean, I
think it is so interesting and
also so helpful to us at this
particular time. There's so much
in there that will help us guide
our way into the future. So I
really appreciate that the book
is a very interesting read in
that it is filled with a lot of
pain and a lot of suffering and
ecstasies beyond ecstasies, and
what I would like to do today,
because there are, for other
people's edification, several
interviews with you out there
where you go into the protocols
and the process. So if people
are interested in understanding
exactly how you obtain this
information, they can a buy this
amazing book and also view those
other interviews. So today, what
I'd like to do is focus on the
content of the journeys and the
teachings that you came to came
to you. Now, I think we'll start
with the worst of it, which you
have called the ocean of
suffering, and you have sessions
in well, let's step back for a
second. You undertook 73 LSD
sessions to obtain this
information. And the book
Chris Bache: goes 79 and 1999
over 20 year period, I did 73
high dose sessions. Actually it
was three medium dose sessions
and 70 high dose but for
convenience, 73 high dose
Unknown: sessions, that is an
undertaking following the
Chris Bache: protocols
established by Stan Grof. So
these were internalized
sessions, so on, so forth,
eyeshades, headphones, sitter,
you know, the whole nine yards.
Unknown: Would you consider that
a clinical setting per se, or a
shamanistic setting, or just
following the protocols that
Stan the Grof actually
developed. Well,
Chris Bache: they were, they
merged in a clinical setting.
But whether you call it clinical
or shamanistic, sort of depends
partly on your cultural
perspective, on your cultural
context. There were clinical in
the sense of they originated in
that therapeutic context, but
they went far beyond therapeutic
applications or therapeutic
impact, and in that sense, it's
not clinical per se, absolutely.
Unknown: That makes sense. All
right, ocean of suffering
sessions 11 through 17,
Chris Bache: yeah, but what had
happened was, in the first two
and a half years, I went through
kind of classic perinatal
symptomology, perinatal that
Stan de Grof Grof describes in
many of his books, and I went
through at the end of the kind
of a shattering ego death
experience. It just kind of blew
me apart. Turned me inside out.
And then after that, a whole new
cycle began, a cycle that lasted
two years of 14 sessions, where
in the purifying phase of the
session, which usually for me,
means the first half of the
session, during the purifying
phase of the session, I went
into vast landscapes, panoramas
of human suffering that went
progressively deeper and deeper
session by session. And at first
I thought this was a deepening
of ego death. But over time, I
became convinced that this was
more than that. It had to be
more than that, because it
involved subjectively, so many
1000s of people and so many
1000s of years, eventually, I
came to the conclusion that
something had shifted inside my
sessions, and the consciousness
that was directing my sessions
was using my sessions to heal
not my personal psyche, but some
aspect of the collective
unconscious of humanity. And so
what happened was I did this
work for a year, I stopped my
work for six years, and then I
began it again after six years,
for another year, the ocean of
suffering, when I resumed after
six years, began exactly where I
had stopped, I think is an
indication of the extra ordinary
intelligence and the precision
of that intelligence that's
directing these arts in our you
know, in our session work.
Unknown: Well, that brings up a
point that I do want to address
with you, and that is the fact
that these sessions seem very
well planned, very well thought
out. They're not haphazard
trips, as people can experience
when doing hallucinogens. And so
tell me a little bit about who
was doing the planning and who
was doing the organizing of
these 73 sessions that took you
on this extra ordinary journey.
Chris Bache: It certainly wasn't
me. I was never in control of
what happened in my sessions.
You can set when you're working.
I worked at 500 to 600
micrograms per sessions of very
high doses of LSD. I don't
recommend this protocol. I
honestly don't knowing what I
know now, but when you do this
work, you can set all the
intentions you want. You can't
direct what's happening in your
sessions. So I think of it as a
collaboration, a cooperation. My
responsibility was to create as
clean a field as possible to
allow clear contact, so totally
isolated from the world, totally
internally focused, and at the
end of every session, writing a
detailed transcript of what
happened during the sessions. I
think that's important, because
it really helps us learn and
hold on to what happened, and
then it provides a clearer
foundation when we return to the
psychedelic state in the next
session. So after I'd done that,
after I clear the set, I focused
myself, did everything I could
to establish a clean contact.
After that, what happened in the
sessions is entirely a matter of
a larger consciousness that was
directing my experiences, or
organizing my experiences. And I
think this went far beyond
anything in my personal
unconscious. Because, you know,
the scale of the sessions are
just far faster than anything I
could dream up or imagine on my
own. So I have to place the
organization that's in the hands
of the universe.
Unknown: Absolutely, it's just
such a for somebody that hasn't
been on this journey, an
inconceivable idea. And we'll
get the little bit further on to
some of the communications that
you actually had, the
interactivity and almost the
discussions, or the dialogs that
you had with this consciousness,
which fascinated me. But for a
moment, I'm going to go back to
the ocean of suffering, just
because some of the words you
use to describe that period. So
session 11, trapped in a chamber
of horrors. Session 12, I was
killed, mauled, maimed. Session
13, reminded of Dante's Inferno.
Session 14, crescendo of torture
and session 15, excruciating
pain and unspeakable heart. So
the first thing is, why did you
continue?
Chris Bache: Well, it's because
of what happened at the in the
second half of the sessions,
first half of the sessions, I
was taken into this terrible
pain and suffering, and in this
when I would go through that,
and one of the most profound
lessons I learned from Stan Grof
is to completely trust the
process. So if you don't fight
what's happening, if you give
yourself over to it completely,
it will build and build, you'll
hit a crescendo and. If you
navigate this crescendo, well,
you will be spun into positive,
Transpersonal spaces for the
remainder of the session. So
these sessions were not just
ocean of suffering, but they
were the ocean of suffering in
the first hour or two, and then
I would be spun into this extra
ordinary series of experiences
I've described in deep time, in
the soul and the initiation in
the universe, so that at the end
of the session, what I would
internalize was a phase of its
intense suffering and then hours
of ecstatic participation in
some aspect of the universe
itself. So I would go back to
it, because I wanted that
initiation into the universe,
Unknown: absolutely, it just
sounds like such a space of
torment. And I spent a lot of
time thinking about the
suffering. And when I first
started reading the book, you
explain you in session 24
actually, you get a little bit
more deep into the cause or the
purpose of the suffering. And
you speak about this
consciousness, being a
consciousness of incredible love
overall. And and you say the
pain had begun in love, and I
was shown that the pain sorry
did not represent a rupturing of
love, but itself was an
expression of this love being
born into space time, even the
very birth of space time itself
was an expression of unshakable
love. And so what I'd like to do
is just understand that a little
bit more, how does all this
torrential pain come from love.
Chris Bache: Well, because
creation comes from love. And I
think the pain that I was
encountering here was the pain
that is somehow lodged in the
collective psyche, the pain of
human suffering over 1000s and
1000s of years, all the wars,
all the terrible things we've
done to each other, all the
rapes, all the brutality, all
this terrible suffering. And if
the suffering is not cleared at
the end of an individual life,
it's not only the individual who
has to bear the consequences of
that undigested pain, but the
species itself, the species
mind, this the collective
unconscious of our species must
also bear the burden of somehow
reconciling itself with this
charitable pain, which it does
in different ways. But one of
the ways it's that seems to have
happened is I was able to go
dissolve into the collective
unconscious. And when the
healing process deepened, it
represented some type of lifting
out of the collective psyche,
this magnitude of suffering. And
so when I say the suffering
began in pain, what I mean is
that all existence begins in
divine love. And that one of the
things I was shown in this
process was we are actually co
creators in this process. We're
not victims. This isn't being
done to us. Existence is not
being inflicted on us, and it's
not a veil of tears. We're not
being punished for anything. But
creation is a long process, very
long and drawn out with many,
many stages of incompleteness
before we get to the greater
places where we are still going.
And so that we knew we were
getting into this when we chose
to participate in creation, we
knew we were going to be dealing
with a very unfinished and as
yet imperfect system. And we
volunteered for this process
because of the grandeur of what
is taking place, the grandeur of
creation itself, moving from
very simple organisms to very
complicated organisms, from
unconscious organisms to self
conscious and deepening self
conscious organisms, that's the
that's the love out of which the
pain emerged, and the pain is
simply the struggles, you know,
the inherent struggles of
existing on this planet. Do you
Unknown: think that the
struggles rise out of a
disconnection from this source,
or do you feel that it's more of
the model that Stanislav Grof
talks about is that it's a
birthing process, that it's
actually, there's a period where
we're birthing into this new
human, if you will, and that
associated journey down the
birth canal is full of fear and
torment and and you know, before
actually gone,
Chris Bache: yeah, well, I think
in the early stages, there is an
aspect of reliving our birth and
experiencing the birth canal.
Because, you know, the womb is
how we get into time and space,
and the grave is how we get out
of time and space. So when our
consciousness is. Expanding
beyond our physical time space
consciousness. There is this
kind of we get into the
revolving door of death and
rebirth. So we often relive our
birth in the process of being
birthed back into spiritual
reality. But I think that
applies, that kind of language
applies particularly in these
early stages. It applies in the
later stages, but not so
literally. In the same way, I
have a chapter in the book,
which I think is maybe the most
important chapter of the birth
of the future human. So I'm
looking at this historical
crisis that we're entering, this
global systems crisis, driven by
a global ecological crisis, as
the context which is giving
birth to a fundamentally changed
human being, creating a shift in
the collective psyche that we'll
get to. And so I speak of that
as a birth, and it is a birth,
but it's not a birth in the
sense of being trapped in a
birth canal or something like
this. It's the larger dynamic of
a species, which is in the
process of self transforming,
self emerging into a higher
order of itself.
Unknown: That's so interesting,
indeed, and we will get to that,
because I do agree with you that
that is a very important message
for humanity, and something that
we all need to understand, and
it kind of makes things a lot
more hopeful
Chris Bache: once we understand
what's really happening
underneath historical events.
One thing
Unknown: I just want to touch
upon is that there is the theme
that this process is not an
individual initiation as it is,
or initial liberation or
enlightenment, that what is
necessary here is this process
is taken by humanity as its own
individual organism, if you
will.
Chris Bache: One of the things
that happened repeatedly over
the years, as I dissolved into
the species mind so deeply, and
then into the context of the
species mind and the
evolutionary order of things is
that it became very, very clear
to me that the creative
intelligence that's behind
Evolution, that's behind our
universe, is not interested only
in individuals, but it's
interested in entire species.
It's trying to awaken not just
individuals, but it's trying to
awaken the entire human species,
the human family as one. So all
of our individual efforts take
our fractal embodiments of a
larger collective effort. So the
collective informs the
individual, and the individual
influences the collective.
Unknown: That makes a lot of
sense, and also it want. It
encourages me to be sympathetic
and nice to other individuals,
which I think is a very
important message, because we
also are one. You know, that
idea of We Are One, there is
another saying that people use
in literature that talks about
awakening and is, remember who
you are, remember who you are.
And that's something that has
always baffled me a little bit.
But in session 18, I believe
remember who you are, you and I
creating that was one of my
favorite parts of the book, even
though it was the worst pain
ever for you in the beginning,
cleansing aspect of that. But I
love the story, where it talks
about underneath the horrors and
the pain and the drama, there
were these little dominoes of
sweetness that would flip over.
Do you want to tell me a little
bit about that? That story for
our audience?
Chris Bache: Well, it would
probably take us too long to go
through the entire session, the
important part of the session,
after going through this kind of
Venetian blind, flipping back
and forth between the terrible
pain of the suffering of
existence, flipping into the
great sweetness, some extra
ordinary sweetness, going back
and forth until eventually, The
process took me into this
beautiful moment of clarity, and
it showed me that the sweetness
that I was experiencing was not
the origin of pleasure, but the
origin of existence itself. And
with that, this bubble broke and
I came to a remembering of who I
was in a deeper level that I was
consciousness. I was part of the
consciousness that was the
creative impulse of our
universe, and that we are all
sourced in, this creative
intelligence, this creative
consciousness, which is driving
our universe forward. This was
it became really this session
was all about. Remember,
remember. You are, remember what
you are. It really gets down to
a very basic point, our memories
define the limits of our being.
We are what we remember being.
Most of us don't have memories
beyond early childhood, but when
you work at psychedelics and
enter Non-ordinary states of
consciousness or through
meditation or near death
experiences, or any number of
different contexts we can
remember. We can our memories
can be extended. Our remembering
can be extended beyond our
childhood, beyond even birth,
beyond even former lives. When
we remember very, very deeply,
our memories take us back to the
creative impulse of existence
itself, the very impulse that
brought time and space into
being, to remember that deeply
they had this as a memory
suddenly changes your self
definition, your sense of who
and what you are. You become.
You understand that you are part
of the creative universe. You're
part of the energy that's
creating the universe. And with
that, there's just a tremendous
reframing of your understanding
of what your life is about, and
your understanding of what life
itself is about.
Unknown: I love in that session
that the you Your face was taken
into the hands, and you were
looked in the eyes, and it was
said to you, it is you and I
creating my love. All suffering
and ignorance is simply what has
happened since we separated. So
one of the things is, in this
book, you have actually met a
cast of characters, if you want
to call them that, but entities,
consciousnesses, and that was
just a beautiful experience. I
can imagine
Chris Bache: it was. It was a
very meaningful experience. It's
interesting. You know, in DMT
sessions, people have many
experiences where they meet
specific entities. And what's
kind of curious about my LSD
journey is that I had relatively
few experiences meeting meeting
discrete individual entities.
Basically, I kept being
dissolved into layers and layers
of being rather than into a
state where I met individual
beings. So this being, something
took my face in its hands,
looked into my eyes and said
this, you and I creating my love
and I so I've had many
experiences of communion,
contact, even conversation,
dialog with an intelligence. But
this intelligence never took
physical form, never took any
kind of cultural specific form,
never took a deity form, never
took any form of archetypes. It
was always a clear presence that
I felt, but it was not a
presence that was visible to me
Unknown: that's so interesting.
So when they took you, you felt
it. It was more of an
experience, and actually seeing
this do
it for you, yeah. But the words
were very clear. The intention
was very clear.
Speaking of the dialog, I love
the Circle of Learning in
session 19, the cosmic tour in
that session, you really seem to
really begin this intense dialog
with this consciousness. Yeah.
So go ahead. It wasn't so much
of a dialog for, say, as an
experiential Yeah.
Chris Bache: Basically, when I
came through the ocean of
suffering. In that session, I
basically came into there were
several preliminary experiences,
but eventually I came into an
arena where I was in dialog with
this consciousness, and I could
know anything that I wanted to
know, if I could endure it. So
in this arena, I would ask
questions, and it would respond
to me by orchestrating my
experience in order to show me
what it was that I wanted to
understand. And then eventually,
it took me on what I call the
cosmic tour. It seemed to be the
creative intelligence of the
universe, and it seemed to be
delighted to be able to finally
be showing human beings and me
only as representative of my
species, coming back to the
creative intelligence, and it
wanted to show us what it had
accomplished during all these
13.7 billions of years. And it
would take me somewhere and show
me something, and I would
understand. And sometimes what I
saw was so mesmerizing. I would
call it, stop and be just
dumbfounded. It by the beauty of
it. And it would hurry it would
come back for me, and it would
say, hurry up. Hurry up. Got
more to show you. Keep up. Keep
up. Come on. This astounding the
magnitude. Of the intelligence
that's embedded in our universe,
that manifests our universe, and
the magnitude of the love that
lies at the very font of
creation. This was a staggering
revelation for me when I began
this work, even though I have a
background in religious studies,
I began this work as an atheist,
I began this work as an
agnostic, an atheistically
inclined agnostic. I really was
very skeptical about the reality
of a transcendent dimension, or
the know ability of a
transcendent dimension, so this
was a major kind of shift in my
worldview to even envision the
possibility that we could enter
into states which were so
cognitively rich as these states
were.
Unknown: Can you share with us
one part of the tour that you
have digested and explained to
us that was beautiful?
Chris Bache: You know, that's
the challenging part. Is that I
simply don't have enough PhDs to
hold in my conscious awareness.
Many of the things that I was
shown if I had PhDs in physics
and astrophysics and cosmology,
I would have a better chance of
being able to have retained
cognitively specific information
that I was shown at that in
those circumstances. In other
sessions, I had very powerful
experiences, and I was able to
bring them back because they
were somewhat related to things
that I was educated in. I I was
shown many things about
reincarnation. I was shown many
things about how reincarnation
works that led me to have an
understanding of reincarnation
is very different than the way
it's presented in Eastern
cultures as well. Yeah, my first
book is a book on reincarnation
called life cycles, because it
just to me. To me, reincarnation
is a fact of life as
overwhelming empirical evidence
that this is the case. We didn't
have this evidence 50 years ago.
We do today, but kind of
psychologically, what motivated
what was behind my writing that
book, though I don't discuss it
in the book, was in the sessions
my own experience of the karmic
intentionality of my life and
some of my former lives that
surfaced in the sessions
themselves. I don't talk about
it in life cycles. I really try
to stay in the basis of, you
know, publicly available
research, but that was the
background to the book
Unknown: you also talk about
that. It's an evolutionary
impulse, yeah, reincarnation. So
again, not just for the
individual, but for humanity as
well.
Chris Bache: Yes, I see
reincarnation as as part of
evolution. It's the higher
octave of revolution of
evolution. So evolution evolves
whole groups. It falls
collective learning forward in
time. Somehow nature has found a
way, or the intelligence of
nature has found a way to evolve
individuals within certain
species and to fold individual
learning forward in time. So
it's not just individual human
beings who are reincarnating.
All of, excuse me, all of
humanity is reincarnating, and
that means we're we're all
growing together, and all of us
growing together is part of our
species, evolving and growing,
developing new capacities over
long periods of time. So it's
very much of an evolutionary
dynamic.
Unknown: And while we hear I may
as well touch upon a question I
had for a little bit further on,
when you're saying that
evolution involves an
individual, and that individual
puts that information back into
the pot, if you will. For the
rest of the reflective there is
a huge theme in your book in the
respect that you by going
through all of this pain in a
way you were digesting and
healing this collective
consciousness. Now I know for
myself on the work that I have
done personally, that I need to
go back into the pain and
release it, or work with it
acknowledge it and thank it and
said it goodbye. So in a sense,
you have done some of this work
on a larger scale.
Chris Bache: I did, and I want
to really emphasize, even though
I went through many layers of
suffering in this process, I
don't carry any trauma from this
work. I mean, there's nothing
undigested that that bothers me
in the you know, I went into
what the Buddhism calls the hell
realms. You know, people go into
the hell realms in different
circumstances. But it didn't
stick in my system as trauma,
because I saw it through twist
DMT. Conclusion, I took it all
the way down to the base.
Whatever was given to me, I took
it down to the base, and was
much more than amply rewarded in
the ecstatic experiences that
followed. So the whole cycle of
going into pain, breaking
through the pain, going into the
reward phase of a session,
that's what I internalize. So
now, yeah, having done this
work, some of the blessings that
I received in later sessions
were the direct correlation or
the consequence of having done
the collective cleansing. So the
principle of karma is whatever
we do for others comes back to
us in one form or another. So I
had been given an opportunity
and an invitation to help in
this collective transformation.
And I think this is nothing,
nothing terribly heroic. This is
what any mother would do for her
children. Any Poulter would do
for his children. If you saw
someone suffering and you had an
opportunity to help them and not
make them not suffer, any human
being worth their salt could do
that. Same thing happened here.
This opened in the sessions, I
had an opportunity. I took the
opportunity. Then later in the
sessions, when this light began
to fill me and when I began to
enter into orders of ecstasy and
beatific visions, that really
was a crescendo in many of many
years of work that was, that was
the natural, organic manifesting
within my individual awareness
of the historic process that
humanity is going through as a
collective. We are going through
a purification process. We're
going through a detoxification
process. We're going through a
collective death and rebirth
process. And that will be very,
very clear in the decades ahead.
We're going through a
Death-Rebirth process, but death
is followed by rebirth, career,
vacation is followed by ecstatic
joy.
Unknown: So Sweetie, what is it?
Is it the seeing it? Is it the
holding it? Is it the
experiencing of it. What is the
mechanism that clears this pain
away? You know, in the respect
that is there, have you? I mean,
on a very, very grand scale,
you've done very, very grand
work, but possibly, if we can
understand the process, we can
undertake some of it ourselves.
So what is the trigger? What is
the, what is the what do we need
to get to to actually work on
this, to help clear some of this
away?
Chris Bache: I think that what
we do in a session is simply
what is happening in life,
always all the time, except it
gets very concentrated and
amplified in a session. But the
dynamics are fundamentally
similar. Remember that LSD, or
psychedelics in general, they
don't give us they don't
predicate a particular
experience. They don't give us a
specific experience. They are
simply amplifiers of
consciousness. So what happens
in a session is simply what is
happening in life, but larger,
faster, deeper. And I think the
key to engaging suffering in a
way that lifts suffering out of
the system is the same way that
is true for therapy or engaging
life in general, we have to sit
with what it is that's bothering
us. We have to enter into a
conscious rapport with the
suffering and let it come into
us, let our awareness take it
in. The only difference here is
that was the scale of the
suffering involved, the scale of
the memories that were being
activated. But the basic process
to let those memories come into
my awareness without
understanding where they were
coming from at the time or what
it was serving, letting them
come into my awareness and my
experience is that they come
into my awareness and they flow
through me. That the sense,
there's a sense of flowing, it
flows through me, and I think it
flows into the light. It flows
and it allows some type of deep
reconciliation to take place.
Unknown: I think conscious
rapport is perfect. I in my own
limited experience, that's what
it feels like to me, that there
is a conscious interaction, a
rapport with it, and that really
does help. Just know that it
works on larger scales.
Chris Bache: Yeah, it does. And
I think it works with in a
reincarnational context. I
think, for example, that there
are many more Bodhisattvas in
the world than we think.
Perhaps. There are many people
who are suffering, so to speak,
in their physical lives, in
their ordinary day to day lives,
they they are suffering more
pain than so to speak is their
just do more pain than is their
explainable in terms of personal
karma, I think there are many
people who are also trying to
lift the collective psyche, and
they are willing to open their
lives to dimensions of suffering
that come at them in very
tangible, concrete ways. It's
nothing you know, become very
tangible. And they take it on,
and they try to change, you
know, they try to change it.
They're trying to change
people's lives. They're they go
into places in the world where
there is suffering. They don't
need to go into those places,
but they go into those places to
take on that pain in some way
and make a difference with
respect to that pain. Same
principle, same principle as
happens in a psychedelic
session.
Unknown: Indeed, council of
elders. Again, this was another
area of interactive dialog, and
I found it very interesting the
idea that to actually perceive
this knowledge, you had to
prepare for it. You needed
explicit training. Can you share
with us a little bit about that
experience?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, when
you start to go into dialog with
this infinite consciousness that
can show you so many things at
so many levels. You truly have
to train yourself to stay
cognitively coherent when you're
working at so many deep levels
of consciousness. And it happens
kind of spontaneously in your
work, but in this particular
session, it seemed that I needed
kind of training to help make
this better. And so I was in
this council of elders. I was in
this surrounded by beings again
that I didn't see, but I felt,
and I could know anything I
wanted, if I could endure the
consequences of knowing it. So I
would put forward a question,
and the elders would take it,
and then they would start to
gather, and they would start to
chant. The music was the Tibetan
chanting, the very deep,
guttural chanting of the gyota
monks in Tibet they would chant
and chant, and then they would
release this knowing at me. And
if I was centered, when this
knowing hit me, it would send me
into an orgy of cognitive
ecstasy, showing me things, just
showing me things. But if I
wasn't centered, if I had
allowed myself to get distracted
and I wasn't centered, when this
knowing hit me. It would just
Shatter Me. It would just
shatter my mind, and I could not
stay cognitively coherent. So in
this particular session, many,
many times I was shattered. Many
times I was sent into cognitive
ecstasy. But the point was to
train to literally have to train
yourself first to reach this
level of consciousness, and then
you have to train yourself to be
to learn how to receive
conscious information that's
coming from different dimensions
of consciousness. You have to
learn how to stay awake and how
to stay coherent in levels of
consciousness which are beyond
any levels that you've ever
experienced before, and it can
be done. I mean, the shamanic
cultures are masters of learning
how to enter these states of
consciousness. Meditation
masters are masters at learning
how to enter these deep states
of consciousness. It's just the
same dynamic, just within a
psychedelic context. Has
Unknown: this training stayed
with you, and is there any
application for it in normal
consciousness?
I hope so. I hope so. I don't
know who's going
to be releasing such ecstatic
knowledge at you in normal
consciousness, but I mean, are
there any have you? Are you in a
place where you can activate
your your mind, your
consciousness, in that way? In
normal consciousness,
Chris Bache: it is the question
of the relationship between the
experiences one has in deep
psychedelic states and then your
ordinary resting consciousness
when your session is over.
That's a complicated question.
It's clearly we cannot take our
experiences back and stabilize
our present Earth consciousness
in those states. It would be
wonderful if we could. I wish we
could. Wish I could, but it's a
more subtle process. I think
these experiences, if we handle
them well, if we record them and
learn from them, they give us
practices. They literally give
me practices that I'm supposed
to do every day after the
sessions, in between the
sessions, if we use. Well, and
particularly if we stay
grounded, because it's the
greatest danger of working in
psychedelic states is psychic
inflation, because we have had
an extra ordinary experience, we
think we must be an extra
ordinary person. That's just not
true. We have to stay grounded.
But if we stay grounded, the
experiences that we're given, I
think, act as strange attractors
and accelerate our evolutionary
development in a certain
direction. So I hope that some
of the not some of the
experiences I've had, some of
the learnings that I've been
given, some of the training, in
terms of focusing my
consciousness is I trust that it
is affecting me and it is
benefiting me outside of the
sessions, both directly and
indirectly. But actually, I
think the proof that's in the
pudding when I die, all in
Buddhism, all spiritual
practice, is training you for
what will happen when you die,
absolutely. So I think the same
thing is true in psychedelic
sessions, if you engage them
conscientiously, they are
training you and preparing for
you to enter into states of
consciousness that are waiting
for you when you die. And so I
think there's a strong
correlation there.
Unknown: Do you have an idea of
what level we go to when we die?
Since you have visited so many
different levels of creation, of
before creation, did you get a
sense of what level we naturally
Chris Bache: end up at? I've had
many experiences that basically
make sense. I understand them in
terms of the Eastern concept of
the Bardo or the multiple levels
of reality one enters when you
die. The basic idea is that you
don't go to a place, but there
is you go to a complex domain,
which has many, many layers. And
the level that you go to
reflects the level of your
present spiritual development,
your ability to stay conscious.
So all of these levels are part
of the Bardo. They're part of
Samsara. They're part of the
evolving cyclic nature of, you
know, of nature, the sick, the
cyclic patterns of nature. It's
also possible to go penetrate
all the way through the Bardo
and enter extra Samsara,
reality, which is sometimes
called extra Samsara, or beyond
the domain of Samsara. This, I
would place the diamond
Luminosity experiences at extra
samsaric reality outside that
reality. So where one goes, when
one dies really depends upon how
much homework one is done while
one is here.
Unknown: Absolutely, my love.
And speaking of dying, you died
a lot, I'm
afraid so guilty,
as I mentioned in the
introduction, you you, you died
over and over and over and over
again. And so it has changed
your perspective on death,
absolutely having died. Yeah,
Chris Bache: one of the things
that you learned that being
afraid of death is just such a
sadness. I mean, I'm not, not
only am I not afraid of dying,
but I'm looking forward to being
dead. I mean, I'm not looking
forward to the act of dying, but
there's absolutely no fear for
me and what happens to what will
happen to me when I die, and I'm
looking forward to it, because
I've I've crossed that line
multiple times over the course
of all these years of work, and
so I feel comfortable where I'm
going. I'm filled with ecstatic
joy of where I'm going. And I
think it's it's not just me, but
I think we should all be filled
with ecstatic expectations,
ecstatic joy at the prospect of
where we go. If we are afraid of
death, then we've got our entire
entire world upside down. The
hard work is done inside time
and space. This is the hard
place where we go when we die.
Is not the far hard place all
this Hollywood malarkey about
the shadows and darkness and
demonic and no, it's much more
benign than that. It's much more
intelligent than that. It's much
more compassionate than that.
Unknown: Yeah, so to me, death
is something I'm looking forward
to.
The first time you died, there
was fear associated with it. Was
the second time a little bit
easier, or was this, I mean,
like, did you get to put Oh,
here it comes again. Oh. Is
there always just a little bit
of, here we go again.
Chris Bache: The essence of
dying, of course, is losing
complete control. You just you
lose complete control of your
identity, you lose complete
control of your knowledge. You
lose complete control of
anything to do with what you are
and who you are, and that always
has a frightening quality. But
if you go through this multiple
times, several things happen.
One of them is you learn to
trust the process, and you learn
that you can die and the very
structure of your life can be
completely dissolved, but you
will reawaken some essence of
you, some better version of you,
will wake up in a different
reality of total, unexpected
joy. You learn that there really
is no such thing truly as death.
The form of your life can be
destroyed, but the essence of
your life is indestructible, and
therefore you cannot die. Now
that doesn't mean that in some
way it gets easier, but when
you're going through the middle
of an advanced death and rebirth
process, it's still terrifying,
and it's still frightening just
because it is a deep, deep
unraveling of anything you've
ever known. So that the
unraveling in the beginning is
the unraveling of your time,
space, identity, your body,
mind, ego.
Unknown: But I've had that
experience because I've Once
done, you know, an LSD trip when
I was in Amsterdam, and I
remember trying to hold on to
the me, the ego me, with all my
strength, and it was terrifying
to think of that being
dissipated, and I hadn't read
the books, and I didn't know
what would happen if I let go.
So it was just so it is
terrifying experience.
Chris Bache: It is and but as
you do it, as you repeat it, you
get a little more used to it. So
that aspect of the total, total
fear that grips you in the
beginning, that's that ceases.
It's a different quality of
fear. It's a more informed
quality of fear, if that makes
sense, in the end, of course,
what happens is that death
becomes your best friend.
Because what I learned, I know
it's a strange thing.
Unknown: I'm a Scorpio, and
that's even
Chris Bache: learn I learned
late in the last five years of
work that there are many degrees
of dying and the deepest
ecstatic experiences, the
deepest visionary experiences
are follow our fault, or follow
the deepest death experiences.
Once you understand that, once
you understand that there are
levels and levels of dying,
followed by levels and levels of
ecstatic revelation. Then death
becomes your friend. You not
only don't want to avoid it, you
seek it out. You create
conditions in your sessions
where you want the turbulence
and the destructuring that is
associated with death, and you
you choose it because you know
what's waiting for you on the
other side of this radical
destructuring. So death becomes
your best friend. Death becomes
your mistress. Sure. I mean, it
sounds strange to put it that
way, but you know, death is your
gateway into Transcendence,
Unknown: speaking of which, on
the other side of death in
session 22 and 23 Yeah. You were
shown the master plan for
humanity, yeah. So you kind of
had to go through Deb, let's
speak a little bit about that.
Chris Bache: Well, this was
actually one of the real
surprises for me in this work,
because when this all took place
between when I was 30 and 50
years old, and this started in
79 to went to 99 and when I
started this work, I wasn't
studying, I wasn't concerned
about the fate of humanity. I
really was completely tuned out
to global ecological crisis.
This was just before that time
for me. But what happened was
starting in the 22nd 23rd
session, the theme of human
evolution, the theme of the
master plan, and I apologize for
the patriarchal quality maybe of
that term. I don't mean it that
way, the master plan of
humanity. And it kept coming
back again and again, and it
actually continued all the way
to the 70th session. So in the
70th session, I was given one
deep, deep final vision, which
was once again the capstone of
the story. And it was always a
consistent story. So the story
in. Basically for about three
and a half years, the story had
different components, but the
story always had the same
fundamental structure. Humanity
was coming to a turning point.
Humanity was coming to a major
breakthrough. This was a
breakthrough in history that
would divide between the before
and after, just an enormous
spiritual breakthrough. And it
was a breakthrough, not of
individuals, but it was the
entire species. And it was
coming up inside it. It was
coming up from within the
collective consciousness, and it
was catapulting us into an
accelerated development beyond
anything that we had known
previously. But in all of these
years of visions, which I
present in the book, and in this
chapter, the birth of the future
human, I was never shown how
nature was going to accomplish
this. It, you know, I did not
understand how it was going to
accomplish this. And along the
way, I began to do my ecological
homework. I began to read the
books, really helping me become
better educated about what's
happening. And then in 1995 in
the 55th session, it took me
into deep time, into it took me
into the future, and it gave me
an experience of the death and
rebirth of our species. It took
me into the critical turning
point that these visions had
been talking about. And I
experienced this not as an
individual. It wasn't Chris
Bache who had this experience,
but at that point, I was
completely dissolved into the
species mind, into the
collective unconscious, and I
experienced the death and
rebirth of our species as the
species, and it was a it was a
period again, and it didn't give
me the details. It didn't give
me any specifics about when,
where and how. But it was a
global systems crisis triggered
by a global ecological crisis,
and it continued for decades. It
and it basically triggered a
profound suffering as we lost
control of the conditions of our
life. Life as we knew it was
shattered at the core, and it
looked for a time that we would
all be killed, that this was an
extinction process. But just
when it was at its worst,
eventually the crisis passed,
and things began to get better,
and the survivors began to pick
themselves up and began to
recon, put things back together,
and when they began to re,
engage each other and engage
life, they found that they were
working in a completely
different internal reality, that
values which had been activated
in the depth of this crisis,
ways of knowing, ways of being
in the world, had been
activated, and a shift had taken
place, we would say, in the
collective unconscious, a shift
at the foundation of our being,
the collective psyche. So the
entire post crisis world was
saturated with new values, new
perspectives, new social units,
new ways of understanding. There
was a tremendous opening of the
human heart into compassion for
other beings, not only human
beings, but for other beings,
other species. There was a
tremendous opening of the human
mind to be open and transparent
to the intelligence of the
universe that can now, could now
infuse itself more cleanly and
clearly into our human
consciousness. So, I mean,
really honestly, it's, it's a
cliche, I know, but we were
becoming, we became a species of
Buddha's humanity became a
collective Buddhas and a species
of Christ and prophets. We
basically made this deep turning
point. And then, in the 70th
session, several years later, it
gave me one final capstone
retrospective in which it showed
me everything that it had shown
me before and gave me a couple
of last pieces of instruction
concerning this transformational
process. The reason I think this
is the most important part of
the book is naturally because my
personal transformation. Who
Cares one person, but this is
all of our children, all of our
grandchildren, my great
grandchildren. This is what,
this is our work. This is our
collective work. This is what
I'm here for, what you're here
for, what we are all here for,
is to participate and to support
this collective,
transformational process. And I
think it's been building through
the 20th century. It's been,
it's being, going to be
continued, to build through the
21st Century, a series of I'm
expecting a series of punctuated
crises that's just going to be
showing us. We're going to be
inheriting, we're going to be
inheriting the limitations of
our previous world view, of our
of our less than conscious.
Participation on this earth.
Unknown: Well, if you think
about it, when you were doing
right now, basically, you cannot
turn on the TV, the radio or
newspaper without hearing about
our climate disaster and our
economic ecological damage. But
when you were doing this work,
it wasn't very forth. You know,
top of mind, it wasn't something
so even having that disclosure
in these sessions was really
very much predicting the future,
if you will, or predicting the
now back in those times and so,
you know, right now it kind of,
of course it would be an
ecological disaster. But back
then, when you were doing it,
that itself must have been quite
revelatory, because possibly we
were thinking more of war or
annihilation, nuclear
annihilation, of those kinds of
things, if we had to put a
finger on what would end us and
also it sounds, go ahead,
sweetie.
Chris Bache: And this awareness
rises not only in psychedelic
states, and it is, it is, I
don't use the word prophetic,
but it is visionary. And when
you go into deep, visionary
states, you breach the laws of
time, you open yourself up into
future time. But it's not just
in psychedelic states, but deep
contemplatives have these
experiences. Indigenous people
have been having this, these
visions of the future of
humanity, and the indigenous
brothers and sisters have been
warning the civilized members of
the human family about what
we're doing to the planet. And I
have a passage from beads
Griffith in that chapter the
birth of the future human who is
a Christian, Hindu saint, you
know, a contemplative, and he
had these kind of visions about
where we're going. Yeah, the
process me completely by
surprise back then,
Unknown: yes, absolutely. That's
That's what I'm saying. We have
to think that this was a while
back, that it's not, it wasn't
what all the awareness that
there is now, the process sounds
very much like an individual
death process. However, in the
respect that in the book, you
talk about how we everything
that we rely on today goes away,
you know, everything that we
take for granted and so that
there's this incredible chaos.
And it's that for the survivors,
that the ability, the necessity
to kind of come up with a new
way of doing things that we had
done poorly before, and that
that is almost part of the
process of the initiation into
the new human.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think that
people individually, who are
making the transition in advance
of the collective, who see
what's happening and they're
making the changes in their own
life. They've made this decisive
steps to take down the barriers
between race, between religion,
between cultures. They have
eliminated those barriers in
their own heart. They're
basically working to live a
different relationship with the
earth, to preserve the life
systems of the planet, to reduce
their foot there, to move into
voluntary simplicity, the beings
who have made the steps in their
personal life. Those beings, I
think, become seed catalysts in
our future transformation. My
sense is that when we go into
this crisis of the future. It's
going to last so long, and it's
going to affect so many people,
and it's going to be so
disruptive and so hard on us
that it's going to stimulate not
only our individual psyches, but
so many people will be having
these disruptive experiences
that it's going to hyper
stimulate the collective
unconscious. It'll drive the
collective unconscious into what
we call non linear systems in a
long linear range. And we know
something about physical systems
when they are driven into non
linear conditions are far from
equilibrium states. I think that
something that happens to
physical systems, there is an
analogy to what will happen in
psychological systems, in the
psychic field of the human
species, and when this field is
pressurized, small
perturbations, the chaos
theoreticians like to say small
changes can produce
disproportionate outcomes, A
capacity the species will be
able to mobilize unexpected
insights, unexpected forms of
knowledge, unexpected
understandings will emerge, so
to speak, almost out of nowhere,
but it's actually emerging out
of our own innate potential, out
of our own being so faster than
we could imagine. The changes
will take place faster than we
could conceive of if we were
looking at the history of the
past, because the history of the
past is somewhat non linear. But
when we go into such a profound
crisis, we move into, I'm sorry,
the past is linear, but when we
go into this profound crisis, we
go into non linear conditions
and non linear dynamics.
Unknown: It's. Sounds very
scary, but very exciting. For
those of us who haven't died 30
times, you know it, but I mean,
the it's like having a baby,
that's very scary too, you know?
But at the end of absolutely,
the reward,
Chris Bache: yeah, having a
baby, it's an excellent analogy,
because when you have a baby,
gestation lasts nine months.
It's a very, very long process,
but labor is very, very intense,
but relatively short. And I
think that's also true for our
species. Going into this crisis,
we had been gestating the future
human for hundreds of 1000s of
years. We've been doing it
through reincarnation,
reincarnation, learning,
learning, learning more,
reincarnation, more development.
But the time of birth is a
relatively short, intense period
that requires makes enormous
demands, just as labor does for
a woman. That's what we're
coming to. We are going into a
labor of history, the labor of
the future, human, yeah, and
it's not going to be fun, it's
not going to be easy, but it's
going to be, I think, profoundly
meaningful, and in the end, when
we die, would you rather have a
nice, happy life, pleasant, but
basically kind of boring, not
very significant. Would you
rather have a life where you
knew you were invested in
something that meant, something
that was worth, something that
was profound? And I think
that's, that's what we're going
into.
Unknown: I look, I agree with
you. I often, I'm also a
believer in reincarnation. And
you know, you see the trends
that are happening right now.
And I often think about, if
nothing changes, how much worse
the next lives are going to be.
So to get in there, to dig in,
do the work that we can be part
of the process and come out the
other end, I think it is. It's a
wonderful option,
Chris Bache: yeah, and it's
really important. I think late
in my sessions, I began to feel
it's important for us to
understand the future human that
we are becoming. Imagine if you
went into labor and you didn't
know you were pregnant and you
didn't understand what was
happening to it be terrifying.
Be terribly frightening. And
when we go into this dark period
of history, if we don't have an
understanding that we what's
happening, that we are really
giving birth, we could succumb
to despair. We could, you know,
we're already seeing all these
trauma movies you know about
apocalyptic, this and
apocalyptic that we really have
to keep our eye on the horizon.
We have to understand what we're
doing. This is a spiritual
transformation. It's a psycho
spiritual transformation.
Unknown: So let's end on the
future. Human tell us what we're
all like.
Chris Bache: I can't tell you
what the world will be like, but
I can describe my experience of
touching the future human, and
several times in the course of
the sessions, I was taken into
deep time and given an
opportunity to try on for size,
so to speak, the human psyche at
The stage of the future human.
And this happened very
powerfully in the 70th session,
at the culmination of this long
process, and such a magnificent
being, just such an extra
ordinary being. It was so
helpful, having experienced the
death and rebirth of humanity,
having experienced so many
different layers to experience
this future, human, magnificent
being, a mind, truly
enlightened, mind tuned to the
deep structure of the universe,
tuned to the intelligence of the
universe, a heart that was
deeply in touch with other human
beings and sensitive to its
history, it's longer history
with other human beings, a heart
which can embrace the entire
planet, a heart which which has
a deep appreciation for the
damage that we've done to the
living systems on this planet
and to the species that are
going extinct, and a commitment
to reverse that, to bring
forward safe habitat, to
basically restore these systems,
but an open heart, an open mind,
a transformed human being,
that's what we're that's where
we're going. And I think that
one way of understanding the
great religious saints and sages
of history, to understand
Christ, to understand the
Buddha, is all of them,
basically are describing what
I'm describing. They're
describing a way of living which
is deeply different than if you
develop your values, basically
only in terms of, you know,
space, time, consciousness,
this. Is the Awakened heart, the
awakened mind.
Unknown: Look, there are people
throughout history. You know,
people that have been burned at
the stake, for example, because
they had such faith that there
was more than just this physical
incarnation. But you know,
there's been so few of them
throughout history, and to have
a whole planet full of people
with this awareness, I think
would be amazing.
Chris Bache: I think we are
basically cleaning our psychic
basement. We are cleaning the
collective unconscious. We're
cleaning our individual
unconscious, and in that
process, we are learning how to
create consciously right now, a
lot of our creativity is
unconscious creativity. We're
being dragged around hither
through our own unconscious
conditioning, our own
unconscious history. But in the
course of this transformative
process, as we clear our
unconscious conditioning as we
clear it collectively, we then
begin to be able to manifest our
intelligence in conscious acts
of creativity. We will be able
to do extra ordinary things that
we can only dream of doing now
in future time, becoming a more
conscious created
Unknown: being you make the
comment that creation is a
result of choices. Yes, and so
it's the conscious choices. I
guess, instead of the myriad of
1000s of unconscious choices
that we make every day, that one
of the distinctions will be as
that we will be more conscious
and the choices that we make
Chris Bache: more conscious of
the choices we make. I think
part of how the word system
works is we're in a living
universe. We're in a dynamic
universe, and we make a choice,
and the universe responds to
that choice by triggering a
series of events. I don't mean
to be superficial in describing
how this process works. There's
layers and layers to it, but in
the beginning, our understanding
is incomplete, and there's a lot
of ignorance in our choices, and
we inherit the consequences of
ignorant choices. And in this
process, we learn. We think, for
example, we can hurt somebody
else without hurting ourselves,
and we inherit the karma of that
act in order to learn that we
are all actually embedded in
each other's lives. We are all
leaves on the same tree so that
we make wiser choices, you know,
more conscious choices, and we
begin to make choices that are
not at the expense of other
beings, but actually enhance the
well being of other beings. And
that generates its own kind of
feedback cycles in our life.
It's not to oversimplify it, but
the dynamics are basically
there,
Unknown: and it feels good. You
know? I know that when I make
somebody else life feel better,
it feels good. And I'm surprised
at how little, or, you know,
that goes on, you know, it's
like, it's just amazing to me,
because it's good for me, it's
good for them, it's good for
everything. But anyway, we'll
get there. It sounds like
Chris Bache: Chris, we will. I
think we will. Kindness feels
good. Courage feels good.
Generosity feels good. Truth
feels good. You know, it's not
to say, you know it's it's hard
to make the right choices and
challenging circumstances. It's
hard when you're not getting
what you think you should have
to basically give what you have
a way to share what you have
with someone in need. But it
feels good, and it takes us in
the right direction Absolutely.
Unknown: Well. Thank you so
much, my dear for spending this
time with me. I really have
appreciated it. And as I said at
the beginning, I really have a
much more hopeful perspective
now for the future, and I'm not
so scared as death of death.
Good reading this. I'm like, if
Chris can do it, I can do it
absolutely.
Chris Bache: You know this,
there is nothing I drop out a
lot of the personal aspects of
my journey in the book, I'm
really only interested in the
larger, universal aspects and
the collective aspects and the
cosmic, logical aspects. What's
important is not that I had
these experiences. What's
important is that these
experiences are available for
all of us to have, and they give
us some insight to the
background textures of our
lives. That's what's important.
As a philosopher, I think that's
the important thing. I've really
enjoyed our conversation.
Vanessa, I really thank you for
the opportunity to have this
time with you and for your for
your viewers.
Unknown: Thank you so much. My
love. You. Have a wonderful day.
You.