Chris Bache: You I want to thank
Swamiji for taking us into such
a wonderful, spacious place. It
was a little disorienting for
me, because I went so deep with
him that when he was finishing,
I suddenly realized, oh, I have
a talk to give. I also would
like to mention that the
cosmology that emerges in
psychedelic research is not a
new cosmology. It's the same
cosmology that has been
discovered and emerges in the
deepest and the best mystical
traditions around the world, we
are simply looking at a new set
of technology, a new set of
techniques for entering into
these states of consciousness.
It's a pleasure to be with the
time waiver community. Again,
when I was with you last year, I
spoke to you about a book I was
writing called diamonds from
heaven. This book has now been
finished, and it will be
released this coming November.
The publisher has given it a new
title. But oh, here it is,
calling it LSD in the mind of
the universe. It's not my
favorite title. It will always
be diamonds from heaven. For me,
the revolution begins with the
question, what is it possible
for human beings to experience?
The work in the global
consciousness project is pushing
the edges of what is it possible
for human beings to experience?
Parapsychological research
pushes that question.
Psychedelic research pushes that
question, what is it possible
for human beings to experience
the experience. The forward to
this book was written by urban
lasso, who I'm so pleased, is
going to be with us this
afternoon, by by television. It
is Urban's work to provide
through his mastery of multiple
scientific disciplines to
demonstrate that there is a
super implicate, super coherent
cosmic intelligence that informs
time and space. It's my
experience and my contention
that psychedelics, when they are
used in a discipline and
therapeutically structured
environment, they give us the
opportunity to enter into a
progressively deepening
experience, a deepening
communion with this cosmic
intelligence.
Now, as you all know here, there
is a revolution, a renaissance
in psychedelic research taking
place across the world. Most
psychedelic research today is
taking place in two forms, or is
focused in two projects. One of
them is mapping the neurology
and the biochemical pathways
that psychedelics activate, and
the second is healing the
personal psyche, the wounds that
we collect in life, post
traumatic stress, depression, a
variety of different conditions.
I think these are important
first steps in reclaiming these
valuable substances, but these
are only the first steps,
historically and cross
culturally. Our experience with
these mind opening substances
has been that healing the
personal unconscious is only the
first stage of a much longer
journey. The psychedelic acts,
the psychedelic agents we have
access to today are so powerful
that I believe they mark a new
frontier in human experience. We
can shatter the shell of the
earth bound mind so consistently
that it becomes hard to describe
the depths of cosmic communion
that follow by taking our life
to its limits and repeatedly
shattering those limits we
dissolve for hours. At a time,
into flows of life that
transcend all measures. By
entering these states with focus
and clear intent, by submitting
to the harsh demands of death
and rebirth, we surrender all we
have been to become something
utterly new for six or eight
hours at a time, a being who can
do things we could never do, a
being who can know things that
we can never know. As we enter
larger and older levels of
existence, the universe receives
us and tutors us. It rewards our
courage with exquisite
intimacies, drawing us into
almost unspeakable ecstasies of
discovery. Now, my own
psychedelic journey began 40
years when I was a brand new
academic, fresh out of graduate
school, and I met the work of
Stanislav Grof, and I read these
two early books by him, realms
of the human unconscious, which
was published in 1976 and for
me, I'm reading this in 1979 and
then quickly followed by LSD
psychotherapy, where he sets out
the methodology of working
clinically, therapeutically and
in a very disciplined,
structured manner with
psychedelics and integrating
them into the therapeutic
process. I want to emphasize
that what I'm describing today
is not tripping. It's not the
recreational use of
psychedelics. It's not the
careless engaging of these
states of consciousness. These
are amplifiers of consciousness,
and when we contain that
amplified consciousness, when we
take it into a meditational
situation, when we take it into
a Kiva, completely isolated from
the outside world, and use this
energy to drive deeper and
deeper and deeper into
consciousness. That's what I'm
talking about. That's what Stan
grofs work is exploring. So
first, let me say a few words
about the protocol that I used,
and then describe where this
journey that I'm telling the
story of in LSD, in the mind of
the universe, where it went.
Most of you who know Stan grofs
work, and I have to assume a
certain familiarity here, most
of you who know Stan grofs Work
know that the fundamental
distinction he drew in their
methodology was low dose
psycholytic therapy and high
dose psychedelic therapy.
Psychedelic therapy was
basically working with lower
doses of psychedelics, maybe up
to between 40 and 100 sessions
where you peel the unconscious
layer by layer stripping down
the various levels of trauma or
angst or our pains that we carry
bit by bit. In Spring Grove
Hospital in Baltimore, Maryland,
they developed a different form
of therapy, high dose
psychedelic therapy. But the
strategy was quite different
there. The strategy was to take
an overwhelming dose, a very
high level dose of psychedelics,
about 500 micrograms, and blow
through all the levels of
consciousness and try to trigger
a Near-Death Experience. They
were working with patients who
were going to die, terminally
cancer, terminally ill cancer
patients, and they wanted to see
if they could trigger a
confrontation with the universe
that would give them a glimpse
of where they were going, and so
reduced the anxiety of death,
and they succeeded in doing so.
Now I came along and I thought,
well, if you could use
psychedelics in this manner
safely three times, and their
protocol was limited to a
maximum of three doses per
patient, if you could do this
work safely three times, then
you could do it safely more than
three times. And that's what I
set out to do. I began a quiet,
covert because I couldn't do
this work legally. I had to kind
of create a barrier between my
professional life as a professor
of religious studies in my
personal life, where I began the
systematic work of exploring my
own consciousness using Stan
Grof protocols in psychedelic
therapy, it ended up being 73
high dose sessions I worked at
500 to 600 micrograms spread
over 20 years. I did four years
of work. I stopped for six years
for reasons that I explained in
the book, and then I did another
10 years of very intense work. I
did this all between the time
when I was 30 years old and 50
years old. I stopped in 19. 99
and it's taken me this long to
digest everything that I had
experienced, to put it in an
organized fashion and to
basically write it down in a way
that I could share it with other
people. And it's not that what's
not important is that I
experience these things. What's
important is that these levels
of consciousness are available
for everyone to experience,
whether through psychedelics or
through non psychedelics,
because it's the nature of the
universe itself. I want to
emphasize that I'm not a
psychologist and I'm not a
therapist. I didn't go into this
work seeking healing. Though I
received much healing. I am a
philosopher. I was trained as a
philosopher, and I had a
philosophical agenda, and in
this I traced this work back to
William James in his Varieties
of Religious Experience, where
he talks about his experiences
with nitrous oxide and the
essence of this new
philosophical modality is this
first three steps, first, to
push the boundaries of
consciousness as hard as
possible, or to push the
boundaries of consciousness.
Second, to write a detailed and
complete, phenomenologically
accurate report of your
experience within 24 hours, and
third, critically analyze your
experience, comparing it to
other form, other bodies of
knowledge, and comparing it to
the experiences of other
journeyers.
So a few words on the
methodology. Oh, I try them
there. But I stopped when I got
to the end of my 73 journeys and
was beginning to write it up. In
the beginning, I thought I was
really just doing an extended
course of psychedelic therapy.
It was just psychedelic therapy.
Nothing new. When I got to the
end, and I was looking back over
the course of where I went over
those 20 years, I realized that
this was something different.
When you enter into this state
so many times in a controlled
fashion, it opens up
opportunities that were not
considered in the early years of
psychedelic therapy, and it also
represents challenges that were
not encountered in the early
years of psychedelic therapy, I
recognize that it needed a new
name. It needed something to
differentiate it, and so the
name I gave it is psychedelic
exploration. The method is
psychedelic therapy. Very
controlled circumstances. Always
working with a sitter, always
working in contained and private
environment, eye shades,
earphones, listening to a very
carefully curated musical list.
The difference between
psychedelic therapy and
psychedelic exploration is the
number of sessions. For me, 73
sessions. Now I want to add that
this is not a protocol that I
recommend. Honestly, I do not.
At the time, I thought I could
do this work safely, and I did
do it safely. I always stayed
within the limits of safety, but
I found that pushing yourself
that hard, that deeply into the
universe, generated
complications that it took all
of my resources to manage in the
course of this time. If I were
doing this work over again, I
would be much gentler on myself.
I would balance high dose
sessions with low dose sessions.
And because LSD tends to be a
high altitude psychedelic, I
would balance working with LSD
with working with Psilocybin and
Ayahuasca, which are more body
grounded psychedelics, I think a
more nuanced approach would
produce better results. Now, I
did this work as systematically
as I could. I had very, very
detailed records. Came out with
about 400 pages of my
psychedelic journal. I kept
track of all the dates of course
of my sessions. I even looked at
the astral, logical variables
when I began to understand from
Stan and from Rick Tarnas Their
proposal that there is a
correlation between the outer
planets and what happens in
one's psychedelic sessions. And
I should mention that my
protocol was highly
standardized, which allowed me
to minimize as many variables as
possible. I always had the same
sitter, who was a clinical
psychologist, whom I happened to
be married to at the time, was
very handy. The same set and
setting, the same location, the
same substance, the same dose
level. Ago, and the same
recording process, and I think
the stability of all those
variables keeping them constant,
it contributed to the clarity
and the stability of the
communion that opened and the
psychedelic window that opened
in this work. Now I want to
mention that the story in
diamonds from heaven, I always
to me, it's diamonds from
heaven. The story that opened is
not primarily a personal story.
I did not I'm not trying to tell
a personal story. In fact, I
dropped out a lot of the
personal details. It's a
personal story, of course,
because it's my experience. But
it's not primarily a personal
story. These ways represent a
series of psychedelic sessions,
which I've drawn overlapping to
illustrate the point that these
sessions are systematically
there is a conversation that
picks up and continues session
by session. The small circles at
the beginning and endings of the
of the session represent the
openings and closing of a
sessions, I found that things
that were relevant to my
personal life tended to occur
when I was leaving time and
space and when I was coming back
into time and space, but during
the peak hours of a session,
after the first 12 or 15
sessions, during the peak hours
of a session, I was usually
operating far beyond personal
reality, and that's the story
which is the most important
story, that's the story which is
the philosophically more
interesting story, that's the
cosmological story. So this
story is not a therapeutic
story. Therapeutic story, the
personal details are very
important in a cosmological
story, they're less important
when one does this work, one
enters into a regimen in which
one undergoes many deaths and
many rebirths, the first death.
This line in this image.
Everything below the line is
time, space, reality. The drop
at the end of this line, at this
blue image, represents our
individual time, space identity,
our egoic identity. The first
circle represents the
Death-Rebirth that takes place
when we transition into
spiritual reality, ego death,
which is gets a lot of attention
in the psychedelic literature,
but it's getting less attention.
So far, are the deeper deaths
that take place at deeper levels
of existence. Now, Stan Grof
uses the vocabulary of psychic
level Transpersonal experience,
subtle level Transpersonal
experience, causal level
experience. And ask because the
universe tends to reveal itself
in layers. One goes through
deaths when one moves into these
deeper layers. Every time one
goes into a deeper level of
consciousness, everything that
one has known up until that
time, including your psychedelic
experiences, everything you know
to be true, including those
psychedelic experiences, must be
surrendered if a truly new and
novel dimension of existence is
going to open. When I was
evaluating all of my
experiences, one of the
questions I asked myself, was
okay, there were many, many
deaths, but how many fundamental
core Death-Rebirth transitions
did I go through? Oh, back up
one circle to describe a
transition into a level of
reality is an
oversimplification. One goes
through levels within levels
within levels. These numbers
represent session numbers. And
there is kind of an iteration, a
repeating going deeper and
deeper and deeper into this
level of reality. But I asked,
how many times? How many core
deaths, Death-Rebirth cycles
that I go through, and I
identified five, and here they
are. The first is the death of
self, the complete shattering of
your time, space, identity,
letting go of everything you
have known yourself to be from
the moment you're born until
that moment in time ego death.
The second was entering into or
took place at the level of the
collective mind, the collective
psyche. The third was entering
into archetypal mind, kind of
the domain described by Carl
Jung and Plato, but different
than either of them portray it,
the third fourth, entering into
causal oneness. Now, oneness is
a theme which emerges much
earlier in the journey, but
causal oneness is something
quite distinctive. There is no
outer boundary at the level of
call. So one. Is, it is the
totality of existence. You
cannot step outside this reality
to get a perspective on it. It
is the totality of existence
moving and living as one. And
the fifth level for me is the
diamond Luminosity, what I call
the domain of diamond
Luminosity, which occupied me
for the last five years of my
journey. Now, what I'd like to
do now is shift to the book and
simply take you through or show
you the relationship between
these stages and the chapters of
the book. The easiest way to do
this is just do it, maybe
something like this, to the
death of self. There is the
chapter crossing the boundary of
birth and death. There's a
methodology chapter, first
explaining the methodology and
the protocol, but then crossing
the boundary of birth and death,
exploring collective mind. There
are three chapters that address
this. The first has to do with
the ocean of suffering. The
second is deep time in the soul,
or the fifth chapter deep time
in the soul. And the six is
initiation into the universe.
I'm going to come back so I'm
just going to push through here.
Archetypal mind. There is a
chapter called The Greater real
of archetypal reality, causal
oneness. There is a chapter that
I call a benediction of
blessings.
Diamond Luminosity is discussed
in Chapter 10, which is the
largest number of sessions in
the book, 26 sessions, almost a
third of the entire journey. But
before I talk about diamond
Luminosity, I talk about the
birth of the future human, which
I have to drop back. And this is
a series of experiences that
actually began during the
initiation of the universe and
continued into the diamond
Luminosity work. And at the end,
after everything was said and
done, when I was in the last
year of this work, a final
vision, which was the capstone
of the birth of the future human
work. So it's impossible to do
more than just touch on a few
themes, a few descriptors of
these chapters to give a sense
of the trajectory of the work.
So first, let's do that, and
then let's move this over.
Crossing the boundary of birth
and death is the easiest to
summarize, because it's the one
that's very thoroughly described
in Stanislav Grof work. It's the
perinatal level of consciousness
entering and transitioning
through the perinatal level.
When one enters this work, one
becomes many people relive their
own birth. One has many profound
encounters with death, death and
dying. We get here by being
born. We leave the physical
world by dying. When one is
pushing the boundaries and
taking consciousness beyond the
limits of physical
consciousness, birth and death
get all complexly intertwined
until one goes through a series
of profound existential crises,
confronting the meaninglessness
of existence, the futility of
life, understood as a physical
purely a physical structure,
until eventually, one goes
through an event that usually is
described as ego death in The
ninth and 10th sessions. This
took me two years and 10
sessions to navigate this
process. In the end, the
universe just snapped me like a
twig. It everything I knew
myself to do to be at the
beginning of the day was
completely reversed and
inverted. I began the day as a
white male middle class
philosopher obsessed with the
meaning of life. In the course
of the session, for hours, I was
immersed in the experience of
women, women of color, women who
were poor, women who had no
interest whatsoever in
philosophical exploration. And
that's what I was. That's what I
became. It was a frightening
experience scared me to death,
but when I let go and when I
allowed myself to become fully a
woman, then everything pivoted
and I was taken into the world
of women. I experienced hundreds
and hundreds of women. I
experienced many dimensions of
female experience under the arm
of the great mother. I wish
every man could have the
experience that I had that day.
It truly was a broadening
experience. And the message was
not reclaim your femininity or
reclaim your former lives as
women, because I know I've had
former lives as women. The
message was where you are going.
Gen. Gender does not exist. Let
go.
Excuse me. I
where things went next. When I
went through ego death, and I
was expecting things to get
lighter. I mean, after ego
death, things are supposed to
get lighter, where things went
actually got much worse. I
entered a domain of
extraordinary suffering,
collective suffering, a domain
of just unbelievable pain and
unbelievable anger and violence,
and it this took place over two
years, and it deepened
systematically, systematically
deepening and deepening,
deepening, until eventually I
had the experience of being,
becoming, in some fundamental
way, all of the human beings of
our entire species, and
gathering experiences that
extended over 100,000 years,
just a massive you.
At first, I thought
this was a deepening of ego
death, that somehow pieces of my
ego had slipped through the
noose, and there was I was
dying. It was my personal death
and personal transformation that
was driving these processes. But
it went on for so long, and it
took so many, there were so many
beings involved, that eventually
I came to a different
conclusion. The conclusion I
came to was that somehow
something had shifted in my
sessions, and the universe was
using my sessions to bring a
kind of healing to some portion
of the collective psyche. With
urban Laszlo, I agree that there
is an Akashic memory that holds
the memory of everything that's
happened in the universe and in
the collective unconscious of
our species. We hold the entire
history of our species. We hold
all the wars. We hold the memory
of all the terrible things that
we've done to each other. And
just as our personal trauma
burdens our personal life and
must be cleansed if our personal
life is to be free, likewise,
our species holds these wounds,
and these wounds, these these
trauma must be cleansed if our
species is going to function at
a higher level. So I came to
understand by the end of this
process that something was
working to transform, not me,
but through me, to to transform
some aspect of the human species
and help us move forward. Now,
there are two phases of a
session in working like this.
There's a purification phase,
and then there's an ecstatic
phase in the purification or
suffering phase, if you allow
it, if you take it as let it
take you as far as it wants to
take you. If you let it take you
wherever it wants to go, even
though you may not understand
anything about what's happening,
it will eventually culminate,
come to a crescendo, and it'll
you'll go through a kind of a
death and surrender process, and
when you go through that, you
wake up into a completely
different reality, completely
unexpected reality, and for the
remainder of the session, you're
in an ecstatic state of
consciousness, and then when you
resume the next session, three
or four months later, the same
process will repeat itself when
I came through the ocean of
suffering. Let me back up, just
like I did, the ocean of
suffering, I said, lasted two
years. There was a year of work,
and then I stopped my work for
six years, and then I resumed my
work on the other side in the
first year when I was going
through the ocean of suffering,
when I came through the
sessions, I entered this
territory that I call deep time
in the soul. I entered
systematically for seven
sessions over the course of the
year, I entered into a state of
consciousness in which I
experienced the totality of my
life start to finish as a
completed whole. All the details
of my life were suddenly
present. I was in the state that
just totally overwhelmed me and
systematically gave me an
instruction on what my life was
about, how it was connected to
the lives of the people around
me. This was the deepest, most
moving experience of my life at
the time in. And yet, at the in
the first time, when I came back
from that experience, I could
not remember it. It disappeared.
I had no reference points in my
time space consciousness to
enter states of to anchor.
States of consciousness would
shatter Time, space or linear
time. But what I found was that
when I went back to this
condition in that state of
consciousness, a second, third
and fourth time, I remembered
more. I was able to hold on to
more. I get more coherent, a
clear understanding of what was
taking place. You can learn how
to stay conscious in levels of
consciousness that you were not
able to stay conscious in
before. And this is an
epistemological and important
epistemological state. Deep
experiences of the universe are
not simply given to you. First,
you have to get to that level of
reality to have these
experiences, but then you have
to train yourself. You have to
be taught by the universe how to
stay conscious in levels of
consciousness that previously
would not be able to stay
conscious in. It takes a great
deal of discipline and training,
and the universe will train you
to have accurate recall of
levels of consciousness that
were previously completely novel
to you in
so after the six year break that
I took, and I began the work
again, the ocean of
consciousness began exactly
where it had stopped six years
before, and it kept getting
worse and worse and worse. The
fact that it started exactly
where it had stopped before, I
think says something about the
intentionality and the and the
the magnitude of the
intelligence that is guiding
one's work. I always felt myself
to be in communion with an
intelligence. This intelligence
never took any form. I never saw
any images that I would
associate with it. There were no
deities or no forms of anything
like that, but I always felt
myself in dialog with a super
ordinate intelligence. When I
began the work after the six
year break, the ecstatic portion
of the session shifted into a
completely different domain. I
entered into a process in which
I was given a systematic course
of instruction in the structure
of reality at a cosmological
level. I know this sounds
terribly arrogant, and I
apologize for that, but that's
simply what happened. Here are
the names of the sessions that I
use, that I that I gave these
sessions and I deal with in the
book. For me, I give all of my
sessions a name. I try to
identify the pith of what
happens in the session, and I
give it a name, so that when I
see the name, it reminds me of
the session, because I'm trying
to hold all of my journey in my
mind. All at the same time, I
not only record my sessions, I
break them down into bullet
points. These are the names of
the sessions that I'm addressing
in the chapter of the initiation
in the universe. Some of these I
discuss in my book, dark night,
early dawn. The Master Plan was
a series of experiences that
took place, which began and
this, this continued for years,
a series of experiences in which
I seem to be being taught what
was happening to the human race
and where the human race was
going. What is the larger
developmental trajectory of
humanity? Once again, I
apologize for the apparent
arrogance of that. It sounds
like ego run amok, but
eventually, the ocean of
suffering culminated in the 24th
century, 24th session, which I
call healing the collective
wound, just an orgy of
suffering, which eventually,
when it came to a head and it it
climaxed, it spun me into a
level of reality that was
ancient beyond reckoning. It
spun me into archetypal reality,
and the collective suffering
never reappeared in any
subsequent session,
where I went next was into the
greater real of archetypal
reality. I entered a reality
that was more real than physical
reality. It was like Plato's in
Plato's cave, where the fellow
gets out of Plato caves, Plato's
the cave and enters a world
which is more real than physical
reality, which is a very
disorienting experience.
Initially and when I entered
this reality, when I entered
archetypal reality for the next
year and a half, I stayed in
this reality over in my
sessions, I went through a death
that was deeper than ego death.
I went through a death in which
I had to cease to be a human
being in any way, shape or form,
my consciousness could no longer
operate within the confines of
even our collective psyche. I
entered a state of awareness
which was beyond the collective
psyche, and it at that level I
was being worked with to be
taught how reality functions. At
this level, the experiences, the
sessions that I address in this
chapter are listed here. My
experiences here are sort of
divided into two levels. There
was kind of the high, subtle
level, the Platonic level in
which I encountered archetypal
forms, archetypal beings that
were just vast. They were
impossible for my mind to wrap
itself around. I imaged them as
galaxies. They were billions and
billions of light years across,
just impossible to imagine
beings of such magnitude. But
these are beings who are the
beings who are responsible for
creating time and space itself,
creating and governing the
emergence of life inside time
and space at a lower level, at a
lower subtle level, I entered
deep into the collective psyche,
and I repeatedly had the
experience of the human species
as a single organism, and that
all of our individual minds were
fractal aspects of its
comprehensive mind, and even our
bodies were cells within the
unified body of humanity. And
that as we heal our minds and as
we heal our bodies, we actually
contribute to the developmental
history and the strengthening of
the mind of our species and even
the body of our species. When I
went into archetypal reality,
the deaths that I went through
involved enormous energy, fire
volcanoes, sun flares, just
excruciatingly difficult
experiences of being burned
alive and consumed at this deep
level. And this, I mention this
because this is an important
point. What I learned was that
as you go deeper into the
universe, every deeper level of
reality functions at a higher
level of energy. This is well
recognized in the deep mystical
traditions. A deeper level of
consciousness is a higher level
of energy. And if you are going
to have stable experience at
that deeper level of
consciousness, you must
stabilize your consciousness at
that higher level of energy. If
you're mountain climbing, you
have to stabilize dealing with
less and less oxygen, and you do
that gradually in your ascent.
But if you're working in deep,
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, you must
stabilize and accommodate to
greater and greater levels of
energy, and you must learn how
to manage those that level of
energy. Otherwise, your
experiences there will be
fragmented, incoherent, and you
will not be able to bring back
much of great detail. Well, I
began to have experiences here
of reincarnation as a collective
phenomenon. Now, I had,
previously, I've written a book
on reincarnation, and the story
I tell there is that
reincarnation is kind of a I
thought of it as an individual
soul story, that that's the
story that's given in our
spiritual traditions, that we
are learning. Hopefully we're
making progress. We die, we're
reborn. We die reborn, and our
individual choices lead to,
hopefully, an improving destiny
as our soul matures. But now I
began to have experiences of the
entire planet as a single
organism, growing itself,
maturing itself through the
pulsating rhythm of its entire
population, reincarnating
century after century, and I
began to understand, or have, or
was shown, that our individual
karma is all integrated and part
of our collective karma. And the
boundary between individual
karma and individual evolution,
and our collective karma and our
collective individual evolution
came down entirely, and that's
the primary theme of dark night,
early dawn, that there isn't.
Separate. It's impossible to
achieve spiritual awakening by
yourself, because there is no
private self to awaken. All of
our awakening emerges out of a
collective context, and it
contributes back into the
collective context. In the end,
we are always working with the
divine for the good of the
entire species and beyond the
species, after the time spent in
the in the where am I? Yeah, in
the greater reel of archetype of
reality, I entered causal
oneness. I entered into a period
of tremendous blessings. It was
a year of unbelievable
blessings. These were the four
sessions that I address in this
chapter. The forest was an
experience of emptiness.
Shunyata, complete transparency,
no self in me, no self anywhere
in the world around me. The
entire world is a living
oneness. And when you experience
oneness, then you instantly
experience no self, the absence
of an independent, separate,
autonomous self. When the self
goes the world is one. Let me
jump over the diamond. The birth
of the diamond soul singing the
universe away, was an experience
of the deep, fertile void, the
primal void of not of that is
the matrix within which all form
emerges. Jesus's blood was an
experience of extraordinary
cosmic love, being just awash
with love like I had never known
anywhere in my life or anywhere
in my previous sessions. But let
me just mention diamonds, the
birth of the diamond soul,
because it comes up later in
this experience. In this
session, I had the experience of
my former lives coming in fast
and furious. I've done a lot of
work through hypnosis and
whatnot on my former lives and
previously, I had experienced my
life 11 years before as a
totality from end of beginning
to end. But in this session, my
former lives were coming in, and
they were like, right wrapping
kites, string around the kites
pool, except that what the lies
were like filaments of light,
and just wrapping them around
and around, and suddenly they
seemed to hit a critical mass.
And when they hit a critical
mass, they fused, and when they
fuse, there was an explosion of
light, an extraordinary diamond,
like light, broke out of my
chest, and I was thrown into a
state of consciousness that was
both individual, but a higher
level of individuality than
anything I had ever known. And I
think what I was being shown in
this experience, what I was
being given in this experience,
was a taste of where
reincarnation is taking us.
Reincarnation doesn't just
result in the development of a
little bit better this life, a
little bit better the next life,
acquiring more more moral
insight, more talents, more
this, more that, eventually,
sooner or later, all of our
experiences, all that we have
lived and learned in all of our
different lives, eventually, all
those experiences which we
remember when we die in this you
know, we die, we expand into the
soul. We come back into egoic
awareness. We expand into the
soul, back into egoic awareness,
eventually, sooner or later, all
of our life experience is
integrated as a singular
individuality inside time and
space. We wake up. We wake up to
the cosmic beings that we are,
that we truly are. We no longer
attempted to identify strictly
with our body, with our time,
space body.
From here the work went into the
diamond Luminosity work. But
before I go into that, I need to
backtrack a little bit and talk
about the birth of the future
human. I mentioned that in the
initiation the universe work, I
started having a series of
visions about the evolution of
humanity. Now this sounds
ridiculous at one level, but
it's not ridiculous. From within
the context of Transpersonal
psychology, when you shatter
your individual consciousness,
you don't simply flip into
totality OF ONENESS
consciousness, but you open into
a multi layered experience, a
multi layered universe, and one
of the layers of that universe
is the consciousness of our
species. And when you open to
the consciousness of your
species, it's only natural that
you would get insights into the
growth of this species, where we
came from, where we are and
where we're going. In my
sessions over five years, I was
given repeatedly the same kind
of story, the same story,
different aspects which I
address. In this chapter, I
gathered all the different
visions having to do with the
future of humanity into this
chapter. The first is the
visions of awakening, six
visions describing a profound
awakening of the human psyche
and the human heart, a profound
what I call the Great Awakening,
an awakening of a shift in the
fundamental architecture of the
collective unconscious. A year
and a half later, after those
first series of sessions, I was
taken deep into deep time,
beyond personal deep time, deep
into collective deep time, and I
was taken into what appeared to
be the death and rebirth of our
species in near future. I
experienced this. I didn't
wasn't given any information
about how or when or why, except
that it would seem to be
triggered. There was a global
systems crisis that seemed to be
being triggered by a global
ecological crisis. I was given,
I experienced the fact of this
transformation, and I
experienced, I was given, a lot
of insights into some of the
mechanisms of how we would make
this transition. As quickly as
we need to do it, we have so
little time to make the
transition. And it has to do
with understanding the
collective psyche. It has to do
with understanding that our
collective unconscious is a
field, and that when this field
is hyper stimulated with the
suffering that we are entering
into, it becomes so hyper
stimulated it enters into non
linear or far from equilibrium
conditions, and that there is a
certain structural parallel
between what can happen in a
psychic field when it is pushed
into non linear conditions and
what happens in physical fields
when they are pushed into non
linear conditions. And we can
extrapolate some of the insights
from from physical fields and
understand what might happen in
a psychic field when it is
pushed into non linear
conditions, specifically the
capacity for rapid, accelerated
change, heightened creativity
and The emergence of a higher
self organization. In my
visions, in my sessions, it was
always this is going to happen
faster than anyone can imagine,
faster than you can imagine,
faster than you can imagine. The
pace of our development in the
past was irrelevant to the pace
of our development in the
future, and it has to do with
what's happening at a deep,
collective psychic level. From
here, I went into the diamond
Luminosity work five years of
entering, progressively entering
into a field of consciousness
that was completely empty,
devoid of content and clear,
clear, beyond imagination, just
clear, clear, breathtakingly
luminescent. Buddhism calls this
Dharmakaya, the clear light of
absolute reality, the clear
light from which physical
reality springs. I called it
diamond Luminosity.
My time is running short. I can
only go through so much because
I take comfort that all of this
is in the book, and you'll be
able to go into greater detail
when you see it. I
out of these four sessions, and
I went into this reality only
four times in five years, five
years of work to spend four days
in this condition, the high cost
to pay in between these four.
Sessions, as you might imagine,
there was intense episodes of
purification, more purification,
more purification. Because when
you just to touch this reality
to be able to return to it and
have stable experience in this
reality, you have to purify
yourself of anything in you
which is less than this reality.
The first two entries into the
diamond Luminosity took place in
sessions 45 and 50. And then
after that, we didn't go deeper.
Didn't go deeper into the
diamond Luminosity, but the
diamond Luminosity began to
crunch itself deeper into my
physical body. It went to. It
was as if this light was
restructuring my biology. It was
restructuring my mind, my
emotions, my subtle energy
system, and actually
restructuring my cellular and
that cellular anatomy in ways
that I won't, couldn't begin to
understand, but it was soaking
itself deeper into my physical
presence. And I learned from
these experiences that the
purpose of this work was not
simply to move into
Transcendence. It isn't to go
into some disembodied,
transcendent reality. These
fields are beautiful. They're
magnificent. But the goal of the
work was not Transcendence.
Ultimately, the goal was to
bring this reality deeper into
our physical existence, to let
as much of spiritual reality as
possible enter into our physical
awareness, and to transform our
lives so that we become an
integrated whole, a being that
balances spiritual reality and
access to spirituality and the
magnificent universe which has
been gestated inside spiritual
reality, the reality of time and
space.
At the end, in the very last
year of this work, I was given
one final vision that was the
capstone of everything that had
gone on before. In this final
vision, the universe put me
through the absolute worst,
stripped down process that it
had ever put me through before.
It was just a cascading,
absolute loss of control,
stripped down, dying, dying,
burrowing deeper and deeper and
deeper until eventually it spun
me into deeper, into deep time
than I had ever been before. And
I haven't even tried to explain
what deep time is, but again,
it's in the book, it took me
into a state of consciousness in
which I was able to experience
100,000 years, kind of as a
simultaneous present. I began to
experience time in terms of the
dying of whole life as a
pulsation of death and rebirth
of whole I experienced whole
generations dying every few
seconds, being born and dying
every few seconds, just a
radical expansion of the time
frame this I was given an
experience of what the Buddhist
would call Samsara in The raw
everything in this world, being
born dying, conserving, growing,
integrating being born dying.
And in this context, I was given
three teachings, which I'll just
mention. The first was that it
showed me that human beings are
actually built for speed. We are
built for accelerated evolution,
and it has to do with the fact
that each of our lives are are
so short 100 years, merely 100
years. But underneath this
repeated reincarnation, there is
a gathering of our knowledge, a
gathering of our of our
experience, and periodically,
this gathered knowledge flips
and becomes a new foundation for
all subsequent incarnations. And
from this expanded time horizon
I was I could see that human
beings were actually designed
for accelerated evolution. We
have a tendency to think human
nature. This human nature that
too statically, we have to think
more dynamically, more open
endedly, in terms if we want to
experience ourselves and
experience the human race from
the perspective of the creative
intelligence that's behind it
all the other two experiences
I'll mention was I experienced
the universe as a diamond maker.
I experienced this
reincarnation, all these these,
the cycling of reincarnation.
And I experienced sparks of
diamond light shooting off
periodically into the deep
space, into the. Deep Sky, and I
understood that the universe is
making diamonds, and the
diamonds the distillation of all
of our experience here into
these crystalline, pure forms
that allow us to enter into
dimensions of spiritual reality
that we could never survive in
if we hadn't gone through this
hyper concentration, hyper
accelerated developmental
process, which is taking place
inside time and space. And
lastly, I was given an
experience of the future human,
taken deep and allowed to
experience for a short period of
time the human being that nature
is giving birth to in this long
developmental process, such an
exquisite being just touching it
for only a few minutes. So
helpful. Just totally expanded
my understanding of human
potential and showed us it's
very important, I think, that we
have an understanding, that we
have a vision of where we are
going historically, because as
the shadows darken as we enter
deeper into this historical
crisis that we are entering into
now, as we enter the dark night
of our collective soul. We could
lose hope. We could think that
it's all over. We could think
that we are somehow being
punished for the sins of our
past. We could think that it's
just we're entering into an
extinction event, but really we
are in labor. We have been
gestating for hundreds of 1000s
of years. Nature has been
gestating us. Gestation is a
long process. Birth is a
relatively short process. Labor
is a very, very intense and
painful process, but at the end,
it gives birth to something
wonderful, something new. I
think that's what's happening
historically, after hundreds of
1000s of years, we are entering
into labor, and the crisis that
we are entering at a global
stage is synchronistically
connected to a developmental
crisis that is taking place
inside each one of us. We carry
the entire history of the world,
in our former lives, in our
heart, in our soul, as the
planet is struggling to become
one. In everything that that
involves, we are working to
become one coherent, integrated
soul, so that there is a
relationship between this
building tension in the global
order, and a building tension
inside our psychological order
as we give birth to a new
species on this planet, and as
we give birth to a new center of
consciousness within our own
person. Again, what is important
is not that I had these
experiences, and I could be
wrong on many different levels,
but what I think is important is
that many, many people are
having these experiences, as
Stani Grof has documented. And
what's important is that these
levels of consciousness are
there for all of us to explore.
And again, I do not recommend
that people explore them as I
explore them. I truly don't. I
would not wish anyone to go
through some of the things I
went through in order to enter
these domains. I would be
gentler. I would be use a wider
complement of experiences, of
techniques and technologies. But
they are there, and they are
there for us to explore. There
is this massive information
field which we can enter
suddenly and temporarily, or we
can just sit here and open up
and let it enter us and soak
into our bones. Thank you very
much. Applause.
Unknown: You