Chris Bache: Like a smile,
another side, purification,
purifications unto death in
order to enter that dialog,
Unknown: what do you what do you
think death is?
Chris Bache: Well, as I say in
the book, eventually you come to
a point, if you've gone through
many cycles of death and
rebirth, you come to a point
where the death loses its
meaning because you've learned
from experience that you can
die. You can lose all your
reality reference points,
everything you know yourself to
be can be shattered and
destroyed, but the Phoenix
always rises. You always wake
up. You a changed. You always
awakens in a deeper capacity and
a deeper level of reality. So
from this perspective,
eventually you learn that there
is no such thing as death. There
is only the shedding of one
particular set of parameters
within which awareness operates,
shedding those parameters and
letting consciousness expand to
a deeper experience of reality.
What we usually mean, and I
think death of the physical body
is something very similar what
you go through in an LSD session
deep one that type of death
approximates what happens when
you go through physical death,
the body dies. You lose your
physical reference points.
Consciousness expands into a
deeper and broader universe, but
eventually the very concept of
death loses its meaning in this
respect.
Unknown: Yeah, yeah. It was two
ways I was going to go. Some
I'll come back. I'll come back
to the way I was going to go on
that the grueling impact of that
on like I spoke to somebody. And
in a way, it's existential. It
can be existentially violent, a
psychedelic experience. Yes, is,
and there's moments. I mean, I
think that's a good it's a good
description, existentially
violent, and what's like, and
that, I don't think also, that
you ever get comfortable. It's
not like you suddenly go, Okay,
I've done 50, and this is going
to be no problem, because
there's bigger levels. Is that
fair to
Chris Bache: say? And that I
thought that you would go
through a period of, you know,
Death-Rebirth and purging and
whatnot, and you would get to a
stable place, and all all
entries from that point on would
be clearer and easier. I found
that that's not true, that the
in the universe is infinitely
deep with an infinite number of
levels, and as long as you keep
pushing the outer edges of your
experience, if you're willing to
go farther, the universe will
keep taking you in deeper, and
it always will require some deep
surrender, some death and
rebirth process, to move deeper
into it.
Unknown: And would you when you
say, universe, what? What do
you? What's that to you? What
does what's that word mean to
you?
Chris Bache: Yeah. Well, my
experience is, of course, when
you let go of consciousness at
the physical level, you enter
into a deeper dimension of
consciousness, and then later is
still a deeper dimension, and
still a deeper dimension. And
it's all coherent from top to
bottom, and it is all
fundamentally unified. For me,
it never took a face. It never
showed an identity as such. It
was always open ended and
perpetually fluid and invisible
and yet very deeply felt. So
what do we call this thing? What
do we call this consciousness,
which we dissolve into its
successive levels. Some might
call it the infinite, the
absolute. I call it both of
those things. I call it the
creative intelligence of the
universe. It feels to be the
creative intelligence that's
inside the universe and behind
the universe. Different. Aspects
coming forward at different
times. In the end, in my heart
of hearts, I call it my beloved
because you do once you enter
into it, once you dissolve into
it, once you recover your true
identity within its identity,
then it opens up dimensions of
love within you, and it pours
dimensions of love within you
that it becomes my beloved.
Sometimes I call it the great
expanse, something to suggest
the vastness, its vastness, its
power, its creativity, its
intelligence, and of course,
since compassion is a mark of
oneness, it's inherent oneness,
so that compassion is a
spontaneous manifestation of its
innate oneness.
Unknown: Yeah, it's funny. I
think you called it some an
Indian guru who used the word
the beloved, and was the guy in
England. He would refer to
oneness. So he would refer to
the Beloved. Tony Parsons talk
about unconditional love, that
that it's but not the love that
we would know it's, it's love
beyond conditions beyond it's
not a personal it's the
allowance of all things. Yeah,
Chris Bache: it's, it's a deeper
love than human love, but I
think it is alive in the best of
us when we experience love. But
it is, it is, it's a radical
love. It's a It's the love that
the Dao has for the 10,000
things. You know, it's it is the
love that being has for its own
self, for its own being.
Because, in the end, from its
perspective, all of us and all
of creation is a manifestation
of its being. So how could it
not love itself? And therefore,
how could it not love us?
Unknown: So let's see, can we go
to go this route and see where
it goes? Say the idea of my
beloved and its Who do you think
is describing when you say it's
my who is describing the
beloved? You know this sort of
perspective? Because there is a
perspective that it cannot see
itself, only in reflections, and
it because it is already what's
happening. The Beloved is
already what's happening there.
Yeah, it can't. It can only ever
appear as, yeah, you know where
I'm going with that. Or do you
have your sense? Yeah, I do.
It's very hard to objectify, in
a way, when that objectifying is
almost what is a part of the
Beloved. Is a happening already.
It's fresh already. Yeah, it's
already complete. In other
words, what you're saying there,
whilst we're kind of talking
about experience that you've had
and you've written a book, it's
it gives the impression of being
Once removed, but obviously it's
a part already.
Chris Bache: Yeah, you know, we
have all sorts of ideas and
stories we tell ourselves about
what this totality consciousness
is and isn't, and what it can
know and can't know. And I think
a lot of that is just cultural
scripting. It's our best guess.
It's our best cultural guess,
and our best cultural guess is
not very old. At this juncture,
we've been kind of making these
metaphysical guesses or
intuitions for 5000 years, but
this intelligence is 13.7 plus
billion years in the making and
unfolding, and we're just kind
of getting to the stop place in
our evolution where we can
really begin to engage it. So my
sense is I don't know whether
this intelligence is not self
aware, except through us that
seems kind of outrageously, puts
enormous privilege of place on
us as to be the mirror of the
Divine Eye. Why should we assume
that this intelligence is not
self aware as it unfolds itself
with seeming pointed accuracy
through time and space. So what
I can say it is this, when I
lose my boundaries as Chris
Bache, while I allow myself to
dissolve as Chris Bache and
enter into these deeper layers,
there's many, many layers of
this phenomenon. So some of the
early layers have to do with my
species consciousness, the mind
of the collective unconscious,
the mind of my species. Other
layers have to do with the mind
of our planet, Gaia
consciousness. And there are
multiple layers going right
through species mind, the
archetypal. Line archetypal
dimensions, the root causes of
some of the patterns inside time
and space, the root cause even
of time and space itself, moving
even deeper into dimensions of
oneness, permutations of
oneness, even entering into the
primal void that appears to be
the formlessness out of which
all form emerges with the Big
Bang and subsequently and then
entering beyond even that. And
at each level of entry, entering
into clear and clearer and
clearer states of being, states
of awareness. Now, yeah, that
and so it's hard for me to
imagine that the being or
dimension of being that I have
been in it for hours at a time,
would not also be self aware in
its unfolding. Now it's also
been the case that I've had the
experience that this creative
intelligence, or an aspect of
creative intelligence, met me in
my sessions, took me on a cosmic
tour, you know, in that chapter
initiation in the universe, and
it seemed to want to show me its
work. It seemed especially
pleased to have evolved
consciousness to the point where
some of that consciousness could
come back and be shown what has
actually been being worked on
for billions and billions of
years. So it seems to delight in
being known. But I wouldn't say
necessarily that it didn't know
itself before I knew it. You
know what? I mean. Yeah.
Unknown: And did you get a sense
of, do you still have a sense of
the despite having spent so much
time that, in a way, you're
still only it's impossible. It's
so the vastness, the extra, the
still scraping the surface the
enormity of the all of
everything.
Chris Bache: So this was a major
change in my thinking. It took
place in the 50th session. So So
my background is I did four
years of work. I stopped for six
years, and then I did 10 years
of work. So 14 years of active
work over 20 years. But when I
was entering into the last five
years of work, or those years of
what I call the diamond
Luminosity work, and this was 26
sessions out of 26 sessions,
that's about a third of all the
sessions in the book. Four of
those sessions took me into this
diamond Luminosity, an
unbelievably beautiful,
ecstatic, empty consciousness
that was just clear, just clear
beyond imagination, just so
clear, so hyper clear that once
you touch it, nothing else
matters except returning to it.
Nothing else I had entered in
earlier stages mattered in the
least compared to connecting
with this. And this is what the
Buddhists call, I think the
closest thing I could find is
what they call Dharmakaya. You
know, they have three
dimensions, or three modalities
of existence, Dharmakaya,
sambhogakaya and nirvanakaya,
Dharmakaya being the deepest and
Dharmakaya the absolute, the
light of the clear light of
absolute reality, just kind of
the light out of which existence
emerges. I'm sorry I got so
involved in the description. I
lost track with the the the
original question focus.
Unknown: Well, I think I know
where you're going though,
because we were talking about
the vastness and scraping the
surface, and you said,
Chris Bache: yeah, yeah. So I
was 50 sessions in. I was in the
second of the four diamond
Luminosity sessions. I was as
deep into ecstatic diamond
consciousness as I had ever gone
and would ever go, it was the
deepest penetration in that way.
And toward the end of the
session, I had this experience
where my visual feel flipped 90
degrees. A huge space opened up.
And beyond where I was there was
another reality, worlds upon
worlds beyond me. And there was
a light there, and a beam of
this light hit me, and it
shattered me. And I called the
light the absolute light, just
to give it a differentiating
name from the diamond Luminosity
light. But what it showed me was
that there were worlds and
worlds beyond where I was, as
far beyond where I was as the
diamond Luminosity was beyond
time and space. So that told me
that an idea that I had taken
into this work, that the purpose
of this work was to get to an
end point, an end stage, a
destination to go home some.
Thing like this, that that was
just not an accurate assumption.
You do repeatedly have a sense
of going home. You do enter into
deep, deep experiences of
Homecoming. And for me, the
diamond Luminosity was my actual
practical destination. I did not
go deeper than that. It totally
satisfied me in all respects. I
continued to do the session
work, but for the next 23
sessions, it wasn't going deeper
into the diamond Luminosity, but
it was internalizing diamond
Luminosity, soaking deeper and
deeper into my physical and
psychological being. But it's,
it's an infinite ocean, and I
don't, I gave up completely the
idea of ever getting to the end
of it. I.