Unknown: Announcer, welcome to
the Human Experience podcast,
the only podcast designed to
fuse your left and right brain
hemispheres and feed it the most
entertaining and mentally
engaging topics on the planet.
As we approach our ascent,
please make sure your frontal
temporal and occipital lobes are
in their full upright position
as you take your seat of
consciousness, relax your senses
and allow us to take you on a
journey we are the intimate
strangers. Thank you for
listening.
Ladies and gentlemen, welcome.
We've got an incredible show
planned for you guys this
evening. We are going to be
talking about consciousness,
psychedelics, namely, LSD, the
exploration of consciousness.
Thank you so much for being
here, especially if you're
listening to this on the YouTube
live version. So sit back, grab
a drink and enjoy this
conversation. The human
experience is in session. My
name is Xavier Katana. My guest
for this evening is Dr
Christopher Bache. Dr Bache is a
professor, researcher and author
who has been teaching and
writing about consciousness,
philosophy and religion for more
than 30 years Christopher
received his PhD in philosophy
and religion from Brown
University and went on to be a
professor of religious studies
at young style, young Youngstown
State University. Christopher
has written a number of books,
life cycles, reincarnation, the
web of life, and his latest is
the is LSD and the mind. Of the
universe, diamonds from heaven,
for the most part, which we'll
be covering this evening. Chris,
thank you so much for making
time. Welcome to hxp.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Xavier,
thank you for this conversation.
It's a pleasure to be here.
Unknown: So Chris, I mean, let's
just, let's start this off with,
you know, how you got into this
work? If, if you want to kind of
get into a little bit of your
background, it's, it's an, I
mean, would you say that's an
unusual field to be in?
Chris Bache: It certainly is. I
was, I come from a very
classical, mainstream
background. I was raised in the
Deep South. I went to Notre Dame
and Cambridge and Brown
University. I was a very
standard classical mainstream
education in religious studies.
And shortly after, I started my
teaching career, right? This is
back now. This is in 1978 I just
I was publishing some articles
out of my dissertation, I was
looking for where to take my
research now that my
dissertation was done and I
encountered the work of
Stanislav Grof. Was the foremost
authority on psych integrating
psychedelics into psychotherapy.
His book, realms of the human
unconscious was an eye opener
for me, and in one reading, I
felt like I had found my life's
work. I thought that this work
was extraordinarily important,
not only for psychology, but
very important for philosophy,
understanding that psychedelics,
in this case, LSD, but in
general, psychedelics function
as amplifiers of consciousness.
So they increase the sensitivity
of our mind many times over for
a short period of time, for an
LSD session that's about eight
hours. And by amplifying
consciousness, it gives us an
opportunity to explore
systematically the deeper
dimensions of consciousness and
what we So I saw this, I
thought, this is tremendous.
I've got to, I want to do this.
But of course, psychedelics had
been made illegal in 1970 in
this country, and so I had to
make a difficult choice. What I
decided to do was divide my
life. And so I had what you
might call a daytime job and a
nighttime job. My daytime job, I
was a professor of religious
studies at Jung sound State
University. I did the things
that professors do. I lecture
and go to committee meetings and
publish. And then I and I my
private life. I went into a very
inner, hidden side of my life,
and I began a rigorous process
of using LSD, following
Stanislav Grof protocols, to
explore my own consciousness.
And then when the bottom dropped
out of my own consciousness, I
moved right into a larger field
of conscious. So large. I think
of it as the mind of the
universe,
Unknown: okay? And that's, you
know, that's where we get into,
sort of the subtitle of your
book, The primary focus of your
book, you know, I really want to
know, did you at any point when
you were beginning the research?
Did you feel as if you know
that? I mean, this is, this is
very much taboo in our society.
And did you feel at any point
that your tenure would be
threatened? Did you feel that
your job would be threatened?
Did you feel like coming out
with this information would risk
your career in any way?
Chris Bache: Absolutely, I think
that was a reasonable assertion.
I knew that I was breaking the
law in order to do this work. I
knew that they would come a
time, as there is now, that we
would reclaim these important
substances. But my entire Well,
I knew that we would come back
around to these substances, but
I couldn't wait until we did. I
knew that if I if this became
public knowledge, if I was too
public about this, I would
probably lose my job. And I love
teaching. I love being with the
students in the classroom. I
love being an academic, and so I
just kept this work private. My
you know, close colleagues in
the department knew, but I kept
it private. I'd never talked to
my students about it. I did not
become in any way a public
figure. I mean, this was between
I did 73 high dose LSD sessions,
following Stanislav Grof
protocol for high dose
psychedelic sessions between
1979 and 1999 Okay, so this is,
this is a between when I was 30
and 50, and I'm 70 now. So this
book, I've spent 20 years
integrating and digesting these
experiences before producing
this book.
Unknown: Okay, I mean, that's,
that's quite a range of time and
a tremendous amount of sessions
to to have with this compound.
Was there a reason that you
selected LSD, you know, namely,
specifically, why not another
substance? Why not DMT,
Psilocybin? Why not Ayahuasca?
Chris Bache: Well, you have to
go back to 1978 and think about
the landscape then Ayahuasca was
this was before the era of
Ayahuasca. Psilocybin mushrooms
were around. It was really
before the era of DMT. But more
importantly, my work really was
founded on Stanislav Grof work
and most of Stan's work, his
early work, was basically done
with LSD, and I trusted what I
saw in his, in his research. So
basically, I chose to work with
the with his, with this
substance, LSD. After I stopped
my sessions, I've had
experiences with other
psychedelics, you know,
Psilocybin, DMT and Ayahuasca.
But my prime, what I consider my
primary work, the core work,
that's the subject of my
philosophical reflections, are
these 73 LSD sessions.
Unknown: Okay, I mean, I find it
intriguing, because I think
Congress passed, you know, into
law that, you know, banning LSD,
I think that went into effect
1967 right? Yeah.
Chris Bache: Well, there were a
series of laws, basically, 67
6970 basically, is a nice,
convenient, easy date for that
was the control Substances Act
that was passed, okay?
Unknown: And I mean, there in
your book, you talk about
certain synchronicities that
started to happen in your world.
Can you talk a little bit about
that that encouraged you to
carry out these experiments?
Because even though you did them
in secret, I mean, did you do
you have, did you have a plan
that you were going to release
this sort of book later?
Chris Bache: I always assume
that there would come a time,
and this became a stronger
conviction, if the work
continued, that there would come
a time when I would bring this
work forward to the world. But I
knew that it could not be while
I was an academic, and I it
could not be while I was still
subject to the statute of
limitations for this work. So it
was only after I retired from
the university and after I was
past the statute of limit of
limitations that I felt
comfortable speaking about this
makes sense. But in the work
itself, I always sort of saw
myself one way or another sooner
or later, finding a way to bring
the core content of these
sessions to others. Because I'm
a philosopher. I was trained to
ask large questions. I was
trained I really wanted to
answer the type ask the type of
questions that you know we.
Keeps us up late at night when
we're thinking about the meaning
of existence, the purpose of
things, and whether there is a
purpose of things, and is there
an intelligence operating deep
in this superstructure and
substructure of the universe?
And this was an opportunity to
explore those questions on an
experiential basis, and I became
quickly convinced in this work,
that the most important
contributions to my field in the
near future, which is philosophy
of religion, would be done by
people who are working not out
of a theoretical basis, but they
would be working out of an
experiential basis.
Unknown: Sure. So I'm not sure
if you you answered my question
regarding the synchronicities,
if you could just touch on that.
Chris Bache: Kind of jumps ahead
in the storyline a bit. Okay, it
wasn't. I did not. I was not
aware of any particular
synchronicities going into the
work. But if I, I'll just tag
this and maybe we'll come back
around to it later. Okay, as my
work deepened over the course of
those 20 years. Even though my
students never knew I was doing
this work, I found that some of
my students were being activated
in their own personal lives by
my psychedelic work. There was a
spillover of consciousness
transformation that began in my
sessions, but because
consciousness is not a private
phenomenon, because
consciousness is in essentially
the deeper levels of
consciousness are
boundarylessness. They're
boundaryless. The impact of my
sessions began to unroll beyond
my personal life, and that's
that led me to do some serious
thinking and research on how to
continue to do my work, while
also taking care of my students
and continuing my work as a
professor writing the heavy
normal life. And that led to
writing the book The living
classroom, which is about fields
of consciousness in group
settings. And in that book, I
don't even mention psychedelics,
because the issue is not
psychedelics. The issue is the
nature of consciousness and what
happens when people come
together and focus their
intention and sustained
exercises for periods of months
and years.
Unknown: I love that. I love
that I'm feeling this resonance
in your words, which I'm really
enjoying. So I mean, we
mentioned that these compounds
amplify consciousness in a way
you said your words. So, you
know, I want to know what were
the some of the questions that
you were asking yourself, what
were the questions that you
wanted answers to?
Chris Bache: Well, I got into
this again. We're thinking late
70s, because I was interested in
enlightenment, and I had been
meditating for a number of
years, and I had encountered the
kind of blocks that people
typically encounter in the early
years of sitting practice, and I
thought that if I could do some
sessions and engage my
unconscious and confront
whatever blocks were waiting for
me in my unconscious, it would
basically speed the process of
my own spiritual realization
that model of individual
transformation is a model that
was shattered along the way in
this work, because within three
years, I was getting drawn into
vast, intense purification
processes that involved 1000s,
10s of 1000s, hundreds of 1000s
of people. I got into a whole
series of experiences for years
that were just far too large and
far too intense to understand
them in terms of some type of
healing or clarification or
realization of one's personal
transformation. I began to
understand that in these deep,
deep, highly, highly energized
states of consciousness, if you
focus in them in a very specific
way, you actually can begin to
impact or heal some portion of
the collective unconscious.
Unknown: Okay, okay, please
continue.
Chris Bache: Well, let me back
up and a little bit about
method. Stan Grof clearly
distinguishes between low dose
psycholytic therapy and high
dose psychedelic therapy. Low
dose psyche lytic therapy,
usually 5200 micrograms, is a
process of peeling the
unconscious layer by layer,
multiple sessions gradually
unfolding the unconscious and
helping heal whatever issues are
lurking in the unconscious.
Psychedelic high dose therapy is
very different. And it in the
early years in the Spring Grove
Hospital, the agenda was to try
working with a patient
population of people who had
cancer or had terminal illness.
They were not they were not
trying to heal them. These
people were going to die. They
basically were trying to blast
through all the layers of the
personal unconscious and trigger
an experience of an encounter
with the universe that would
give them some kind of glimpse
of where they were going when
they died. They basically were
trying to trigger a near death
episode experience in these
subjects. It was a very
interesting and a very
successful project. So I came
along later and I thought, well,
it's like if LSD can be used in
high Oh, their protocol was
limited to three sessions, no
more than three sessions. Okay,
so I thought, if you can do it
safely three times, and you can
do it safely more times. So I
chose, partly for matters of
efficiency, a number of
different things I discussed in
the book, but I chose to work
after about three sessions, to
work with very high doses of
LSD. And I worked at 500 to 600
micrograms consistently for
those 20 years now, the state of
arousal, the state of
amplification, when you're
working with doses of LSD that
high, plus when you completely
internalize the experience. So
let me back up for a minute.
We're talking about sessions.
We're not talking about
tripping. Never gone to a
concert on acid, never stayed up
all night talking with my
friends. Okay, the days when I
did these sessions, I was
totally isolated from the world.
I was working with the sitter
who kept took care of me. I was
lying down with eye shades and
earphones, a very, very
carefully curated playlist. And
what you do is, when you're when
your consciousness becomes
hyper, amplified like this, if
you focus it internally, if you
really create conditions where
you do not engage the world, but
you engage just your mind. A
series of things began to
percolate, and you confront
deeper and deeper levels of your
consciousness when you are
working with very high doses of
LSD like this eventually, in a
relatively short period of time,
after 10 or 15 sessions, you're
just blowing your consciousness
far, far out into the universe
and then slowly gathering it
back in at the end of the day,
and then making a detailed
record of your experience within
24 hours. That's the method to
open up consciousness experience
the universe as cleanly, or
experience whatever it is as
cleanly and clearly as you can,
with no distortions and no
complications. Come back and
then write it down and then
analyze your experience. Keep
track of your experience. And if
you do this, basically, there is
a conversation that takes place
with the universe, or a
deepening communion that takes
place with the universe. You are
initiated, systematically, step
by step, into a deeper
experience, not only of your own
mind, but into this larger mind,
which is the context and
surround mind which underpins
your mind.
Unknown: Okay, okay, so this was
just to, just to restate what
you just mentioned, was you
established this protocol for
yourself with a therapeutic
protocol to engage high,
extremely high doses of LSD, and
you purposely set up ways where
you would disconnect as much as
possible from contact with the
outside world civilization to
better understand these
questions you were asking, or
better understand The
information that you were
receiving. Studying the universe
Chris Bache: understand, wanted
to understand my own
consciousness, and through that,
to understand the nature of
reality itself. Stan's early
work gave me evidence that one
could have not only knowledge of
one's own unconscious, but you
can have knowledge of the mind
of the universe, or the mind of
the cosmos, or, some would say,
the mind of God. So I was
interested in learning as much
about the universe as I could,
and I also wanted to know the
truth about my own being. What
was my being? Because I was a
professor of religious studies,
and because I taught courses in
comparative mysticism. I knew
about the spiritual traditions
of the world. I knew what the
cosmology were of our deepest
mystical traditions, and I sort
of I kept that all on the maybe
table, and I just set out to see
what I could learn using this
protocol.
Unknown: Yeah, so I mean, what
was it? What did you find?
Chris Bache: Well, that's not an
easy, sure question to answer,
because these experiences are
extremely complicated. They have
many layers and layers to them,
and it takes years literally to
you mean you understand them
when you have them, but it takes
years to really unpack the
deeper themes and the
correlations that emerge over
this course of time, how to,
where to what did I learn? I
hmm,
Unknown: was there something
that you know sparked some sort
of realization for you, as far
as why we're here? You know,
what our purpose is, our
connection to this reality, what
happens when we die? I mean,
what was, what was the lesson
you
Chris Bache: think, yes to all
of those things you basically, I
mean, it's, this is one of those
things where, I mean, I'm a
professor, and I like to do
things in an organized fashion,
and that means starting in the
beginning and laying it down,
phase by phase by phase. If I
jump into the end stages or the
later stages without covering
the earlier stages, it'll sound
very ungrounded. It'll sound
very, you know, druggie, you
know, psychedelic kind of
conversation. And that wasn't
the nature of my experience. And
so I'm kind of hesitant to sort
of get to the conclusions too
fast, basically,
methodologically, here's how I
understand it. When you go into
these hyper states, if you were
willing to confront Honestly,
even courageously, whatever
emerges, you'll go through a
series of death and rebirth
processes, as I have looked back
over all of my accessions, over
the over the 20 years that I did
them, I basically identified
five layers, or five cycles of
the Death-Rebirth process. It
took me into different levels of
consciousness. The first layer
is the death of self, where you
basically go through ego death,
and you go through the death of
your time, space, identity, the
identity that we all walk around
in, the identity that basically
emerges from birth to death.
After that, I entered into a
level where the dynamics were
all larger than private self.
The dynamics for the dynamics of
the collective mind. I entered
into a domain that I call the
ocean of suffering. Entered into
an experience, a year's worth of
experiences, where I experienced
my entire life, from start to
finish, beginning to end as a
complete now, all past, present
and future collapsed into it.
Now I went from there into a
series of deep, systematic kind
of instruction. I was given a
course in cosmology. 101, I You
can't control these experiences.
I mean, I could set my
intentions, but when you're
working with doses this high,
it's impossible to control these
experiences. The best thing to
do is completely surrender, let
it take you wherever it wants to
take you, and where it will take
you is into these deeper, deeper
levels, where you have to allow
yourself to surrender, over and
over again, and eventually to go
through the series of
Death-Rebirth processes. So
after death of self, two years
of work at the collective mind.
Another two years working at
what I called archetypal mind,
the greater real of archetypal
reality, beyond that, the level
of causal oneness, where you
enter into a completely
different experiential reality
where all the dualities that we
conventionally recognize as part
of time and space are dissolved.
And then after that, the last
five years of my work, I entered
into a domain that I call the
diamond Luminosity work. This is
what Buddhism calls Dharmakaya,
the clear light of absolute
reality, an extra ordinary,
subtle, subtle, refined, clear,
clear dimensions of
consciousness. In the process of
going through all of these
levels, the sessions gave me
many, many experiences, of many
experiences when I hesitate to
use language of the Divine
because the language of God or
the divine has so many
culturally imported limitations
that I understand I'm. Not
comfortable with, but it is the
closest we have in our culture
to really speak about these
things. I talk about the
creative intelligence of the
universe. One is, I mean, you're
basically taken deep into,
dissolved into the intelligence
of the universe. So naturally,
you have, I had many sessions,
many teachings around what we're
here for, what's going on, what
is our relationship to the
universe, and very importantly,
lots of experiences having to do
with human evolution, and
particularly the phase of
evolutionary challenge that
humanity is facing right here,
right now, what is happening in
our time in history? This came
to be one of the most consistent
and dominant and recurring
themes of the book. And there's
a chapter in the book called The
Birth of the future human. So
lots and lots of levels, what
happens to us when we die?
Certainly, one can go into the
realms of what the Tibetan
tradition, Buddhism tradition
would call the Bardo dimensions
you go when you die. And you can
also, if you work really hard
and consistently, go into what
the Bush called extra Samsara
reality, or reality beyond all
the cycles of reincarnation, all
the cycles of existence, going
into that reality that lies well
beyond the incarnated domains.
So there's lots of insights that
emerged in this work. And what
I've done in this book is I
simply have taken the reader in
as efficiently as I can,
starting in the beginning of the
work, breaking it down, chapter
by chapter, year by year, where
I went, what happened, what what
emerged, and I really well, I
just lay it out like that as
transparently as I can.
Unknown: I mean, it sounds
phenomenal, right? I mean, and
you seem to have the language
very clear, which, which I find
incredibly important when
discussing these types of
experiences, it seems like
you're very cautious with your
verbiage, which I respect very
much. You know? What I'm curious
about is to know how you worked,
the integration aspect of it.
You talk about something called
psychic inflation in the book. I
mean, how did you maintain
because it is important to have
this sort of critical
discernment that you used, and I
think it would encourage others
to when they're in these
experiences, to also have that
as well, because sometimes I
hear about people that
experience a sort of
depersonalization when they
experience something so
Transcendence, so profound, it's
difficult to integrate, it's
difficult to come back and and
apply that In a practical way to
your understanding of of life,
reality?
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah, it is.
And I think integration is it
isn't a topic that's being given
more attention now. I don't
think it's been given nearly
enough attention. There is an
anthology out in England later
this year, 2020, devoted
specifically just to
integration. First, first, the
most important danger of working
in these states is psychic
inflation. We can have this
experience. We can have dramatic
experiences, extra ordinarily
deep experiences. And we can
think sometimes that by having
these experiences, we become a
deep person, but that's really a
fool's delusion. You have to
really, really keep yourself
grounded. You go into these
states for a few hours, you come
back, you write them down, then
you get back to your nine to
five job, you get back to your
children, you get back to your
world response responsibilities,
and you first, you remember your
experiences, and then you think
about them, and you try to
understand them, and you put
into practice, because you put
into practice the teachings and
the values that you were given
You were shown to me, the two
critical features for using
these states of consciousness in
a productive way that leads to
deep transformation is one,
courage, willingness to confront
the hard experiences that rise
in these experiences,
confronting the shadow and more
And more than that. And
secondly, grounding, really,
really grounding, and that means
grounding them in other sets of
spiritual practices, grounding
them in a daily meditation
practice, grounding them in care
for the body. And that's really
important, because usually we
describe these states as states
of consciousness, but. They are
also states of body. They have
profound effects on your body,
both your physical system and
your subtle energy system. And
so it's really important to take
care of your body, take care of
your diet, to take care of your
lifestyle. Because if these
states are opening you into
increasingly deep states of
oneness, and if your lifestyle
is violating oneness, you know,
if it's not a lifestyle of
compassion, if it's not a
lifestyle of service, and you're
living in one way in your daily
life and in your sessions,
you're going into a different
way. And you know you're either
going to neutralize your
sessions by your daily life, or
you're going to kind of tear
yourself apart and become as a
kind of spiritual schizophrenia
that can sometimes result so
really staying very, very
grounded in the world. And to
me, this was really strongly
from two things for me, my
teaching, because wherever I was
on Saturday, on Monday, I was
back in my classroom, doing my
teaching. And the second thing
was my family by marriage and my
children really, really keeping
me grounded.
Unknown: I mean, were there
certain protocols that you use
for grounding specifically? I
mean, was there, you know, a set
sort of amount of things that
you did every day after your
sessions. What I mean? How did
you ground yourself better,
other than just kind of a
cursory look at, you know,
maintain your relationships and
and accountability to yourself,
how did you like? Were there
some practical things that you
did as far as grounding well?
Chris Bache: Once again, because
I because of what I do for a
living, I knew a fair amount
about Shamanism. I knew about
mystical spiritual tradition, so
I understood the practices that
come out of that tradition. I
had a good grounding in Western
religious thought, and I did a
lot of teaching in Eastern
religious thought, so I had that
background to draw upon. But
basically, you know, it's not
that dissimilar from what
happens if you go on a two week
retreat, you know, meditation
retreat, you're with the
teacher, and you go out in the
woods, or, you know, you're in a
retreat center for two weeks,
you move into a state of
consciousness, and then when you
come back, it's often grinding
to come back and engage traffic
jams and you know, the regular
physical world. It's the same
thing that happens in the LSD
session. It's just that you get
into it deeper and faster, and
you come back faster. But the
basic process of holding still,
absorbing these experiences,
taking them deeply into your
mind and into your body, you
know that's that's kind of
shared by all spiritual
practices. So practically, I
think that the deeper you want
to go in Non-ordinary states of
consciousness using
psychedelics, the more important
it is to have a daily spiritual
practice. And for me, this meant
a meditation practice, also a
light yoga practice to helping
take care of the body. I was
helped in this in that my sitter
was my wife. She is a clinical
psychologist, Carl, and she was,
she is a very serious spiritual
practitioner, Kuhn, whose
practice I respect a great deal.
She never did a psychedelic
session. She was a sitter for
all of my sessions. Never did
one herself, because they did
not call to her. They you know,
she was basically a meditating
person, and she found what she
needed on the meditation
cushion. And she really helped
kept keep me grounded during all
these years when I was jumping
out and exploring different
dimensions of the Universe, she
really kept reminding me What's
important is not what happens on
the day of a session. What's
important is what you can do the
day after a session. So that
really is that really calls it.
You really have to integrate
these experiences into your
daily lifestyle. And that takes
practice. I mean, it takes self
clarification, critical self
examination. It takes. There's a
social dimension, a moral
dimension of compassion and
equality, you know, but these
are traditionally recognized in
all traditional spiritual
practices, yeah, and it's
essentially the same.
Unknown: I think it's so
important, because when you're
unraveling the aspects of the
psyche in this way, can be very
dangerous. I mean, as you said
that, you know, there was never
a time where you kind of you
dosed and then hung out with
friends. There was never a time
where you dosed and went out to
a concert. So you. Know, for
you, it was a very deliberate
intention to connect with
yourself and explore
consciousness, to ask these,
these larger questions, but you
know, specifically, keep it into
in this controlled environment,
controlled setting,
Chris Bache: yeah, and in that
controlled setting, of course,
the most important thing is you
have to ask yourself at the
beginning of every day every
session, are you ready to die?
Are you ready to give it all up?
And because you confront, you go
through many, many deaths in
this process. You know you don't
die physically, but you go
through death processes that are
so deep you think you're dying
physically. And then you go
through processes where to put
this on again. I don't want to
jump in too deep, too fast, but
you go through processes where
the death agonies are not
personal. The death agonies
really are species wide, and you
go through processes when you're
moving into archetypal reality
and then moving out of
archetypal reality, you're
dealing with orders of magnitude
that are really hard to relate
to anything on earth.
Unknown: Let's do so. Let's
define archetypal reality. Sorry
to interrupt you.
Chris Bache: Yeah, well,
archetype of reality that the
two figures that come to mind
most are Plato and Carl Jung in
his work on the collective
unconscious. And so Plato's
ideas that basically there is a
reality behind the physical
world which informs and
organizes the fundamental
structures of the physical
world. It's a it's an order
beyond that, beyond physical
reality. And Carl Jung, of
course, in talking about
archetypes and the collective
unconscious, he's talking about
the way, the idea that there is
a collective mind, which is the
soup within which our individual
mind floats, so that all of our
thinking and feeling and
processing is contextualized
within a species mind, within a
collective unconscious of the
species. When I went into
archetype of reality, I had
experiences on both levels, on
both the high levels, kind of a
quasi platonic level, where I
encountered beings of such
magnitude I could not wrap my
mind around them. I mean,
there's just vast beings that I
knew were the beings responsible
for creating space time and for
in sort of infusing or growing
the order that's emerging in
space time. But they were so
vast and in such a different
order of reality, I could not
give them firm description. I
describe what I what I
experienced in the book, but
they don't lend themselves. And
I describe this as a quasi
platonic sense, because the
archetypes that I experienced
were not Plato's eternal ideas
in the minds of an unchanging,
infinite consciousness. My
experience was that the
archetypes, these deep, deep
archetypes, were living
structures. They were living
entities. They were, they were,
I hesitated to call them
entities, because they're like
Galaxy size. I mean, they're
vast dimensions, but they're
living. They're dynamic. They
change very slowly, relative to
us, inside time and space. But
they still change. They evolve,
they grow. Likewise, when I went
into sort of a lower level of
archetype of reality, the
collective unconscious of
humanity, the more quasi Jung
Ian level, as I didn't
experience archetypes, the way
Jung describes it, but I
experienced over and over again,
the mind of the human species as
a living, integrated whole. And
I had many experiences where I
experienced all of our
individual minds as nodes, as
fractal nodes within the larger
landscape of consciousness, and
I was shown how our individual
consciousness interacts in
complex ways with this larger
species mind. Now, when you
here's another little, just a
footnote, or in a way, every
level deeper into a deeper level
of consciousness is a step into
a higher level of energy. So
when you shift from one level of
consciousness into a deeper
level of consciousness, you have
to learn how to manage a much,
much higher level of energy. And
so every time you go. Go into a
deeper level, and you know, I'm
just describing five or six
different levels, you go through
intense purification processes.
Otherwise, if you go into these
levels and you're not
acclimated, you haven't done
your homework and you haven't
been able to acclimate your
energy to this very, very, very
intense energy levels, then your
experiences there will be
fragmented. They'll be
incoherent. You won't be they
won't make as much sense to you,
and you won't be able to bring
them back clearly. But if you go
back to these levels again and
again and again, and you submit
to the purification processes
and the Death-Rebirth processes,
then you basically acclimate so
that when you go into these
states, you learn how to stay
conscious in levels of
consciousness that previously
just swallowed you whole. Okay,
wow. And you do it in a
consistent fashion. You then
break through into deeper and
deeper levels. But every time
you break through, you have to
go through more purification
processes, more Death-Rebirth
processes, just in order to stay
clear, to establish clarity at
these levels.
Unknown: Okay, so I'm really
enjoying everything that you're
saying, Chris. So you know, I
want to, I want to inject a
little bit of my own personal
experience. I, you know, I've
only had a handful of LSD
sessions, but Ayahuasca, for me,
is a big part of my life. I take
it in a highly controlled
setting with instructed shamans
and the the state in which
you're describing, and I do my
best to, you know, regard it in
as skeptically as I can and as
critically as I can, and I've
definitely had that experience
of encountering an intelligence
that I can't explain or I mean,
and it's very difficult to
understand kind of what it's
trying to show me, but when,
when I look at at it in the
perspective that you just
mentioned, that it's a
purification protocol, that it's
it's a it's a refining of your
yourself, of your own
consciousness, to bring you to a
point in which you can sort of
understand the larger reality
that fits into a puzzle piece
for me?
Chris Bache: Yeah, absolutely.
Ayahuasca is a beautiful
medicine, an extra ordinary
medicine. If I were starting
this whole sequence over again,
first of all, I would not do it
the way I did it. I would not
work so consistently in the
sustained fashion in high dose
LSD sessions, I just wouldn't do
it. I'd do it differently. I'd
balance low and high dose
sessions. I'd also balance LSD
with Ayahuasca sessions and
Psilocybin sessions. Because
Psilocybin and Ayahuasca are
more kind of body grounded
psychedelic experiences. LSD
tends to be a high ceiling. It
tends to push the high cosmic,
logical ceiling. And so
balancing those, I think, give
you overall, a better trajectory
in your experiences. But
Ayahuasca is an extra ordinary
teacher. And you know people who
do Ayahuasca sessions seriously,
conscientiously, you don't have
to be convinced that there is an
intelligence communicating to
you in these sessions, because
it's just so clearly that you
engage levels of intelligence
that know you, that look at you,
that see you, and that help you
unearth those things which are
holding you back and showing you
truths of existence that lie
outside your normal state of
consciousness. But once you see
them, then things begin to make
sense to you. Make more sense,
and you begin to understand what
some of the great spiritual
teachers have been saying and
the great saints of our
different traditions have been
saying for hundreds of years,
it's a living intelligence. You
know, that's really that's why,
in our universe, we now have an
approximate idea of just how
vast our universe is. Okay? So
let's just temporarily imagine
that the unit the universe has a
mind, that there is a mind of
the universe. And then imagine
if you were going to become one
with that mind. You really want
to do that. I mean, that's an
extra ordinary. Imagine being
one with every life form, just
on our planet, let alone our
galaxy. It's just vast, vast,
huge energy dimensions here. And
so what these substances do is
open us up and allow these
larger layers of mind with
beings that are part. Part of
that allow them into our
awareness and begin to interact
with them, have a communion with
them, to have a conversation
with them, to have an
interaction with them. And if we
do this in a sustained fashion,
if we do it a little at a
certain level, then we have a
little bit of a communion. Can
teach us some very important
things about ourselves and
about, you know, it can give us
an understanding of what happens
to us when we die. But if we go
deeper and go deeper and go
deeper, we engage this
consciousness, these this
infinite consciousness at deeper
and deeper levels, until
eventually, you know, all form
is left behind. One moves into
domains of what traditionally
call the primal void or
formlessness, and then into the
domain of light, this absolute,
crystalline, clear light.
Unknown: I have so many
questions. Okay, so, Chris,
we're running out of time. So,
you know, I want to know, Chris,
let's many of the people that
are gonna be listening to the
show. I know already that. You
know perhaps they're not gonna
have access to LSD or Ayahuasca
or any of these compounds. Is it
possible to reach these states
through meditation, through
inner work?
Chris Bache: Absolutely,
absolutely. I mean, the
cosmology that emerges, I think,
on this work is not a new
cosmology. It's the same
cosmology we see emerging in the
very deepest. And of course,
there are many levels of
mystical tradition, but in the
very deepest, the highest levels
of teaching, the cosmology that
emerges in psychedelic states is
the same cosmic these are, this
is simply an amplifier of
consciousness. So it's
consciousness that does the
work. It's not that psychedelics
are giving you experiences.
Psychedelics amplify your
consciousness. So naturally,
anything that you experience in
that state will find corollaries
to experiences that emerge with
just meditative experiences.
Having said that these
experiences can become so deep
and so profound, I mean, you
don't usually transcend time
when you're even if you have a
regular and consistent
meditation practice, and you
don't transcend time to go into
the future, into future time,
and you don't necessarily go
back to the beginning before the
Big Bang to experience the
context out of which the Big
Bang emerged. I mean, so on the
one hand, yes, you can
experience these things with
just meditation, absolutely. On
the other hand, some of these
experiences are so radical that
they only show up in the very,
very most subtle spiritual
traditions where they become
comfortable with the things that
I'm saying, talking about
experiencing future time, so on
and so forth.
Unknown: Okay, okay, fair
enough. So I want to move back
into gear of where we were going
with, with where you stopped,
diamond, Luminosity. Let's
address that. I mean, this is,
this is a part of your book that
you, you talk about, and I'm
very curious to sort of hear
your, your first hand account of
what is diamond Luminosity. How
did you engage this? How did you
get to this point? Would you
call it the final point? Would
you call it reaching this state
of oneness with source?
Chris Bache: Or, yeah, when this
came earlier than diamond
Luminosity, okay, this is, this
is, you know, hard to put this
in short, succinct form. When I
did this work. I was, I was 15
years in the work. First, let me
mention, I did four years of the
work. I stopped for six years
for reasons that are in the
book, and then I resumed and did
a very intense 10 years. So even
though it spread over 20 years,
it was actually 14 years of
intense work. So I'm about
halfway through the second
that's 10 year period. And I
had, you know, gone through ego
death. I'd gone through the
ocean of suffering, done a lot
of work at the collective level.
I had gone through archetype of
reality, and then I went came
into a year of just jaw
dropping, extra ordinary
spiritual experiences of
Shunyata, emptiness, the oneness
of existence, primordial void, a
variety of experiences that I
talk about in a book called the
benediction of blessings. By the
time I was done with that, I
felt absolutely incomplete.
Completely existentially
satisfied. You know, there was
work that I had been asked to do
on behalf of others, and I had
done it voluntarily, and the
universe had rewarded me with
just extra ordinary blessings of
experience. I felt completely
content, but there was still
five years of work to go when
you go through this series of
Death-Rebirth experiences, many
people experience it. When they
come through a Death-Rebirth
experience, they encounter
light. It's very common. One
experiences different orders of
light. And this happened for me
too. There were many experiences
of light. Through those years
that I talked about what
happened after the experiences
of oneness, of permutations of
oneness and the primal void, I
went through yet another series
of Death-Rebirth experiences,
which brought me into a quality
of consciousness that was beyond
individual consciousness, beyond
the species mind, beyond even
ONENESS consciousness. It was
basically to be a hyper, hyper,
clear, incredibly. It was light,
but but a particular quality of
light. When I use the word
diamond Luminosity, I'm not
using simply a colorful metaphor
to describe the light. I'm
trying to describe a particular
quality of light, hyper, hyper
clear. It's just the Buddhist to
write to touch it once undoes
1000s of years of wandering lost
in Samsara. It's just so clear,
so pure. And in the last five
years of my work, over 26
sessions, I made contact with
this diamond Luminosity four
times and only four times. All
right. So for me, the recession
is 45 5060, and 66 very specific
days in between those four
times, tremendous kind of
purification, tremendous
detoxification in order to be
able to come back into this
territory. This light how to
describe it. Once I touched it
in the 45th session, then it
became the sole agenda of my
work to return to it. There was
nothing that I had touched in
any of the other levels of
consciousness interested me at
all compared to returning to
this light. I think it's very
similar to the light that some
people when they have near death
experiences, when they enter the
light. It's something like that.
It's on the order of that kind
of experience. It's in many ways
contentless in lower levels of
consciousness. I had many
experiences of being taken on a
tour of the universe and being
shown this, and being shown
that, how this works and that
works. But when you move into
the diamond Luminosity, or
again, what Buddhism calls
Dharmakaya, the domain of
Dharmakaya. It's, it's
absolutely contentless. It's not
about it's not about content.
It's not about things. It's not
about the dynamics. It's, it's
the quality of consciousness
itself. It's, it's the matrix
within which time and space
emerges. It's the light that
infuses all time, space reality
and receives all time. Space
reality at the end of our
lifetime.
Unknown: I mean, it's such a
profound state of being. And you
know, like I said, I've said
many times, I truly, sincerely
appreciate the way in which
you're explaining it, and it
really does sound you know that
it was resounding for you and
changed you. You know, forever
was there? You know, was there
something that you felt, that
you left behind or that you
should have done, because I know
there was a point that you
decided to stop. And yeah, I'm
wondering, you know, what pushed
you up against that decision to
stop? Yeah? And if there was a
sort of catalyst, yeah?
Chris Bache: Well, I stopped for
two reasons, as I explained in
the book, I stopped because of
pain and because of heartache.
The pain was when you move into
the states of consciousness this
large. And this intense, it
activates very, very powerful
waves of energy that move
through your body. And my subtle
energy system, you know, what
the Indians call Prana, and the
Chinese would call Qi, my subtle
energy system, basically, was so
hyper stimulated, was so hyper
aroused that even though I had
done lots and lots of spiritual
practice specifically to work
with my subtle energy system, I
was basically plunging myself
into the furnace of creation so
many times and so deeply that my
subtle energy system was having
trouble managing the flows of
energy. I mean, I could manage
it all fine on a day to day,
month to month basis, but
cumulatively, I was in a state
of chronic uncomfortableness. I
was uncomfortable in my body,
and I knew that it was time for
me to stop, to let my body cool
down, to really focus on
integrating experiences that I
had had, rather than plunging
into still deeper experiences.
Remind me to come back to it's
an infinite progression. Just
remembering, I wanted to say
this, you don't get to an end
point. It's an infinite
progression. But the second
reason I stopped, and the
primary reason was heartache.
Basically, when you when, I'll
just keep it personal, going
into such hyper, clear, hyper
Transcendence states where you
were dissolved into light, you
are light. You are dissolved
into the crystalline body of the
Divine coming back into time
space became just too painful
for me. It became I was
basically it became too painful
for me to keep going back and
forth and back and forth, I
eventually decided. I realized
it was time for me to stop. It
was time for me to finish
digesting everything that I had
had been given, and I just
couldn't take the heartache of
going into the Luminosity
anymore
Unknown: because you were
leaving or,
Chris Bache: well, no, I mean, I
knew I was leaving, yeah, at the
end. I mean, at the very end, I
knew I was leaving. I knew that
I would not that there would be
no time in the rest of my life
when I would ever be this
absorbed so intimately into the
universe, because I could not
take a massive dose of LSD and
get into that space today, it
takes years and years of
sustained work to build up the
momentum, to build up the energy
to crack into these states of
consciousness so that I knew
when I was leaving. I knew I was
leaving for the rest of my life,
and I basically made a deal with
the universe. Should Never bring
me back until I can stay and
that's when I really that's when
my sessions really did end. Wow.
Now the thing about it open
ended when I was deep in the
diamond diamond Luminosity work.
I was halfway through that five
year period, and I got as deep
into the Luminosity as I ever
went. It was the 50th session,
so I was in an extremely clear,
really, really special place.
Right when I was in it, my
visual field pivoted 90 degrees,
and I saw reality Far, Far in
the distance. And the light of
that reality hit me, and it hit
me like a lightning bolt, and it
just shattered me. It just
completely transfixed me. And so
I called it the absolute light,
just to give it a name, but I
knew that there was a reality as
far beyond the diamond
Luminosity as the diamond
Luminosity was beyond space
time, and that's when I came to
understand that it's an infinite
progression. Because, like many
people, I had assumed that there
was an end to this journey. You
become one with God, or you
enter into the primal, meta,
cosmic void. And I had
experienced oneness with God.
And I learned that there were
many degrees and levels and
permutations of oneness. And I
experienced, had experienced the
void, and I learned there were
even permutations of the void.
But I always assume that there
was an end point. You would
reach a point, and it would be
absolutely you had reached your
destination. Right now for me
personally, the diamond
Luminosity was my end point. It
was my destination. It filled as
many experiences had been with
an absolute sense of Homecoming,
Homecoming, and just when I was
at this point, the universe
showed me that there are
dimensions of reality beyond any
that I. Be able to touch in this
lifetime, even using this
powerful method, and that's when
I understood it's an infinite
progression. You don't get to an
end point. That's one of the
reasons why I would be gentler
with myself if I were doing it
again, and why I would recommend
that other people be gentle with
themselves. Because the goal, I
think, is not to get to some
state of being or some state of
consciousness which the which is
an end point. The goal, I think,
is to open us to the universe,
and to let us much of the energy
of the creative intelligence of
the universe into our being, to
purify ourselves and to engage
it, and to enter into dialog
with it, and then basically, let
nature take its course and let
us grow. I'm more patient with a
slower transformational process
than I than I was when I was a
young man.
Unknown: Chris, I mean, I've
thoroughly, thoroughly enjoyed
this, this conversation, quite
surprised by the preciseness in
your verbiage and the way that
you're discussing and talking
about this, if you could, you
know, somehow bring this all
together and perhaps include a
warning for explorers, people
who are, I mean, we've seen this
surgence resurgence In the usage
of psychedelics. Many people use
them without caution, you know,
they're doing them at concerts.
And so if people are going to do
them, you know, and and they're
aiming for connected states,
such as the ones that you
describe, you know, maybe a
warning for those explorers and
those travelers. And then, if
you could wrap this together in
being a bow tie, because even
though your journey didn't have,
you know, a specific end point,
this conversation does have an
end point.
Chris Bache: So yeah, yes, yes.
The more experience I've
collected using psychedelics,
the more cautions I am and the
more uncomfortable Ian with
people taking psychedelics in
less than controlled
circumstances. Now, many people
have had very deep life changing
experiences tripping, and I
wouldn't want to, I don't mean
to criticize that, but when you
are taking a substance that has
the potential to open up all the
sluice gates in your mind and
open up into these deep, deep
levels of reality. If you do
this in a complicated or a
socially complicated or
sensitive, sensational,
complicated sensation,
complicated setting. It can be
really complicated, and you you
can get over your head quickly,
and you can, well, you can get
over your head. You can really
have experiences that can leave
you traumatized. And in order to
go where I went, you have to be
willing to enter into
unthinkable places, but you also
have to see all of your
experiences all the way through
to the very end. If you stop
midway, if you enter into some
of the intense purification or
threatening death of self
spaces, and you try to stop
that, then it's like you leave
the spring coiled in your
consciousness that just always
trying to finish the job. So I
really encourage be very, very
cautious. I would hate for
anyone to take my book and and
use it as a guide book to try to
have similar experiences and
injure themselves. It would just
be terrible. And it is possible
to injure yourself using these
amplifiers, I recommend extreme
caution. And very to note, get
the literature, do your
research. There's lots of good
literature out there, lots of
good books on methodology.
There's more coming out every
year. And if there were a
takeaway, if there were one
thing, I wish that I could lift
from people's lives, it would be
the fear of death. I mean to me,
not only am I not afraid of
dying, I'm honestly and truly
looking forward to it. I'm not
looking forward to the dying
itself, but I'm looking forward
to being dead because my
experience of the universe, of
the intelligence of the
universe, and the compassion of
the universe and the wisdom of
the universe, is such that I
have a sense that I have I have
touched where I'm going when I
die. And it's a magnificent
reality, layers and layers of
reality. And to be afraid of
death is to have the whole world
upside down. Time space is where
the hard work is done. Time
space is where we're here and
we're working and we're trying
to regain our consciousness. And
there's lots of important work
to do here. Death is like
graduation. Death is like
homecoming. Death is. A return
to source and essence. Now, if
you die before you die, you know
there's a monk who said, Those
who die before they die do not
die when they die. It is
possible to enter into the
reality that one enters into
after you die, but to enter into
that while your body is
physically alive. That is, I
think classically, I wouldn't
say that's what the
enlightenment experience is, but
that's we're going in that
direction where you can stand in
the physical world, be
completely transparent to
spiritual reality and live
consciously in the physical
world and in spiritual reality
at the same time. And there are
many, many permutations of that
kind of experience. But to be
apt, to be afraid of death,
that's such a heartache, because
that's that's to not understand
how the universe works and how
it's organized. That's why my
first book, of the ones you
mentioned, my first one, was a
book on reincarnation, because I
think we have a great deal of
empirical evidence that
reincarnation is simply true.
And if you don't understand
reincarnation, then you don't
understand your relationship to
the universe.
Unknown: I love it, Chris, this
was such a phenomenal
conversation. If, if you could
just remind me how I say your
last name, and also where people
can go your website, URL, yeah,
book,
Chris Bache: my last name is
pronounced Bache. There people
can contact me at this email
address, C, M, Bache, my
initials, and Bache at y, s,
u.edu, but within a month,
around the time the book comes
out, around Thanksgiving, I'll
have a website complete, and it
will be Chris bache.com and that
will be the easiest way to reach
me.
Unknown: Okay, wow, guys, that's
gonna do it for us here at hxp.
What a phenomenal conversation.
I hope you guys enjoyed it as
much as I did. My guest, Dr,
Christopher Bache, and the book
is called LSD and the mind of
the universe, and I guess you
guys have his email address for
those of you that had questions
in the chat that I didn't get to
I apologize if you're listening
to this on YouTube, or if you're
listening to this on the podcast
version, please make sure you
subscribe to us on YouTube as
well so you can catch the live
shows if you're if you're as
well, if you're listening to
this on the podcast version,
please get over to iTunes,
subscribe, leave us a review.
One of the main things that I
hear is that people just haven't
discovered the show yet. So one
of the biggest compliments you
can give us is just sharing what
we do with your friends and
family. Thank you guys, so much
for listening. Really, really
appreciate your presence. We
will be back next week. You you.