Jessica DiRuzza: Welcome. Hello
everybody. I'm Jessica diruzza
from trust psyche, and it is
such a pleasure to be able to
spend this Sunday together. This
is our free monthly trust psyche
live stream that we host right
here every first Sunday of the
month, all are welcome, so
please invite your friends. We
host a variety of speakers on a
myriad of topics, and you can
find out more about us at trust
psyche.com and you can sign up
for these live streams at trust
psyche.com backslash live stream
to participate live and to ask
your questions. If you value
what we do here today, the best
way you can support us is by
subscribing to our YouTube
channel, liking this video and
sharing it with all of your
friends. I'm very honored and
excited to present our guest
speaker for today, Chris Bache,
who's going to be presenting on
his forthcoming book LSD and the
mind of the universe. Diamonds
from heaven, released this
November 26 you can pre order
your copy today through Amazon.
Up until the 1700s humans
believed that the edge of our
universe ended at the planet
Saturn, the last visible planet
that we can see with the unaided
eye. With the invention of the
telescope, we turned it to the
heavens, and to our great
surprise, we discovered the
planet Uranus, twice as far out
as the planet Saturn. Our
universe doubled in size. Then
in the 1800s with the discovery
of Neptune, our universe once
again doubled in size. Then in
1931 with the discovery of Pluto
our universe then again doubled
in size, and now less than 400
years later, from the discovery
of Uranus, we have the Deep
Space Hubble Telescope, which
shows us that there are
trillions upon trillions of
galaxies in our universe. For
me, this is analogous to the
work that Chris has done in his
deep exploration of
consciousness, radically
breaking open and through our
cosmology and our philosophy and
our metaphysics, through the 73
high dose LSD sessions that he
did over 20 years and began to
share with us in his work, dark
night, early dawn, Steps to a
deep ecology of mind now with
LSD And the mind of the
universe, Chris takes us further
into diamond Luminosity and
brings back the diamonds from
heaven that he so graciously
shares with all of us here
today. There couldn't be a more
important time for Chris to
share his work with all of us,
both in the greater
understanding and acceptance of
psychedelics today, but also
because of the psycho spiritual
death and rebirth that our
collective human species seems
to be going through right now.
So please help me give a very
warm and loving Welcome to our
beloved friend, Chris Bache, and
when Chris is done speaking, you
each have an opportunity to ask
your questions, so please have
those ready, as that is our
favorite and most special part
of these live streams. Thank you
so much for being with us here
today.
Chris Bache: Hi everyone. Thank
you Jessica and Travis. Thank
you for this opportunity to
share my work with the
participants in trust.
Psyche.com. Is truly an honor to
do. So it's also an overwhelming
task, because this book covers
so many dimensions of
consciousness. It covers so many
years of work, and when I talk
about it, I have a tendency to
get absorbed naturally into the
experiences I'm describing, and
that makes compressing 20 years
of work and 20 years of thinking
and writing into a very short
presentation really challenging.
So to me, a talk is the most
effective way to get to question
and answers. So I'll try to keep
this contained and as brief as I
can, and then save a good half
hour at the end for Q and A, and
we'll see where that goes, maybe
even more than a half an hour.
So I'm going to start with,
well, a little bit of
background. First of all, those
of you who know me, someone who
don't know me, I'm the last
person you would expect to have
written a book on psychedelics.
I was raised in the Deep South,
in Mississippi. I was raised in
a middle class Catholic
background. I wanted to be a
seminar priest early in my life.
Was in the seminary for three
years in high school, I studied
theology at Notre Dame, New
Testament. Criticism at
Cambridge, and then philosophy
of religion at Brown. By the
time I had finished graduate
school, I was an atheistically
inclined agnostic, and the 60s
had completely passed me by. I
was not psychedelic involved in
in my college or graduate school
at all, so I was naive,
psychedelically, and I was
atheistically inclined,
agnostic, philosophically. And
then came LSD. Shortly after
beginning my career, I met the
work of Stan Grof, and that set
my life on the course that I'm
still harvesting today. So
first, let me start a PowerPoint
that I'll be using, and then I'm
going to keep this on only for
about 10 minutes, and then I'll
shift in and out of it again.
Later, let me see if I can get
this started here. This is what
the book will look like, and
I'll tell you a secret about
this book. This is the
publisher's title, LSD in the
mind of the universe. My title
is diamonds from heaven, because
diamonds from Heaven is a story
of a journey. But they wanted a
more marketable title, and
that's LSD in the mind of the
universe. The beginning of this
book goes back 40 years, over 40
years, when I had begun graduate
school in 78 right then I met
the work of Stanislav Grof, his
book realms of the human
unconscious, turned my life
around, followed quickly by LSD
psychotherapy, he gave me the
method and the confidence to
pursue the method of exploring
my consciousness, and through
that exploration to come to know
the deep psyche, the deep
universe better. I want to
emphasize that I did this work
as a philosopher. I was not a
therapist. I was not primarily
seeking healing, though healing
did come, but I was seeking to
understand our universe as
deeply as I could by exploring
my consciousness as deeply as I
could so a few observations on
method, and then we'll kind of
go right into the content
everyone is aware I think of the
distinction between low dose
psychely therapy, that Stan
develops, and high dose
psychedelic therapy. Low dose
psychedelic therapy peels the
mind gradually, layer by layer
in very intense therapeutic
encounters. Psychedelic therapy
is a very different protocol.
It's a protocol trying to
trigger, in the early days,
we're trying to trigger a
Near-Death Experience for people
who had terminal cancer, they
weren't trying to heal them, but
to trigger an encounter with the
universe that would open them to
the world that they were about
to enter. When I began my own
work, I chose to work with high
doses of LSD, primarily because
it was simply difficult to get
time to arrange a day of inner
journey with a dual career
marriage, and I wanted to make
the most out of every day that I
could put into this. I thought
of myself as basically doing an
extended regimen of psychedelic
therapy, doing just psychedelic
therapy, but for a longer period
of time. Originally, psychedelic
therapy was limited to a maximum
of three sessions. And I
thought, well, if you could do
three sessions with this work
safely, you could do it more
sessions and do it safely. When
I got to the end of this
journey, and was looking back
over its length, I began to
appreciate that what happened in
my work was different than what
I saw being recorded reported in
psychedelic therapy, so
different that I thought it
needed a new kind of language to
describe it. So I've chosen the
term psychedelic exploration.
Psychedelic exploration is the
method of psychedelic therapy,
isolation, earphones, head
headphones, music, total
protection with a sitter. The
difference is the number of
sessions involved. In my case,
73 high dose sessions between
1979 and 1999 I worked for four
years. I stopped for six years
for reasons that I described in
the book, and then I resumed for
a very intense 10 year process.
I did this work between when I
was 30 and 50 years old. I'm now
70 years old, so I've taken a
long time to present this work
completely candidly to the
world, partly for legal reasons
and partly because it simply
takes a long time. It took me a
long time to map and understand
all the dynamics of the sessions
that unfolded during these
years.
I want to say at the outset that
this is not a methodology that I
would recommend today if I were
doing it over. Again, I would be
gentler on myself. I would take
a slower process of engaging the
great expanse of the mind of the
universe. I would balance high
dose work with low dose
sessions. I would also balance
working with LSD, with working
with Psilocybin and Ayahuasca,
more body grounded psychedelics
for a variety of reasons, all of
which I discuss in the book.
Don't have time to go into here.
I tried to do this work as
systematically and rigorously as
I can. Working as a philosopher,
I made it of high priority to
make a complete and
phenomenologically accurate
record of my sessions within 24
hours, and then studied the
sessions and the dynamics arcing
across sessions and comparing my
experiences to those who were
that had been had by other
psychedelic journeyers. This is
a snapshot of my journal, about
400 pages my psychedelic notes
that for me, are my personal
Bible. They are the record of my
deepest experiences of the
universe, and therefore, in my
life, they come before all other
discursive thinking and analytic
analysis. Kept detailed records
of my sessions all the way
through I looked at and studied
the astrological transits of my
sessions, trying I was aware of
Rick and Stan's thinking about
the relationship between the
outer transits, the outer
planets, and the global
transits, and how they affect
one's work in deep, Non-ordinary
states. So I wanted to study
this hypothesis myself, and look
at how my sessions projected
against the rhythms of the solar
system during the years I was
doing this work. I want to
emphasize that the story I'm
telling in LSD, in the mind of
the universe is not primarily a
personal story. I mean, it is a
personal story at one level, but
in another sense, it's not
primarily a personal story. This
series of curves represents a
series of LSD sessions, and I
found that after the first 15
sessions or so, when I was
working insights and help in my
personal life tended to come at
the beginning and end of my
sessions, as I was leaving and
returning to time, space,
reality that's reflected in
these small circles when the
session was in its peak hours,
represented by the large circles
I was usually operating beyond
PERS my personal reality beyond
Crispus reality, not entirely,
but largely. And so the story
I'm telling in LSD in the mind
of the universe, is the story of
what unfolded in those large
circles at the peak hours of my
psychedelic sessions. This is
primarily a cosmological
narrative. It's not primarily a
therapeutic narrative. The
details, the personal details,
are important in a therapeutic
narrative, not so much in a
cosmological narrative. I found
when I did this work that what
unfolded in my work was a
series, a multiple series of
experiences of death and rebirth
that eventually kind of
concretized into this picture.
The drop below the line. That
line is, kind of represents the
border of time space. The drop
below the line is egoic reality,
our individual space, time
consciousness, and the first
death and rebirth, which is the
one most frequently talked about
in the literature, is ego death,
which takes place in that first
level when we make the
transition from ordinary
consciousness into early
Transpersonal consciousness. But
if you continue to work and
press the limits of your
experience, I found that there
are other deaths which take
place at other levels of
consciousness. Now I follow Stan
Grof in using the vocabulary of
psychic, subtle and causal
reality to describe some of
these deeper levels of
consciousness. I don't have a
vested interest in how many
levels of reality there might
be, or how many times a circle
of death and rebirth may turn.
What's important is the
principle that if s1 pushes
deeper and deeper and deeper, if
you do this work systematically,
there are a series of deaths and
rebirths that open in the
process. As I have looked back
and mapped them, these circles
oversimplify, of course. These
are a number of sessions, and
what is shown here is the sort
of circles within circles, the
deaths within deaths, the. Mark
a deepening of progressive
deepening into causal level
reality. So yeah, circles within
circles. When I looked over the
entirety of all of my
psychedelic work, I identified
five fundamental Death-Rebirth
processes, or levels of
consciousness where death and
rebirth were operating. These
are the five levels. First, the
death of self, by which I mean
the death of our time space,
identity as our individual,
identity as our sense of who and
what we are moving into
collective mind. There are three
chapters in the book dealing
with the dynamics of collective
mind, the ocean of suffering
deep time, then archetypal mind.
Experiences at the high
archetypal level, experience at
the lower archetypal level,
followed by immersion in causal
oneness. Oneness services, of
course, much earlier in the
sequence. But there is something
quite distinctive about causal
level oneness and finally, the
diamond Luminosity work after
everything that had taken place
before emerging into the diamond
light that Buddhism calls
Dharmakaya. I call the diamond
Luminosity. So let me before
turning off the PowerPoint, let
me simply take you through a
list of the chapters of LSD in
the mind of the universe, there
is a methodology chapter chapter
one, but then in terms of the
content of the experiences,
crossing the boundary of birth
and Death, the ocean of
suffering, deep time in the
soul, initiation into the
universe, the greater real of
archetypal reality, a
benediction of blessings, the
birth of the future human
diamond, Luminosity and final
vision. And then there is the
last chapter coming off the
mountain. It took me actually a
year just to write that last
chapter. That is a chapter in
which I reflect on what has been
happening in my life in the 20
years after I stopped my
psychedelic work, what I'll do
is go through each of these
chapters and simply mention a
few points on each of the
chapters. Work through the list
as quickly as I can, and then
we'll open it up for questions
and answers. Let me keep track
of my time. Okay, first crossing
the boundary of life and death
is the one that's easiest,
because it's most familiar. It's
so thoroughly described in Stan
Grof literature. When I entered
this domain, which took about
two and a half years to navigate
and 10 sessions, my work began
saturated. Became saturated with
confrontations with death, fetal
sensations, all sorts of severe
perinatal seizures, a purging of
the body, eventually culminating
in ego death. My ego death
basically involved a complete
reversal of everything that I
knew myself to be at the time. I
was an academic, a white male
academic, a philosopher,
passionately concerned with the
meaning of life. I became the
complete opposite of that. I
became women, women of color,
women who were not interested in
philosophical reflection at all.
I became it was a frightening
experience, a terrifying
experience, but when I let go,
when I let go and allowed myself
to become all these women who
were so different from me, I
entered the world of women and
was given the experience of
hundreds and hundreds of women
under the arm of the Great
Mother, it was a truly life
changing experience for me, and
I wish every man could have that
experience. When I went into,
when I went through that death
and rebirth process and went
into continue to work, I entered
into a
domain of suffering and pain and
agony, collective pain and
suffering that was so severe I
came to call it the ocean of
suffering. So let me back up
just for a second, working at
these levels as I did it, every
session basically had two
phases, a first phase, which was
a purification phase. Phase, and
the second phase, which was the
ecstatic phase, the purification
phase, would be some type of
very profound, cathartic
purification engagement. And if
that was allowed to continue to
its culmination, there was some
type of crescendo, a
breakthrough, and then the
recession pivoted to an ecstatic
portion for the remainder of the
session, when I'm describing the
ocean of suffering, I'm
describing the purification
phase of the next two years of
work, tremendous suffering. At
first, I thought this was a
deepening of ego death. I
thought somehow that pieces of
my ego were still in play, and
that this collective suffering
represented a deepening of ego
death. But eventually this
continued for so long and it was
so severe that I came to a
different conclusion. The
conclusion I came to is that
somewhere along the line,
something had happened in my
sessions, that these ordeals
were not really aimed at my
personal transformation at all,
that somewhere along the line,
the focus of my work, at this
point, became actually the
purification and healing of some
aspect of the collective psyche,
some aspect of the collective
unconscious, that somehow I was
tapping into pain and suffering
which was lodged in the
collective psyche, and by
engaging this pain and suffering
consciously, it was in some way
being lifted out of the
collective psyche and Therefore
lightening the kind of karmic
burden that our species was
holding. Well, I wrote dark,
night, early dawn, primarily to
understand this whole dynamic,
primarily to understand how my
sessions, how death could become
as large as it became in my
sessions, and by integrating
Rupert Sheldrake concept of
Morphic fields into Stan Grof
paradigm, the way open to
viewing these experiences as
part of a larger
transformational practice aimed
at the collective psyche in the
ecstatic portion of these next
these two years of sessions in
the ecstatic portion, I entered
into what I call deep time in
the soul I and I began to have
experiences of my life as a
completed whole, from start to
finish, with all the time
moments of my life, with all the
themes and all the people and
circumstances of my life
simultaneously present and I was
basically taken into this
territory consistently for one
year, over and over again, seven
sessions, went deeper and
deeper, and was basically given
a profound crash course in Chris
Bache his life, what It was
about who the people were that I
was involved in my life was
taken into a kind of a spiritual
distillation of what my life was
about and what it was going to
be about when I first entered
this reality and came out of it
after the Session, it had been
the most powerful and
transformative experience of my
life, and yet I couldn't
remember it. After the session
was over, I could not hold on to
transtemporal experiences of
this magnitude, because there
simply was no reference point in
my ordinary consciousness to
anchor them. But when I went
back again and again and again,
I found that I was able to hold
on to these experiences more
effectively. I was able to
remember them. I was able to
bring more and more of them
back. And this is an important
point. If you want to enter into
these states and cultivate
systematic recall of the
experiences in these states, you
have to really work with a lot
of discipline. You have to
engage them very
conscientiously, record them
conscientiously. And if you hold
this position well, you
literally learn how to become,
how to be, stay conscious in
states of consciousness that
previously you were not able to
hold conscious awareness in. And
this pattern repeated every time
I would break through to a new
level, there was always a period
of disorientation, a period of
loss of memory. But then when I
would keep going back over and
over and over again to that new
level, my cognition improved, my
perception improved, my ability
to understand and record all the
experiences improved. Now the
ocean of suffering. Work, I
said, lasted two years and 14
sessions, but this was actually
divided into one year of work
and then I took my six year
break. Then I started my
psychedelic work again. When I
started after my six year break,
the ocean of suffering began
exactly where it had been in the
first year of work. So six years
later, completely different
circumstances in my life,
completely different
expectations and different
astrological conditions.
Nevertheless, my sessions began
exactly where they had stopped,
which is an indication of the
the intentionality of the
intelligence that's guiding our
work. When I started this after
the break, the ecstatic portion
of the sessions began at a
completely different place. The
ecstatic portion of the sessions
began in what I came to call
initiation into the universe. I
was taken systematically by some
intelligence that never adopted
any form, but I always felt an
intelligence that seemed to be
intent on teaching me how the
universe functions, how it
operates. I was given a crash
course in cosmology, 101 in this
material, the initiation of the
universe. I should mention. I
give names to my sessions. I
give every session a name. The
name reflects the pith content
of the session, and I break the
session down in bullet points
the names of the sessions that I
gave this chapter on initiation
of the universe. These are the
sessions that are discussed in
that chapter. You and I creating
was really a crash course in
cosmology. The cosmic tour was
an extraordinary tour of the
universe. Then there was a
training session that I called
the Council of Elders, a session
which was training me on how to
maintain coherent consciousness
as these deeper levels of
awareness were opening. Dying
into oneness was an
extraordinary immersion into
oneness. The master plan was the
beginning of a series of visions
that I'm going to come back to
later. It was a series of
initiations into what appeared
to be the plan that the creative
intelligence had for the
evolution of the human species
at this point in its history. I
know it sounds monstrously
arrogant to talk like that, but
this is simply what happened in
the sessions and then healing
the collective wound. Healing
the collective wound was the
ocean of suffering, came into a
culmination. It came into an
extraordinary hard to describe.
I lay it out of the book as best
as I can, hard to describe the
magnitudes of suffering that one
can enter into in this work, and
when that work came to its
crescendo, I was spun from there
into archetype of reality, and
the ocean of suffering never
returned in future sessions.
There was a lot of work. There
was suffering, but it was never
this collective suffering that
seemed to reflect the history of
the human species.
After the initiation of the
universe, I entered archetypal
reality. This lasted about one
and a half years and 11
sessions. When I entered
archetypal reality, I entered a
reality that immediately was
recognized as more real than
physical reality. Every time I
entered this level of work, I
had the sensation that I was
entering a reality that was more
real, more existentially real
than time and space. In fact, it
became very disorienting to
realize how diluted and watered
down reality is inside time and
space. Reality. When I entered
this work, my human identity
began to fall away from me. I
found that we have a sense of
being human that is deeper than
our sense of being any
individual human, an ego death
is a death of our individual
experience of being human, but
entering archetypal reality
required that I somehow let go
of human experience at a deeper
level, and eventually, I could
no longer fit myself back into
any cognitive frame of reference
related to Homo sapiens. I
entered a level of consciousness
that I experienced as being
above and beyond human
consciousness, and there I was
systematically worked with and
given lessons on how reality
operated. There these
experiences kind of broke down
at two different levels, at the
high platonic level, at the high
subtle level, I encountered
beings that were completely
beyond my ability to
conceptualize and understand my
mind image them. Like galaxies.
They were just vast beings that
were the creators of time and
space. They were the creators of
life on this planet. They were
the guardians of existence. They
were the massive constitutional
forces that actually create
everything that we know as time
and space in this magnificent
universe at a lower archetypal
level, at more of a Jungian
level, I was taken and given
many experiences of the
collective consciousness, our
collective psyche, our
collective unconscious, and even
kind of a collective body that
all of our bodies are cells in I
was given many experiences on
how the collective psyche works,
on how reality functions at this
level. These all took place
primarily at subtle level
reality. So I was given
exercises in the nuts and bolts
of how reality works, how our
individual minds ourselves
within a larger mind, and even
how our individual bodies are
cells within some kind of
fundamental core archetype of
the human body, and that when we
engage and heal diseases in our
individual body, we
simultaneously are impacting the
health of the human family's
larger body. The list of the
sessions that I address in this
chapter,
the 28th session was an
extraordinarily positive
session, ecstatic session in
which I broke through and
touched causal level reality for
the first time, an extremely
clear, lucid, hard to describe,
state of hyper clarity. And then
I was quite surprised to go
through three sessions of just
gut wrenching cleansing, just an
ordeal of physical psychological
cleansing that had absolutely no
cognitive content associated
with it at all. It's just a just
a gut wrenching cleansing. In
time, to make a very long story
short, I began to realize that
what there is a cycle that I
came to call the cycle of
purification. Cycle of
purification is that every step
into a deeper level of
consciousness is a step into a
higher level of energy. So that
when we, when I first broke into
causal level reality in the 28th
session, I touched a reality
that was so pure that it
triggered a purification process
in my being that lasted three
sessions, extending over six
months. And I found that this
pattern repeated itself over and
over again as I continued to go
deeper every time I broke into a
new level of conscious and had
that ecstatic experience of
waking up in a deeper level of
reality, the following sessions
were very, very difficult, very
much involved in cleansing,
carrying out the garbage, so
much so that I began to dread
the sessions that immediately
followed the major breakthrough
sessions. I should mention here
that one of the things that
opened up at this level is I
began to experience
reincarnation as a collective
phenomenon previously. And those
of you who know my book on
reincarnation life cycles. Now
that the story of the soul of
the story I'm telling of
reincarnation, there is a story
of our individual evolution,
directing our individual
evolution over many lifetimes,
reflecting our individual
choices and our individual
learning. But now I began to
have experiences of the entire
planet entering into a
reincarnation process. And I
experienced millions of people
over time, century after
century, millions of people
incarnating in a way that was
integrated, that was not
uniform, but that was integrated
so that all of our individual
karma, our individual soul
aspirations, our individual
challenges, were all part of the
collective karma, collective
challenges and our collective
development as a species. It was
magnificently beautiful to
witness this interplay between
individual and collective
reincarnation again, all of
these taking place at the subtle
level of reality when one is
gaging the deeper architecture
of the universe. After spending
about 11 months exploring
archetypal reality. Reality. And
at going through this 11
sessions, going through this
very quickly, I entered what I
came to call the benediction of
blessings. It was a period of
extraordinary blessings, just
given one massive blessing after
another. These are the names of
the four sessions that I address
in this chapter, the forest was
an experience of Shunyata,
emptiness of self, no self in
me, no self anywhere around me,
an experience of radical and
profound transparency, the birth
of the diamond soul. I'll
mention in a second, singing the
universe away was an experience
of primal void, an experience
that culminated in the
experience of Satchitananda
consciousness, being and bliss,
eventually moving into a
complete void, the fertile void
that subsumes and is the origin
out of which the physical
universe emerged. Jesus blood
was an experience of
extraordinary, cosmic love, love
like I've never known it before,
just super saturated soul,
saturated, engaging of love, the
birth of diamond soul. I want to
mention because it'll come up
later in the work. In that
experience, in the birth of the
diamond soul session, which was
really a deeply moving, long
lasting session for me, I began
to experience all of my former
lives coming into me very fast,
very quickly, 11 years before, I
had experienced my entire life
from beginning to end. Now, I
began to experience all my lives
coming in, and it was like we
were wrapping kite string around
a spool. And at some point this
spool ignited. It was as if we
hit critical mass and all of
these lives fused into a
singularity. And when they fuse,
an extraordinary light broke out
of my chest. It was my first
contact with what I later call
diamond light. And I think what
I was being given in this
session was an experience of how
reincarnation works and where
reincarnation is taking
humanity. This process of
accumulating more and more
experience more and more lives,
is not simply improving us and
making us better beings, one
life at a time, adding a little
bit here, a little bit there.
But eventually we're collecting
experience. And I think
eventually, in the entire human
saga, all of us are coming into
a stage where eventually all of
our knowledge, all of our
experience, everything we've
ever done, everyone we've ever
known through these lives, there
is a fusion of that knowledge,
and when that knowledge fuses,
we are catapulted into a higher
operational status, a different
relationship to the universe, a
greater transparency to the
universe, and also a different
relationship with everyone
around us, because we have been
connected to each other for so
many lifetimes. We have been
fathers, mothers, enemies,
friends, partners in so many
lifetimes, when we become whole
within ourselves, it opens up a
depth of compassion to all
beings we experience around us,
and not just human beings, all
beings on our planet.
Jessica DiRuzza: You
Unknown: after
Chris Bache: the benediction of
blessings, where the work went
next was into the diamond
Luminosity work. I was
completely existentially
satisfied after the the
benediction of blessings work, I
had given something that I had
been asked to give in the ocean
of suffering, and I had been
repaid and given more in return
that I could possibly have
imagined. But then we went into
the diamond Luminosity work. But
before I begin to tell you about
that, I want to back step a
little bit and talk about the
birth of the future human
because it's been a reoccurring
theme in my session, starting
all the way back the 22nd
session, all the way through to
the end of the sessions, a
reoccurring theme is what is
happening to the human race.
Where are we in our evolutionary
journey? Now I tell this story
in the book, I brought together
in one place all of the session
material related to the birth of
the future human in this one
chapter. So in the starting with
experiences that first appeared
in chapter six, the initiation
and. Universe running all the
way through, I gathered them all
together and collected them into
two segments. First is a segment
that I call the visions of
awakening, which are visions
that I had been given in
different piecemeal fashion
about where we are and where we
are going. I break this down
into six visions. These are the
six themes of our awakening.
What was most striking to me
about this was first, how
dramatic this process was and
how the experience was that we
were poised to move into an
evolutionary to make an
evolutionary jump that would
completely propel us into a
higher order of functioning, not
only as individuals, but as a
species. We are poised on the
edge of a profound, great
awakening, but in all of these
visions, and I'm going so fast,
I hate to go so fast through
them, but in all of these
visions, I and which kept
pointing to an awakening taking
place on the planet of the human
species, of the entire species,
the consciousness of our
universe was actually Trying to
awaken the entire human species.
I was not shown how this was
going to take place. I was not
shown how this was even
possible. And then, about a year
and a half after the last of the
visions of awakening, I was
given a session right in the
middle of the diamond Luminosity
work. I had entered the diamond
Luminosity in sessions 45 and 50
I would enter it again later in
sessions 60 and 66 right in the
middle, I was taken into the
deep time of our species. I was
given an experience of tape
being taken right into the
center of the Great Awakening
that we are coming into. And
there I experience this
transformation, not as an
individual human being. My
boundaries had been blown open
so many times in the years
preceding that I experienced the
Great Awakening as our species.
I was taken inside the
collective psyche and was given
an experience of what will be
happening from the perspective
of the collective unconscious.
My experience there was that for
there to be a great awakening of
this magnitude, there must first
take place, a great death, a
great surrender. We must be
purged and emptied of all our
old ways of thinking and feeling
before the space is created to
allow awakening of a higher
order of knowing, so that the
time of Great Awakening was
preceded by a time of great
breakdown, loss of control,
literally, an unraveling of life
as we know it. Just as in a
psychedelic session, one must
let go of everything and
experience a profound death
before great visions open.
Likewise for our species, we
must let go of everything that
has dominated our past, all the
constrictions of our thinking,
the constrictions of our mind
and the constrictions of our
heart, in order to open to this
new future which is coming.
There is a third segment on the
birth of the future human, and
that came later in the chapter
on the final vision. I want to
say that my visions didn't tell
me how this was going to take
place. It didn't tell me when it
was going to take place. It
didn't give me any information
about the details. It took me
inside the collective psyche and
gave me an experience of the
collective psyches, experience
of this and it also gave me an
understanding and experience of
some of the mechanisms that are
involved at the collective level
that will help us make this huge
transition we are trying to make
in the little time that we have
to make it. I discussed this, I
present this. I discussed it in
dark net early dawn, and I lay
it out again in LSD, in the mind
of the universe, the diamond
Luminosity material, as I said
before, after the benediction of
blessings, I had no idea where
the work was going to go. I was
completely existentially
satisfied. I felt I had been
drawn deep into the cosmic
process. I had been overwhelmed
with cosmic love. I had been
taken into the fertile void
underneath all physical
existence. I had no idea where
things would go, but there were
still five years. Ahead on the
journey and the diamond
Luminosity gathers four years of
the work and 26 sessions. It, by
far, covers more sessions than
any other chapter in the book in
a longer period of time. What
happened was, after going
through yet one more very
intense death and rebirth
process. I was taken into a
reality, a level of
consciousness that was well
Buddhism, calls it Dharmakaya,
the clear light of absolute of
absolute reality. I was taken in
a domain of consciousness it was
absolute, pure light. The most
striking thing about the
experience was how clear, clear,
clear, beyond imagination, this
domain was just to touch this
for a few minutes. Was life
transforming, in and of itself?
Absolute? Clear, clear, beyond
the species mind, beyond
archetypal reality, beyond
physical, any derivative of
physical consciousness, into
this hyper, clear, celestial
state. Over the next four years,
I entered this reality four
times, and only four times out
of 26 sessions, only four of
them took me deep into this
reality. Here are the names of
the sessions, death state,
diamond, Luminosity, the
universal field of light in the
nature of mind. In between these
sessions, as you might imagine,
there were many sessions of
continuing, intense
purification, because this was a
deeper level of reality, a much
more pure level of reality, and
that required the purification
of my physical and psychological
system in order to stabilize
consciousness at this reality,
they also scattered in these
sessions, there was a great deal
of personal healing that took
place, which is kind of curious
to me, because I would have
thought that personal healing
would have taken place much
earlier in the journey, but it
took place here, and I
discussed, I came to understand
why things were unfolding in
that order. The first two of
these sessions were taking me
deeper and deeper into diamond
Luminosity, which really peaked
then in the 50th session. The
second two sessions, 60 and 66
the diamond Luminosity was
crunching itself deeper and
deeper into my physical system,
into my psychological system,
into my physical body. As I
said, talking about these
sessions, they're very powerful.
They draw me into them just to
try to describe that the time is
short. So I want to move through
and we'll keep going, and we can
come back to mend the question
and answers. Let me mention one
thing midway through this
process, in the 50th session,
when I went into the deepest
transcendent experience I ever
had in any of the sessions, into
the deepest level of diamond
Luminosity. I was as far into
the crystalline body of God as I
had ever been and would ever be.
And right in the middle of this
session, I had an experience
that completely changed my
understanding of existence. In
the middle of this session, my
visual field pivoted 90 degrees,
and I saw reality that was far
beyond the reality that I was in
inside diamond Luminosity, and a
ray of light came out of that
distant reality and hit me, and
it completely shattered me. It
just I just absolutely shattered
me. And in that experience, I
realized that there is no end to
this journey. There is no
destiny point and end point that
one eventually reaches, that the
Divine is infinite and will
never, ever, I will never, ever
be able to reach, even using
this powerful method, to the
absolute ends of that reality.
Now this is important because I
had absorbed, and many of us
have absorbed, the idea that
there is an end point to this
journey. You become one with
God, or you enter into the meta,
cosmic void that there is an end
point, and you keep pushing
until you reach that end point.
And I had experienced oneness
with God, but I discovered that
there are many permutations of
oneness. There are levels and
levels of oneness. And I had
experienced the formless void,
but I had learned that there are
actually dimensions of
formlessness. There. Depths of
formlessness. When I when the
diamond Luminosity work opened,
I thought it came with such a
profound sense of Homecoming. It
was so deeply satisfying. I
thought I finally found my
destination. I finally found my
stopping point. I had found the
end of the journey. And this
session, session 50, showed me
that there are dimensions beyond
even that, and I would never,
ever reach some final
standpoint. The reason that
death kept returning over and
over again in this work is if
you keep driving yourself and
you have a method that's
sufficiently powerful to keep
taking you past your then limits
the universe will keep taking
you deeper and deeper and deeper
into yourself, into itself, and
will never be able to reach the
very end of it. And that's why I
would be gentler with myself if
I were doing this work over
again, because now I understand
that the goal was not to get to
some end state or some ultimate
dimension. The goal is to open
ourselves to the transcendent
realities and let us much of
that spiritual reality into our
hearts and into our minds, to
let it change us down to the
heart and soul, and incorporate
as much of it as we possibly can
and bring as much of divinity
into time and space as we
possibly can and be patient with
the rest. I'm a little more
patient now than I was when I
was a young man doing this work.
And then this brings me to the
final vision chapter, the
chapter where I'm going to take
a shortcut here, I'll simply say
that I was put through a
horrendously powerful, stripped
down process, and was taken
deeper into deep time than I had
ever been taken before, And I
was given an extraordinarily
powerful series of visions about
human evolution, and was allowed
to experience again the future
human that we are in the process
of becoming, to experience the
architecture, the inner
architecture of the Deep psyche
of the future human. And this is
a magnificent being. Just to
just to think about this being,
just to remember the magnitude
of this being, brings tears to
my eyes. It's so important for
us to hold on to the vision of
what we are going and what is
happening in the deep structure
of history, because as the
shadows of our travail deepen,
as we enter the great time of
unraveling, as we enter the
purification that we are coming
into. Now, it's going to be very
tempting, and there'll be all
sorts of voices talking about
Armageddon and Apocalypse and
the extinction and the end of
times. And this is not the end
of anything. This is the process
of giving birth to a new and
finer version of humanity after
this, the consciousness guiding
my sessions. Wrapped it up. I
didn't know we were stopping,
but it wrapped it up and took me
through two experiences, which I
call the goodbye sessions. It
basically wrapped up all of our
work. And at the end of the 73rd
session, I knew that it was time
for me to stop. I want to talk
about very briefly, coming off
the mountain overall, I think I
did a good job integrating my
sessions as I went. I paid a lot
of attention to my body. I took
good care of my body. I did a
lot of spiritual practice. I
wrote my sessions down
carefully. I tried to
internalize them as deeply as I
could session by session, I
think I did a good job of
integrating my sessions. And
because I had been given so many
gifts and so many blessings in
the course of my 20 years of
work, I thought that I could
simply stop my sessions and step
back, and I would continue to be
nourished by those experiences.
And I was and that did happen.
But that's not all that's
happened. In the years following
the ending of my work in 1999 I
found myself gradually entering
into a period of what I call the
deep sadness, a profound
existential sadness. I Yes, what
I was suffering from was a loss
of communion with the divine. I
had entered so deeply into the
divine, so deeply into the
luminous reality of such
supreme, super, cosmic reality,
that I. Knew I would never enter
that deeply into reality, into
the Divinity again. Before I
died, I knew I was going away. I
was setting it aside and coming
back in it for variety of
reasons too much to go into
here. I had to stop my sessions.
It was important for me to stop
them, but I knew I would never
experience the divine this
deeply again until I died, and I
would experience it again when I
die, but not being able to
return this deeply into divinity
became an open heartache for me,
once you have been have known
the joy of dissolving into the
Divine Light. Once you have
dissolved completely into the
boundaryless condition
transcending time and space,
life on Earth can tend to feel
kind of dried up. And basically,
I was losing interest in
continuing to live inside time
and space. Eventually I realized
I was just waiting to die. I was
taking care of my children, I
was taking care of my students
and teaching writing, but in my
heart of hearts, I was waiting
to die so that I could return to
my beloved, to the divine. And
then years passed, I realized,
this is not right. This is not
the way it's supposed to be.
Everything about my life was
screaming failure to integrate.
But because I had tried to
integrate each of my sessions so
carefully and so
conscientiously, I did not
understand where the failure
could lie, but I had no choice
but to recognize that somewhere
along the line, something had
gone wrong that it would leave
me feeling so existentially
adrift in its wake. So I turned
and studied my work further to
try to figure out what had gone
wrong, and what I learned was
integrating an entire journey is
different than integrating
individual sessions that
basically
hard to talk about in a matter
of seconds and a half a minute.
It's hard to describe the
process of, in a sense, having
too much God. It almost sounds
like a contradiction in terms.
Surely, more of God is always
better. Now this entire physical
universe is the body of God. I
knew that. I know that I'm
standing here and surrounded and
part of the body of the
Divinity, but even that
knowledge which had been given
me in my sessions did not save
me from the consequences of
having entered into full divine
presence so many times in time,
I began to realize that I had
lost a balance in my sessions,
and the balance was between
Transcendence and imminence. I
had entered so deeply into
transcendent reality that I had
lost my foothold in space, time
reality. Transcendence is a
magnificent thing. It's very
healing to experience
Transcendence. It's very it's
very sane making it's very It
teaches us what and why we're
here. But too much Transcendence
can be disorienting too much.
Transcendence can actually make
you lose contact with another
great truth, and that is the
truth of our embodied existence.
I made a completely strong
commitment to re establishing my
presence inside time and space.
It took me about 10 years. I did
it through conscious exercises,
and I did it through a sheer
commitment to live as I was
where I was for the my remaining
years in this earth. And it took
me about about 10 years to
really get solidly grounded and
operational on the earth. I will
say at the same time that I've
learned to manage my memories of
Transcendence, my memories of
communion. But they are always
there in the back of my mind.
They always guide me in in the
larger trajectory of my life.
Unknown: Yes, hello. Thank you
very much for sharing this
amazing experience that you
have. I'm from Israel. I wanted
to ask two questions. First. Of
all the about the when you say a
high dose, what is, what is?
What are the doses that you're
talking about? Yeah? So, yeah,
okay, sorry. Go ahead and the
second question I wanted to ask
about all this, all the
settings, you know, what was the
setting? Because, you know, I
consume. I do a lot work with
with the with plants, and I was
very interesting to know about
the setting. How was the setting
of the of the of it, of the of
the journeys, how you did it,
how you prepared yourself, how
you did what was in the moment,
if you're sitting, if you're
lying, your eyes closed. Music,
no. Music, nature, all of these
things, and they would like to
know about this and about the
also about how you were in the
daily life, what kind of things
helped you to stay here in a
good way, like what spiritual
practices or exercise or food or
something that was, thank you
very much.
Chris Bache: Yeah, good
questions. Thank you. I worked
at 500 to 600 micrograms, which
is very high doses of LSD, and I
mean low dose psychedelic. Work
may be one 200 micrograms. This
was very high levels. My
setting, I was always working in
complete privacy and inside, I
was either in my own house or at
my wife's professional office. I
was always lying down. I was
basically, if you, if you look
at Stan's book, LSD
psychotherapy, you'll get the
protocol laid out in great
detail. Music was very carefully
curated to pace the stages of
the opening and closing of the
session, always wearing
eyeshades, not really the only
way my sitter would be in
communication with me was
primarily through the music. She
took care of my body and took
care of the music and so I was
not in nature. What was the
other part of your Oh, the
grounding practices really
important. You have to maintain
grounding is a dynamic balance.
My life was very kind of
grounded in a schedule. In
reality, first of all, was
grounded in relationships. It
was grounded in a long marriage,
my first wife, 24 year marriage.
It was grounded in my roles and
responsibility as a father, I
have three children, so wherever
I was on Monday, I was on
Saturday, I was back in the
classroom on Monday, and I was
taking care of my children on
Sunday morning. In my teaching,
I had a rhythmic, a constant set
of responsibilities that kept me
always on track, always kind of
I always grounded in my
responsibilities of teaching my
students. I was always doing
spiritual practice. I was always
doing a form of meditation. I
coordinate different types of
meditation over the years, but I
was always meditating. Took care
of my body, doing yoga, various
physical practices, it's really
important to stay in lively
contact with one's physical
world while doing this work. So
basically we're just blowing
consciousness out to its
farthest limits, and then it
spontaneously recongeals. And I
found that myself, I had a
seemingly a natural capacity, an
easy capacity, Jessica can no
doubt explain in my chart the
markers of that, a capacity to
let loose and let go of
boundaries and then to recongeal
back into my time, space,
reality. Yeah. Does that cover
your questions?
Unknown: Enough? Yes, that yes.
Thank you very much. So I just
the last question, just to
consume this. You always made
sure, let's say there will be
someone like in a distance, on a
house or somewhere that if you
need, you need assistance, or,
yeah, like you always you make
sure that they nobody will be
there.
Chris Bache: Yes, in my is my
mic on, yes, okay, yes. I was
never left alone. I was always
taken care of. My wife was my
sitter. She's a clinical
psychologist. My first wife,
Carol, she was my sitter. How
she never left me alone and she
she had complete responsibility
for taking care of our world. We
were always isolated. We were in
private. There were no
interruptions. My work, when I
basically closed the door and we
entered this world, there was
absolutely nothing that was
going to intrude from the
outside world. I think that's
really important. It's important
to have an absolute clear
container. I call it entering
the Kiva. Just as in the
southwestern United States, when
they would do spiritual
practice, they crawl into the
Kiva, a hole in the ground, they
pull up the ladder, and you're
isolated completely from the
world while you're doing this
work. If you're going to go deep
into the universe, it's very,
very important to have a
completely grounded, isolated,
protected environment, so that
you know that whatever you're
confronting, and I've confronted
some pretty horrendously
difficult experiences. But
whatever you're confronting, you
know that it's not coming from
outside you. It's coming from,
in a sense, from inside you or
from in it's coming from the
universe, but purely through
your own consciousness. So no
outside complications. I did not
try to stay in contact with the
outside world at all.
Unknown: Let's hear from Carrie.
Go ahead. Carrie,
hi everybody. Chris. I just want
to say thank you so much for all
your work. I've heard you speak
years ago through PCC and CIS,
and I've enjoyed your writings
and and many bits, but I loved
this presentation that you did
today, so coherent, and walking
through each of the stages and
sessions and the way you
organized the arc of the journey
is really impressive and super
rich. So thank you so much for
that. Thank you. Three
questions. You can pick one if
you want, if it seems too long,
but the astrological integration
I'm really curious about, you
know, your individual chart,
your transits, how the
individual chart kind of
functioned as a lens for you to
entering these, you know, either
subconscious parts of yourself
to be able to see them, or the,
you know, the collective
unconscious as well, all of the
parts there. And you know, how
much of the of the chart Do you
think remained as you entered
these less individuated states?
Yeah, the one, the individual
part to the transits, and, you
know, just any little head bits
that stick out, I guess. And
then the third one, I'm really
curious, particularly it came up
for me when you were talking
about being in the ocean of
suffering and the the healing
that can come about from
processing that internally and
individually. And I'm curious if
you if those effects you felt
them in your I'm just going to
call it your waking life, your
normal states of consciousness
in if it kind of came back from
people around you, or in world
events or, yeah, any potent
moments where that, where that
you really felt, that reflection
of your internal experience from
the external world?
Chris Bache: Yeah, let's start
on your last question and then
work forward into the earlier
ones. Yeah, it did manifest.
There were manifestations that
emerged in the outer world. And
so let me mention my book, The
living classroom, and there's a
chapter on teaching in dark net
early dawn. What my I never
talked to my students about my
work, right? I just made a
firewall between my professional
life and my inner shamanic work,
and yet I found over time that
various students were being
activated by my inner work, that
the deeper I went, the more
powerful the activation became,
and it became such a prominent
part of my teaching that I found
that I had to I had to
understand what was going on. I
had to learn how to work with
these forces. So for me,
integration doesn't mean simply
personal integration into my
personal life, but it also means
helping take care of all the
derivative social fallout of
one's own experiences. I found,
for example, that while I was
teaching and I would just be
reaching to give examples of
something I was trying to
explain, that the examples that
I would reach for would without
my even being aware of it.
Students were coming up after
class, and they say, you know,
it's interesting that you use
that example, because that's
exactly what happened to me this
week. And this happened over and
over again, that there was some
kind of boundary which had come
down between my mind and my
students mind. It was and not
only, not only were these things
kind of like triggering, sort of
an aha moment for my students.
Isn't that curious, but the
deeper I went, the more the
synchronistic touches began to
trigger very, very deep healing
experiences in the students. It
was as if their souls were in
communication with my soul, and
they were giving me. Bits and
pieces of insights into where
they were, what they needed,
where they were suffering, where
they were hurting. And this was
happening without me being
consciously aware of the process
at all. And so I really had to
study this. I really had to
understand what was, what was
driving these processes. And
eventually I wrote, after dark,
night, early dawn, I wrote an
entire book on the living
classroom, on the collective
dynamics in the classroom. And I
don't mention psychedelics
there, because this is not a
psychedelic phenomenon. This is
simply about the nature of
consciousness. At one level, we
have private mind, but just
beneath our private mind. Mind
does not have privacy. There are
collective dimensions of mind.
It's like throwing a rock into a
lake, the ripples spread out
when you do deep, deep work, the
ripples of that work spread out
and touch the lives of people
around you. The place where I
experienced this most profoundly
was in my classroom because I
was working in a collective
context, I could see these
ripples coming back at me all
the time. The first the issue of
astrology and individual and
global transits, this is a
complicated question, and I'm
not an astrologer, so I want to
be very careful about this. I
tracked my sessions. I used
astrology to plan my sessions
after I learned from Rick Tarnas
about the correlations between
outer planets and inner
experience in psychedelic days.
So I planned my sessions by
transits, and I also tracked the
patterns of my breakthroughs
projected against the pattern of
the planets, and I found it to
be a very complicated
correlation. While there were
correlations between my
individual transits and global
transits with the unfolding of
my psychedelic experience, there
were also differences that I
wasn't expecting. There was a
kind of a failure to find
correspondence. For example, my
breakthroughs were not always
paired with with Uranus, all
right, my my really, really
intense up against the wall,
death in your face. Experiences
were not accompanied. We're not
marked by Saturn transits or
Saturn global transits or even
Pluto transits. And so it was a
complicated process when, when
my work began to go off the edge
of time and space, when I began
to enter deeper and deeper into
archetype of reality, and then
beyond archetype of reality into
Dharmakaya or the diamond
Luminosity, I found what I felt
was a kind of a roll off of
astrological variables that the
astrology did not seem my my
psychedelic dance did not seem
to map very easily into the
astrological dance, and I began
to think that there actually
might be a roll off effect of
one's solar dance and one's
session experiences. And this
continues to be an area of
active dialog. For me, it's an
active consideration. There is
an appendix in the book. The
last appendix is called pushing
the limits of astrological
correspondence. And in that
chapter, in that appendix, I
give the dates of all of my
sessions. So if one wanted to,
one can look at my natal chart.
One can look at the sessions,
when you look at the
correlations or lack of
correlations, and so forth. Now
I know that that's not a there's
not enough sessions given in the
book to really give a definitive
answer, but I wanted to support
the discussion of the
relationship between astrology,
astrological transits and global
transits and one's own
psychedelic work. To me, that's
an open question at this point.
I know that there are
correlations, particularly in
the early stages of one work,
whether those correlations
continue to be as strong in the
late stages of one's work. I'm
not as convinced of okay, and in
terms of my own chart, that's
that gets too complicated. I
mean, I I have a lot of Neptune
in my chart. I have a lot of
water in my chart. I have a sun
square Neptune with Neptune in
the first house. So there are a
lot of I have some other
dynamics that I was destined to
do this type of work, you know.
And I want to mention the ocean
of suffering. This was not
something that was forced on me.
I didn't understand it at the
time. But this and. I don't
think the universe forces any of
us into this type of work. This
was too too hard, too demanding,
too difficult for to have it be
forced on me. What I learned
over time again is that this is
something that I voluntarily
took on in this incarnation. It
was part of the plan of my
incarnation to do this work and
to do the ocean of suffering
work in particular. So I'm a
volunteer, and I think we're all
when we get into this deep, deep
muck that we get into, we're
volunteers for this work.
Unknown: Awesome. Thank you so
much. Thank you, Kerry, Hi,
Chris.
This is Paul and amber in
Poland, and we are so happy to
finally see you live and thank
you. Wanted to say how much we
appreciated your call. I have a
few questions, but let's start.
Let's continue the theme of the
ocean of suffering where we
live, in Poland, of course, was
the site of one of the most
horrific events that happened, I
would say, for centuries. Which
by which? I mean, of course, the
Holocaust when you had your
experience of the ocean of
suffering, did you experience
anything specific, or was the
specific information or visions
that you had that might have
related to something like this?
The reason I'm asking this
question is because the event,
which happened 80 years ago, is
so palpable that it's still in
the atmosphere. It's still in
the collective. You can feel it
here in the land and you know,
it's it's there in the
collective, whether we like it
or not, and I was just
interested in whether in any of
your sessions, you actually had
a sense of what happened then,
yeah,
Chris Bache: I did not go into
specifically identifiable
historical traumas like the
Holocaust, what happened was, I
basically was taken into deeper
and deeper and deeper into pain
and fury and chaos and
extraordinary suffering That
kept getting larger and larger.
It wasn't narrowly focused in
any century or any country or
any place. It expanded to
include hundreds of 1000s,
millions of people, and it
expanded to include hundreds of
years, 1000s of years, until
eventually, my subjective
experience was that it included
all the human beings and all the
conflicts that emerged in the
history of humanity. I mean
something of that scope. So I
have no doubt that trauma like
the Holocaust, or trauma like
the extinction of Native
Americans and other tribal
conflicts and so on. I have no
doubt that those were implicitly
present in what I was working
with, but it wasn't explicitly
present. It was like to me, you
know, Stan has this concept of a
Coex system, a system of
condensed experience. I think
the collective psyche also has
these massive aggregate, these
balls of collective experience.
I call them the meta matrices.
They are. They are the meta Code
Systems, the COEX systems of the
collective psyche that fuse
multiple historical periods and
multiple cultures and multiple
people's experience. Late in
this whole series, it became
very clear to me was that what I
was engaging was memory, the
living memory of trauma that was
embedded in the collective
psyche. I should mention that
where I live in Youngstown,
Youngstown, Ohio, we haven't had
a holocaust here, but we have a
long history of violence. It
goes back to the Native
Americans, and there were some
massacres that took place here.
There is a tremendous influx of
Eastern European This is a town
that made steel. There's there's
a lot of old world patriarchy, a
lot of violence against women, a
lot of old institutional
violence and the mafia took over
our town. For decades, there
were gang land shootings in
neighborhood parking lots. My
sense is that because the ocean
of suffering was on the agenda
in my work, that I was actually
brought to a place. Place where
these poisons run close to the
surface in the collective
psyche. And I'm sure that if I
were working in Poland or in a
place that it would have been
more explicit the historical
trauma that you're referring to.
Unknown: Thank you. Thank you.
First of all, Chris, thanks so
much for all your work over the
decades. Been a huge fan forever
and ever and ever and just so
wonderful and on this ocean of
suffering issue that's been
brought up and touched on,
because that's kind of like the
next stop on the journey for a
lot of the people out there
working your book dark night,
early dawn was extremely helpful
to Petra and I. We don't work
with LSD. We work with
Holotropic Breathwork, which is
just another technique in order
to connect with these things.
And what we had noticed over the
years was that there were
individuals who, under not
predictable circumstances, began
to contact what seemed to be
this ocean of suffering. It
wasn't a past life, which
happens often enough, but there
was something big about it. And
then we realized, my goodness,
people need some clarity that
this is not just their personal
stuff that they're saddled with
and have to carry around
forever. They are, in a sense,
volunteers. Yes. And so this was
extremely useful, and some
people in spiritual emergency
that come to us began to
realize, oh, so I was trying to
solve the basic problem between
men and women for the last 5000
years. Okay, well, you know,
I've got other things I've got
to do today, and so that I want
to thank you very much for that,
and it's clear now how this work
will make more available to many
more people, whatever techniques
they work in, even with
spontaneous experiences. And
what we developed was using
systemic constellation work,
then to do a constellation for
the individual that is caught in
this that would say, Okay,
here's the representative for
the part of the man woman story,
that's mine, and here's a
representative for the part of
the man woman story that, hmm,
you know, that's a great big
thing, and then to let this,
this clarity, simply, let them
settle into wow, I do have work
to do. We all have work to do.
And there's something else going
on that we're all involved in,
but I don't have to have it done
by tomorrow afternoon. Yeah, and
so I just want to thank you for
the earlier work. I'm so glad to
see this. Thank all the powers
in me that brought you living,
breathing, laughing and loving
into this especially tense time
that we have now. So I'm looking
forward to see if we get to the
stage in our workshops in which
the the the the comments about
the other other stages of the
past become similarly useful.
Chris Bache: Thank you. I
completely agree. And I think as
we go deeper into this
historical crisis that we've
entered, I think we're entering
into a collective dark night of
the soul. It seems like there's
a profound detoxification taking
place, that the poisons of
history are coming out of our
collective pores. I mean, we see
it if we look around us and
embody politic, but it's coming
out of our pores, and it's
coming up underneath us and
flooding so that if we're
interested in doing purifying
work, if we're interested in
doing transformational work,
when we open we open it. If we
have a technique that's powerful
enough, like Holotropic
Breathwork, we open at an
individual level, and then we
open at these deeper levels. Now
I'm not a therapist, but if I
were a therapist, and if I were
working with people entering
these states, I think just what
you're describing,
differentiating different levels
of the work that emerges,
recognizing kind of what is mine
personally, and what is not mine
personally, but mine
collectively. It's important to
have closure and to be able to
close these collective levels,
and there would be, I would
think, an importance of kind of
winding those sessions down and
kind of concretizing the
collective work in contrast and
separate from one's individual
work. Now I will say that I went
into this work voluntarily. I
stayed into it voluntarily, and
I'm infinitely glad for just
personal reasons, let alone the
collective reasons. I am
personally very glad to have
done this work because. The
rewards that came were not
simply a karmic paying back, but
when one opens and embraces
one's life as a member of the
species, when one open to the
species and takes responsibility
for the pain and suffering of
the species, it sets in motion,
not only a healing of that
species, but there is a
tremendous infusion of light
that enters into the collective
psyche and into your psyche as
it enters into the collective
psyche. And so I have been so
deeply rewarded, more than amply
compensated, for the work that I
did in the ocean of suffering
and other levels. And I think
that this is true for other
people too, that when we give
deeply and generously to those
around us, sooner or later, we
don't know when, how or where,
but sooner or later, there is a
deep fruition that comes up
underneath us, that carries us
individually where the universe
is intent on carrying the human
species as a collective, and
that is into this birth of this
profoundly new quality of
consciousness that I'm calling
the diamond soul, or the future
human.
Jessica DiRuzza: Thank you so
much. Chris, as Carrie said,
that was such a beautifully laid
out coherent arc. And I'm so
grateful for the time that you
have spent with us today, and
for all of you here connecting
from all around the world. Thank
you so much for uniting today in
both our hearts and our minds,
and we send each of you so much
love and infinite blessings on
your journey as you deepen into
your own explorations and the
healings that we're all here
doing right now, today in this
world. Thank you so much. Be
well, and we will see you next
time you.