Rick Archer: You welcome to
Buddha at the Gas Pump. My name
is Rick Archer, Buddha at the
Gas Pump is an ongoing series of
interviews with spiritually
Awakening people. I've done over
500 of them now. And if this is
new to you and you'd like to
check out previous ones, please
go to batgap.com B, A, T, G, A,
P, where you'll find all the
look under the past interviews
menu you'll find all the
previous ones organized in
several different ways. This
program is made possible by the
support of appreciative
listeners and viewers. So if you
appreciate it and would like to
support it in any amount, there
is a PayPal button on every page
of the site, and there's a
donations page for people who
don't like to deal with PayPal.
My guests today are Michael
Pollan and Chris Bache. I'll
introduce Michael first. Michael
is the author of eight books,
including how to change your
mind. Michael, say something,
because Chris's voice is,
picture is on the screen.
Michael Pollan: Yeah. Hi, Rick,
hi Chris, perfect to be here.
Rick Archer: There we go.
There's Michael. Mike, I think
Chris sniffled or something,
brought him up. He's the author
of eight books, including how to
change your mind, which is the
one we're going to be talking
about today, and the number of
books about food, including
cooked food rules in defense of
food, The Omnivore's Dilemma and
the Botany of Desire, all of
which were New York Times
bestsellers. Michael is a
longtime contributor to the New
York Times Magazine. He also
teaches writing at Harvard and
the University of California,
Berkeley, where he is the John S
and James L Knight, Professor of
science journalism in 2010 Time
Magazine named him one of the
100 most influential people in
the world. Okay, Chris Bache has
been on batgap before in a panel
discussion about five or six
years ago, you go ahead and say
something, Chris, so your
Chris Bache: picture Good to be
here, looking forward to our
conversation today. Good. There
you go.
Rick Archer: My software
switches back and forth
according to who's talking.
Chris is a professor emeritus in
the Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University where he taught
for 33 years. He's also adjunct
faculty at the California
Institute of integral studies
and a fellow at the Institute of
Noetic Sciences, an award
winning teacher. Chris' work
explores the philosophical
implications of Non-ordinary
states of consciousness,
especially psychedelic states.
Chris has written four books,
life cycles, a study of
reincarnation in light of
contemporary consciousness,
research dark night, early dawn,
a pioneering work in cycle,
psychedelic philosophy and
collective consciousness and the
living classroom, an exploration
of teaching and collective
fields of consciousness. His new
book is LSD and the mind of the
universe, and get the cover up.
That's Michael's book. LSD, in
the mind of the universe,
diamonds from heaven. And I
didn't show Chris Michael's book
when I mentioned it. Here's a
picture of Michael's book, how
to change your mind. The
subtitle is what the new science
of psychedelics teaches us about
consciousness, dying, addiction,
depression and Transcendence. So
it's great to have you guys as
I've been really looking forward
to this and really enjoying
preparing for it, and there's
been a lot of excitement, I
think, among the batgap
listeners and viewers. In fact,
I mentioned this interview the
other day on some Facebook
group. I mentioned Michael
Pollan's name, and some guy said
the food guy. Michael, how did
you, how did you switch, if you
did from being the food guy to
invest into exploring
psychedelics.
Michael Pollan: Well, before I
was the food guy, I was, I was
kind of the nature guy. I've
always been interested the
reason I got into food is I was
very interested in the in the
reciprocal relationship between
people and particularly plants,
but other species in general,
and CO evolution, and in book
you mentioned earlier, the
Botany of Desire, I had looked
at this whole question of
domesticated plants and propose
the idea that they manipulate us
as much as we manipulate them,
and that that a very fine
evolutionary strategy for a
select group of plants, and this
is true for animals too, is to
figure out. And by that I mean
you know, through trial and
error, natural selection or.
Visual selection, what sorts of
how, how to gratify human
desire. And a big human desire,
obviously, is for food. And
that's, that's what most
domesticated plants have worked
on, that strategy. But beauty is
another. And I mean, there's a
whole bunch of them, and but the
one that I found most curious is
is the plants that thrive by
gratifying our desire to change
consciousness. And so in that
book, I wrote a long chapter on
cannabis and and looking at the
you know how it has served the
cannabis plant to basically
through trial and error, figure
out how to engage with the whole
receptor network in our brains
and elsewhere in our body. And
so I've had this long standing
interest in in plant medicines
and psychoactive plants. And so
that was and I kind of laid
that, you know, aside while I
was doing all this food research
for the last several years, and
then stumbled on this new
research going on to use
Psilocybin specifically, which I
realize is not a plant, but a
fungus. Mushroom to Well, no,
it's technically, it's not. It's
another kingdom entirely.
Actually, we're more like fungi
than we are like plants. Plants
are primary producers. They can
take sunlight and make food from
it. We are parasitic on them,
and so are mushrooms. So we
share that we depend on plants
use of photosynthesis anyway, I
heard about this research giving
Psilocybin to people who were
had terminal cancer, and that it
was helping them deal with the
prospect of death or the fear of
recurrence. And this struck me
as a very curious, very curious
thing to do. On its face, I
didn't see the logic of it and
and then I was also, kind of, as
journalists do, picking up that
there was something in the air
around psychedelics right now,
and that there was a kind of
renewed interest that was very
serious from a scientific or
philosophical point of view. And
that came, I was at a dinner
party and with a group of
people. I didn't know it was a
long table and a big house, and
I heard down at the end of the
table this woman who looked at
beauty about my age, talking
about her acid trip, and I
figured she was talking about
some college adventure. And then
I listened a little closely, and
it was a couple of weeks ago,
and here she was, she's very
prominent developmental
psychologist, talking about the
insights into the consciousness
of children that her new
acquaintance with LSD had given
her. And so as journalists, we
put together a couple of data
points, and that was enough to
convince me that there's
something going on here that I
want to look into so that that's
kind of how it happened. I was
also just thrilled to have a new
topic as rich as this and and
one that, you know, I mean, I
was a total neophyte when it
comes to spiritual matters,
neuro scientific matters,
psychological matters. So to me,
the great thing about writing
books and being a journalist and
not a specialist is you get to
master whole new topics as an
adult, and you get paid to do
it. It's kind of a gig.
Rick Archer: Yeah, I kind of
feel that way doing this. It's
although it's pretty much the
same topic, but a different
flavor of it every week, and I
love just focusing on it. So one
thing that comes through in your
book, Michael, is that, and one
thing you just kind of alluded
to, is that there's certain
intelligence in the plant
kingdom, and also, and
specifically in the psychedelic
plant kingdom that you know,
they're not just dumb chemicals.
It's almost as if there's a
spirit of the of the plants,
which has an agenda, which has
an initiative, which wants, in
some people's estimation, to
foster human evolution by
providing themselves to us as
means of shifting our
consciousness. You want to touch
upon that a little bit?
Michael Pollan: Yeah, I don't
think I would go that far, or I
haven't had evidence to go that
far, that plants are bearing a
message and trying to get us to
save them or save the planet. It
could be true, but I don't have
evidence of that. But I've, have
written on plant intelligence,
and I'm I'm constantly amazed at
what plants can do and how much
we underestimate them. You know,
we're learning now that plants
have a pretty elaborate
communications network, that the
trees in a forest convey
messages using mycelium, which
are the filaments of mushrooms,
to send messages to trade
nutrients that the trees and
forest can warn each other when
there's a threat, and when they
when they told to that threat,
they'll actually change their
flavor and in their leaves to
make them less appealing to
insects, or they'll start
producing toxins a very. Various
kinds. Plants have memory,
plants, plants are intelligent.
I have no question about that.
It has something to do with how
you define intelligence, of
course, but a basic definition
is a problem solving ability
that their reactions to
situations are not simply
automatic or instinctual, but
that they can deal with novel
threats in novel ways, and that
they can remember things too.
There have been some very
interesting trials. Monica
Gagliano is a botanist who's
who's demonstrated that that
plants can remember and store
information in a way. So I have
enormous respect for them. I
think that they do have we have
to acknowledge they have a kind
of subjectivity the way we do.
They're conscious, not in the
sense I think we normally mean
by that word, which also folds
in ideas of self consciousness
and a subjective sense of what
it's like to be Chris Bache or
Rick Archer or Michael Pollan, I
don't, I don't. I don't have any
reason to believe they have
that, but they have a point of
view, and they have interests,
and they pursue these in a
different way than we do, and
they're conscious in the sense
of being aware of their
environment and responding
appropriately.
Rick Archer: We may get into
this later, but some say that,
you know, consciousness is
fundamental, and matter is sort
of an epic phenomenon of
consciousness, rather than the
other way around, and that all
forms of matter reflect or
express consciousness to varying
degrees, even a stone and
obviously way On up the
evolutionary ladder. But let's
table that for for a little bit
later. So you heard, you
overheard this conversation at
the dinner party. And so how did
you proceed? I know you
proceeded in many cases with a
great deal of what every case
with a great deal of caution and
seriousness, reluctance,
trepidations. You were often
unable to sleep the night before
a session because you were sort
of anxious about what might
happen.
Michael Pollan: So, you know,
the idea of even having a
session came, you know, came a
little later. The first thing I
did was reach out to an editor
at the New Yorker and say, I've
got a really cool story I want
to write about these trials,
interview the people who are who
are going on these Psilocybin
journeys, talk to the
scientists, try to understand
the neuroscience of it and the
psychology. And to my delight,
they were willing to underwrite
that project. So that was the
beginning of my investigation,
and I wrote a piece for The New
Yorker, which came out in
February 2015 called the trip
treatment, and it's available
online for free. And if you just
search that, and that was a kind
of straight ahead piece of
science journalism, there was no
participatory angle to it. I
don't think they would have
published it if there were. It
was all like white coats and
scientists and and patients,
volunteers and but the
interviews were extraordinary,
and the people I met and the
kinds of transformative
experiences that a single
psychedelic journey had given
them completely resetting their
attitude toward death, lifting
their fear entirely. In many
Rick Archer: cases, any cancer
patients, I'm sorry, cancer
patients,
Michael Pollan: these are cancer
patients, yeah, with serious
diagnoses. I mean, some were
terminal, some were paralyzed by
fear and anxiety at the threat
of a recurrence. But in all
ways, they were. They had this,
what the doctors call
existential distress and and
they found relief in about 80%
of the cases, which is quite
remarkable, and it's a single
intervention. I mean, we don't
have much like that in
psychiatry, right? Or palliative
care, you know, we have morphine
we give people which dulls their
perception and relieves their
pain but doesn't, doesn't help
them spiritually, deal with the
situation they're in.
Rick Archer: Tell us some more
anecdotes, and give us an
overview of the research that's
taking place. And it's not only
cancer patients, but alcoholics
and depressed people and right?
And so it
Michael Pollan: started with
cancer patients. You know, the
first kind of clinical
applications, and the reason for
that is a couple. One is it's a
sympathetic group. The
regulators are a little less
worried about any potential
toxicity in the case of people
who have terminal diagnoses. In
the same way that you know
people with AIDS, they would,
they were willing to give drugs
that hadn't been thoroughly
vetted yet if people wanted to
take them. So there was a
comfort level, I think, for the
regulators, and a sympathetic
angle for the for the public in
general. I mean, how could you
withhold this from someone who
was dying and had fear, you
know, tremendous fear. And here
was something that promised to
to lift it. But since then.
Since the success of those
trials, there have been several
others looking at different
indications, medical
indications, an important one
that's being worked on now is
depression. And this grew out of
the the cancer trials in that
they saw that depression scores,
as the psychologists measure
them, had dropped significantly,
and so the FDA actually
encouraged the researchers to
Why don't you look at depression
more widely? Because this is a
tremendous problem. The tools we
have to treat it are very poor.
Rates of depression are rising
rapidly. I think a big question
remains is whether depression is
one thing, and if the kind of
depression that a cancer patient
experiences is similar to the
kind of depression of someone
who has a, you know, general
depression or treatment
resistant depression for years
and years and years, the cancer
patients depression is recent,
very often and has a has a
clearly defined cause. And
that's not true for everyone
struggling with depression. So
we'll see. We'll see if it
works. There's some evidence
that it will. There was a trial
at Imperial College in London of
depressive patients treatment
resistant. I believe they were,
and many of them, most of them,
showed significant but short
lived results. They their, their
depression lifted for a couple
months, and then gradually it
returned, not in all cases, but
in most of them. So there's,
there's encouraging reason to
pursue this. And there, there
are two big trials going on
right now for depression are
about to get started. There have
been, as you suggest, trials for
addiction in in alcoholics and
cigarette smokers and cocaine
addicts and those, in a
preliminary way, are showing
very promising results. And I
think that's interesting, and
may turn out to be, I think
behavioral change may be one of
the really big applications of
psychedelics. With that in mind,
they're looking at Johns hop
Johns Hopkins, I think, is going
to look at eating disorders, and
that's very important, because
anorexia is actually the hardest
psychiatric illness to treat,
and has the lowest rates of
success and the highest
mortality of all psychiatric
problems. So I think if we can
make progress on that, it'd be
fantastic. Let's see what else
is being tried. There was a
small trial of obsession,
obsessive compulsive disorder,
and there'll be more work with
that. The drugs have been used
with high functioning autistic
people who have social anxiety
and that that result has been
encouraging also. So there's a
whole range and to people who
think, well, how can psychedelic
be such a panacea? I think it's
important to note that the kinds
of problems it works on or seems
to be effective with have a lot
in common. They're all at the
end of the spectrum where
people's thinking becomes too
rigid, too trapped in deep
grooves of habit, whether mental
habit or behavioral habit,
people are in these loops and
they can't break out of them.
And what the psychedelics seem
to do is is a real jolt to the
system, and gives people the
kind of perspective on their
lives that can actually break
mental habit, and it needs to be
accompanied by lots of
therapeutic intervention. These
aren't people going off and
having a Psilocybin trip in the
woods alone. These are guided
trips, and I think it's a really
important distinction. People
are very carefully prepared in
advance, told what to expect,
how to deal with difficulties
that will come up if they you
know, because it can be a very,
very frightening things can
happen, especially if you're if
you're facing your mortality,
and then during the experience,
the guides are with you the
whole time in the university
trials. Are usually two guys, a
man and a woman, and they're not
saying very much. It's very non
interventionist. The idea is to
basically give you a sense of
safety so you can surrender to
what can be a very disturbing
set of mental events. And then
after the session, you come
back, usually the next day, or
in the next couple days, and you
have what's called an
integration session, where you
tell the therapist what you saw,
what happened, what you're
puzzled by, and with the
therapist, you try to kind of
come to some interpretation of
what's happened and figure out
how you can take the lessons,
the insights of That trip and
apply them to the conduct of
your life.
Rick Archer: Have these
therapists usually taken
Psilocybin themselves so that
they have a better idea of what
the person is going through?
Michael Pollan: Well, I can only
guess about that, because none
of them will admit it. But, you
know, but I. Can see why it
would put them at reputational
risk for objectivity. People
would challenge the study,
saying, These people are, you
know, aficionados of
psychedelics. You know, I have
reason to believe that some of
them have but none of them would
talk about it on the record. A
couple would talk about it off
the record, and some would just
simply say, No. So it's hard to
believe you wouldn't develop the
kind of curiosity I developed,
because in the course of doing
this research, I it became clear
to me that I couldn't really
understand what these volunteers
were going through without
having a similar experience
myself. And that's and that then
became the more autobiographical
part of the book where I engaged
with several underground guides
because I couldn't get into the
above ground trials and work
with them to have a very similar
experience in a slightly
different context.
Rick Archer: Yeah, your your
answer to that question brings
up a point, which is that,
since, I guess it was the early
70s when Nixon declared Timothy
Leary to be the most dangerous
man in America, and psychedelic
research was clamped down upon,
there hasn't really been much
going on. And now it sounds like
it's kind of burgeoning, but is
it, I mean, can anybody,
anywhere who's qualified study
this, or is it still like a real
trickle compared to what might
be taking place?
Michael Pollan: The only reason
it's trickly at all is that
there's no federal funding. All
the funding is is private money,
charitable donations. And
luckily, there's a lot of
visionary people with a lot of
dough in this country, and
they're supporting the work, but
there's quite a bit of it. There
are many universities around the
country getting interested and
getting involved. There is these
two depression trials, each are
going to have six or eight
sites, each of which is a
medical school or a university.
The FDA is not standing in the
way. They made a decision way
back in 92 because people have
been knocking on the door for a
long time, that they would treat
psychedelics like any other
drug, and if you could persuade
them that there was a good
reason for this experiment, they
would grant permission, and the
DEA would grant a license to use
it. So I haven't heard of
people, you know, I mean serious
researchers, encountering
federal obstacles. The main
obstacle is money, okay,
Rick Archer: yeah, your comment
about the kind of commonality of
all the types of difficulties
which are being addressed with
psychedelics, being that all
these people are too kind of
rigid or locked down in their
thinking or in their
perspective. I was thinking that
as you were leading up to that
comment, it seems like
Psilocybin and some of these
other drugs they're using are so
different from usual protocols,
because most things tend to dull
you in one way or another, you
know, whereas this is a real
opening up of your awareness and
a radical shift of your
perspective. In fact, I think
you say many times in your book
that a lot of people say, Wow,
that was the most profound
experience I ever had in my
life. And I don't feel like
drinking anymore, taking smoking
cigarettes anymore or something.
So it's interesting that there
could be such a thing that, you
know, with one session would
give you such a radically
different perspective and shift
your behavior permanently.
Michael Pollan: Yeah, and the I
also, you know, other
psychiatric drugs essentially
deal with symptoms, and you take
them every day, perhaps for the
rest of your life, and chemicals
are in your brain all the time.
Here you've got this one shot or
two shot intervention, the
chemical, which is not very
toxic, whether you're talking
about Psilocybin or LSD, is in
your brain for a short amount of
time, and you are dealing with
cures. In many cases, you're
solving the problem because
you're, you're, as you say,
you're not dulling the patient.
You are opening them up, and, I
think relieving them from ego
consciousness for a period of
time. I think that's, that's
probably important way, you
know, mechanism for how this
works. One of the really
interesting findings of the
research that I cover in the
book is, you know, the effort to
figure out what's going on in
the brain when someone's having
a psychedelic experience and the
current thinking is that there's
one particular brain network,
the default mode network, which
is this tightly linked set of
structures in the midline that
connect the prefrontal cortex to
older, deeper areas of memory
and emotion in the posterior
cingulate cortex. And this, this
is kind of the the orchestrator
or conductor of brain activity.
This network you. It is closely
associated with the generation
of the idea of a self and so
it's where self reflection takes
place. It's where time mental
time travel takes place. Theory
of Mind, the ability to impute
mental states to others, and
what's called autobiographical
memory, the faculty by which we
take the events, whatever
happens in our lives, and tie it
into the story we tell ourselves
of who we are. So you know, if
the ego could be said to have an
address, it's probably in this
area, and this area of the brain
is suppressed dramatically. And
this was a big surprise, because
they thought psychedelics in the
brain would just represent a lot
of fireworks, an excitation of
everything. In fact, it's the
opposite for this one particular
network, and you can correlate a
radical down regulation of the
default mode network with
reported experiences of ego
dissolution. When people tell
you, yeah, on that trip, I just
completely my sense of self was
obliterated. They will see on
the FMRI that their default mode
network has been essentially
deactivated. So that's a very
interesting insight into where
that kind of thinking to the
extent it has a material
manifestation, where that's
happening. And it may be that
the relief from ego
consciousness and an overactive
default mode network is
implicated in a lot of these
problems, like depression. You
know, there is research to
suggest that depressed people
have an overactive default mode
network that's that is kind of
punishing, and they can't get
out of their heads, because the
default mode network also lights
up when you're when you're mind
wandering, when you don't have
anything in the world getting
your attention. It operates in a
seesaw relationship with the
intentional network, the
attentional networks, and so
giving people a vacation from
that, that of you know, that
kind of regulatory authority
allows lots of other activity to
bloom. And there's an
illustration in my book that
shows it was an attempt to show
people how the brain gets
rewired during the Psilocybin or
LSD experience and so and in
this drawing you around this
circle, you get all these
different brain networks, you
know, the visual cortex or the
auditory networks, or the you
Know, the networks that direct
your physical activities, and
suddenly you get all this
communication between networks
that don't ordinarily
communicate with one another,
and that might explain
synesthesia, the phenomenon of
being able to see musical notes
that perhaps your auditory
center is talking directly to
your visual cortex without Going
through the default mode
network, so the brain is
temporarily rewired. And we know
that brain connections, you
know, are new ways of thinking,
and if you have them, even
temporarily, you can exercise
them and make them more salient.
And so it's just a theory, but
that's one of the operative
theories of what might be going
on here that you know, when you
have some profound insight on
psychedelics, it may be that the
product of, you know, connecting
the dots literally in a new way.
Rick Archer: Yeah, a couple of
thoughts on that. One is that if
we think of the brain as a
filter or a lens or a receiver
of consciousness, rather than as
a generator of consciousness,
then you know, what you said
about the default mode network
shutting down or being becoming
more quiet would imply, perhaps
that there's less filtration
taking place, so whatever
consciousness is can shine
through more fully. And you
know, the ancient traditions say
that consciousness is bliss in
one of its attributes. And so,
you know, you can experience
very gratifying, fulfilling
states if that default mode
network is shut down. Somewhat.
Another little point there is
that a lot of the meditation
research has shown that there is
a remarkable degree of coherence
between different parts of the
brain that are ordinary, not
correlated or coherent with one
another, as measured by EEG. So
you know, frequencies will just
sort of line up in synchrony,
whereas before they were
asynchronous.
Michael Pollan: And also, you
know, the meditation research
done by people like Judson
Brewer, who also has taken fMRI
images of experienced meditators
while they're meditating, those
scans look very much like the
psychedelic scans. He saw that
actually, and was quite struck
by the similarities. So that
meditation also down regulates
the default mode network. And I
think that's really significant.
But your point. Too about, you
know, opening up the doors of
perception, as Huxley called it.
You know, when he talked about
the reducing valve, it was
pretty clear he was talking
about the ego. The ego is really
what walls us off from, you
know, whether it's internal,
unconscious material or external
sensory information, and what
seems to be, you know, it is
what defends us from being
overwhelmed by reality, by being
overwhelmed by nature, by being
overwhelmed by what's in our
unconscious and and those walls
come down, I think, during
psychedelic experience, and that
that accounts for the sense of
merging that people have. And so
I think that, you know, I think
we're talking about a lot of
different vocabularies for the
same thing. I'm using ego and
walls, and I know that's very
psychodynamic, and you're using
a more spiritual vocabulary, but
I think we're talking about the
same thing, yeah, I think so,
Rick Archer: Chris, do you have
any questions or comments on
what we've been saying so far?
Chris Bache: I've just been
enjoying Michael's presentation
a great deal. I'm so deeply
appreciative that a person of
your caliber, Michael has done
such an excellent job of
presenting the history and the
issues in the people's lives
being touched in this form of
therapy, you just open up the
conversation to many people who
previously would have just never
been willing to have a
conversation about psychedelics,
and you've done such a good job
with it. You've done it so well,
and you capture the
personalities involved so well.
Just really appreciate what
you've done.
Michael Pollan: Thank you. Well,
I was, you know, I was
approaching it from outside,
obviously, and with a certain,
you know, naivete and skepticism
and, you know, I mean, there are
people with a lot more knowledge
and experience in the
psychedelic world, but they've
tended to be in a conversation
that takes place within the
psychedelic community. And I
wasn't coming from there and,
and I also always write for an
audience that I don't assume has
any interest in the subject. I'm
just much more interested in in
in talking to the general reader
and, and, you know, grabbing
them by the caller and say, Hey,
this is really cool. You should
you should read this stuff,
whether it's about food or
agriculture, all these kind of
things. So I think that that
stance was very useful to me in
in bringing people into this
conversation. And it's been very
gratifying to see how many
people and whether they're in
the therapeutic community or the
neuroscience community, have
gotten excited in the last year
about the potential here, and
want to get involved as
researchers and as people
experimenting with psychedelics.
So, you know, look, this
Renaissance was happening. I
mean, I was reporting on saying
that was already happening, but
I feel very lucky that I was
able to play some role in
bringing people into the tent,
yeah.
Rick Archer: So we can probably
spend an hour going through all
the various stages of your
exploration, you know, with
psychedelics and different
experiences you had, and all
that stuff and all that is
covered very well in your book.
So I think what I'd like to do
is just ask you a question which
came in from someone actually
named Susie Parkinson in
Carlsbad, California. She asked,
since your original psychedelic
journeys, or as a result of
them, perhaps, has your belief
system or perspective changed,
deepened or taken on a meaning
which it didn't previously have.
Michael Pollan: Yeah, it's a
great question. Thank you for
posing it. My experiences have
changed me in various ways. I
think for the most part, the
personality changes are pretty
subtle. You know, my wife's not
here right now, but I would drag
her in to say, to tell you that
I've asked her this question
because your partner knows you
better than anybody else and is
very sensitive to any changes.
And she basically feels that I'm
a more open and patient person
than I was, and she was very
apprehensive when I started
getting involved with this, that
I might change for the worse.
She doesn't seem to think I have
intellectually, there has been a
change. I think my understanding
of spirituality has changed, and
what that means. Think it's
important to understand you guys
work on these issues all the
time, but I was really kind of
spiritually retarded before I
started this, it's just a part
of my life, my mind, that I
hadn't developed. I mean, some
people look at body and desire,
and I think that's a very
spiritual take, right? I talk
about food in a very spiritual
way, and the importance of
communion, but I really didn't
see myself as spiritual, partly
because my understanding of
spirituality was that it
existed. Suggested in opposition
to science skepticism, and that
implied a I'm telling you, I was
retarded, but it implied a
belief in the supernatural
things beyond the scope of
science never to understand. And
so I approached it that way, and
I was very much a pretty
confirmed materialist in my
philosophical outline, that that
the laws of nature could explain
everything. And I realized how
limited this was. And so I had
after my psychedelic journeys,
and after one in particular,
where I had a very profound
experience of transcending my
ego, my usual sense of self, and
I actually beheld myself
dissolving. I'm first bursting
into a little cloud of post it
notes. That was me, and it was,
there was nothing left. And then
another time where I was, I felt
myself kind of spread out on the
ground like a coat of paint or
butter. And but a new
perspective arose for me to
observe this scene, and that was
the spooky part, and it's the
part I still don't understand.
From what new point of view was
I taking in the scene? It was an
eye that wasn't familiar to me.
It was an eye that was
completely fine with what was
happening, unburdened,
untroubled, disinterested and
reconciled to whatever there
was. And it was quite profound
and and once that sense of self
was gone, I was totally open or
unprotected, undefended against
anything and and then started
merging. And in this in this
particular instance, I merged
with a piece of music I had had
my guide put on this
unaccompanied Cello Suite by
Bach number two and de Mudra,
which is a very sad, beautiful
piece of music, and I became it.
There was no subject object
duality at all. I was identical
to this music. I could feel yo,
yo, Ma's the horse hair on his
bow going over my skin. And I
was inside this dark well
looking out and the breeze of
the vibrations of the music. I
could physically feel them. It
was, it was remarkable. And I
came out of that, you know, the
next day, I went to my guide for
integration, and I said, Well,
I'd have this experience of
complete ego dissolution and the
and she said, What did you learn
from that? I said, well, that
you're not identical to your
ego. You don't have to there's
another ground on which to
stand, but it was a very
mysterious other ground. And she
said, Well, wasn't that worth
the price of admission? And I
said, Yes, but it was really
interesting. But what do you do
with it? You know now my ego is
back in uniform, back on patrol,
and so what good was it? And she
said, Well, you'd had a sample
of this way of being, and you
can cultivate it. And I said,
How? And she said, through
meditation, basically. And like,
I'm, like a great many people
and a great many American
Buddhists, this opened a door
into and made it it made me much
more comfortable in the mental
space of meditation, and I could
navigate it better. And
sometimes I do attain that
perspective that I had had
during that that Psilocybin
trip. So did that make me more
spiritual? I am not prepared to
conclude that that new
perspective that opened up, it
was some Transpersonal
perspective or some universal
consciousness. I know that
Aldous Huxley, you know, when it
happened to him, said that was
the mind at large, which was
something that we tune in,
that's outside. I'd be really
here, curious to hear Chris's
take on that. I don't know. It
could just as easily be another
product of my mind that, you
know, I hadn't experienced
before, because the damn ego,
you know, overshadowed it, but I
came to see that my my
understanding of spirituality,
was faulty, because the what
spirituality is, for Me is
powerful connection, an
openness, an undefended ability
to connect, whether it's to
nature, which is very important
to me, the natural world. And
during another psychedelic
experience, I had the sense of
nature being very much alive. I
mean, the leaves in my garden
were returning my gaze, in some
sense. And it was a beautiful
experience. It was really
wonderful. So there was the
connection to nature that is
opened up, and then there is
connection to other people, the
feelings of love that so many
people report on psychedelics,
and this powerful connection to
other people and the universe in
some more general way. And so
that's what spirituality. Is now
to me, it's it's opening the
gates so you, you can connect at
a very deep level without any
screen between you and the
other, no subject object. And so
I learned that the opposite of
spiritual, the word spiritual,
should not be material, as I
understood it. It should be
egotistical, because it really
is the ego that stands in the
way of those powerful
connections, and that the Ego is
the Enemy of spiritual
development. So that's kind of
that was my takeaway. It's not
final in any way. I think I have
a lot more to learn from the
experience, and I might come out
in a different place. I'm very
curious about, Well, Chris, I
would be curious to know how you
would interpret that experience
of this new perspective opening
up on your dissolved self.
Chris Bache: Well, you know, as
I listen to you speak, I'm
reminded of Sri Suzuki in his
beautiful little book on
meditation, big mind, little
mind, and you know, it's like
there's little mind which is
very efficient getting things
done, sits at our desk, you
know, answers the phone, and
then there's big mind, which is
really that dimension of mind
which is just so profoundly
larger than other than and
inclusive of little mind. It's
just a different wavelength of
consciousness. And so then the
question is, of course, all of
the meditation traditions agree
that there are many, many layers
to ego. So you can kind of get
clear at one level and get
caught in another, and clear at
that level get caught another.
It's a labyrinth kind of thing.
But according to their ways of
thinking, it is possible to
profoundly quiet still allow ego
to become transparent. And when
ego becomes transparent, this
this larger background context
surfaces in awareness. So that
rings true. In my experience,
the question then becomes, okay,
if there's little mind and big
mind, what is the nature of
mind? Just mind, and that opens
it, then we're then we're off to
the races, because then we get
into a very interesting
discussion of what is the nature
of consciousness, and what is
conscious, and who can have
consciousness, and so on so
forth. So,
Michael Pollan: I mean, what is
the nature of mine? I know
that's a big fat question.
Chris Bache: Yeah, that's a big
one. And it's, it's, it's,
personally, I don't have a
vested interest in specific
definitions of consciousness and
specific definitions of mine.
I'm kind of happy to go where
different people want to go with
under with definitions of
consciousness per se, as long as
the definition is open to a
complete phenomenology of mind,
because my background training
is in philosophy of religion and
phenomenology has been a large
part of that. So I think it's
important for us to critically,
not naively, but critically,
look at the broadest body of
data that we have for what mind
is and how mind manifests, and
what it can do. So, can mind
influence the health of the
body? Can mind actually
influence physical objects? The
telekinesis can Is there a mind
can linking between human beings
and plants, so that there can be
a genuine exchange of
information at some level. I
mean, that opens, that gets us
into the deeper question. And
then when we go to Aldous
Huxley, and he goes to mind at
large, that's the assertion of
an encompassing mind that holds
all minds, all sub minds, held
within a master kind of
intelligence of the universe.
I'm comfortable with that
concept, just because I've had
so many experiences of so many
dimensions of that mind that I'm
comfortable I talk about the
creative intelligence of the
universe. I don't know what to
call it on site. I don't know
what name we should give it, and
I'm sometimes I'll talk about it
as the divine, but I'm not a
theist, and I'm not a
supernaturalist. I completely
agree with you on that way, to
me, it's all natural, it's all
nature. It's all part of nature.
And there's nothing about for
me, the study of consciousness,
which should be beyond the range
of scientific investigation, but
I've spent so much time over the
many years exploring different
aspects of that mind that
Unknown: using what tools,
Chris Bache: well, my primary
tool has been LSD. In my
explorations, I also have
experience. With Psilocybin and
other in Ayahuasca and salvia
dip and norm and but my primary
instrument of exploration was
LSD use in a particular a very
specific modality. So I don't
should I describe this Rick?
Should we do this now?
Rick Archer: Or let me just wrap
up a point that Michael made
earlier, and then let's do it.
Michael was saying that he used
to have a sort of a version to
the notion of spirituality
because he felt it was anti
scientific. Excuse me, if I
didn't express that quite right,
but there was, you know, some
distrust of it, because it
seemed probably you've heard,
you heard a lot of woo things. I
mean, look at I mean, religion
and science have been at each
other's throats for a long time.
People used to be burned at the
stake for believing that the
earth wasn't the center of the
solar system. And I feel that
we've reached a point where
science and spirituality can
complement each other
tremendously. If we take
anything that spirituality or
any religious tradition has ever
proposed or suggested as a
hypothesis, rather than as
something that we ought to
believe in, then it's something
that's potential that might be
open to investigate,
experiential investigation. And
I think Chris will comment on a
lot of things he's investigated
experientially, which might seem
extremely hypothetical to the
average person that has some of
these things have very far
reaching implications for
humanity, for religion, for
spirituality, I don't think
there's a heck of a lot of value
in just believing in something
because somebody says you ought
to, or some tradition says you
ought to, or anything. I think
everything should be open to
experiential investigation. So
that's what the scientific
attitude brings to spirituality.
On the other hand, spirituality
can bring something to science,
because science doesn't possess
the tools for investigating the
subtle realms that spirituality
has specialized in, has dealt
with. And LSD is such a tool,
although ultimately our own, our
human nervous system, is such a
tool. And throughout the ages, I
think what mystics have been
doing is using that tool to and
fine tuning it and learning how
to use it such that they can
explore all sorts of subtle
dimensions, and, you know, add
to human knowledge in ways that
modern science Couldn't even
hope to begin to do at its
current stage. So anyway, I just
wanted to get that out. And then
you go ahead, Chris, and segue
from that, well,
Chris Bache: just a footnote.
Add a note on to what you said.
Rick, it's one thing to study
the quantitative qualities of
consciousness, and it's another
thing to study study the
qualitative nature of
consciousness. And I think
science is extraordinarily good
at studying the quantitative
nature of consciousness and
looking at the various
physiological correlations,
various states of awareness, so
on, so forth. But I think we can
study scientifically, if we
broaden our methodology of
science, we can study the
qualitative characteristics of
consciousness. We do so by
controlled experiment. We do so
by getting carefully screened
different people from different
backgrounds, for example,
putting them through the same
exploratory regimen, carefully
recording their experiences
afterwards, comparing their
experiences across populations.
I mean, we can't put experience
under a microscope, but we can
use all of our critical skills
to study the qualitative nature
of experience, and then we can
start broadening it into cross
cultural and historical
analysis. So I think we can be
critical, but being critical is
larger than being neurological
Michael Pollan: Well, I mean,
you can't. I mean, the
interesting, what's interesting
to me about consciousness as a
subject for scientific
exploration is you can't study
it without experience. There's
no other tool, right? I mean,
phenomenology is the only tool
to understand the subjectivity,
and at least so far. And so,
yeah, I think I agree. I think
you have to, you have to go down
that path, and you can do that
path with a lot of rigor. And
it's one of the interesting
things about the psychedelic
work. The reports of the
volunteers are critically
important, and you car and
sometimes you correlate those
reports with what you're seeing
on your brain scans and some but
sometimes you don't need to. So
but, but going back to this
question of but, I think a big
question is whether you know.
Know whether there's any real
evidence to think that brains
don't produce consciousness, or
that, you know, that mind
precedes matter? I think that's
a very interesting question. And
I went into my own
investigations assuming, because
that's the consensus among
scientists is that, well, we
don't know how it happens, but
we assume that these neurons,
these cells, are producing
consciousness in some way. Even
though it's it's very hard to
get from cells to that
phenomenon. Nobody has a clue
how to do it. That seemed to be
the more parsimonious, you know,
or starting principle. But a lot
of people, after experience of
psychedelics come out in a
different place.
Rick Archer: Yeah, I interviewed
a guy a few months ago named
Mark Gober who wrote a book
called The End to upside down
thinking, which addresses this
very point. And, you know, it
may seem parsimonious initially,
that consciousness is just an
epiphenomenon of brain
functioning, but there are so
many anomalies, when you look at
it that way that keep pecking
away at that materialistic
worldview. And Mark and his book
really goes through these in a
very brilliant way. And what's
the name of the book? It's
called the end, or maybe it's an
end. I think maybe the end to
upside down, thinking, by Mark
Gober, G, O, B, E, R, and he's
he's been on back gap a few
months ago, so you can find him
there. But it's like there's a
new
Michael Pollan: book also by
Jeffrey krapal. Yeah, this book
is fascinating. I recommend him
for back on the show. But he's
also looking at a series of
people, some of them scientists,
others philosophers, who
underwent this flip in their
thinking to to believing that
their that you know mind may
well perceive matter and has
these case histories, among
other things.
Rick Archer: Yeah. Oh, go ahead,
Chris, you're gonna say the
Chris Bache: field of study that
shifted my thinking in that
regard. Because I finished
graduate school, even though it
was in philosophy of religion, I
was a pretty atheistically
inclined agnostic. By the time I
finished graduate school, I was
well versed in the rise of
science and human in human
values and in enjoyed that and
join that movement fully. I tell
my students, if you haven't
fallen in love with Kant, with
science, you've missed the
great, one of the great romances
of history. I mean, this is just
such a massive, extraordinarily
ground shaking pivot in human
understanding. But one of the
areas which shifted my thinking
about the idea that our brain
creates consciousness, and of
course, clearly, our brain does
generate consciousness, in a
sense, but it was the
reincarnation research. It was
Ian Stevenson's Research at the
University of Virginia and the
multiple volumes that he had
published documenting very
detailed cases of from around
the world, children, very small,
345, years old, who had detailed
memories of what appeared to be
their previous life. And he was
able to extract, get those
memories, consolidate them, and
verify sufficient number of
those memories to build an
extremely strong case for the
fact of reincarnation without
knowing the theory of it,
without knowing how it actually
takes place, that there is some
type of continuity of
consciousness. Now, there's lots
and lots of levels of issues
involved in this one life to
another life. Yeah, it seems to
be. I mean, some people would
say, well, those memories are
actually drawn out of the
collective unconscious. And you
know, that doesn't show
continuity of life to life, but
I think Stevenson's evidence is
really a strong evidence for
some type of continuity of an
awareness from lifetime to
lifetime, especially his last
two book, which is a two volume
book on philosophy and on
reincarnation and biology, in
which he studied 170 87 cases of
children who not only had
psychological recall from their
previous lifetime, but actually
bore the marks in their body in
the form of birthmarks, which
replicated wounds of death in
the previous incarnation. So
somehow, it was as if
consciousness had been
traumatized in such a way that
it not only imprinted on
subsequent mind, but it
imprinted on the body of
subsequent mind. So after
looking at this data a lot, I
think what it tells us is we
have information in our mind
that predates this body, and if
that's the case, if and if those
can be legitimated, verified
memories, then that indicates
that there is at least in some
way in which our awareness, our
memory, our mind, is not
generated by our.
Rick Archer: Brain. A very
simple metaphor for this, which
I'm sure you've both heard is,
you know, I mean radios and
televisions, they are detectors,
or not transmitters. They're
receivers of fluctuations in the
electromagnetic field, which is
ubiquitous, and if the radio
breaks, the radio transmission
from the, you know, tower 50
miles away or something, doesn't
stop. Other radios can still
pick it up, and we can get a new
radio and listen to it again. So
if consciousness is a field, as
opposed to just a product of the
brain, then, you know, very
we're all tapped into that
field, and we kind of share it
in common as a foundation. But
then, how do you account for
individuality, and an
individuality moving from life
to life, from from one body to
another? And that leads me into
a question I'd like to ask,
which will get us a little bit
back to psychedelics, which is
that, you know, research shows
that subjective experiences in
meditation and other spiritual
practices have physiological
effects, which we've been
talking about. And Western
science is only able to measure
the gross physiology, and
traditionally, it's understood
that we also have a subtle
physiology. Chinese and Vedic
systems offer elaborate
explanations of the subtle body
using terms such as Qi or Prana
or Sushumna and Ida and Pingala,
nadis, etc, and these traditions
understand that it's necessary
to condition and strengthen the
subtle body to sustain the
enormous flows of energy that
accompany spiritual awakening.
Often spiritual aspirants spend
years or decades doing this
before awakening occurs. So what
are so this whole subtle body
thing has implications for
reincarnation, because it would
be the subtle body that moves
from one gross body to another
when the gross body wears out.
The Bhagavad Gita says it's like
changing clothes. So, but here's
the question, what are your
thoughts on the fact that anyone
can ingest a psychedelic
substance without having
prepared the subtle body, or can
psychedelics facilitate such
preparation? Either of you can
answer
Michael Pollan: this. Give this
one to Chris.
Chris Bache: Thanks, Michael.
Michael Pollan: Now the question
is built on an understanding of
subtle bodies and gross bodies
that i is totally unfamiliar to
Chris Bache: me, in answering,
in responding, I don't want to
assume the your observation that
is the subtle body that
transfers from incarnation to
incarnation. It may be, I'm just
not sure that we've nailed it
down that close. Let's take its
hypothesis and so again,
individuality is the whole
question is, what is
individuality? So is the
individuality of one life
transferring to the
individuality or intact in
another life? And I think those
are very subtle and complicated
questions, and I don't mean to
prejudge them at all, so I don't
want to assume a set answer to
what is individuality or what is
the subtle body that said my
experience, I have a lot of
convictions around the subtle
body, and specifically the
impact The way psychedelic
experiences can impact the
subtle body. But to explain, I
mean, I can't let me say a
little bit of about my
background, because there are so
many different variations of
psychedelic experiences, and I
want to define mine. That's the
body of data that I draw from
when I finished graduate school
in 78 I met the work of
Stanislav Grof. Immediately, he
had just published realms of the
human unconscious. He had 100 of
100 essays published by that
time, and I was immediately
taken atheistically agnostic as
I was, I was immediately taken
by his research proposal that
through these substances, if
they were used in a careful and
controlled circumstance, that we
could use them to experience
deeper dimensions of our own
mind. And I was particularly
interested in his observation
that one can go deeper than
personal consciousness. One can
go deeper than even collective
unconscious. You can go deeper
into the mind of the universe
itself. He didn't say it quite
like that, but that was the
implication of what he did. And
I was immediately fascinated by
that, because I was a
philosopher of religion and
exploring the the consciousness
of the universe, if there is a
consciousness of the universe,
could have enormous implications
for a variety of philosophical
questions. So this was 1978 and
I wanted to do the psychedelic
work. I was just like Michael,
after doing the research and
looking at the literature and
looking at some. Other people's
lives had been changed. I wanted
to participate, and I basically
did what Michael did. I
basically made a choice to have
some underground experiments
with psychedelics. I mean, I
don't like going underground.
I'd much rather be in a legally
sanctioned experimental
protocol, but that wasn't
available to me. So I chose to
learn Stan Grof methods for
working with psychedelics and
can and how to have a
psychedelic session, and all the
ins and outs that have now
become kind of standardized in
psychedelic protocols, to use
his methods, and then to use
them privately, to explore my
own consciousness, and to do it
as rigorously as I could, using
all the philosophical and
phenomenological and
psychological tools I had
gathered in graduate school.
Now, Stan differentiates between
two different types of
psychedelic work, low dose
psychedelic work, usually
between 15 200 micrograms and
high dose psychedelic work,
which is usually up to maybe 500
micrograms, 600 micrograms, the
low dose method generates a sort
of a gradual, slowly peeling
back the layers of consciousness
to this personal unconscious
through The perinatal or the
Death-Rebirth dynamics into
Transpersonal reality. The high
dose psychedelic work was in the
early years, focused on working
with terminally ill patients,
cancer patients, and they were
basically trying to not heal the
personal unconscious, but to
kind of blow through all the
levels of the personal
unconscious. Trigger a near
death type experience, a trigger
a profound encounter with the
universe, and then see let that
encounter with the deeper
structure of the universe, to
see how it might impact their
anxiety around their imminent
death. So what I did, after
about four three low dose
sessions, I opted to work with a
very intense regimen with LSD, I
worked at psychedelic therapy. I
did what turned out to be a 20
year regimen of doing high dose
psychedelic therapy, always
using the same protocol, always
using the same test conditions.
I worked at 500 to 600
micrograms, which is not a
protocol that I recommend. I
really don't I didn't know as
much then as I don't know. But
what I did was to do 73 high
dose, fully internalized,
therapeutically focused
psychedelic sessions with the
sitter and my wife, first wife,
Carol, who is a clinical
psychologist, agreed to be my
sitter. And was my sitter for
all of my sessions. And I just
press this I worked for four
years, then I stopped for six
years, and then I came back and
worked for 10, very aggressive
years. So over the course of 20
years, I did 73 sessions. Now I
wouldn't recommend this
protocol. I would really
recommend people work with lower
doses. And you know, there is no
research protocol right now
federally sanctioned that is
recommending or looking
considering using doses as high.
But I wanted to push the limits.
And I thought that if
psychedelic, high dose
psychedelic work could be done
safely three times in the Spring
Grove project, then it could be
done safely more than three
times. What I found was that it
could be done safely more than
three times. But it's very, very
demanding work, and it's more
demanding than the original
protocols that Spring Grove
envisioned, and it opens up
opportunities that the early
protocol did not envision, but
it also opened up challenges
that the early protocol had not
envisioned, and one of those
challenges has to do with how
these deep states of
Consciousness impact our body
and impact our subtle energy
system. Because what I found was
that when I would go, when I
went into these states and went
into deeper levels of
consciousness, and then
stabilized my level of
consciousness, my consciousness
at that level, so that my
conscious experience was
coherent and stable at that
level, eventually pushing,
continued to push, I would drop
down later into a deeper level
of consciousness, and then
stabilizing at that level and
then dropping into a deeper
level of consciousness. Each
state into a deeper level of
consciousness was a state into a
higher level of. Energy, just
extraordinarily, very, very
powerful levels of energy, so
that I had to work very
conscientiously, as all long
term psychedelic journeyers do,
work with the body, work with
the subtle energy system. Work
to detoxify the body. Work to
clarify negative emotions. Work
to basically strengthen the
subtle energy body. So
basically, purification, I
think, is essential and is
endemic to working with
psychedelics. In Tibetan vadna,
the monks have to do ngondro
before they are allowed to take
into the high teachings capable
of generating, you know,
enlightenment. So ninja, with
the found ninja are the
foundational practices. They're
the five, 100,000 practices that
every monk does in Vajrayana.
One of those practices involves
doing 100,000 prostrations while
reciting mantras and prayers and
doing visualizations. That's a
tremendous transformation,
clarification, strengthening of
your subtle energy system, and
they do this as a preliminary to
entering to receiving the
teaching that will allow them to
enter into the very, very deep
states of consciousness that
vara makes possible. If you go
into these deeper states of
consciousness quickly, like you
tend to do in psychedelic
states, tremendously powerful
purification processes are are
triggered. Physical purification
processes, physical
detoxification, emotional
detoxification, mental
detoxification, there's a
tremendous kind of catharsis
that takes place at all of those
levels. And some of those
levels, I think, are well
described in terms of our subtle
energy system. So we you really
have to work with the subtle
energy bodies, and I don't think
of them as just one body, but
multiple bodies, but mesh very
well against the Indian
Ayurvedic system or the Chinese
acupuncture meridian system.
Rick Archer: Yeah, you're
actually almost downplaying what
you went through here. If people
were to read your book when they
do, it's a tribute to your wife
that she was able to sit through
these sessions as your sitter
watching you go through this
because you were going into
convulsions, there was
projectile vomiting, you were
making all kinds of weird
noises. And you know, what you
were experiencing subjectively,
was excruciating. In many cases,
I mean suffering beyond anything
you could have imagined. And you
chalk it up to deep
purification. You say in your
book, the core of the cycle is
this increased awareness
triggers the surfacing of toxins
in the system, that in turn
precipitates a crisis of
disease, followed eventually by
a higher level of health. This
cycle operates at many levels,
at the physical level, the
psychological level and the soul
level. And very often I'm just
summarizing here, but very often
in your sessions, the first part
would be one of these horrible
ordeals that you would go
through, and then the second
part, having cleared that away,
you'd go into an ecstatic realm
and experience all kinds of
beautiful things.
Chris Bache: Yeah, basically,
again, might. I'm going to
discuss this strictly in terms
of the LSD body of work. After I
stopped my sessions I had. I've
done Psilocybin a number of
times. I'm comfortable in that
world. I've done Ayahuasca
several times. I'm comfortable
in that world, but I really
would like to restrict myself to
just the LSD work in describing
this,
when you when you die as a self,
when, when You know when you I
understand psychedelics
following Stan Grof, and this is
a description in terms of their
psychoactive properties, not in
their physiological or
neurological properties, but
psychologically. They seem to
activate. They seem to function
as amplifiers and catalyst of
psychological processes. So they
take what is small and make it
loud, and they take what is
distant and make it close so it
basically hyper it's a hyper
catharsis and a hyper
amplification. We for a number
of hours, we enter into a
temporarily hyper sensitive
state of awareness, and what we
do with that awareness
determines what happens in a
session, we can listen to a
concert and have a good time, we
can have conversations, or we
can go deep within and use this
hypersensitivity to unearth the
obstacles to healthy
functioning. But then if we go
deeper, we can enter into deeper
levels of existential
functioning and deeper relations
with the universe. Is, it's
important to remember, I think
that what we are doing in our
laboratories is we are
rediscovering a class of
chemicals that have been used in
cultures for 1000s of years. And
you know, Ayahuasca is we have
at least 1500 years in
Psilocybin mushrooms and Peyote
and Mescaline. So there's,
there's a lot of history between
humanity and these substances.
Now what we're doing is studying
them in a particular context,
which is giving us great insight
into these processes. But
there's also a large body of
wisdom held in these cultures
that have been using these
materials for a long time.
According to many of these
systems, their view is that
consciousness is a universal
quality of life. We are
individually conscious. Other
aspects of the physical world
are individually conscious, but
the universe is conscious, and
that there there are many tiers
of comprehensive functioning in
the universe, and when you enter
into deeper states of awareness,
each of these deeper states is a
higher level of energy, which
then requires a stabilization
that requires a purification
process and stabilization
process to be stay coherent at
that level. Now here's the
tricky part. When I started this
work, I was thinking, this is
all about therapy, or this is
about healing my personal
psyche, or it's about
enlightening Chris, spacious,
poor psyche. You know, it's
about something personal, but
some of the pain that you're
referring to Rick came about
when I went through after two
years of work, went through a
crushing ego death experience
just cracked me wide open, and
then it took me into a new layer
of work, where, for the next two
years, I went through
excruciating psychological,
psychophysical suffering. So it
was so large and so broad and so
deep. And it went on for so many
years that eventually I became
convinced that this was not
about healing Chris Bache his
psyche. It's not about purifying
something that's somehow
personal to Chris Bache, that
eventually I was forced to draw
the conclusion that somehow
something had happened in my
sessions, that the universe, or
some functional dynamic of the
universe, was using my sessions
to bring about some type of
healing at the collective level
of consciousness, some type of
healing aimed at the personal
psyche that there is. And
eventually, the way I understand
this is that just as I remember
all Chris spacious experiences,
for better or for worse the
human species, there is a mind
of the human species that
remembers all of the experiences
of all the members of its
species. So then, if you think
about all the terrible things
we've done to each other, and
all the wars and all the killing
and all the bloodshed and all
the rape and all those terrible
pains, that somehow the species
is stuck with those and has to
digest those in the same way
that I am stuck with Crispus
experiences, and that just as
it's good for crisp Bache, if I
can somehow confront the darkest
pieces of my shadow and bring
that to rest. The same thing
happens at the collective level
for the species as a whole.
Usually that type of
confrontation takes place in
terms of social transformations
or social revolutions. But I
think in very, very deep
psychedelic work, my experience
was that somehow something was
using my sessions to de effect
some body of pain and suffering
that was stuck or lodged in the
collective psyche. So to me, I
just had to go to a collective
model in order to understand the
data. This actually
Rick Archer: gives new meaning
to the saying that Christ died
for our sins. You know. I mean,
if, if a being is of, you know,
great enough stature in terms of
his the vastness of his
awareness, then it's like, you
know, an ocean being able to
dissolve lots of mud and stuff,
as opposed to a glass of water,
which can only take a little bit
of mud without becoming entirely
overwhelmed by it.
Chris Bache: We see that also in
the Buddhist traditions, the
Bodhisattva is basically someone
who basically places the good of
the whole over their individual
good makes that their project. I
don't think this is heavy duty,
spiritual requiring great, great
beings. I think any mother, any
father, worth their soul, would
do what they can to help end the
suffering of a child that they
solve. This is just part of the
natural case. What it means to
be a human. So if you're given
an opportunity, and in some deep
psychedelic sessions, you
sometimes are given an
opportunity. If you're given an
opportunity to relieve
suffering, it's just the most
natural thing in the world to
try to do that as best you can,
sure,
Rick Archer: but as best you
can, it's a question of
capacity. You know, Rupert
Sheldrake talks about Morphic
genetic fields, and you were
just alluding to fields being
able to store the traumas of
humanity. And I've also, I've
heard it said that wars break
out when there's enough stress,
if you will, accumulated in the
field that it can no longer be
contained, like the way
lightning strikes when there's
enough static electricity built
up in clouds. And so if we can
sort of become that field, or
attune ourselves with it, then
it seems, from what you're
saying in your book, that we can
become an instrument for its
purging, for its purification.
Yeah.
Chris Bache: I think the
universe seems to be intensely
interested in us as individuals,
but the universe also seems to
be intensely interested in us as
a species. And when you're
moving into that level of
consciousness where the universe
is communing with the species.
And you kind of you've gone
through ego death, and you've
gone through a series of deaths
where you basically have
dissolved your boundaries and
have basically opened up into
not all that is not mind at
large, but species mind, the
collective mind of the species.
It seems very clear that the
universe is nurturing the well
being of this universe of this
species, just as it nurtures the
well being of all individuals
within the species and all the
other species on the planet that
there is a there is a tremendous
power that cascades through all
of our lives, individually and
collectively.
Rick Archer: Yeah, Michael, have
we lost yet?
Michael Pollan: No, I'm
fascinated by what I'm hearing.
I don't know by how to process
it. I'm kind of curious to know,
Chris, what? Where did that turn
come from thinking you were
dealing with your individual
suffering, to realizing that
this was a collective matter,
that this, this was a
Transpersonal question, was it?
Was it an insight you had during
one of these, one of these high
dose experiences, or was it in
processing it after the fact?
Because that's a big that's a
big shift.
Chris Bache: Yeah, it was a big
shift, and it is a both and, but
probably the most important part
of it was after the session, as
I processed and worked it. It
took me years because I kept
trying to process in terms of
Stan's paradigm, in terms of the
paradigms that were available,
and all the paradigms
approaching psychedelics were
always about healing the
individual, enlightening the
individual, something like that.
And I kept trying to understand,
and I wrote Dark Knight early
dawn, in large part, to answer
the question, Why did suffering
get as large as it did in my
psychedelic sessions, to try to
answer this problem. And
eventually, that's where I made
the jump beyond the person
centered model into a collective
model. Now my thinking has gone
further since then, but that was
where I made the jump, and I
wrote that 9596 I started the
work in 79 I wrote that book
when I was about 15 years into
that process. So it took me at
least 10 well after when these
experiences started, it took me
years before I could really say
that idea and then agree to that
idea. And then once I began to
see it and understand it, then a
whole lot of other things began
to make sense, because the
collective level, yeah, yeah,
when going after going through
that ocean of suffering, I call
it the ocean of suffering, which
lasted two years, when that came
to a culmination, when that.
Culminated, and I went through a
death and rebirth process that
was associated with that level
of consciousness, and went
deeper into archetypal reality,
high archetypal and low
archetype of reality I had, I
had many, many experiences that
basically showed me how that
worked. Showed me how the
species mind is alive within all
of our fractally embedded
individual minds, how our
individual minds feed into the
collective mind, as Rupert
Sheldrake says, and how the
collective mind move feeds into
the individual mind. That this a
constant feedback system in that
process, and that's
intellectually it was Rupert's
work. When I integrated Rupert's
Morphic field theory into Stan
Grof paradigm, that's the part
that gave me the intellectual
permission to make this radical
reinterpretation of the
Michael Pollan: data that's
fascinating. And how do you how
do you respond to people who
say, Well, you just had a drug
experience. You mess with the
chemistry in your brain, and you
had these delusions that you
were getting some kind of
insight into something
collective. I mean, that's how a
lot of a lot of people not
versed in this world or having
had this experience, would
automatically go like, why
should a molecule afford such
insight?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, that's
an anthropological question, and
I'd rather leave that one to the
anthropologist. But I understand
the objection. I understand the
cautionary concern. I mean, I
was trained as an analytic
philosopher, and I was trained
in a highly, kind of, highly
skeptical discipline, so I
really affirm that I value that
skepticism, but I also I think
it's important that we look at
the history of human beings use
of these substances, and look at
some of the literature and how
these substances have been
regarded in other civilizations.
I think it's important to look
at all the data that is emerging
in the modern study of
psychedelics, so that in dark,
night, early dawn, I have a
chapter on the methodology of
basically taking a philosophical
approach to psychedelic inquiry.
And I list some of the reasons
why we should take these series
these experiences seriously and
we should not dismiss them. One
of the data is we sometimes get
knowledge in these states of
consciousness that we did not
have prior and we can reasonably
exclude that we did not have.
But this knowledge turns out to
be true and valid,
Michael Pollan: like the
perinatal research that stand
it. For example,
Chris Bache: some people have
will relive aspects of their
birth that they can later
verify, or, kind of more
radically, one can have an
experience which teaches you
something about how whales give
birth, or how lions experience
hunger, which you had never no
idea of before, never crossed
your awareness before, and it
turns out to be physiologically
accurate. Sometimes, in one
case, I remember Stan saying
that in one of his sessions, he
was confronted with a person who
basically was insisting that
Stan call his mother and father
gave them a telephone number and
wanted to reassure the parents
that he was okay. And this was
really, really strange and out
of left field, but they wrote
down the number, wrote down the
names, and after the session was
over and everything was stable
again, Stan very carefully
reached out to this phone number
and found the husband and wife
on the other side end of the
phone, And it turns out that
their son had just died. I don't
remember whether it was several
days ago or several weeks
before, and they they understood
that their son would wish them
to know that he was okay. So you
get very, very unusual
circumstances like that.
Rick Archer: So wait a minute,
this wasn't the physical person
in the room that gave the phone
number. This is something Stan
kind of cognized in some
psychedelic state, and was was
given a phone number by some non
physical entity, and then called
the parents, and it panned out.
It was very fine. Wow. Yeah,
that's interesting.
Michael Pollan: So Chris, you
said also though that you
wouldn't recommend this kind of
regime, I have two questions
about that. Why not? And second,
after the agony that you went
through in these sessions, how
did you ever muster the courage
to do it again, let alone two
more times?
Rick Archer: Yeah, before you
answer that, Chris, I just want
to add a little related bit. Did
you ever. Feel that maybe you
were frying the circuitry you
know in your action, that all
this suffering was a result of
some damage that you were
inflicting upon yourself, or
that maybe you were opening
yourself up to some negative
astral level, or something like
that. How did you have the
confidence to proceed? I'm just
adding that on to Michael's
question.
Chris Bache: Well, I really
trusted Stan Grof work. I mean,
that's why I consider myself in
his lineage. My work is based
upon his scholarship. I trusted
what I saw in Stan's work. I
trusted the methodology. I
trusted his surveying of the
literature. I trusted his
evidence that there was no
physiological, no genetic
damage. I trusted the cases that
he presented. I appreciated the
rigor with which he had digested
all various bodies of
psychodynamic theory, as he does
in beyond the brain, and
integrated them into the
phenomenology of psychedelic
discourse, and primarily that
one of the primary things I got
from Stan's work was an absolute
trust that if you surrender
completely to what arises in
your psychedelic session, it
will you can trust that. And you
may not understand it going in,
and it may be absolutely
horrendous and painful going in.
It may take you months or years
to understand why things are
unfolding the way they are, but
you can trust it, and it will
always come out good in the end.
And I that was the procedure I
took. I found, why not doing
this work, and then what
happened in the work? Why not
doing this work? I wouldn't work
in doses that high. I mean, it's
not that I wouldn't recommend
doing doses that high
occasionally, but I wouldn't do
such a pounding, blowing of
consciousness apart so
aggressively for so many
sessions and so many years, even
though I was doing it in a very
responsible manner, I was doing
it about five times a year, so I
had a lot of time to recuperate.
I was taking care of my body. I
was doing spiritual practice
during all this time. I was
keeping detailed notes. I made a
phenomenologically precise
record within 24 hours of every
session. I studied the session,
so I was really trying to be as
methodical as I could. But
basically, by the time I was at
the end, time I was finishing
this journey, I had a number of
breakthroughs and a number of
insights we can talk about. But
I came to understand that one
other assumption that I had made
about this work was wrong. The
assumption was that there is a
certain goal that you can get
to, that there was an end point
that you could some it could be
oneness with God, or oneness or
the meta cosmic void, or the
super cosmic void, that there
was an end point that you would
get to. And what I found
eventually, when I had gotten I
had experienced many
permutations of oneness, I found
that there are variations and
subtleties of oneness, and there
are even variations in the void,
in the domain of formlessness.
And if you if you have a method
which is so powerful it keeps
pushing you to the edge of your
experiential boundaries, it'll
keep taking you through
remorselessly boundary after
boundary after boundary, leading
into deeper, deeper intimacy
with the I call it the creative
intelligence of the universe. I
don't know what else to call it.
It's infinitely vast. It's
infinitely intelligent, it's
infinitely compassionate. I
mean, it's just what it has
taught me, and just the
experience of dissolving into it
without any boundaries. Left
over has been enormous. Has been
deeply life changing. But late
into the process, about 17 years
into the process, I had an
experience where I was as far
deep into the diamond
Luminosity, I call it deep into
what the Buddhists call
Dharmakaya, the clear light of
absolute reality, as far into it
as I had ever gone. I was in
deep state of bliss and clarity,
and all of a sudden, my visual
field pivoted 90 degrees, and I
saw reality Far, Far in the
distance. It looked like
galaxies, and a ray of light
emerged from that reality and
hit me, and it absolutely
shattered me. And in those few
seconds, I realized it's an
infinite progression. You cannot
get to the end of the universe.
You cannot get to the end of the
mind of the universe. It's an
infinite progression. And. And
that that's one of the reasons I
would be gentler with myself. I
would be gentler because I think
what we can do with these
substances, we can open
ourselves up to the infinity,
and we can take in as much of
the infinity as we can get into
our system, as much as we can
psychologically digest,
emotionally digest, physically
digest. And I I'm more patient
now with the slower trajectory
of spiritual and psychological
development than I was when I
was a young man running into the
states.
Rick Archer: What you were just
saying addresses something that
Michael brought up a few minutes
ago, which was, how can some
molecules adjust our brain in
such a way that we actually
begin to have cognitions, deep,
meaningful cognitions about the
meaning of life or the nature of
reality and all that. And I had
written down a question here,
are psychedelic visions merely
projections of our personal
psyche, or do we experience
things that actually exist but
are originally better,
ordinarily, beyond the range of
our perception? But what you
just said about the creative
intelligence of the universe, or
the mind of the universe,
answers the question, because if
that's the way it is, if there
is a mind of the universe, if,
if the foundation or the ground
state of of the universe is an
ocean of creative intelligence
out of which the universe
emerges. Then by whatever means,
psychedelics or meditation, or
whatever, that we manage to
merge with that ocean, then we
sort of realize our ultimate
essential identity with that
mind of the universe, or with
that creative intelligence,
which is, we can say, the
repository of all the laws of
nature, the repository of all
knowledge. And although, as a
human being, we can only kind of
express so much of it, we'll
always have our limitations. As
a finite instrument, we can kind
of dip into it in such a way
that that there is that we we
share in a kind of omniscience,
in a way you know what I'm
trying to say and and we absorb
it to some extent. And so all
the great pronouncements of the
mystics throughout the ages have
been their attempts, through the
human form, through human
language to express that merging
that they experienced.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think when
we have temporary experience of
infinity, it leaves a lasting
impression, even when we are
back to being a finite being.
And if we have temporary
experience of infinite love, all
embracing, all inclusive, and a
love that transcends species and
reaches out to the molecules of
existence, the atoms of
existence itself. Then when we
congeal back into our ordinary
time space suit, it has an
effect. It has a profound
effect. And I guess that's one
of the other reasons I would
suggest that we should give
these experiences a measure of
credence. It's not just because
of the empirical assessment,
empirical data and the
correlation between multiple
experiences. And I want to
mention, there's always
deception, there's always
incompleteness, there's always
distortion, we always are going
to have to deal with. Well, what
if it's just this and not that?
You know, absolutely, that's the
nature of the dialog. That's a
discussion. It's a worthy
question, and it is a word. The
experience
Michael Pollan: has an enormous
authority. I mean, I think it's
one of the most striking things
about psychedelics is that, you
know what William James called
the Noetic sense. And speaking
of mystical experience, that it
is, these don't seem just kind
of subjective opinions. They
seem like authoritative truths.
And yeah, and that's one, that's
one of the reasons they're so
sticky. I wonder, Chris, whether
you feel that I agree with the
proper discipline and
commitment, you could get to the
same place with meditation.
Chris Bache: Absolutely, I think
so, with some qualifications in
that, since I'm professor of
religious studies, and I've
taught courses in comparative
mysticism, and I studied, I have
had the luxury of studying some
of the mystical traditions. The
great masters who do this
through entirely natural means
are and there are masters who do
it with other assisted means as
well. The great masters have
always been my guiding light in
this material. And it's always
been. You know, to be able to
sustain these states for a few
hours is great, but to be able
to sustain them for months
years, that's greater still and
to be respected. Now I'll
mention that Carol, my sitter,
is a serious Vajrayana Buddhist
practitioner. Her always was
during the years we were working
together, and she never did a
psychedelic session, never did a
session with me. She was always
much more contemplative in her
practice. And subsequently,
after we have separated and
she's remarried and I've
remarried, we're still close,
she has gone on and completed
her three year, three month,
three day retreat under the
supervision of her teacher. So
she's a serious practitioner,
and I'm a modest practitioner by
comparison, but I understand the
relationship between my
psychedelic experiences, and the
experiences which are preserved
in the meditative traditions
that she has introduced me to,
or that I've introduced been
introduced through her. And I
see a very, very strong
correlation. I don't think the
unit the cosmology that we're
encountering with deep
psychedelic work is original.
It's not new. We see this
cosmology in the great
spiritual, mystical traditions
of history. That said, I think
that all of those traditions in
history are all stage specific.
They all reflect a certain
historical context and
anthropological context and even
an evolutionary context. I don't
see them as eternal truths. I
see them as approximations of an
ever growing, expanding truth.
So I think that there are
certain ways in which the
cosmology that psychedelics can
introduce us to can push the
edges of those classic
cosmology, and you can push the
edges, and that opens up new
possibilities. I don't think,
for example, a deep immersion
into transtemporal experience is
is a deeply ingrained quality in
mystical experiences, but that
is happened a great deal in my
psychedelic experiences I
mentioned. Let me back up and
say I started this work, you
know, 1979 because I was
interested in spirituality. I
was interested in enlightenment.
I had been meditating for a
number of years. I thought that
I could, I encountered the kind
of blocks that are pretty
typical in early stages of
meditation, and I thought that
by doing some sessions, I could
deal with those blocks, blast
through them, and I could reach
enlightenment faster. Didn't
work out quite that way. But
what I found was that when I
really went into it, that was
one track, the Enlightenment
track, a second track opened
that was really a very different
track, and that's the track of a
cosmic exploration, to actually
explore the consciousness of the
universe, to explore deeply the
fabric of reality and experience
it all its ins and outs. It's
not that these are incompatible,
but the cosmological inquiry
came to dominate my sessions. So
I wouldn't want to use the
measure of enlightenment as
meaningful and beautiful and
important as that is as the
criteria for evaluating
everything that happened in my
sessions. I sort of see their
different projects, and only in
the very late years did it kind
of come back around into the
classical enlightenment kind of
work.
Rick Archer: I think there have
been plenty of Yogis and Siddhas
and so on, who have done plenty
of cosmic exploration. And
they've they've written down
their their findings, you know,
they've just gone about it
through various other means. Did
you want to add something there?
Michael, no, no, okay, I have a
line of questioning here that'll
shift our gears a little bit.
Chris Bache: Let me just mention
one thing. If psychedelics, if
LSD is only an amplifier of
consciousness, then by
definition, it does nothing that
can't be achieved through other
methods for exploring
consciousness. Because it's not,
it's psychedelic, which does
this, it's consciousness which
does this. We're simply
amplifying and focusing it. And
you, you're focusing
consciousness in meditation. You
can go into these places in
meditation.
Rick Archer: Yeah, yeah. And
that thing you said about
patience as you get older and,
you know, kind of abandoning the
enlightenment or bust attitude.
I mean, you know, I had done
some psychedelics in the 60s for
about a year, and then I learned
to meditate when I was 18. And
I've been doing it for 51 years,
you know, a couple hours a day.
And it's for many years there
was a sort of a desperate
feeling of, gotta get
enlightened, you know, gotta
break through. After a while
that just sort of dissipated. It
just sort of oozed away. And,
you know, contentment kind of
dawned. And I just don't think
that way anymore. I don't know
whether that's due to a, you
know, natural maturation, or
whether it's due to the results
of meditation bringing about. A
kind of an abiding sense of
fulfillment which is not
dependent upon any external
circumstances, but one way or
the other. I think that you
know, whatever one chooses to
do, safety first is a good rule
of thumb, because impatience can
result in some pretty
unfortunate situations. You
know, if one proceeds recklessly
in any sense,
Chris Bache: yeah, absolutely,
yeah, yeah. Okay. So
Rick Archer: here's a question I
want to ask. I have a good
friend named Dana Sawyer, who
was, we've been friends since we
were kids. Practically. He's a
he's been a professor, professor
of religion and philosophy at
the main College of Art and
adjunct professor of Asian
Studies at the Bangor
Theological Seminary, and he's
written biographies of Aldous
Huxley and Huston Smith. And he
had two questions that are
related. One is, what are the
connections? We've kind of
covered this, so maybe we'll
maybe the answer to this first
bit will be quick. What are the
connections, similarities and
differences between psychedelic
state, psychedelic states and
mystical states of
consciousness? Have we? Have we
covered that adequately? Maybe
we have,
Michael Pollan: well, you know,
the researchers that I spent a
lot of time interviewing see
them lining up very closely, and
sometimes they'll use the term
mystical like experience,
because I think they don't want
to offend anyone on the on the
religion side. But you know,
they, they studied very closely
the the anatomy of mystical
experience, especially as
William James described it. And
they, they feel that it has all
the six, seven or eight
characteristics.
Rick Archer: Yeah, actually, I
was reminded, and a question
just came in that Ram Dass gave
some LSD to Neem, Karoli Baba,
and apparently it had no effect
on him. Because presumably, I
guess, the interpretation was
that he was already in some kind
of high abiding state, and LSD
really couldn't add to it in any
way.
Michael Pollan: I've always,
I've heard that story for a very
long time, and the dose was one
of Chris's doses. It was like
five or 600 micrograms. And I've
always, I have to say, I've
always thought it was
apocryphal. But we have to ask
Chris Bache: now that you'll
find the story in the book
miracle of love, which is Ram
Dass, this collection of
anecdotes about dim Karoli Baba.
And according to Ram Dass, he
gave him 600 micrograms the
first time, and then he, you
know, then, basically he wasn't
affected. He came back the
United States, and he told his
friends, and they said, Oh, he
must have palmed it. Nobody can
take 600 mics and not be
affected. And he went back to
the ashram, and Neem Karoli Baba
called him over, and he said, Do
you have any more of that
Western medicine? And he brought
everything. He had 1200
micrograms and RAM and neem.
Karoli Baba, according to Ram
Dass, put them on his tongue and
made him see that he was taking
them and swallowed them and and
it didn't affect him.
Rick Archer: Did you ever hear
Bruce Joel Ruben story? No.
Bruce wrote the screenplay for
the movie Ghost, and he won the
Oscar for that. And he also
wrote the screenplay for, what
is it, Jacob's Ladder and some
other movies. Anyway, he'd been
on batgap, but he was a teenager
living in New York City in some
apartment, and somebody brought
over like a glass mayonnaise jar
full of liquid sand dose that
was going to be shipped up to
Millbrook for Timothy Leary's
gang, and asked if they he could
store it in their refrigerator.
So it was in their refrigerator.
And so they're sitting around.
They think we should try this,
you know. And so his friend was
going to put a drop on his
tongue using a dropper, and he
squeezed the whole dropper.
Anyway, you can look it up.
It's, it's quite a story.
Chris Bache: Grof says that
there is a natural threshold of
about 500 micrograms. If you
take more than that, you don't
necessarily get higher. So
there's a kind of a cut off
there, around five to 600
micrograms. That's good to know,
saturation point. So here's the
Rick Archer: important question,
then we should let Michael go.
This is my second one from Dana.
This I should have asked this
one first, he said that Huston
Smith once argued that traits
matter more than states, and
even if psychedelics can trigger
trigger religious experiences,
it's less clear they can develop
religious lives. Dana mentioned
that psychedelics can definitely
trigger genuine mystical states
as measured by, you know, eight
of the nine parameters of the
states Pankey typology, but the
ninth parameter is continued
improvements in behavior. So is
there evidence that psychedelic
experiences lead to more
compassionate or selfless
behavior?
Michael Pollan: I think it's a
really good, good question. I
don't, I don't think I know the
answer to it. You know, some
people feel that. That the fact
that attaining knowledge through
psychedelics is so rapid, I hate
to use the word easy, especially
after what Chris has told us,
that it is it is less enduring,
has less traction in our lives.
You know the analogy sometimes
used is that if you climb the
mountain and you get to the top,
and you get that view, and then
someone lands on the mountain in
a helicopter, they get the same
view, but they haven't earned it
in the same way, and therefore
it is less powerful that strikes
me as kind of a Puritan view.
You know that, you know that
that that you need works. You
need good works to justify
faith. So I don't know if it's
true. I think that there are
many people who've had
psychedelic experiences that
they've carried the insights and
the convictions through to their
lives and change their lives and
become more moral or more
ethical people, and there are
people for whom it hasn't been
sticky, and I think that's part
of the work of integration. I
think that's part of you know,
of approaching it with reverence
and recognition of the power
that that that there is another
big step, which is, how do you
apply what you've seen, and what
do you do with it, and how does
it change your behavior? And I
don't think there's any. There's
nothing inherent in the
experience that makes you more
or less likely to to do that.
It's it's really up to us. But,
you know, I think it's something
everyone doing these
explorations should bear in
mind. It's not going to be
automatic. I mean, there are
people who've done psychedelics
and come out and behave really
badly, and there are people
who've had their ego dissolved
and during psychedelic
experience and then it inflated
enormously after. And so I
think, I think we have to be
very wary of those pitfalls,
Rick Archer: you know. And I
think the same can be said of
meditation. I know people who've
been meditating for decades that
I wouldn't want to associate
with, they act like real sobs
sometimes, and others who really
underwent a deep transformation
and became much better people.
So maybe there does need to be,
in addition to whatever the
practice for dipping in the
consciousness, maybe there needs
to be a kind of a conscious
attention to ethics and you
know, being being a more
responsible human being?
Chris Bache: Yeah, I completely
agree with both of you. I agree
with you, Michael, that a
mystical experience does not a
mystic make, to paraphrase
Huston Smith, but also a
mystical experience. Can a
materialist philosophy unmake
and but I think, and so I think
it has philosophical
significance. If we have X
number of people who do X number
of sessions and have an emerging
consensus around what they
envision the cosmics to be like
that's significant, but I think
you're absolutely right to have
an experience does not
necessarily make you a wiser,
kinder, gentler person, but if,
if you use those experiences and
work conscientiously in
integrating them, then hopefully
they will there. They don't flip
a switch. They don't make you
what you are becoming
automatically, but they act as,
I think, a seed catalyst. Yeah,
cultivate those seeds.
Michael Pollan: Yeah, yeah.
Well, I think that's a great
note for me to leave you on. I'm
very sorry I have to leave but I
have another appointment, and I
thank you very much for a very
stimulating conversation, and I
look forward to continuing
sometime.
Rick Archer: Yes, thank you so
much. And I should add that
Michael's book will be coming
out in paperback on what did you
say the 14 Tuesday? Well,
Tuesday. Well anyway, by the
interview is up, the book will
be out, and you can get it on
Amazon, and I'll have a link to
it on the page on batgap.com
where I feature this
Michael Pollan: in Chris. I look
forward to your new book, and
I'll be sure to order
Chris Bache: it. Thank you,
Michael, we have more
conversations. I hope we have
lots more to talk about.
Michael Pollan: We've just
begun. Thank you, absolutely,
pleasure
Rick Archer: and those who are
listening, hang on, because I'm
going to continue a little
longer with Chris. Let me start
Chris by asking a few questions
that have come in from the
audience, and I want to save
time before we wrap up to talk
about your notion of the birth
of the future human, which I
think is fascinating, and the
and the changes that humanity
may have to go through as that
birth takes place. Okay, so
let's budget our time. Let me
know when you feel like we
should cut the questions and get
to that. So here's one from Amit
in New Zealand. He asks after
Ayahuasca sessions, I
experienced some detrimental
energetic shifts, for lack of
better words, waking up deeply,
physically tired for months
afterwards, that became somewhat
worrisome. Are there specific
methods or practices that you
can personally recommend for the
most efficient integration and
minimum. Of any potential
detrimental physical energetic
effect after some deep sessions,
Chris Bache: it's complicated
question, first, because every
psychedelic is a little
different, and so you have to
you're talking about Ayahuasca,
it has a different quality than
LSD and a different quality than
Psilocybin mushroom, but
basically, Ayahuasca,
potentially. Let's assume a
rather strong dose of Ayahuasca
has tremendous impact on our
physiology and our psychology,
and when we jar ourselves that
way, when we, when we enter into
these temporary conditions of
awareness which are so radically
different than our ordinary
awareness, it's going to shake
up our system, and it's going to
impact us and it I think we have
to be gentle with ourselves, and
we should cultivate practices of
contemplation to help us
integrate these experiences. I
don't think there's necessarily
any formula that will ensure
ensure an outcome that doesn't
lead to these periods of
physical exhaustion or sometimes
a psychological kind of
exhaustion that follows. But
basically, I think if we go to
the spiritual literature, and we
look at the literature about
what is it, what does it mean to
take up a spiritual practice, my
belief is the more powerful the
psychedelic experience you want
to cultivate, either by the
nature of the chemical, the
strength of the chemical, or the
frequency with which you're
doing the chemical, The more you
push your system into this new
territory, the more important it
is for you to cultivate
meditation and the classic forms
of contemplative practice,
taking care of the body,
stretching the body, taking care
of the subtle energy system,
taking care of your emotional
life, taking care of your of
your mental Life, your spiritual
life. I think those are all
important now, how actually
cashes out to a specific
regimen? I mean, I know I have
my regimen. I always have had my
regimen that changed through the
years. I just think it's good to
ask the question that he's
asking he's asking, and to to
seek advice and to cultivate the
regimens which will help
stabilize the system when it's
come back from such an extreme
experience. Good answer.
Rick Archer: And there's other
things, exercise, diet, you
know, I mean obvious stuff that
anybody benefits from if they do
it regularly and properly. So,
you know, all that stuff,
everything is interconnected.
This is a question from Bobby in
Griffin, Georgia. Bobby asks if
psychedelics give a glimpse into
true nature or reality, then
that seems to beg the question
of there being some sort of
sheath or mask covering common
daily experience. Is this sheath
or veil developed during early
childhood, and therefore, would
infancy and early childhood
experience be akin to
psychedelic experience?
Chris Bache: Well, I understand
the logic, and I sort of see
that, and I know a number of
people would say that, and at
the same time, I hope no child
has ever had some of the
experiences that I've had on
psychedelics, not just the
negative ones, but even the
cosmic, ecstatic ones. That's an
extremely powerful experience,
and I hope a child doesn't have
to take that in. But within that
caveat, I think there's a
certain sense in which children
are more naturally receptive to
some of those sense more
sensitive dimensions of
consciousness, and they lose
that sensitivity as they get
older. And this kind of talked
out of them and conditioned out
of them until later they have to
rediscover it. I think it's,
it's, it's not just like
something that happens in
childhood, you know, there's
again. I don't just study
psychedelics. I study
reincarnation research, near
death episode research, out of
body research. I study lots of
different forms of Non-ordinary
states of consciousness. And I
think the image that's coming
clear is that when we die, we
expand into a larger, subtle,
higher state of consciousness,
and when we incarnate, we
contract into a small,
physically dominant kind of
consciousness. We die. We expand
into great spaciousness. We
incarnate. It gets small. We
keep this up over and over and
over again. The more we do it,
the more over 1000s and 1000s of
years, the more we do it slowly,
we begin to integrate spiritual
dimensions and physical
dimensions. That they're not
really an either or that they
begin to be a both and within
our own lifetime, within our own
body. So I think it's actually
taking up an incarnation at all
has a naturally contractive
effect on consciousness. So I
don't think it's something we're
doing wrong to our children,
though, once you understand that
progression, I think there are
things that we can do that would
help our children adjust to this
world.
Rick Archer: Yeah, that cycle
you just mentioned can be true
of meditation, too. I mean, you
use my teacher used to use the
example of dying a cloth in
India, where they'd take the
white cloth, dip it in the
colored dye, then bleach it in
the sun, then dip it in the dye,
then bleach it in the sun, go
back and forth and back and
forth until eventually it
becomes color fast, even if you
leave it in the sun. So, you
know, you dip into Samadhi, and
then you engage in activity, and
you do it again, engage in
activity. Then the nervous
system gets transformed,
thereby, yes, and the Samadhi
becomes stabilized. So you end
up having Nirvikalpa Samadhi all
the time, you know, or whatever
they call the term doesn't have
to just be with eyes closed.
Unknown: Yeah.
Rick Archer: Okay, one more
question from the audience, and
then I want to get into the
birth of the future human. So
David from Cambridge, England,
asks if Psilocybin, or similar
substances were made widely
available to the public. Do you
think there would be a negative
side effect to consciousness
andor society? Are these
substances restricted, perhaps
due to society not being ready
for them? And I'll add that
Michael Poland wrote an op ed in
the New York Times just the
other day commenting on the
recent permissiveness in
Colorado for the use of
psychedelic mushrooms, and he
cautioned they decriminalized
mushrooms, right? So he
cautioned, you know, take it
easy. You know, we shouldn't go
too fast here, because, you
know, there could be negative
consequences.
Chris Bache: Yeah, we should
have gotten Michael to comment
on that. Since that just came
out today,
Rick Archer: ran out of time,
yeah, yeah, yeah.
Chris Bache: Okay, focus on the
Cambridge question again.
Rick Archer: Oh, just, you know,
is it perhaps prudent that
psychedelics are restricted to
the extent they are, or at least
to some extent? Because, you
know, all hell might break loose
if they just became like the
Libertarians you know, want to
want to legalize all drugs. I
don't know if that would be
advisable.
Chris Bache: One of the points
that Michael makes in his
article, if I can just invoke
something he said there, which I
completely agree with, is that
when you look at cultures who
have a long term relationship
with psychoactive substances,
you do not find them being used
recreationally. You find them
being used under very careful
ritual spiritual conditions. You
find them being used in
collective circumstances that
you don't just go trip out by
yourself. We have a great deal
to learn from cultures who have
a living history with these
substances. Our culture has very
little living history with these
substances except recreational
or in the underground movement.
So we are given our naivete.
Maybe it is good to be cautious
for bringing these into our
culture. But I absolutely agree
with something else Michael
says, is that nobody should be
put in jail for possessing some
psychoactive mushrooms. I mean,
it's just, I don't think they're
they're toxicology they're very
safe, psychologically, extremely
safe. They're not habit forming.
You want to use them carefully.
You want to use them under
guidance, but, but there's,
they're much less destructive
than cigarettes or alcohol, and
we've learned how to live with
cigarettes and alcohol. So I
think, I hope that we will
decriminalize. I hope that we,
more importantly, we will learn
how to work respectfully with
these very positive, powerful
substances. They can be life
transforming, but we have to be
careful as we approach them.
Rick Archer: Good. So well said,
you have a section in your book
towards the end that's entitled
The birth of the future, human
global awakening and its impact
on society. I just want to read
a couple little bits from it.
You say I believe that the
global systems crisis taking
place in the world outside us is
deeply connected to the
evolutionary metamorphosis
taking place inside us. You say,
humanity is coming into a time
of great awakening, a profound
shift in the fundamental
condition of the human psyche.
But for there to be a great
awakening, there must first take
place a great death. This global
crisis will be so severe that it
will impact not only
individuals, but the collective
unconsciousness, unconscious of
humanity itself. And I'm just
going to read a little bit more,
because when you had that
session in which you kind of
cogs that you wrote, or you
wrote recently, it took me. More
than a year to recover from this
session. For months, I walked
around the city where I live,
feeling like someone walking
around Hiroshima a week before
the bomb was dropped, with
unbidden knowledge of what lies
ahead and profound respect for
all the participants. It was
terrible to experience
humanity's Coming Collapse, but
redemptive to experience the
rebirth that followed. Since
that session, I have never
doubted the larger arc of our
evolutionary journey, even as I
mourn its casualties, without a
vision of where nature is taking
us, without understanding the
higher good that our collective
suffering is bringing forward in
history, we might drown in the
sorrow that lies ahead, and we
must not drown. I believe the
form that the future human will
take will be the diamond soul.
So that gives you a springboard.
Chris Bache: Let me just back up
just a second when you work with
high doses of LSD, when you're
doing it in a totally
internalized, compacted for and
you intensify it with music and
eye shades and all that usual
good stuff. You basically just
explode your consciousness. You
just shatter your consciousness,
and you explode it. And for six
hours or eight hours at a time,
you become a different kind of
being. You become a you're not a
human being. You open yourself
up into unprecedented intimacy
with the universe, and the
universe is in the role of
teacher and in the role of
instructor. And the universe
decides where you go and what
you learn. It seems to be a
balance between what you're
capable of taking in and what
the universe wants you to take
in. So as as my journey
continued, and I was doing this
systematically over the years,
one of the things that began to
happen about oh, 23 sessions in
started then, is that I began to
have a series of visionary
experiences of where the
universe was taking. The human
race, the human species,
basically about the the
evolutionary dynamics of the
species, once consciousness
became such a powerful factor in
human evolution where we're not
right now fundamentally changing
our body very fast, but we are
changing consciousness
relatively fast. And so I had
many experiences of the
evolutionary dynamics of where
humanity is and where it's
going, and the vision that came
through over and over again was
that humanity was poised on the
edge of an enormous
breakthrough, just a tremendous
breakthrough that would forever
change the foundation of life on
this planet. And it wasn't
simply a civilizational
breakthrough or an economic
breakthrough or technological
breakthrough, or an industrial
production breakthrough. It was
a breakthrough in the
fundamental platform of
consciousness, the fundamental
baseline of human consciousness,
and that we were that there was
a tremendous pressure building
up, and there was a tremendous
kind of acceleration of our
content. Conscious dynamics. And
there was a tremendous
detoxification taking place in
the reincarnation of generation
after generation. So this was
not simply influencing
individuals, it was influencing
the entire human species. There
was a collective dynamic. So it
basically, it showed me the
vision that we are coming to a
great awakening, just an
exponential increase in our
psychological and psychophysical
capacity. But it didn't give me
any indication of how it was
going to accomplish this. I had
no idea, after years of vision,
how it was going to accomplish
this. And then in 1995 the
universe took me deep into deep
time. It was a grueling
experience to get there, but
eventually blew me out into a
radical, expanded time framework
and took me into the heart of
the death and rebirth of
humanity. It the state of
consciousness that I was in when
I went through this process was
not Chris Bache having a
collective experience. I
dissolved completely, and I
experienced this, a coming
crisis. Ask the species
experiences it. It's like being
able to experience a
thunderstorm where you can
experience the storm. It's a
totality, and each individual
drop simultaneously. And what it
showed me was that this
tremendous global systems crisis
that we are entering, which
seems to be driven by an
ecological crisis this world
climate change. Change ego
crisis leading to would lead to
a tremendous global crisis of a
fundamental institutions, major
die off around the planet,
tremendous pain and suffering,
but that this pain was actually
transformative, that this pain
was actually part of a process
of confronting our past and
confronting the legacy of that
past, essentially confronting
karma and going through a death
and rebirth process that would
basically carry us beyond our
standard level of functioning
before this point in time. So
there was a sense in which in
this event, it's not a single
event, it's a evolutionary
process. I don't know how many
generations it will take. I'm
assuming it would take multiple
generations for this to be
enacted, but that we actually
will be brought to our knees. We
will lose control. We will
basically suffer terribly. Our
children and grandchildren will
suffer terribly. But that this
suffering was actually labor. It
wasn't simply a destructive
process. It wasn't simply an
extinction process, or it may
feel like that at the time, but
it was a labor process that when
this process reached its
absolute peak, and it looked
like we would all die, the storm
passed, and there were
survivors, and as the survivors
began to pull their life
together, they began to connect
with each other in new and
unprecedented ways. That was a
time of new values, new
insights, new technology, new
social relationships, new a new
internalization of deep
spiritual values, fundamentally,
a new experience of oneness in
our daily lives, that we really,
truly experience that we are all
one in this process, and we have
deep responsibilities to all
life forms, not only to each
other and human life forms, but
to all life forms on the planet
and elsewhere. Now that's sort
of one kind of that's the part
that you quoted, there's another
part of the sessions which
basically took reincarnation,
which is, I wrote my first book
on reincarnation. I've spent a
lot of time thinking in terms of
reincarnation, but it took me
deep and I began. It took me
into an experience where I began
to integrate all my former
lives. They began to come in to
be very fast and furious, and
they they began to it was like
winding light a kite string made
of light around a school. And
when I had integrated so many
lives, eventually, there was a
fusion of all of their learning
and all of their experience
fused into one, and when there
was a fusion, my consciousness
exploded into a diamond, like a
diamond light consciousness, and
I became an individual, but in
an order of individuality which
I had never experienced before.
It was the sum total of all of
my lives that had cascaded and
lifted me into a state of
consciousness that was more than
just the sum of all their
experiences, there was a
catalyst into a deeper
functioning of conscious
awareness, with respect to
myself, With respect to other
people and with respect to the
universe, that's what I came to
call the birth of the diamond
soul. That when we reincarnate
over and over and over and over
again, we are not simply making
incremental improvements on our
quality of life, more
compassion, more knowledge, so
on so forth, but in an
evolutionary sense, there comes
a time when, sooner or later,
the soul wakes up inside our
physical incarnation. So all of
our former lives, all of our
learning, all of the experiences
we have, kind of fuse and reach
a crescendo, and we wake up.
It's like the bubble pops and we
wake up and we know we are not
just this body, we know we are
not just this ego. We know we
are not just this incarnation
that we have relationships with
everyone around us that's been
going on for 1000s of years, and
it opens up new possibilities
for a deeper communion with the
creative intelligence of the
universe itself. I think what my
visionary experience has been is
that this is a transition which
we are making as a species. We
are growing into the birth of
the diamond soul. We are also
obviously going into a cascading
series. Of crises at the global
level. So as we are trying to
become one planet in the
outside, I think there is a
synergistic coupling to the fact
that we are trying to become one
being internally, we are
integrating all of our farmer
lives into our self as we are
trying to transcend the
limitations of our past
engineering and ecological
industrial practices. We're
trying to become one planet,
geophysically, geopolitically,
we're trying to take
responsibility for the healthy
functioning of a planet, the
same that reinforces and is
fueled by this intra psychic
process where we're trying to
grow up. We're trying to come to
terms with who and what we
actually are. This is what I
call the birth of the future
human I think this crisis that
we are entering and that we that
will dominate the 21st Century
will continue, probably on to
the 22nd this crisis is not
simply an economic crisis. It's
not simply an industrial
production crisis. It's a crisis
of consciousness. It's an
evolutionary crisis, and it's
giving birth to a future human.
Late in my sessions, at the
very, very end, at one the last
great vision that the universe
gave me in one of my sessions,
it took me deep into deep time.
It took me deep into the future,
and it gave me my last
experience of the future human.
It was as if it took me into the
future and allowed me to try on
for size, the fundamental
blueprint of the human psyche at
that point in the future. This
was the most extraordinary
being, just I can't describe to
you quickly what an extra
ordinary being This being is.
Just picture the highest, finest
qualities we've imagined.
Picture the highest spiritual
capacities we can imagine, a
mind completely open to the
universe, a heart completely
open to each other, just
extraordinarily magnificent
being. That's what's at stake
here. That's what we're trying
to become. That's where I think
we're going.
Rick Archer: Beautiful. So
eloquently put, can't really add
anything to it. And we're almost
out of time. And I'll just say
that if anybody finds what you
just said frightening in terms
of what the world may go through
in transition to this beautiful
future, you know, I mean, there
are people who are sort of
stocking up food and stocking up
guns and doing all kinds of
things, you know, in preparation
for the chaos they feel will be
coming. I'd say that what you
really want to stock up on is
consciousness. You know,
spiritual evolution, as much of
it as you can get under your
belt, through whatever means
works for you, that will be the
best form of preparation for
whatever life may bring.
Chris Bache: I absolutely agree,
the old, the kind of survivalist
is basically trying to take care
and hold on to ego, but what we
really need is cultivation of
service, transformation,
generosity, compassion. Those
are the qualities that will
carry us into this future.
Rick Archer: Yeah. All right,
well, I've really enjoyed this
conversation. I really enjoyed
reading your book. I want to
close with an endorsement from
our friend Anne barring, who's
been on batgap about your book.
She said, once or twice in a
century, a book appears that has
the explosive force of a
supernova breaking through the
limitations of religion, science
and culture. LSD, in the mind of
the universe, is such a book, a
gripping account of an utterly
unique and extraordinary hero's
journey that opens our minds and
hearts to a new vision of our
universe and ourselves as
inseparable from the ineffable
being we have called God. All
beliefs fade before the
incandescent revelations
contained in this book a deeply
moving template of our
evolutionary journey, I think,
beautifully written, and it was
a marvelous book. So the book,
as you said, won't be out until
when November, or something like
Chris Bache: that, November 26
Amazon has it on pre order, but
it'll be out then, yeah,
Rick Archer: and I have a link
for it prepared so people can
order it now and it'll come for
in time for Christmas, there you
go. Yeah. So I did
Chris Bache: this work for 20
years, and then I waited to
publish this book for another 20
years. It took a long time to
digest everything that happened
in those first 20 years before I
was really ready to share them
with with other people.
Rick Archer: Yeah, and it's been
a great conversation there. Yes,
conversations like this could go
on for many more hours, but
interviews are meant to be a
sort of a sampling. So this is
Chris Bache: a sampling
wonderful Rick, and the work
you're doing here, the number of
minds that you're opening, the
number. Number of conversations
you're having, bringing people
together talk about a catalyst
for positive change in our
future. Way to go, Really,
Rick Archer: thank you very
much. Really, hope to meet you
in person one of these
Chris Bache: days. Yes, let's do
that. Yeah,
Rick Archer: okay, so let me
just close by thanking those
who've been listening or
watching. I encourage you to go
to batgap.com and explore the
menus. There's a few things
there you might want to do, like
sign up for the email
newsletter, or subscribe to the
audio podcast, or donate if you
feel like donating. And there's
some other things on the site if
you poke around. So really
appreciate your time and
attention those in the audience,
and also you, of course, Chris
and Michael, who has left, but
we it was a great conversation,
and I'm really glad We got to do
it. Thank you.
Unknown: Thank you. Applause.
You.