Marc Caron: Welcome the spirit
plant medicine community here in
Vancouver and around the world,
and to the Facebook live
audience who may be watching and
anybody out there who's
watching. Today, we have a very
special guest, Mr. Chris Bache
is joining us. Bache, sorry,
with Mr. Steven gray. Chris is
going to be one of our great
presenters at the spirit plant
medicine conference coming up
here in just about a month and a
half. And my name is Mark Carl.
Really happy to have Chris with
us. And of course, my co
producer and organizer, Steven
gray with the conference, I'm
going to pass it to Steven to
introduce Chris and his work and
what we'll be talking about.
Stephen Gray: Sure, thank you.
Mark. This is going to be a very
brief introduction. There's bio
on the conference website,
spirit, plant medicine, calm. If
anyone wants to read more, I
will just say that Chris is a
retired University professor at
Youngstown, Ohio who was
teaching in religious
philosophy, I believe Chris
Philosophy and Religious Studies
Department, yeah, Philosophy and
Religious Studies Department,
more relevant to what we're
doing today, or more
specifically relevant anyway, is
that he became interested in the
work of Stanislav Grof, who did
a lot of remarkable pioneering
work in LSD therapy, and over a
period of 20 years, from 1979 to
1999 undertook a remarkable,
what Joseph Campbell would
probably truly call a hero's
journey of 20 years of 73 high
dose LSD sessions, privately
with a sitter with eye coverings
and headphones on, with a
carefully create a curated
playlist. And the results of
that are truly stunning. He
wrote about about it in a lot
about it in his 2000 book, Dark,
night, early dawn, and has a
forthcoming book called diamonds
from heaven, in which he
actually takes the reader
through a sequential journey
through those 73 sessions, if
I'm correct. Chris, yeah, so
perhaps a good way to start, as
I've mentioned to you in some of
our email exchanges, I've got
about 1,000,005 questions,
because I delved back into your
work again. Watch the
Transpersonal conference
interview or presentation, an
interview with some guy named
Ian Campbell or something like
that as well. And been reading a
bunch of dark night, early dawn,
which actually has transcripts
from those journeys in it so but
perhaps for the viewers, maybe
just you could say a little bit
briefly about beyond what I said
about, you know, hearing about
Stan grofs work, what, what led
you into doing this? You know,
why you, why you?
Chris Bache: Well, let me just
frame this first date wise, and
that's maybe the most important
thing to start with. I came out
of graduate school in 78 and I
started this 20 year journey in
1979 and finished it 99 so you
have to take your mind back to
what was happening in 1978 Stan
Grof had just published his
first book, realms of the human
unconscious. I had come out of
graduate school in philosophy
religion. I was an agnostically
an atheistically inclined
agnostic. I read Stan's book,
and it just clicked something
deep inside me knew that I had
found my life's work, I was
convinced that the people
working in my field, which was
philosophy of religion, who
would be making the most
important contributions would be
people writing out of an
experiential basis, not simply
an intellectual basis. So I
began this process of
systematically undertaking the
inner journey to push the limits
of consciousness as far as I
could and to see what I could
use learn using this methodology
that Stan had pioneered. I
didn't like going outside the
law. I would have much rather
had done this legally, in a
legally sanctioned manner. But
this was after the control
Substances Act was passed in
1970 the only option I had to do
this work was to go underground,
to do it secretively. So I
learned the method. I studied
all the sources. I devoured
Stan's next book, LSD
psychotherapy always worked with
a sitter. Worked in a very
rigorous manner, and settle down
to the work. I worked for four
years, and then I stopped the
work for six years, and then I
resumed it for a very intense 10
years. So it was actually 14
years of active sessions,
averaging about five or six
sessions a year during that
time. Yeah.
Stephen Gray: So you where you
went with this is, you know,
almost impossible to conceive of
for most of us. I kind of
jokingly said to a couple of
friends that it made Terence
McKenna's description seem like
a pleasant walk on a Sunday
afternoon. God bless Terence.
Minus the aliens, of course, the
self, self replicating
basketball aliens, yeah. But to
be more serious about it, maybe
the simplest way to get it going
further at this point is to just
ask you to say a little bit
about, I mean, I'm familiar more
or less with that, you know the
sort of sequence of that
journey, but essentially, you
just kept going deeper. You use
the word, by the way, universe,
which seems to be a kind of a
synonym for what other people
might call, you know, the
creator, or the creators, or the
Holy Spirit, or whatever. But in
any case, this, whatever that is
the universe which was
communicating to you, and take
taking you very aware of you,
doing this as an individual, and
meeting you in the same place
you left off the previous time,
and taking you farther each
time. Maybe you could talk a
little bit about how that went,
you know, yeah.
Chris Bache: Well, first of all,
I worked at very high dose
levels. I made a conscious
choice after the first three
sessions to work at what I
considered to be the sort of the
maximum intensity, dose level. I
saw myself as simply doing an
extended course of LSD
psychotherapy. I mean, there's
psychedelic therapy, low dose
work, psychedelic therapy, high
dose work. And I saw myself
doing a series of that over
time, I realized that I was
encountering phenomena and
pushing boundaries that were not
showing up in classical LSD
psychotherapy, because that
method was limited to three
sessions maximum. And of course,
I was doing many more than that.
I don't recommend really having
done this work looking back on
it. I wouldn't if I were doing
it again, I would do it
differently. I wouldn't push the
system as hard as I push the
system. There's price to pay
along the way. So I just say
that as a preface, as a caveat,
before we get started where I
went might just be easiest, just
to ping through the chapters
where I tell the story in
diamonds from heaven. First two
years, I went through the
perinatal level of
consciousness, going through
reliving birth and going through
many experiences of birth and
death, culminating in the
complete shattering of my ego,
just being turned inside out as
I went into the next stage. Then
I went through two years. Well,
let me back up. Sessions always
divide between a cleansing
portion and a and an ecstatic
portion, a purifying portion,
and then the revelatory portion.
In the cleansing portion of the
next two years, I went into what
an ocean of suffering just vast.
You know, I'm thinking, I'm
jumping into the details too
quickly. Let me back up a little
bit
Stephen Gray: Sure, quick
interruption before you Yeah, do
you mind telling us what dosage
you were actually taking in
micrograms?
Chris Bache: I was working at
500 to 600 micrograms. Okay,
Marc Caron: and so my question
then is for our listeners, what
would be the you know, when
people are doing LSD in a
regular setting, if we can even
call it that, what's an average
dose of the average, you know,
hard to say,
Chris Bache: maybe 100
micrograms. It's really hard to
say, you know, a micro dot often
is 5075, micrograms of blotter.
It really depends, but it could
be 100 150 something like that.
Basically, low dose goes up to
300 micrograms, usually around
200 micrograms. I think many
people party at at 100
micrograms. I don't know. I
mean, I really don't, I don't
really have contacts in a
parting psychedelic world. It's
just not my world.
Marc Caron: You know, I
understand. I just wanted to
maybe kind of get a context for
what the average person would,
you know, the way they relate
to, yeah,
Chris Bache: this is an
extremely, very, very intense
regimen. I mean, it's very hard
on the body. It's very
challenging. It really requires
kind of an Explorer's
constitution to weather it well.
But I found that this dialog
opened up between me and the
universe, or me and the creative
intelligence of the universe, or
however you want to language it.
And I think that the. Caliber of
the conversation and the
continuity of conversation that
just went systematically layer
by layer by layer, is not simply
a result of the drug state or
and it's not simply a result of
the consciousness that I was
engaging, but I think it is in
partly a result of the
seriousness and the thoroughness
with which I tried to retain
complete consciousness at all
levels of the conversation, so
that I was methodical in
recording the conversation,
getting it written down within
24 hours after every session,
and I spent a lot of time in
between sessions thinking about
What had happened, trying to
internalize what had happened.
My experience is that the more
seriously and conscientiously we
engage these deeper states of
consciousness, the more
seriously and conscientiously
they engage us. And then this,
this spiral that I went through,
a series of Death-Rebirth
processes over these years,
taking the somewhat
systematically, rather
methodically, systematically
into deeper and deeper levels of
consciousness. As I said, the
first two years were kind of
spent in ego death, or
culminating in ego death. Next
two years took me into a realm
that I call the ocean of
suffering. It took me deep into
the collective psyche of our
species. It took me into, well,
what I write about in dark
night, Lord Dawn, is is a depth
of human suffering that I
eventually came to understand,
or came to believe, that what
was happening in these sessions
was not aimed at my personal
healing or transformation, but
it was aimed at the healing of
the collective psyche of
humanity itself, that somehow in
reliving 1000s and 1000s of
years of pain and brutality,
there was a healing taking place
In those sessions, during the
positive side of those sessions,
for one year, I went into a
state that I call deep time,
where I experienced the entirety
of my life, from start to
finish, beginning to end, as a
simultaneous present. And the
second year of the ocean of
suffering, which actually six
years later, I took my break.
Right then I had one year of the
ocean of suffering beforehand.
One year after, I went into this
series of experiences, deep
initiation into various cosmic
processes, initiations into the
universe. I was given teaching
an initiation systematically
into an understanding of
creation, into the processes of
creation. From there, I, after
that, culminated, and after two
years, I went into what I came
to view as archetypal reality. I
spent about a year and a half
exploring different dimensions
of archetypal reality, being
drawn into vast dimensions of
collective consciousness and
some of the workings of the
collective psyche, I began to
have experiences of
reincarnation, not as an
individual, but as a species,
the entire species,
reincarnation, generation by
generation, and what that was
about, and the intelligence
there. After those I went for
another year or so deep into
what Stan calls causal reality,
non dual consciousness,
Shunyata, emptiness began to
enter into the primal void. And
then that took me about 15 years
in and I still had five more
years on the journey, and in the
last five years of the journey,
I went into many levels of
experience, but basically an
encounter with what I call the
diamond Luminosity. My
understanding of this is, this
is what the Buddhists call
Dharmakaya. It is the domain of
light that lies outside Samsara.
It is the crystal and clear
light out of which all physical
existence emerges. And so I was
taken into that reality over 26
sessions, I entered that reality
only four times the years. In
between those four entries,
which came about once a year, I
went through a and this was
always happening, very, very
intense, rigorous purification
processes, because states of
consciousness, the deeper you
go, the pure the state of
consciousness. To stabilize
consciousness at these higher
levels, you have to purify your
entire physical psychological
system to be able to maintain
coherent consciousness at these
levels, if you just glance into
them, that's one thing. But if
you want to hold awareness for
hours at a time stably in these
states of consciousness, your
system has to be purified in
order to maintain. Incoherent
cognition there. I was
Stephen Gray: just going to ask
you about that. Actually, it's
one of the questions I had
written down for myself.
Actually took a quote out of
Dark Knight that says you have
to train yourself in order to
maintain coherent cognition in
these radical states of
consciousness. And then you also
use the term you have to learn
to learn. Learn how to learn. So
I'm always thinking about, you
know, the people who are
watching this, in case there is
any person brave enough and
perhaps foolhardy enough to and
take undertake a somewhat
similar process. Can, is there
something important you could
say to that person or those
people about, you know, how they
need to learn how to maintain
that coherent cognition and
learn to learn as they would go,
you know, into a continuing or
an ongoing process like this.
Chris Bache: I can and I will.
But first, some preliminaries.
One, okay, never work alone.
Always be working and, you know,
do your homework, do the
reading, read the books,
understand what you're getting
into. Never work alone. Always
have an experienced sitter, not
a guide, necessarily, but a
sitter, preferably one. Well, it
really has to be someone who
knows the ropes, who has entered
these states of consciousness,
because you're going into
territory that is so foreign,
that people who are not familiar
with this territory can get can
easily get frightened and
intimidated by what is coming at
them. You need someone who can
help you stay grounded and help
you find the courage to face
whatever darkness may arise in
those conditions. In terms of
me, once you take care of
safety, once you've curated the
playlist, once you have an
agreed upon arrangement with
your sitter, once you have
created all the conditions of
containment that allow for these
states to be engaged safely,
once you have the rules of
conduct established, so to
speak, then it's a matter of
finding within yourself the
trust and the capacity to go
wherever your consciousness or
wherever the session wants you
to go, wherever it wants to take
you and it'll take you into
excruciating pain, and one at
different times, and one of The
things I I learned from Stan
Grof and I he, I absorbed from
his writing, is a trust in the
process, that if you surrender
completely and let the process
take you wherever it wants to
go, it will take you through
potentially excruciating
dynamics, and it may break you,
but in that breaking, in that
surrender and dying process, it
will also heal you, and it will
bring you alive in new ways that
you ways you had not been alive
before. So it's trust, it's
courage, it's seeing things
through all the way down to the
bottom every session. It's
really important that every
session be taken as far as it
can possibly go, so that you
don't leave unfinished business
behind you. Usually, when you
reach a peak and you go through
a Death-Rebirth process, you go
through the remainder of the
session into some positive,
ecstatic state, and then the
system will calm down. The next
session, you'll resume into the
wherever you stop the cleansing,
if you hold it long enough,
eventually this will reach a
peak, and then you'll go through
into the ecstatic state again.
So one
Stephen Gray: of the things you
Oh, sorry, well, one of the
things you've spoken about in
dark night is that, you know, I
think the universal Primal Fear
for human beings is the fear of
what Buddhists would call non
existence of the individual
self, right? So I found it to be
quite instructive in in dark
night that you pointed out that
while whatever that illusory
self is dies, individuality
doesn't. There's a different
kind of individuality somehow
that arises out of that, you
know, I'm always thinking of
like the people that are
watching this, the kind of
people who will come to the
conference, what they what they
can learn about this, because I
think perhaps some reassurance
about that might be helpful, you
know, especially for medicine
people, right? Yeah,
Chris Bache: well, you know, in
the Vedanta tradition, the
individual is illusion. So the
goal is you destroy the
individual, you destroy ego, you
die, and then you dissolve into
the infinite. And that's not a
while. That's a, you know, a
widespread and deeply held set
of convictions that I don't
share. That conviction, my
experience, is that the. Of our
life can die. Everything that we
know ourselves to be and
everything we've ever known may
die when may completely be
shattered and just completely
die. But in that process, you
then are reborn. You wake up in
a new world and a new context
and as a new being. And if you
go through this process multiple
times, you begin to realize that
the form of your life is
repeatedly dying at deeper and
deeper levels, but the essence
of your life is indestructible.
The ego Chris Bache is
destructible. You know, that's a
temporary form, but the essence
underneath that is
indestructible. And there is as
the superficial layers of our
being perish and fall away.
There is a there is a liberation
and a freeing of a deeper form
of individuality. And I think
this is a developmental process
is taking place in
reincarnation. Just as we die
and then we're reborn. We die,
we're reborn, there is emerging
in that process, a a germinal
seed that is individual, but not
isolated, individual, but open
to life on all sides.
Stephen Gray: Maybe I can. It
just begs so many questions,
Chris, maybe I can get about six
questions into one. Somehow, it
all has to do with a central
element of your work. Perhaps
the central element in terms of
other people that you're
speaking to is that on several
levels, there's this individual
ego death and rebirth process.
There's the collective ego death
and rebirth process. And in that
vein, there's you've been shown
by this creative intelligence
the universe, that several
things, one that we're probably,
maybe even certainly, you could
correct me on this approaching
an imminent economic and
environmental collapse and and
secondly, that that actually has
to happen because of the need
for the great death, as you've
called it before, the Great
Awakening. And then the the one
that they want to kind of
squeeze into that question, as
well as given that I don't think
very many people are going to do
the kind of deep, deep, extended
work that you did for this
essential consciousness
revolution to actually manifest,
I'm wondering if there's things
that you could you can think of,
or guidance that You could think
of for people that are
interested in working with
psychedelics, but not at that
level. I mean, you know, ways
that others can approach this?
Yeah,
Chris Bache: I hope not many
people would choose to work in
the way that I did or at the
level that I did, and I wouldn't
do it that way again myself, if
I were doing it from scratch. I
think we are continuously in
dialog with an infinite
intelligence right now, you and
I are existing in our bodies,
but our consciousness is in
intimate rapport with an
infinite consciousness. When we
take a psychedelic of any form
and we take a medicine, we hyper
sensitize our system, and a
system begins to go through a
spontaneous purification
process, and we begin to have to
face things that we'd rather not
face. We begin to have to look
at things that often would
rather not look at, and we have
to remember things that many of
us would rather not remember.
This is the universe healing us.
This is how the universe helps
us become whole, helps us heal
the fissures which have gotten
embedded in our particular
system, in that process of
healing the body and healing
consciousness and healing the
soul, healing the former life
trauma that we all carry in that
process, we not only remove
negativity from the system and
heal the system, but we also
open the system to new levels of
intimacy with the universe
itself. So we awaken capacities.
We awaken emotional capacities.
We awaken intellectual and
spiritual capacities within the
organism. Everybody has to find
their own modulation of this
dialog, of this stance, whether
or not I think this is happening
continuously, even if you never
take a psychedelic, we're
constantly living we're making
choices. We're living in dialog
with the universe. It's just
it's a process that's moving
very slowly. Reincarnation is a
very finely tuned system.
System, but it moves very
slowly. When we begin a
spiritual practice, whether it's
meditation or yoga or trans
dancing or psychedelics, we
accelerate that process. As we
accelerate the process, it not
only gets deeper, but it gets
larger, so that we enter into
deeper rapport with the
universe, and we also enter into
larger rapport with the
universe. So people often begin
to be touched by our so called
Private work. One of the things
I learned in this process is
there is no such thing as
private spiritual practice.
There is no such thing as
private healing. Whenever we
heal deeply the individual, we
always touch the lives of people
that we karma connect,
karmaically connected to whether
we ever meet them in the
physical body or not. And then
if you, if you have a, I think,
if you have a deep heart, if you
have a deep, felt commitment to
other people and to animals and
just to the planet, when given
the opportunity to do something
constructive on behalf of other
people, I think most people
would say, Yes, I'll help. I'll,
you know, I'll, I'll undertake
that. Show me what I can do.
This is what happened with me in
the ocean of suffering, what
happened in all the work when
your individual consciousness
shatters, you don't
spontaneously pop into oneness.
I mean, some people do and but
you pop into a larger field of
consciousness. You move into the
consciousness of your species.
You move into, perhaps the
consciousness of Earth, you move
into the consciousness of other
life forms. When I moved into
the consciousness of my species,
I experienced my species as a
living organism, and I
experienced my species on a
developmental trajectory, and I
experienced over and over again
in a way that I was completely
unprepared for. Caught
completely by surprise. I was
not at all really well versed in
the global systems crisis, but
over and over again, I was shown
that humanity is coming into a
critical hour in its destiny, a
critical bifurcation point in
its evolutionary process, and
that we were poised on the edge
of a profound cycle, spiritual
awakening, just a profound
before and after point in human
history, something that would be
marked by, well, it would be
used as a marker in history for
the turning point in humanity.
The proportions of this are hard
to estimate, but and so there
was a particular session called
the Great Awakening, which took
me deep into this awakening of
the entire human species. And I
don't know when. I don't know
how. You know, it's not like I'm
getting details on those. But
the the certainty of the
conviction that humanity is
moving in this direction, that
we're going there was very, very
strong and for their justice and
mystical traditions, for a
person to achieve spiritual
awakening, oneness with God, or
there must first take place, the
dark night of the soul, the
tremendous purification, the
emptying of all the old habits,
the emptying of everything that
keeps us small in order to allow
us to open into that which is
large. Likewise for humanity, if
humanity is going to go through
a profound spiritual awakening.
There must take place a a dark
night of the soul for the entire
species, what I call the Great
death. There must be a cleansing
of all of the choices that
humanity has made, which have
kept it fragmented, which have
kept it small. You know, the
choices against race, the
choices against religion, the
choices of class, all the ways
we've divided and carved up the
planet. What?
Stephen Gray: Lots of questions
about that. But here's one of
them. Excuse me, you know this
in terms of this great, great
death and great, you know,
rebirth or reawakening of the
species. You know, you know. We
know that as people lose their
ground, of their sort of known
world becomes unstable. And I'm
not talking about the seekers
now. I'm just talking about, you
know, the you the regular folk
in a country or whatever. Yes,
there's a crack that could open
up for a potential rebirth. But
it seems to me, also that is a
recipe potentially for a very
dystopian scenario, you know,
with the sort of, you know, I
guess Adolf Hitler. Would be a
classic example where his, you
know, his people got, got
treated like shit. After World
War One, Mark went nuts, there
was all kinds of stability, and
Hitler, you know, as a
psychopath or whatever, a
fascist took advantage of that.
So I'm wondering, like you know,
if we are increasingly, you
know, falling into economic and
environmental collapse, the
instability and fear that that
could generate, could they not
go the opposite way? I mean,
what? What is the universe
telling you about that it
Chris Bache: can go the opposite
way? We are coming entering
frightening times and hard
times. I think the global I
think there's a global systems
crisis that is fermenting, which
is being driven first by
ecological forces and then by a
series of historical and
economic forces. I think if what
I'm seeing is correct, we're
entering a time of
deconstruction, a time when the
normal assumptions of life are
going to be stripped from us.
We're going to lose control of
more and more of our lives. And
when that happened, when that
has happened historically, and
when it happens in the lives of
individual, it doesn't always
produce a beautiful being at the
end, it often produces, it
sometimes can produces very ugly
results and very destructive,
regressive us against them. At
this point, I think we're going
to have to choose, as a people,
individually and as a people and
as a species, as we get into
this crisis, we're going to have
to make a choice over and over
again. We're going to have to
make a series of choices. We're
going to have to choose on the
basis of ego, meaning, on the
basis of our individual private
experience, of what serves our
individual private good, or what
serves a larger collective good,
what serves the good of the
commons. If we choose inclusive
solutions to the crises that are
coming, then I think we will
make an accelerated pivot into
an unbelievable positive future.
If we make regressive, silly
choices, if we choose a narrow
option, if we choose only what's
good for us and our kind and us
in a narrow sense, I think we'll
probably go extinct, because you
basically can't run this planet
on the basis of the ego and have
nuclear weapons and biological
weapons destructive capacity
without there being catastrophic
consequences. I think it's the
pressure of extinction which is
actually an extraordinarily
powerful evolutionary driver,
which is will be pushing us, I
think, to make better choices in
the future than we've made in
the past. I don't think this is
like any a magical process
where, you know, Spirit is going
to take over and the Holy Spirit
is going to occur, and
something's going to happen to
save us from ourselves. It's not
about saving us from ourselves.
It's about growing up. It's
about taking responsibility for
ourselves in history. And one
way of thinking about it is it's
about living from our soul,
because the soul knows that we
are more than this body. The
soul knows that we have web of
relationships. The soul knows
that the Earth that we leave is
the earth we're coming back to.
The soul has a depth and a
perspective. But we, we, we have
built a civilization based
largely upon the ego's
perspective, private self,
private me and mine. We are in
the process of outgrowing that.
I think we're in the process of
growing into the experience of
the soul on earth, our soul
consciousness, which most people
only experience when they're in
between lives in the Bardo, is
actually waking up inside
historical existence. But that's
not an easy process. That's a
birth process. But what my
sessions show me, what they tell
me, is that we will make it.
There's no guarantee. You know,
it's an evolutionary process,
and there are no guarantees in
evolution. But where I have
been, what I have seen in my
journeys through deep time is
that we do make it. And what's
emerging on our planet is an
extraordinary being, just the
next generation, or the next
form of humanity, what I call
the future human, is just, it's
it's just an extraordinary
being. We are in the process of
birthing this being into
history. It's like as a species,
we are a woman going into labor.
We're beginning to get into the
real thick of it, where things
really begin to fall apart.
Imagine if we didn't know we
were pregnant. Imagine if we
didn't know what we were doing,
if we were. Giving birth. We are
in the process of giving birth.
I don't think we You can't stay
in labor too long. It's
dangerous for the mother and
child. Likewise, the planet is
not going to be able to stay in
labor too long. It's going to
drive us to to precipitous and
rapid choices, critical choices,
if we make those choices, well,
if we do a good job with this
process, I think it will usher a
completely different era in
human history
Stephen Gray: that's beautifully
said and and in spite of the
terrifying possibilities,
incredibly positive, because it
shows us that there is, you
know, something you know, that's
available to the species and to
all human beings. So from there,
that almost seems like hard to
come back to, you know, somewhat
more prosaic or specifics.
However, you've made reference
to reincarnation and versions.
There of a little in this, in
this conversation, and I know
you made a study of it, you
wrote a book about it, and
you've had some very interesting
thoughts about it. I'm curious.
I'm curious about a couple
things here. One of them kind of
hits a little trigger point in
me and but so sort of, sort of a
two or three part question here.
One is, I, you know, I think it
would be really instructive for
people to hear you talk a little
about your understanding of
incarnation, because you also
talk about beyond incarnation
and stuff, but within that, I
have something kind of specific
that I've sort of wondered
about, and I'm going to read you
a quote from your book. Okay, if
our experience in this life is
convoluted and torn by
conflicting forces. It was
transparently obvious. It was,
in other words, it was shown to
you that this is caused by the
carryover of exercises from
other space time, encounters,
dot, dot, dot. What we are is
the result of everything we have
ever thought. So. The thing that
I'm wondering that you could
clarify a little on that one is,
I think a lot of people would
hear that as somehow they're
guilty or at fault or to blame
for everything that they're
experiencing now. And what I
wonder about, I understand the
principle of what you're saying.
But if you're right now living
in, I don't know, say
Bangladesh, and you know,
there's just been another one of
those floods, or something like
that, you're a good hearted
person. You're trying to make a
good life for your family. Do
you have some culpability or
responsibility for being in that
situation in the external as
well.
Chris Bache: Yeah, do no, no,
no, okay, yeah, you know, I want
to step back just for a moment.
I feel guilty. You know, we kind
of we're jumping into really,
really heavy topics, or jumping
into, you know, psychedelics and
deep states of consciousness and
the future of humanity, and, you
know, really, and we're about to
jump into reincarnation. These
are all very substantive and
deserving issues that need to be
taken time. They need to be
unfolded carefully and
gradually. When I when I teach a
taught a course in my university
called Transpersonal studies. I
spent a third of the semester,
five weeks just looking at the
evidence for rebirth. Okay, it
says it takes time to really
unpack all the components and
all the nuances. And I think
likewise for reincarnation to
bring it here. Reincarnation is
one of the oldest philosophies
on the planet, and it has kept
company with many primitive
beliefs, which I don't think are
really deserving. There are
different theories of
reincarnation, different
sophistications around our
understanding of reincarnation,
but the key is simply this, we
are a learning system. We learn
by challenging ourselves. We
enter conditions, we make
choices. We inherit the
consequences of those choices.
We internalize those and
eventually we die. And this
learning continues. The soul
gathers its knowledge. The
species gathers its knowledge,
generation by generation, we
plunge back into the process. We
keep this process going. We keep
trying, we keep exploring, we
keep pushing ourselves. And as
we go through this process, we
activate potentials that are
latent within us, classically in
the Hindu system, we activate
the chakras we move through from
the first all the way up to the
seventh chakra of oneness. I.
When we when we incarnate,
classically, our story of
reincarnation has been a story
that's focused on individual
karma, the end of evolution of
the individual. I think we've
overly personalized karma. We've
overly personalized
reincarnation. It's not that
that's not a true story. That is
a true story. The soul is making
choices. The soul is growing.
But there's another dynamic
that's taking place, and that
is, there's a collective dynamic
of reincarnation. There's an
evolutionary dynamic of
reincarnation, and what the
individual can accomplish is
always tempered by or influenced
what the species is able to
accomplish, what is going on in
the species. There's one of the
hardest things for all of us in
any philosophical system or any
religious or spiritual system to
address or to understand, is
suffering, just seemingly
gratuitous, painful suffering of
natural causes and diseases and
the things, the terrible things
we do to each other. I don't
think there's a simple formula
for understanding any of these
things. They're they're
different perspectives that give
us different perspectives on how
things on what levels we want to
address this question at. I
think we choose generally. The
evidence from a number of
sources suggests that we choose
where we incarnate. We choose
who we incarnate with. We choose
incarnating in conditions that
can be debilitatingly painful.
And if there is an intelligence
to the system, if there is a
fundamental intelligence to the
reincarnational process, there
is an intelligence expressing
itself even circumstances of
such such profound suffering
that we can't make sense of it.
We can't understand why anyone
would choose to submit
themselves to that kind of
ordeal. And yet, if we can find
meaning in certain context, if
we can take people into deep
states of consciousness and
uncover their individual history
and find meaningful connection
between their former lives, then
I think we have grounds for
thinking that there is meaning
taking place even in those
circumstances where we can't
necessarily understand it. When
we're trying to understand
individual suffering, there's a
set of issues and dynamics that
we look at. But if we're trying
to understand collective
suffering, we're trying to
understand the suffering that
touches hundreds of 1000s,
millions of people's lives, all
at the same time, generational
suffering, we have to bring in a
different a larger picture, a
larger apparatus.
To me, reincarnation is the
higher octave of evolution. In
evolution, the creative
intelligence of the universe is
folding collective learning
forward through the evolving of
the whole species through
reincarnation, the creative
intelligence of the universe is
folding individual learning
forward, but individual learning
and collective learning are all
intertwined because the
individual is a human being, and
the human being is a species at
a certain stage of its
Evolution. So as the individual
grows, the species is growing.
I think our entire species is
going to a point, or this is
what's hard, because it is such
a long discussion. There are so
many stages. I feel really
guilty trying to take the
shortcuts that I'm trying to
get, to extract an answer in a
matter of five minutes. When
it's a really it's it's a long
process.
Stephen Gray: People are going
to have to dive into your work
more. And one of those ways, of
course, is going to come to the
conference and post conference
talk you're going to give called
The Birth of the future human.
So maybe I can throw
Chris Bache: it I'll mention
that's this is going to be the
first time I've given a public
lecture completely dedicated to
that topic, the birth of the
future human. I've written about
it. I wrote about it in dark
night, early dawn. I write about
it in diamonds from heaven. But
I've not really tried to
publicly speak about this a lot,
so that's I'm really working
hard to prepare that
presentation.
Marc Caron: One thing I'd like
to say, Chris is, I think it's
great material, just based on
your experience that a lot of
people haven't experienced, and
the questions really come.
Around. And I really respect,
you know, the you know, what you
want to bring to your answers,
because I understand that
they're not, you know, quick and
something that can just be
answered in a sentence or two.
What I do really appreciate is,
you know, the curiosity and the
inspiration and the questions
that even come through my mind
just listening, because I'm in
on what you're talking about.
And as Steven says, a million
questions. So, you know, I've
got a million too, and I'm sure
the same, but it's, you know,
what I love about this
conversation is that it gets
people curious to ask more
questions, to look deeper into
their own consciousness, and you
know how they choose to then
expand that as well, because you
know your experience is just one
of many different ways people,
sure, use plant medicines and
different attributes to enhance
and expand their consciousness.
Yeah, and it's obvious that the
work you've done, you certainly
went on a hero's journey, like
73 times. I just admire, I
admire that work, because, like
we said before, we just got on,
you know, very, very brave and
courageous for the work that you
did to find the answers and the
insights that you did. So I
thank you for that, and I also
want to thank you just for
wanting to give the answers to
the questions. You know, that
level of intellectual meat
potatoes, I guess, yeah, the
answer, you know,
Stephen Gray: that almost sounds
like an ending. Let's not stop
there.
Unknown: I just wanted to
clarify, because I could see we
could be here for hours, right?
What?
Chris Bache: What I've learned
is in studying all the
literature that I studied in
order to write life cycles, the
book on reincarnation and out of
the session says the
circumstances in which we find
ourselves have significance.
They have meaning. They're not
accidental, they're not random.
They have meaning. Some of that
meaning is individual, some of
that meaning is collective. But
how we respond to the
circumstances in which we find
ourselves, how we allow it to
change us, how we allow us, how
we make ourselves better human
beings in responding to those
circumstances, how we learn
that's the vital thing. We may
not understand why things are
the way they are, but as we
respond completely in heart and
mind to our circumstances. We
change as we change. We grow.
When we look at our lives
through multiple iterations and
even generations, we're growing
we're changing. The species is
growing and changing. The planet
is growing and changing, and
we're all hard wired into each
other in so
Stephen Gray: amazing, isn't it?
Yeah, yeah. So I got a few more
questions I'd like to fire at
you another some more. These are
like, like, oh god. How do I
get, you know, all my curiosity
into one or two simple kind of
things. And this one has to do
with, no, it's impossible. So
this one has more to do with
what you what you might call, or
has been called, you know, non
embodied intelligences. You've
talked about the universe in the
general sense. You never, I
don't recall you ever saying
that you'd encountered anything
in particular that presented
itself in some sort of visual
form as an entity or a being or
anything like that. But
certainly, lots of people
working with the medicines these
days talk about that, with
Ayahuasca and so on that. And so
that's part of the question.
What you would say about that?
And another component of that
sort of same area of curiosity
for me is I was involved in the
Native American church Peyote
ceremonies for about a dozen
years, those people very
passionately, not only believe
but claim that there's a there's
a power in prayer, in especially
a group, intention all being
focused together. But they claim
that, that you know, when you
put out a prayer that sincere
comes from the heart and perhaps
amplified by a medicine like
that, that you are indeed, that
prayer is indeed capable of
change in the material realm. So
I'm wondering, you know, if you
thought much about that, and
then just this general sense of,
you know, how intelligence, you
know, can manifest or present
itself, you know, outside of our
human even to the point of like,
is the earth a being? Is the
earth an intelligent being?
Anyway, whatever you can do with
that, yeah, please, please do
Yeah, well,
Chris Bache: I'd say yes and
yes. I mean,
Unknown: okay, thanks. Charles,
those are some easy answers.
Chris Bache: I think intention
is powerful. A collective.
Intention is powerful, focused.
Intention amplified. Intention
is powerful. It influences our
body. It influences
circumstances around us. It
influences other people. So I'm
really comfortable with that. I
think David Nichols had written
a book called subtle activism,
where he's talking about these
you know, he's one of people who
organizes global meditations
focused. So we're gathering
hundreds of 1000s of people in
meditational exercises,
basically integrating their
consciousness into prayerful
exercise. Guru Yoga in the
Buddhist and other traditions,
where they are focusing all the
disciples from all over the
world, all the students of a
particular teacher doing a
particular practice on a
particular day at a particular
time. I think these have, these
are very, very powerful and
focused exercises. My sense is
that the spiritual universe is a
highly populated world. I mean,
it's just we tend to like to
see. I mean, imagine if for
every physical life form, there
were spiritual life forms. For
every level of physical life
form, there were levels of
spiritual life forms. Certainly
the sacred medicine tradition is
when we take these various herbs
and substances and Peyote and
mushrooms that we encounter
these living life forms at
different levels, we encounter
them and we find, much to our
surprise, they're interested in
us, and they're willing to help
us, and they're willing to work
with us. I'm really comfortable
with that. I mean, I've
experienced enough Ayahuasca and
enough Psilocybin mushroom
sessions that have encountered,
you know, the living some of the
living entities of the universe
in my LSD work. This is a
particular medicine that has
particular characteristics, so I
want to be careful that that's
my primary medicine work. I've
done other work, but my primary
philosophical work has been the
LSD work. And LSD tends to be,
first of all, it doesn't have
many historical fields
associated with it. You know,
Peyote has been being used for
1000s of years. Ayahuasca has
been used for 1000s of years. So
there are fields associated with
these medicines. LSD is a new
medicine. Doesn't have a lot of
fields associated with it. It
also tends to be a high altitude
medicine, so it tends to blow
into the cosmic, logical
ceiling. It's not a it's not
like my mushrooms or Ayahuasca,
which tends to work at a certain
level of spiritual reality. It
tends to push into kind of the
cosmic, logical level. So it
also tends to just grind the ego
up fine as dust. And my sense is
that it's kind of like you have
to be a being to encounter
beings, and if you're not a
being, you don't tend to
encounter as many beings. It's
not that those beings aren't
there, but you kind of our
presence evokes the conversation
or evokes the experiences that
we have from the infinite
potential of consciousness. In
my experience, in working with
LSD, when I die at lower levels,
I don't simply become a
conscious Chris Bache, having
interesting Transpersonal
experiences, I cease to be Chris
Bache, except with continuity of
memory. I have continuity of
memory with Chris, but I become
different kinds of being. And in
my case, I enter different
strata of consciousness. So it's
kind of like if you were looking
at atmosphere. You enter
different layers of the
atmosphere of a planet, I just
dissolve into patterns of
consciousness which are not
individual, but they tend to be
very large and very wide, not
all different medicines tune us
to the infinite potential of
consciousness in different ways.
Peyote tunes us in a certain
way. Mushrooms tune us in a
certain way. We have it's not
like it's all covering the same
highway. We have different roads
into the landscape and different
experiences. But my I'm
convinced that the entire
spiritual landscape is hyper
consciousness, hyper aware, and
is populated with beings.
Stephen Gray: You know that what
you were talking about with, you
know, LSD having its particular
characteristic of kind of
blasting you out into the Cosmo,
so to speak, high altitude and
all that. It. Your talk at that
Transpersonal conference. This
is something that I've been
quite curious about, and I'll
try to explain and turn it into
a question. Is that you said
that it was at some point became
very difficult to come back
after the end of this 20 year
journey, that you really missed
that, and that a certain point
you were quite confessional
about it. Said you actually felt
like you were waiting to die,
that, you know, the kind of a, I
don't know, maybe a flatness or
something about existence here.
So, so the where I'm going with
this as a question is, you know,
I guess I'd have to confess at a
much more kindergarten level of
experience in these realms, my
assumption, or, you know, I
guess predilection is been quite
influenced by a Buddhist teacher
that I worked with for quite a
long time. You might have heard
of chugyam, Trungpa, yeah. Well,
a lot of Trungpa Rinpoche
teachings were focused on, you
know, this precious human birth
and how we, in a sense, revel in
it. You know that, you know, he
would use things like learning
how to appreciate the redness of
red and the blueness of blue,
you know. And he said that
enlightenment, or, I don't know,
I'm not quoting him word by word
here, but something effective,
you know, wisdom or
enlightenment is as much about
learning how to make a proper
cup of tea as anything else you
know that, that you know we're
given this an amazing gift of
this particular you know,
constellation of, you know,
energies or whatever densities
and all that, with this amazing
ability to appreciate this, you
know, through our senses and our
you know, our music and you know
our everything, right? So I'm
wondering, you know why that
seems so flat to you when you
came back from this process?
Chris Bache: Yeah, good
question. Well formulated. You
know, I got into this work for a
number of reasons, but
certainly, you know, I was
interested in enlightenment.
I've been meditating for a
number of years. I'd encountered
the kind of blocks that usually
show up in the first years of
practice, and I thought that if
I did some LSD sessions, I could
break through these blocks and
expose my own foibles and and I
would wake up sooner. I would
kind of accelerate my own
enlightenment. What I found was
that working in the particular
modality that I did, very high
doses, it took me so far that I
began to realize that a lot of
my experiences that were
happening, first of all, were
not concerning me personally,
but they were larger than me.
And they were there was
something deeper going on than
enlightenment. Enlightenment is
a perfectly acceptable and
wonderful focus for one's life,
but what was happening in my
sessions was something
different. At the end, it curved
back around toward the
Enlightenment tradition. But it
was something different. It was
it was a process of exploring
the cosmos. So there's the
Enlightenment project, or
spiritual development, and then
simply exploring the calm the
cosmos, going deeper and deeper
into the cosmos itself. What
happened for me is that in the
last five years of this work,
when I went into the diamond
Luminosity work, when I went I
dissolved so deeply into that
light, into that into the body
of God, you might say, into the
in the Dharmakaya. After doing
that, that particular phase of
the work for five years, I came
to a point where I knew I had to
stop. And I had to stop for a
couple of reasons. One is
because my system was running so
hot. It was just running so hot.
It was always uncomfortable. I
was having some subtle energy
issues. I was overheating my
system, essentially. But the
main reason I stopped was that I
could not bear the heartache of
coming back. So I had dissolved
so intimately into the divine
that when I came back there was
such a sense of withdrawal and
such a sense of loss that I just
couldn't keep going out into it
and coming back. Now, ideally,
of course, one wants to open up
to that kind of intimacy in a
way that you don't have to come
back from. You want to open up
into oneness with the Divine, or
experiencing the divine
Luminosity in a way that you can
sustain in your physical
consciousness. That is the
spiritual ideal, in a way,
working with psychedelic
particularly the way that I work
with them, this is a path of
temporary immersion. It
temporarily opens you to the
universe, and then you come
back, and temporarily opens you
come. Back, and I drove myself
so deep into the universe that
eventually, when I stopped my
work, when I stopped my work, I
thought I was just going to be
able to stop and process and
enjoy the many gifts that I had
been given. But after I stopped,
I found myself entering a deep
and profound sadness, and that's
why it's not just a hero's
journey. It is I understand
that, but it's also the story of
the Wounded Hero. It's someone
who was wounded deeply by the
sheer beauty of what he she
discovered. So I found it when I
did come back, when I began to
stop my sessions, when I did
stop my sessions, I found that I
was so I was missing the
communion with the divine so
deeply that I really was just
waiting to die. I was waiting to
wrap up my life. I was taking
care of my children, my family,
and I was teaching and doing
things, but this life had become
flat, and it's I knew that the
physical world was the body of
the Divine. I knew that the that
that it was the manifestation of
the creative intelligence of the
universe. It was the divine and
manifest form. I knew that the
limitations were all mine, what
I had done in all this, the way
I did the work, I lost the
balance. There's a balance
between Transcendence and
eminence. There's the
transcendent divine and the
imminent divine. I had pushed
myself so deeply in the path of
Transcendence that I had lost my
foothold in the imminent divine
so it was. It's a balancing act
between opening up to the
totality of all that is in all
of its dimensions and all of its
levels, and then grounding in
the present body, in the present
day, in the present life, in
your present form. I got those
out of balance, and it took
years of work to sort of commit
myself, to regrounding myself in
the here and now as I was, as I
am for the remainder of my life.
That's why, for among other
reasons, that's one of the
reasons I wouldn't encourage
people to do what I did. It's
funny. It's a tricky thing. A
little bit of Transcendence is a
very good thing. It can heal us.
It can show us who we are. It
can help us understand what's
going on in life. It can
activate very positive
dimensions of our being. But if
you plunge yourself too deeply
into Transcendence, you can lose
your footing in the here and now
and the the blessings of the
here and now are equally
important blessings to the
blessings of Transcendence this
physical world is a sacred
special place. And I think
enlightenment is an attempt to
awaken into to become
transparent to the totality, but
in a way that keeps your feet
solidly planted on the earth.
Stephen Gray: Do you think you
would have been able to come
back with the same kind of
incontrovertible understandings
and insights. Had you not, you
know, done it that intensively?
You know, the
Chris Bache: path not taken?
Yeah.
Marc Caron: So my question then
is, you know, one thing we see a
real need for within our
community is the need for the
integration after doing this
kind of work. Yeah, and then,
which leads me to the question
is, how did you then adjust to
transform yourself so that you
weren't just kind of waiting to
die? How did you get that joy
for this life
Chris Bache: back. I think
integration is the emerging, one
of the very powerful emerging
themes in the psychedelic
community, and it's really,
really important. It's been
under, undervalued and
understated. I mean, as long as
we're staying close to
conventional reality and we're
healing the personal psyche, I
think we we have medical models
for what integration, healthy
integration, looks like, and if
we go deeper to experience the
intelligence that runs through
all things and the continuity of
life after death, we still have
spiritual models that help us
Understand and integrate those
experiences into a into a well
lived life. But when you go
farther than that, when you go
deeper than that, when you go
beyond physical space, time,
reality, when you plunge deep
into the universe, then I think
integration becomes a more
fundamental question. And.
Frankly, I've spent a year
writing just the last chapter of
diamonds from heaven, which is
the chapter of coming off the
mountain. Is the chapter on
integration.
In order to kind of regroup
myself, I grabbed my my life,
and I recommitted myself to
being on this earth. I renewed
my contemplative practice. I
deepened my contemplative
practice. I renewed my
commitment to the body. I
renewed my commitment to
relationships. But the other
thing I found was the sad
sadness of leaving the communion
with the divine was exacerbated
by the silence that my society
forced upon me because of its
prohibitions around
psychedelics. I wasn't allowed
to talk about my experiences.
I'm a teacher. I want to
discover and I want to share. I
wasn't allowed to share my
experiences. I had to keep
quiet. I wasn't allowed to talk
to my students. I wasn't allowed
to talk to my colleagues about
this work. I wasn't I did this
work as a philosopher, but I was
not being allowed to function as
a philosopher, and what I found
was this section in the chapter
I call the sickness of silence.
Integration is not simply a
psychological process. It's a
social process, and socially, I
was not allowed to integrate my
experiences into my life. I had
split myself in half, and it was
really writing diamonds from
heaven, first writing dark
night, early dawn, and then
writing diamonds from heaven,
where I began to put together
the two halves of my life. I
began to put together my
psychedelic half and my
professorial, you know, physical
half. And it really begin to
speaking clearly and powerfully
about my experiences and writing
about them that I've begun to
feel myself more grounded on the
earth in a way that I have not
felt in years prior. So part of
it is integration, means
bringing the experiences back
and being willing to share them
and talk about them and engage
people around them. Excellent.
Marc Caron: Yeah, ourselves. And
one other question was then, oh,
slip my mind, Steven. Go ahead.
That's great.
Stephen Gray: Well, I think, you
know, people have taken in so
much if they're watching this,
that at this point they're
probably going to go have to
pour themselves a whiskey
anyway, just to calm down a
little, you know, you know
they're not in Kansas anymore
now. So perhaps, just to kind of
end on a, you know, an uplifting
note, so to speak. You know, you
talked about how, you know, we
can do it. We will do it in a
sense, and you know that we have
choices. But, you know, let's
assume that that the process
works out in the best way that
can the journey for the species
over the next, whatever it is,
several decades or so, and we
are able to, you know, go
through that consciousness
revolution and so on. Maybe just
you could sum up with a little
bit what does the future human
look like?
Unknown: I first
Chris Bache: we've been building
the future human for 10s of
1000s of years. We've been
building it with every
incarnation, every repetitive
cycle. We've been building it.
We've been activating the form
that this human being is. We've
been learning it, stretching it,
teaching it, growing it,
lifetime by lifetime, lifetime
by lifetime. I think where we're
going, what's going to be
happening is all of our former
lives are coming together as we
become more coherent, as we
become more integrated, all of
these lives come together. The
way I experienced it in the
session was I experienced one
session where all my former
lives began to come together,
like wrapping string around a
kite spool, and at a certain
point they fuse. There was an
explosion of energy, and they
fused. And when they fused, this
diamond light broke out of my
chest and threw me into a
completely different state of
consciousness. It was
individual, but it was a form of
individual consciousness that
was beyond anything that I had
ever experienced before. And it
wasn't simply the sum of the
individual lives that all of
those lives had been actualized
in a higher form of evolutionary
expression. I think the future
human was. I touched there was
my own personal version of the
future human that is evolving.
In evolution, we have to picture
a species where we have healed
all the pains of history, where
we've healed all the divisions
against each other and against
our own body and against our own
soul, where we have opened our
heart to all, not only all human
beings, but all life forms,
where our mind is in conscious
communion, more conscious and
open communion with the
intelligence of the universe, as
I in one of the very last
sessions. It was one of the most
difficult sessions I ever went
through. I went through a huge
trip down was taken far into the
future, deeper into deep time
than I'd ever been. And one of
the gems of that session was to
actually experience the
archetypal form of the future,
human, what we are in the
process of becoming. And truly,
I mean, it's like a you hear it
said, we're becoming a planet of
Buddhas, a planet of Christ, a
planet of Prophets. We're
becoming the picture, the
highest levels of spiritual
realization that we have known
in history, individuals have
accomplished, and picture the
entire species operating at that
level. What kind of species
would we be when the entire
species is is enlightened, when
the entire species is uplifted,
spiritually and emotionally and
psychologically? That's what
we're in the process of becoming
once we have once we have
activated that deep level of our
own being collectively, then we
can really begin to cook. Then
we can really begin to do
something exciting on the
planet, off the planet, into the
galaxy. I mean, intelligence
that created this universe
thinks on a scale that just
still boggles our mind. And I
think our planet is one of many
hot houses where consciousness
is being incubated. But it's not
going to stay on this planet.
It's going to migrate. It's
going to move. It's going to go
forward. But in order to make
this jump, we first have to grow
up. We first have to come to
terms with what we are. We have
to stop thinking in terms of
this body, this life, and open
ourselves to the full depth and
splendor of the being that lies
within and we
Stephen Gray: are full. I think
we are Thank you, beautiful.
Does that sound like a good
place to end?
Marc Caron: Mark, it could have
been a better segue in this
whole conversation to you know,
tail off such a deep and
inspiring and thought provoking
conversation, for sure. So I
thank you very much for that,
Chris. I look forward to meeting
you in person. I look forward to
hearing your talk at the
conference,
Chris Bache: and I'm looking
forward to it very much. I'm
looking forward to that that
weekend, it's going to
marvelous. I can't believe the
wonderful people that you've
gathered for that weekend. It's
just, I'm really looking
forward.
Marc Caron: It's growing, and
it's just getting more and more
popular every day. We're really
excited to what, what's going to
transform here for for this
year's conference, and, you
know, it's just exciting to be
part of it, yeah, and, you know,
Chris, I Oh, love to reach out.
The invitation at some point
too, is, you know, if you're
interested in doing more of
these kind of conversations, to
share some of your your insights
with people, you know, I'm sure
Steven and I would be happy to
facilitate, to do some things of
that nature as well, because I
sure there's, you know, we
barely even scratch the surface.
There's so much to talk about
here with you that, you know,
I've got tons of questions
myself, but I'm also kind of
left here just a little shell
shocked.
Chris Bache: Well, when we
gather in Vancouver, then maybe
we can sit down and have some
conversations about where we
might take the future
conversation.
Stephen Gray: Excellent. Do you
have any projected publication
date for diamonds from heaven?
The the forthcoming book, it'll
Chris Bache: be out in the
second half of 2019 that's all
I've been able to get from the
publisher. So it's in the
process, so hopefully, within a
year from now, it'll be out.
Stephen Gray: All right, thank
you very much. And no, just, oh
no, just, thank you. It's, you
know, it's amazing, you know,
I'm really amazed at the work
you've done, and really grateful
actually, you know, I mean, it
was very difficult for you to go
through that process, as you've
made clear, and you know, you've
kind of done the work that not a
lot of people are going to do at
that level. So you've brought
back gems to share. And, you
know, it's, it's wonderful.
Thank
Chris Bache: you. It's been an
honor. It's a privilege. And.
I'm really looking forward to
meeting both of you in person,
likewise.
Marc Caron: Okay, well, until,
uh, until we see you in November
2. Okay, live your life.
Chris Bache: Awesome. Yep.
Blessings,
Stephen Gray: awesome. Good day.
All right, bye, bye, thanks
again, gentlemen. Until next,
bye, I'm stopping my camera.