Chris Bache: We are planet in
crisis. This is very clear.
Everyone knows the list of
challenges that we're facing,
expanding world population,
unchecked, industrial pollution,
escalating climate disruptions,
increasing drought with the
associated forest fires, warmer
oceans, with stronger
hurricanes, rising sea levels,
collapsing water tables, species
extinction, fished out oceans,
extreme economic inequality,
unprecedented refugee
migrations, unstable,
interlocked national economies,
cities and nations going
bankrupt, stockpiled weapons we
dare not use, and knowing no end
in sight, it's not an extreme
statement to say that We are
planet on fire, if you subtract
a few from this list or add a
few cumulatively, the list is
overwhelming. What I would like
to do today is share a
perspective on the world crisis
that we are entering and will
continue to deepen over the
years ahead, on the basis of the
perspectives that were given me,
or the teachings that I received
during my psychedelic
experiences that I report in
LSD, in the mind of the
universe. But first, let me give
a little bit of background just
to my work to set the stage for
what for the visions, the
sharing of the visions that I'm
going to draw from that work.
Let me move this over to the
side here.
Unknown: Okay, okay.
Chris Bache: So the work I'm the
visions I'm just sharing today
come from my work, diamonds from
heaven, or LSD in the mind of
the universe. Now my lineage, my
psychedelic limit lineage is
squarely in the tradition of
Stan Grof. It was his early
writing, his books published in
76 and 80 that were the
foundation of my work, which
determined the methodology that
I used in working with
psychedelics. As you know, those
of you who know Stan's work, his
work differentiates very clearly
between two different modes of
working with psychedelics, low
dose psycholytic therapy, which
is designed to uncover the
layers of the unconscious
slowly, gradually, with
therapeutic focus. And the
second method, a very different
method, psychedelic therapy,
working with high doses here,
the goal was less to heal than
to trigger a Near-Death
Experience that would give
terminal patients, terminal
cancer patients, an experience
of where they were going when
they died, to trigger a near
death episode experience, and
therefore to relieve death
anxiety. What I chose to do in
my work was to work with very
high doses. I saw that if this
could be done safely a few
times, it could be done safely
more than a few times. And what
I did, As Janet mentioned, was I
worked did 73 high dose LSD
sessions over 20 years, between
1979 and 1999 at the end of my
end of my journey, I realized
that I had gone places and had
experiences that were not
covered in the descriptions of
the early psychedelic therapy.
So I coined the term psychedelic
exploration to describe this
protocol. It's the protocol of
working therapeutically, meaning
in complete isolation with
eyeshades, headphones, a sitter,
carefully protected, totally
protected from the world,
isolated and then going very,
very deep. The difference
between psychedelic therapy and
psychedelic exploration is the
number of sessions, the high
number of sessions used. Now,
though the method was extreme,
500 to 600 micrograms is a very
high dose of LSD. And I do not
recommend this protocol.
Honestly, I don't today, there
were circumstances in my world
that allowed this work to be
very grounded. Through all these
20 years of work, I followed the
same protocol, the exact same
set and setting in all the work,
the same sitter, using the same
substance at the same dose
level, even in the same location
in Northeast Ohio, and using the
same recording process by
stabilizing all these variables,
I think it created a very, very
strong platform that allowed me
to generate particularly clear
access to the deep consciousness
of the universe. In this work,
entering into deeper and deeper
states of consciousness and.
Digesting it as carefully and as
thoroughly as I could. I kept
track of all my sessions, taking
careful note of their dates as I
went through I made a detailed
record of each session within 24
hours after the session was over
when you work in a sustained
fashion with this powerful,
psychedelic high doses of LSD,
you go through not one death and
rebirth, but you go through a
series of deaths and rebirths.
In this image, the drop below
the line represents our time
space, identity, our egoic
identity. And that first turning
of the circle represents the
process of ego death, the first
death and rebirth, the loss of
one's identity as a physical
human being, and one's first
entry into spiritual reality.
The subsequent circles represent
repetitions of the death and
rebirth process as one enters
deeper and deeper levels of the
vast expanse of spiritual
reality. I follow Stan in
adopting his vocabulary to
describe these states as the
psychic level of Transpersonal
experience, the subtle level and
the calls of love. I have no
vested interest in cosmology
that goes with this, but it's
simply the principle that
repeating the process of
surrender leads to deeper and
deeper encounters with well
leads to encounters with deeper
structures of existence. Now let
me give a different image for
this. LSD is sometimes likened
to a nuclear bomb of the psyche,
which was the nuclear bomb being
developed in the same decade
that LSD was developed, when you
do a sustained course of a very
intense psychotherapeutic
process, it sets in motion a
tremendous catalytic energy that
is sustained over a period of
years. So the sessions get
deeper and deeper and deeper in
a sustained fashion. And it's
not unlike a nuclear bomb in
this case, which reveals as the
explosion continues, deeper
levels of the atmosphere. These
levels of the atmosphere were
always there, but they had been
previously invisible, and now
the force of this nuclear
explosion brings them into our
visual awareness. Now this is
just an analogy, but something
like this also happens in
sustained psychedelic work. The
deeper you go, if you go in a
very sustained fashion, you
don't simply start over at the
beginning of every session, but
one session starts where the
subsequent session stopped, and
you go deeper and deeper, and
eventually enter discrete levels
of consciousness, which have
their own discrete rules. And
you acclimate to these levels of
consciousness and learn how to
become consciously aware at
these deep levels. But we're not
talking about, of course,
nuclear bombs. Here we're
talking about entering the mind
of the universe, entering the
great expanse of the
consciousness, which is the
consciousness? Well, how do we
describe this consciousness?
Some would describe it as God,
or the divine I would prefer, or
like to call it the mind of the
universe, the mind of the
cosmos. So in my personal
journey into this mind, into
this vast consciousness, which
holds all of existence, I went
through multiple layers,
experiencing deaths and rebirth
on this journey. So I would
differentiate five basic core
levels of reality that I was
working with in my sessions. The
first took place at the level of
my personal mind, once personal
unconscious. The second at the
level of the species mind, the
third at the level of archetypal
mind. The mind the fourth at the
level of causal oneness, and the
fifth at the level of what I
call the diamond Luminosity,
which is the source of the name
diamonds from heaven. So let me
very briefly just touch in on
the chapters of the book, to
correlate them with this model
at the level of personal mind,
there is a chapter called cross,
crossing the boundary of birth
and death. This is about what
Stan calls crossing the
perinatal level of
consciousness. We get into time
and space by being. Born, we
leave by dying. When
consciousness is expanding
beyond physical reality, one
enters a very complex domain
where one's experience of having
gotten here by birth and leaving
by death get intertwined in a
complex fashion. One goes
through horrendous existential
crises as one enters into a
process which culminates in ego
death and entry into spiritual
reality at the level of species
mind, there are actually three
chapters in the book pertaining
to this level of the work. The
first is the ocean of suffering.
The fifth is deep time in the
soul, and the sixth is
initiation into the universe.
Now I'm skipping some of the
chapters in the book. As you can
see, there's an introductory
methodology chapter, and there's
a chapter three where I give a
typical session day, but these
are the chapters having to do
with the content of the
visionary experiences. It opened
when I entered the ocean of
suffer suffering. I entered two
years of work in which I engaged
vast, vast stores of suffering.
I experienced myself to become
1000s of human beings spread
over 1000s of years experience
great rage and violence and
abuse on a collective scale.
Eventually, I came to the
conclusion that this work was
not about healing my personal
psyche or deepening my personal
ego death, that the intelligence
of the universe was using my
sessions to being to bring some
type of therapeutic release to
the collective unconscious of my
species, the collective
unconscious of my family. And I
go into this at great length in
the book deep time in the soul
was my first entry into what I
call deep time, which is a mode
of time which lies outside
linear time and space. It's not
eternity, it's not timelessness,
but it's a different modality of
temporal consciousness. In this
chapter, for a year and seven
sessions, I experienced my
complete life start to finish as
a simultaneous whole. It was
both ahead of me, yet to be
lived, and yet, from another
perspective, it already had been
lived, and I could see it in its
entirety, the experience of deep
time deepened in the next
chapter, initiation in the
universe, where the universe
took me far beyond my personal,
my personal concerns, and took
me into a series of instructions
and initiations into the
functioning of the universe. And
it's here that the story that
I'm going to be telling today
began in the middle of this
work. Entering archetypal the
level of archetypal mind is
described in the chapter the
greater real of archetypal
reality, entering into a domain
which was at the one hand, lies
beyond the species mind engaging
the archetypal forces which are
responsible for creating time
and space and for the emergence
of the forms that come forward
inside time and space, entering
into a level of causal oneness,
where the world ceases to
operate in parts, even the very
large parts of archetypal
reality. But the parts become
the reality, the parts, the
parts dissolve into the
universe, experienced as a
single organic whole, a single
consciousness, dissolving all
the boundaries between beings,
all the boundaries between
levels and one can experience
the universe, or I experience
the universe as a single,
living, pulsing, throbbing
singularity, a oneness that
underlies all differentiation.
The diamond Luminosity story is
told in chapter 10. It reflects
four years of work and 26
sessions during which I entered
the state of diamond Luminosity,
only four times the remaining
sessions during this four year
period were spent in very
intense cleansing as my system
worked to acclimate the
enormously powerful energies
that were present in these very,
very pure states of
consciousness, what I call the
diamond Luminosity, what
Buddhism calls Dharmakaya, the
clear light of absolute reality.
And after. That the final year
of visions, a final vision, four
sessions, one year of work. But
the missing chapter, here is a
chapter I want to talk about
today. It is the birth of the
future human. And this is a
story which completely surprised
me in my work, because when I
began this work. I thought this
work was about personal healing
or personal enlightenment or
some type of personal
transformation, and yet my work
seems to have been profoundly
connected to the work that our
species is doing in history, to
the collective purification
processes and the collective
transformational processes. So
in this chapter, the birth of
the future human, I summarize
the teachings that were given to
me over about a 15 year period.
It started in session 22 in the
initiation End of the Universe
material. It continued up
through the greater reel of
archetype of reality and the
benediction of blessings. It
actually also continued into the
final vision material. And
session 70 gave me one final
installment in the vision of
what is happening at our time in
history. So this is the material
I'd like to talk about today.
And just to give you a quick
preview of where we're going in
the birth of the future human
material, I discuss two
different bodies of visions. The
first I call the visions of
awakening, or a series of
visions that I received between
1991 and 1994 over about a dozen
sessions. I divided them into
six areas, six discrete
visionary themes. I'll come back
to that in a second. The second
installment is one particular
session that states from 1995
that I call the Great Awakening.
Now I'm about to turn off the
PowerPoint, but just to give you
a quick preview of the
categories where we're going,
the six themes of the visions of
awakening are divine, love, all
humanity, a guiding
intelligence, our species as A
single being, collective
purification and the future
human, the Great Awakening
chapter is a story of one day
when I was taken deep into the
future, and there experienced
the death and rebirth of
humanity. So that's where we're
going. Let me close this down.
All right inside. So come back
to here. Get me back to zoom.
I'm trying to get back to my
Zoom page.
Okay, let me stop. Ah, there we
go. Good. All right. Thank you
for your patience, everybody.
You
what I would like to do is share
these visions with you today,
and I'd like to take a chance do
something a little different. I
could talk about the visions, or
I could try to share the visions
in a deeper, more experientially
oriented way, and that's what
I'd like to try to do today. I'd
like to try to share these
visions in a way that would
invite you to hear them at a
deeper level than simply my
talking about them. What I
suggest that we do is a little
experiential exercise. I would
invite you to sit back and relax
and close your eyes while I read
a Condon, a condensed version of
these visions to share them with
you as I actually recorded them
myself. My sense is that the
spoken word has a initiatory
power that simply describing
about things or talking about
things don't have. And I'd like
to share these visions with you
in a more direct and
straightforward manner. So I'd
suggest to sort of detach from
your command. Computer screen.
There's nothing going to be
interesting here except me
reading some of these visions
for several minutes, and I
invite you to listen to them
with a deep heart, with a deep
receptivity. I'm not going to
put these visions in context, I
would just simply remind you
that there was a great price to
be paid for receiving these
visions, for where these were
taken. And when I say visions, I
don't mean things that I have
seen. When one learns at this
level, one learns by becoming so
you actually must become the
reality that you are seeing in
order to have deep knowledge of
it. And I know that these
visions will sound perhaps
extreme. They will sound exotic,
I would just remind you of the
context that these are visionary
statements that come out of
years and years of sustained
psychedelic work. So let's begin
first the divine love, the theme
of divine love, this was in the
early initiation in the universe
material. Now it was taken back
to the beginning of creation,
and there I experienced creation
as an act of supreme love. I was
overwhelmed by the most
extraordinary cosmic love coming
at me from every direction. It
was a love unlike anything I had
ever known before, and to awaken
to this love was to remember a
primordial decision that I had
somehow participated in. All of
us had voluntarily chosen to be
part of the evolutionary process
of creation. And creation was
motivated, was driven by a
cosmic love. I then experienced
all the suffering that humanity
had endured throughout history
as taking place inside this
love. I realized that all the
suffering inherent in evolution
was noble beyond words. It was
all part of a cosmic plan that
we had entered into freely,
however unconscious of this fact
we have become along the way,
the nobility of great suffering
voluntarily shouldered in the
name of divine love of suffering
that would stretch across
millions of years, suffering
that would become so inscrutable
that it would be used as
evidence that the universe was
devoid of compassion. This was
the nobility of humanity's gift
to the creative intelligence of
our universe. This was an
important vision because it set
the context for all the visions
that followed. And what it says
is, no matter what is coming
forward in history, no matter
how hard the times are that we
are entering, it is all taking
place in the context of the
Divine Love that inspired
creation, and our love to
participate, and our free choice
to participate in creation in
response to this divine love,
The second vision all of
humanity out of the seething
desires of history, out of all
the violent conflicts and the
schemings of individuals and
nations, there was now driving
forward a new awareness in human
consciousness. Its birth in us
is no less difficult or violent
than the birth of a new
continent. It drives upward from
the floor of our being,
requiring a transposition of
everything that has gone before
to make room for its new
organizational patterns. The
great difficulty I have is
describing the enormity of what
is being birthed. The true focus
of this creative process is not
individuals, but all humanity.
It is actually trying to awaken
the entire species. What is
emerging is a consciousness of
unprecedented proportions. The
entire human family, integrated
in a unified field of awareness,
the species reconnected with its
fundamental nature. Our thoughts
tuned to Source consciousness,
the scale of what I was
witnessing the. Took my breath
away. This was a jarring
expansion of my horizon, because
coming out of the religious
traditions and spiritual
learnings that I had
internalized, which really
focused on the transformation
awakening of an individual, of
all individuals, this showed me
that underneath that there was a
deeper process taking place, and
that the creative intelligence
of the universe was working to
awaken the entire species. The
third vision guiding
intelligence you
I saw humanity climbing out of a
steep valley, and just ahead on
the other side of the mountain
was a brilliant, sun drenched
world that was about to break
over us. The time frame was
enormous, after millions of
years of struggle and ascent, we
were poised on the brink of a
sunrise that would forever
change the conditions of life on
this planet. All current
structures would quickly become
irrelevant. All truths would
quickly be rendered. Passe truly
a new epic was dawning. The
lives of everyone living in this
pivotal time in history were
helping to bring this global
shift about. As I witnessed this
scene, I saw that though we did
not know the deep future at a
personal level, there was a more
encompassing level of
consciousness that could see it
very clearly. This was a deeply
moving and clarifying experience
for me, individually, we humans,
could not see what was coming,
and so did not understand why
things are the way they are, yet
isolated from the future the
present makes absolutely no
sense to be ignorant of what is
being built would be to be
functionally blind. And our
species is not blind. There is
an intelligence within it,
guiding it an intelligence that
knows the future and is
preparing us for it as
systematically as we prepare our
homes for the change of seasons,
the fourth vision our species as
a single being that was taken
deeper into the unified field of
existence and experienced the
dynamics of humanity's awakening
as movements being initiated and
orchestrated by a single
integrating intelligence. I
experienced the evolution of our
species as the systematic growth
of a single organism, a unified
being that all of us are part of
the subtlety of the cooperation
of the parts with the whole was
extraordinary to experience the
incredible diversity of our
species as a single unified
field made many events clearer.
New patterns sprang into view,
and the patterns made
transparent sense. Nothing in
our theological or philosophical
systems does justice to these
facts. What I then saw was that
the unified field of humanity
was moving decisively and
precipitously to become more
aware of itself, whereas
previously it had existed as an
extended fabric, largely
unconscious of itself. Now it
was waking itself up visually.
This took the form of energy
coming together in Swift,
contractive spasms that created
bright flashes of awareness. I
repeatedly saw extended webs of
energy suddenly contract and
explode in brilliant flashes. In
the past, these flashes had been
swallowed by the inertia of the
collective psyche and had not
endured now, however, the
flashes were beginning to hold
their own and to connect with
other flashes occurring around
the planet. And as I trace the
Black Lives Matter movement, I
think of this vision. I think of
the contraction and the
explosion of light which is
throwing light on these dark
shadows. And. Our culture,
the fifth vision, collective
purification. When an organism
is called on from within to
become more conscious, it must
first cleanse itself of the
psychological by products of
living at its lower level of
awareness, it must bring forward
the residue of its past and
purge that residue from its
system in order to lay the
foundation for a more refined
level of operation. Our species
was doing this in a wholesale
manner and with great
determination, by crystallizing
within itself generations that
embody our toxic legacy. It was
the coordinated exercise of the
self evolution of the species as
a whole, the poisons of
humanity's past were being
brought to the surface in us,
and by transforming these
poisons in our individual lives,
we were making it possible for
divine awareness to Enter more
deeply into future generations.
We had volunteered for this role
for both our personal good and
the collective good. I saw that
this century formed a watershed
into which the karmic streams of
history were flowing, and that
this, as this process came to
fruition, the future condition
of our species would be beyond
anything we might project from
our current state of
fragmentation. The present form
of humanity is transitional. We
are cells in a super organism
intent on rapid change our very
constitution, the form of our
species, is a stage in a longer
evolutionary journey. And
finally, the sixth vision, the
vision of the future human at
one point, I was given a brief
experience of the future, human
we are becoming. I was carried
deep into the distant future and
allowed to experience what will
be the abiding state of humanity
at that time, what a magnificent
being. Just touching it filled
me with rapture, calm and sheer
delight. It felt clear, warm and
whole. There was an abiding
sense of oneness that went
deeper than just the feeling of
being interconnected. It was a
feeling of being truly one
underneath the diversity of
life, such expansiveness, such
breadth of being. It was fully
embodied spiritual realization,
the tantric awakening of our
entire species, spirit and
matter in perfect balance. This
penetrating glimpse transfixed
me. Its beauty, grandeur and
simplicity pierced my heart.
So for these four years, in the
background of these many
sessions, these messages kept
coming forward, kept presenting
themselves, kept filling in the
blanks in the background helped
me understand what was taking
place in history at the deeper
level that we were on the cusp
of this profound spiritual
awakening that we were had
entered into this voluntarily,
and that everything that was
happening to us was all part of
a larger cosmic plan, which was
all part of The love that the
creative intelligence would
share with us in the act of
creation itself. The net result
of these experiences, though,
they gave me a sense of what was
happening. They helped me
understand why things were
unfolding the way they were. It
helped me understand why the
ocean of suffering what was
taking place in these collective
purification processes? It
focused me on the question, how,
how can the entire species be
awakened? What will it actually
take for humanity to make this
quantum jump in its awareness,
the visions? Of awakening showed
me that this was the project of
history, but nowhere did it give
me any idea how nature, how the
creative intelligence of the
universe, was actually going to
pull this off. Meanwhile, my
psychedelic journey continued. I
had been going through the
benediction of blessings. I
entered into the diamond
Luminosity work. I had entered
into the diamond Luminosity
twice, with two more to come
down the road. About once a
year, I was entering into the
ecstatic bliss of the diamond
Luminosity. And then right in
the middle of that sequence,
when I was expecting to be taken
again into the diamond
Luminosity, instead, I was taken
into the death and rebirth of
the human species. I would
emphasize that this experience
completely introduced new
categories for me, because there
was absolutely nothing personal
about the state I was in, not
even the residual personal of
individual, ecstatic awakening.
Instead, there was a wholeness
about it that was species wide,
its movement was the movement of
my species, as often happens in
these sessions, the experience
preceded understanding, and I
simply began to experience new
things, and only slowly did I
get my bearings on what I was
experiencing. So this is the
Great Awakening session that
took place in 1995 after a long
personal cleansing process and a
long introduction, I dissolved
into the species mind
completely, and there had the
following experiences the core
scenario,
and they feel the relative calm,
a small anxiety began to grow.
Slowly, people were looking up
and becoming alarmed. Humanity
was waking up in alarm to events
that had overtaken it.
Conditions got worse and worse.
People became more and more
frightened as the danger
increased, forcing them to let
go of their assumptions. At
deeper levels, there was less
and less for people to hold on
to, fewer Givens that they could
assume, how they would live,
where they would live, what they
would do for a living, how
society was organized, what
could be possessed the world as
they knew it was falling apart.
Decades were compressed into
minutes, and I felt the people's
fear deepen as they lost more
and more of what they considered
the normal and necessary
structures of their world. Step
by step, events were forcing a
rapid reassessment of everything
in their lives. The events that
had overtaken earth were of such
scope that no one could insulate
themselves from them. The level
of alarm grew in the species
field, until eventually everyone
was forced into the melting pot
of mere survival. We were all in
this together. Families were
torn apart, parents from their
children, children from each
other. Life as we had known it
was shattered at the core. We
were reduced to simply trying to
survive. For a time, it looked
as though we would all be
killed, but just when the storm
was at its peak, the worst of it
passed, and the danger slowly
subsided. Though many had died,
many were still alive as the
survivors began to find each
other, new social units began to
form, parents and children from
different families joined to
form new types of families
everywhere, new social
institutions sprang into being
that reflected our new reality,
new ways of thinking, new values
that we had discovered within
ourselves during the crisis.
Every aspect of life was marked
by new priorities, new
perceptions of the good, new
truths and. These new social
forms reflected new states of
awareness that seemed to spread
throughout humanity like a
positive contagion. These notion
new social forms then fed back
into the system to elicit still
newer states of awareness in the
people and the cycle of
creativity between the
individual and the group
spiraled. The whole system was
becoming alive at new levels,
and this aliveness was
expressing itself in previously
impossible ways. It was as if
the Eco crisis had triggered the
myelinization of nerve cells in
our species brain, allowing new
and deeper levels of self
awareness to spring into being.
And repeatedly, there was the
message, these things will
happen faster than anyone could
anticipate because of the hyper
arousal of the species mind,
1000s of fractal images drove
this lesson home again and again
faster than anyone can
anticipate. The pace of the past
was irrelevant to the pace of
the future. I
Yes, there were other components
that were shown me over the
course of my long journey. A lot
of sessions were spent exploring
the dynamics of reincarnation
and showing me what I came to
call the birth of the diamond
soul that all of our former
lives eventually come together
and fuse into a singularity, and
in their that fusion, there is a
release, an explosion of this
diamond light inside us and
opening us to A completely
expanded sense of identity ego
yields to Soul, the small world
of the present body mind, yields
to the much, much larger world
of the soul that travels in and
out of time effortlessly. So to
summarize, the core vision that
came from my sessions that help
me personally understand what's
happening in history now under
our feet that humanity is coming
into a time of profound
transformation, a shift in the
collective unconscious of our
species, a shift in the
archetypal blueprint of humanity
and a profound awakening into
oneness. But for there to be
this great awakening, there must
first take place a great death.
We must be empty to the old
before the new can emerge. We
must surrender our smallness. We
must surrender the ego's
constant self, cherishing with
all the divisions that it brings
between races, religions,
classes, nations and even
species, I believe that we are
entering the dark night of our
collective soul. All mystics go
through the dark night before
awakening into the bliss of
oneness. They go through the
dark night, which is a time of
intense purification. And now I
think humanity as a whole is
entering the dark night of its
collective soul. It is a time of
emptying, a time of intense
anguish, of loss of control and
breakdown, a global purification
unto death that will last
generations. But through this
hard labor, we will give birth
to something truly
extraordinary, more than just a
new civilization. What is
emerging is something is nothing
less than a new order of human
beings. Through the global
systems crisis, our planet is
giving birth to the future
human, a higher form of
humanity, the diamond soul, is
being born in history, and we
are all part of its birth. I
believe that each one of us,
before we incarnated knew what
we were getting into, and we
consciously chose to incarnate
at this time in history and in
the places where we are in order
to contribute to to participate
and contribute to the spiritual
awakening of humanity. Thank you
very much. And I think we have a
few minutes, if we can, to
handle some questions. Yes, so I
turn this back over to Jason and
Jeanette.
Unknown: Hi, gosh, I'm all
choked up. Chris, that was
beautiful. Thank you, right.
Let's have a look at the
question. There's one question
here from Katie Carr. Katie, do
you want to ask that question
yourself. Jason, can we unmute
Katie? Or can I unmute Katie?
Jeannet Weurman: There she is.
I'm here. Thank you so much.
It's actually two questions.
I'll read them out. First, I'm
intrigued in what you said,
massive appreciation, but about
the centrality of the human
species in these visions. And it
seems kind of anthropocentric,
given that we invented the
concept of species anyway. And
I'm wondering about like, the
place of non human life in this
expanded consciousness? Yes, and
Chris Bache: this first one, and
then you can ask the second one,
how about that? Because this is
a really important question. I
have friends who have spent a
great deal of time at the
interface of the human species
and animal species, and actually
immersing themselves into
various animal species with
various insights. And my work
has not been like that. My work
has been really focused on the
human species. And I don't know
why, except for one particular
thing, I think the human species
is the most dangerous species on
the planet right now, it is our
the imbalances of the human
psyche which are placing the
lives and well being of the
other species in peril. If we
can heal and make right, make
whole the human species, then
the other species will be saved
and they will be safe on our
planet. My best understanding is
that my work is really focused
on the human species, not that
it denies the importance of the
other species, but that it's
trying to basically get at the
problem where it lives. And
right now, the problem where it
lives is inside the human heart
and our insensitivity to the
larger, deeper rhythms of life
that we share with all the other
life forms on our planet.
Jeannet Weurman: Yeah, I hear
that it's like the biggest
potential for purification is
right here with us.
Chris Bache: The essential, if
the human species can be fixed,
so to speak, can be wakened up,
everyone will be safe on the
planet. If we're not saved, if
we don't save ourselves and wake
ourselves up, then all life
forms will continue to be in
danger. Beautiful.
Jeannet Weurman: Thank you. The
second question was, after this
incredible gift of realization,
it's a big question, what have
you been doing with your life
for the last 20 years?
Chris Bache: Good question.
Well, I spent 20 years really
thinking about these sessions
and trying to understand them.
It takes a long time to
integrate experiences this deep.
It turned out to be, much to my
surprise, coming down the
mountain of these visions was
almost as difficult as going up
the mountain. And the last
chapter of the book is a chapter
called coming off the mountain,
where I describe some of the
challenges I face, coming away
from the visionary state,
entering back into the fully
grounded condition. So what I've
been doing is I continue to
teach. I mean, I taught for a
number of years, and I really
couldn't talk about my
psychedelic practice openly
until I had retired from the
university, because I love
teaching, and if I talked about
let people know what I was
doing, it would have terminated
my academic career. I continue
to take care of my children, to
shepherd them as best as one can
into their adult lives. I have
tried to deepen my spiritual
practice. I've always been a
meditator, always done some form
of spiritual practice, which I
think is really important if
you're going to enter into what
I would call the path of
temporary immersion, which is
working with psychedelics, it's
really important to have a
stable practice, spiritual
practice, a daily practice that
takes care of your body and your
mind and helps you integrate
these extreme swings of energy
and these extreme ideas that
pour into us during a
psychedelic session. So I
basically it. So I've been
digesting my work. I've been
finishing out my life process.
In the middle part of my life, I
retired from the university. I
did a little more teaching, but
basically I wrapped all that up
by about 2015 it took me five
years to write this book, even
though I had all the sessions
beforehand. It took me five
years first. It took me a long
time just to get myself in the
psychological space where I
would be willing to share these
experiences, because they are so
personal. I mean, they're so
deep, they are so intimate, they
are about my relationship with
the divine. And it took me a
long time just before I was
willing to let anyone have
access to such deep places
within my own life history. But
spirit kept telling me, No, you
don't have the luxury of being
private right now. It's all oars
in the water. Things are
speeding up. People will be able
to use your work in order to
strengthen and support their own
life's journey, as we go into
this time in history. And so it
turned right after I'd finished
my sessions, Spirit said to me
in my meditation, 20 years in,
20 years out, which meant that
it would take 20 years for me to
digest all the gifts that I had
been given in that 20 year
journey. And it just so happens
that diamonds from Heaven was
published 20 years after I
stopped my last journey.
Jeannet Weurman: Thank you. I'm
really, really grateful that you
started so young, and have
shared with us. Thanks so much.
Chris Bache: Thank you. Katie,
yes, I did start young. I did
this work when I was 30 to 50,
and I'm now 71
Unknown: thank you. Okay, is it
okay to move to the next
question. So this Jamie Mills,
can we, can we unmute Jamie
Mills, and thank you, Katie, for
your question. It was both
questions, very good questions.
Can we unmute Jamie? I have done
Jamie,
hi Chris, thank you for your
heartfelt sharing.
Chris Bache: Thank you. Nice to
meet you.
Unknown: As someone with
children, I'm and trying to hold
this aspect in awareness I often
struggle with a normalcy of
life, as well as with some
awareness of what is to come.
And as part of that, I suppose
there's the question of, Do you
anticipate seeing more? Seeing
these changes in your lifetime.
Chris Bache: You know, I want to
emphasize that in my visionary
work, I was never given any
particulars of how, when you
know, you know how it was going
to manifest. It's it appeared to
be a global crisis that was
triggered by a global climate
change crisis. It seems to be,
seem to be ecologically driven,
that impacted the political
process, the economic process,
our social process, but in terms
of when, how, specifically, no
content whatsoever. I was shown
that it was happening, that it
would be happening. I was shown
some of the collect, some of the
mechanisms of the process, and
specifically how the role that
the collective psyche would play
in catalyzing this change
underneath our feet as quickly
as is needed for us to survive
our foolishness. I have
children, like many of us here,
and I've been surprised,
frankly, with covid 19, how
quickly we have escalated into a
sense of global crisis, how
quickly we've had the rug pulled
out from under many of our feet
we've been had to rearrange our
lives dramatically. To me, the
pandemic feels to be like an
overture to a symphony. It
starts the process. It touches
some of the themes of the
process that we're getting into.
But it is not itself the key
crisis. It is the beginnings of
a series of punctu. Weighted
crises that will move and deepen
in the years ahead. And we're
not powerless. In fact, how we
respond in the next 10 years
will be very important with how
deep this crisis will be and
will be generated. I think we're
beyond the point of being able
to stop it, but we're not the
to influence it. During my
lifetime, I expect that I am
watching it begin, but I don't
think I'll be watching it
finish. I think that work is
going to fall to my our children
and to our children's children.
I suspect this will last
generations, because we're
talking about the pivoting of an
entire planet, and this will
take time. One of the authors
who has really laid out the
escalating scale of the crises
that we're facing is Dwayne
Elgin, whose latest book. He's
been an elder thinking through
these issues for decades in his
life, and he's just published
his last book, and it's called
choosing earth, and He lays out
the next five decades, decade by
decade, how these crises are
likely to be compounding
themselves, and it's all data
driven. It's not visionary
driven. He really does his
homework thoroughly. He's been
monitoring all the international
forecast, crunches the numbers
and gives us a sense of what's
likely to be happening in the
decades ahead. And the whole
last part of the book is, what
can we do? What can an
individual do? We don't have to
simply sit, take this lying
down. In fact, we don't want to
simply take it lying down. We
need to get up and mobilize, and
mobilizing at two different
levels, inwardly, doing our
spiritual homework, confronting
the shadow that we have carried
into this time in history and
outwardly supporting the process
of healing the collective psyche
and confronting the shadow that
it has brought into this time in
history. So there's plenty of
work to be done. Thank you.
Unknown: Thank you, Chris. We've
got a couple of minutes, if my
clock is right until quarter
past. Do you want to take one
more question? Chris? Or shall
we?
Chris Bache: Yeah, one more is
fine.
Unknown: So the next question is
Claudius Schwartz plot, I hope
I'm pronouncing that correctly.
And thank you, Jamie, for your
question. Uh, can we unmute?
Claudia, Hi, Claudia, Hi, Chris.
We met about one and a half
years ago at the conference in
Philadelphia. Yeah, I really
enjoyed talking to you, and
later I read your book. And
yeah, I'm really fascinated with
your work. So my question is,
from a Christian perspective,
I'm wondering whether the vision
of the future human could refer
to something like heaven,
because what you described
sounds a lot like the Christian
descriptions of heaven, but of
course, how you are describing
it, it's still on Earth? Yes. So
I'm wondering whether there's a
way we could integrate your
insights with the Christian
teachings, and whether
Christianity has ever played a
role for your explorations.
Chris Bache: Certainly
Christianity did play a role in
my exploration. I was raised in
the Deep South. I was raised in
Mississippi, and I was raised
Catholic, and I got a good shake
from the Catholic Church. I
really, I have no complaints
about my experience being raised
Catholic, and in fact, my first
vocation in life was to actually
be a Catholic priest. I was in
the seminary for three years in
high school, even then one year
in college, and I left that
behind in order to choose a
different course, a course with
children, a course with
marriage. My life has been
deeply influenced by all the
spiritual traditions of the
world. I've taught world
religions for years. I consider
all of them dear friends, but
the two which have influenced me
most deeply has been
Christianity and Buddhism. Those
are the ones that I've drawn
most inspiration from. I think
you're absolutely right. I think
what we're looking at is heaven
on earth. That is the vision of
moving forward, that this is an
embodiment of heavenly states of
consciousness in our physical
existence. Now, stepping back
very quickly, I know we don't
have much time, so very quickly,
all the religions of the last
5000 years have all been what I
would call up and out cosmology.
The idea is that you achieve a
state of salvation, our
spiritual awakening, and once
you. Achieve that state you
leave. The Hindu word for
enlightenment was moksha,
escape, escaping time and space.
I think all of these cosmology
has got half of the message, but
lost half of the message. Hadn't
gotten the second half of the
message yet, and therefore they
represent incomplete visions of
history, because it leaves
unanswered the question, what is
the purpose of time and space?
What is the purpose of this
magnificent universe? It's been
called a veil of suffering. It's
been called a place where we
just want to get out of it as
quickly as we can. We want to
get back into the bliss of
divine existence. And I
understand that in the period of
history that it covered when we
began to actually have
experiential access to the deep,
deep divine truths, naturally,
we would feel drawn to being
there. And then we could not
realize these truths here, we
would want to be there. But I
think the deeper truths are
really coming into our awareness
today, the more we understand
the extreme age and how much
intelligence and how much effort
has been invested in unfolding
this universe for 13 point 8
billion years, and will continue
to be unfolding for billions and
billions and billions of years
more, the more we begin to
understand a different vision
for humanity. And that is not
that our goal is to awaken and
leave but our goal is to awaken
and incarnate Divine
Consciousness here in our body
on this planet, and in this
process, cooperate with taking
creation into a new
developmental level, truly
heaven on earth, truly, fully
awaken spiritual Consciousness
in our physical bodies, our
egoic consciousness, our present
Mind, Body Consciousness,
exploded into the larger
consciousness of the soul,
another Christian theme, but a
soul textured with all of its
former life history, a
tremendous expansion of the
human heart, because we have so
many Relationships with so many
people over so many centuries,
and also an expansion of the
human mind as we open more
easily and more naturally into
the divine consciousness that
nurtures all I think it's very
it's very compatible with
Christian vision, once We
understand and make a couple of
small adjustments. Thank you.
Unknown: Thank you, Chris, do.