Joe Moore: Joe Moore, hello
everybody. Welcome back to
psychedelics today. This is Joe
Moore coming at you from
Breckenridge, Colorado. On this
episode, Kyle and I talked to Dr
Chris Bache, who is a very
interesting character, he went
through over the course of a
number of years, 73 high dose
LSD sessions, and had some very
interesting things to report
back and personal growth and
much more. We get into it in the
episode in quite a bit of
detail, and the name of the book
is LSD and the mind of the
universe. We are giving away
three copies. And you can find
that in the show notes, we'll
have a link to the contest
there. And also in our social
media, you can find a link to
our contests and giveaways.
Typically, you can also find it
just at psychedelics
today.com/welcome, and it was a
really mind blowing episode for
me. We don't really need to
spoil anything, but Dr Chris
Bache has some extra ordinary
things to share, and as a
recently retired University
professor, comes with quite a
bit of perspective and education
on topics that I think we should
all be aware of if we're if
we're going to get into the
Transpersonal so I think that's
it for right now. So enjoy this
episode. This show is brought to
you by on it, o, n, n, i t.com,
use the code side today. P, S,
Y, today at checkout for 10% off
everything but fitness
equipment. I've, I've tried a
bunch of their products. I
really do like their Alpha Brain
product, which is kind of like a
nootropic, like a cognitive
enhancer, and it's, it's gotten
me out of some really tough
situations that I've been in in
the past, you know, business
meetings and whatnot. It's just
really helpful. And if you're
working on a problem,
cognitively difficult problem,
alpha brain might be there to
help you, along with some
coffee. Also got some good
stuff, like new mood helps
balance your neurotransmitters a
bit, supplements where you might
be missing some things in your
nutrition, and a lot of people
just love it. I've used it a
bunch. I've actually used it as
a supplement to help me come
back from a long party weekend,
and it's been great. I've also
got some melatonin spray on
there, so if you're having
trouble sleeping, melatonin can
really help. They've also got
all sorts of like fish oil and
supplements that you can check
out nutrition as well, like
coffee and various drinks,
shirts and other merch. So
again, on it, on
it.com/actually, that's just it,
on it.com, and the code side
today, Psy today, for 10% off
your order. We are also brought
to you by Audible, Audible
trial.com/psychedelics, today,
or again, psychedelics
today.com/welcome, and you can
find your audible free trial
link, 30 day free trial and a
free audio book if you sign up
using our link, and it helps us
quite a bit. There's some great
books up there, from Tim Leary
books to Terence McKenna and
more, even the recent Mike J
book on Mescaline is up there,
and it is extraordinary. So
check that out and let us know
what you think. I I think if
you're into podcasts, you will
also like audio books. So check
it out. You owe it to your brain
to give it some books. Once in a
while, books are where people
can really flesh out an idea in
full, and it's, uh, it's good
for your cognitive diet. Also,
we have a course coming up
called navigating psychedelics
for clinicians and therapists.
This course is designed to help
you understand this coming
landscape of psychedelic drugs
to clinical practice. There is a
huge variety of interventions
coming up for different, you
know, indications, and it's
going to be a really big deal in
medicine. I would say it's
already a big deal in medicine.
So if you want to understand
micro dosing, macro dosing,
psychedelic, psychedelic therapy
at you know, the basic level,
this is only an eight week
course. We can't teach you
everything. More than you know,
it'd probably take five years to
really, really get you to a
black belt grade. But this is
where you should start. If
you're a clinician or therapist.
We've moved it from a five week
to an eight week course, because
five weeks just really wasn't
enough. We've got some really
great master classes there from
different experts in the field,
names like Dr Catherine McLean,
Ashley booth from the AWARE
project, Mitch Gomez from Dance
safe. Is Shannon Claire Carlin,
who helps run the MDMA therapy
training program at maps. Ingmar
Gorman, Jessica Katzman, Sai T
who does ketamine assisted
psychotherapy. We've got all
sorts of great stuff up here.
Raquel Bennett, who runs the
crea Institute and the crea
conference, really big into
ketamine as well, and more. So
check it out, psychedelics
today.com or psychedelic
education center.com you can
learn more about our navigating
psychedelics for clinicians and
therapists. Classes start in
February. We have course times
that are friendly for a European
audience and a American, North
American audience too. So right
around 7pm Eastern and 7pm
London time, I believe, but the
time specifics are on the
website. So I hope you join us,
or at least, you know, come to
our website to learn more, or
tell your friends. We would
really like some referrals. And
there's some great testimonials
up on the page too, if you want
to check it out. And of course,
also comes with a, I think, a 30
day money back guarantee. I'll
probably put that up on the
website soon, but yeah, so you
know, no real risk. If you jump
in, it's okay if it, if you find
out it's not for you. But if
you're a clinician with an
interest in this field, we think
this is for you. Also, if you
like our show and you have
friends that might be interested
in this topic, probably the most
flattering thing you can do to
to us. If you want to see me
blush, tell your friends about
psychedelics today. Maybe send
them a link to a couple
episodes, or invite them to the
Facebook group. We're up to
about 3000 people on there now,
and that would be amazing. And
if you want to support us with a
small monthly donation, you can
do that to
patreon.com/psychedelics today.
Donation. Donations as small as
$2 a month help quite a bit. So
thank you all for tuning in to
psychedelics today. I hope you
enjoy this interview with Dr
Chris Bache, and we'll see you
on the other side. Hello
everybody. Welcome back to
psychedelics today. Today on the
show, we have Chris Bache,
retired professor and Professor
Emeritus at Youngstown State
University and author of the
recent book LSD and the mind of
the universe. We're also going
to be doing a giveaway. So stay
tuned on that. Chris, thanks for
joining us.
Unknown: Glad to be here, guys.
So
Joe Moore: I, I had been talking
about you, I think even a couple
years ago, when I found out
about your, your kind of long
term project before probably the
book was even with a publisher,
and I, and I was really excited
by the idea, and then I just
totally forgot, and then all of
a sudden, we got connected, I
think, through the publisher.
And now I'm very excited to
record with you, because this is
quite the project you've
undertaken, and you've got some
very unique insights to share.
How do you how do you like to
start this story, like, how did
maybe, maybe we can start with
psychedelics? How did
psychedelics come on your radar
initially?
Chris Bache: Well, I just
finished graduate school. I was
publishing a few articles out of
my dissertation. I was looking
for where to take my research. I
was a brand spanking new
university professor, and I met
the work of Stani Grof, and
that's what really snapped my
head to attention. I did not
have a psychedelic history. I
was I finished graduate school
in religious studies as a pretty
deeply convinced atheistically
inclined agnostic, but I read
Stan's work, and the light bulb
went off inside of me, and I
said, this is important, not
just to psychology, but it's
important to philosophy of
religion, which was my training.
And I wanted to get involved. I
wanted to do it, but, of course,
it had been made illegal, so I
split my life in my ordinary day
job. I continued to function as
the professor of Religious
Studies in the Department,
taught conventional kind of
courses, or semi conventional
courses. And I began a 20 year
what became eventually a 20 year
journey, working with LSD,
following Stanislaus paradigm,
and then pushing the limits of
that paradigm pretty far, much
farther than I appreciated at
the time. And I was trained in
philosophy of religion, so I
kept careful records, careful
notes, tried to make the
engagement as clean and as
productive as possible. And I
knew there would come a time,
sooner or later, when I would
share the experiences or share
the insights from the
experiences with a broader
audience. And after I retired
from the university, that time
finally came, perfect.
Joe Moore: And what was the
first Did you have any kind of
previous spontaneous. Mystical
experiences or anything before
that, that kind of clue you into
how important these things might
be.
Chris Bache: I've always been
envious of people who have had,
you know, I was 12 years old
when I had my first spontaneous
mystical experience. That's not
the way it's been for me. I've
always been kind of deeply
locked into my body and my
physical experience. You know, I
I was reasonably well educated
in Western religious thought. I
became educated in Eastern
religious thought, in a broad
spectrum of contemporary
thought. But no, I had no
background. In many ways, I'm
the last person you would have
expected to write a book on deep
psychedelic states of
consciousness. Just, I mean, I
grew up in Mississippi. I got a
degree in theology from the
University of Notre Dame before
going on to graduate school, so
it wasn't part of my background
at all.
Unknown: I'm curious, how did
you stumble across Stan's work?
By not having any exposure to
psychedelics beforehand.
Chris Bache: Well, I was reading
widely in different areas. I was
reading in kind of emerging
Transpersonal psychology. It
interested me two people whose
work I met my first year out.
One was Ian Stevenson, whose
work at the University of
Virginia convinced me that
reincarnation is a simple fact
of life. And that was a jolt,
because it hadn't been part of
my education anywhere. And then
I met Stan's work, and he had
just published two years before,
realms of the human unconscious,
and that was a book that really
did it for me. And so Ian gave
me kind of empirical evidence
that there had to be another
dimension of reality, other than
the physical world. Because
there, if there is any time
interval between the death of
one personality and the birth of
the second personality, there
has to be a place for them to
exist during that time. And Stan
gave me the methodology that
allowed me to the prospect of
exploring that reality. So I
just decided to go for it.
Joe Moore: It's awesome. So
maybe next like what? What did
the protocol look like to you?
Like it to me, it looks like a
very clearly looks like the work
being done at Hopkins and by
maps now. But was, was it any
different in your perspective at
this point?
Chris Bache: No, I think it's
pretty much conventional in that
respect, you're always working
in complete isolation. You're
always working with the sitter,
you're always working with a
very carefully curated playlist
of music. The difference is,
after I did three medium dose
LSD sessions and then shifted to
working with very high levels of
LSD. So I worked at 500 to 600
micrograms. At first, I did it
simply for efficiency, because
it was hard to get time in a
dual career marriage for, you
know, arranging a session day,
and I wanted to make the most
out of every day. I also thought
it would get me to my early goal
of enlightenment faster, if I
could kind of do my karma in
bigger bites that eventually is
a project that just dissolved
along the way, and the whole
concept of a personal spiritual
journey, or strictly personal
evolutionary project that fell
out along The way. So the
difference, I think, is the
quantity. The first the
psychedelic used very different
than Psilocybin or MDMA, working
with very high doses, which
changed the whole trajectory of
the experience. And then I
basically began to curate a much
more aggressive playlist with
the music. I used a lot more
indigenous music. I didn't use
classical western music. I used
a much more aggressive approach
in music itself, but otherwise,
very much like contemporary
therapeutic approaches to
psychedelics.
Kyle Buller: Yeah, huh, that's
interesting. I guess back track
a little bit too. So your book
really kind of covers these,
what was it? 73 high dose
sessions. So like, your book is
covering all these insights of
your experiences and some of
your philosophical work, and
really understanding
consciousness from these
experiences. So I don't know if
I forget if we gave a little
show there, so that's just to
give some context of what we're
talking about, and what Joe
meant about protocol, of how
you're setting that up. And I'm
curious why did the music change
over time?
Chris Bache: I happened upon
some indigenous chanting music,
and I threw it into my session
on the next day or the next
week, and it had such a profound
impact on the intensity of the
session, it basically rattled my
cage much more aggressively than
some of the more even aggressive
classical music I like, the
effect I recognize. I said it's
more disorienting, more giving
me stronger support for going
deeper into consciousness, so I
just began to cultivate and
collect that type of music.
Kyle Buller: Yeah, that's really
interesting. And from your
perspective, how important is
music when you're doing high
dose psychedelics or just
psychedelic kind of therapy and
that self discovery format,
Chris Bache: I think it's very
important. Now, I've done
sessions without music,
eventually, after long down the
road, and I've done Psilocybin
sessions with and without music,
but in working with a very
strong psychedelic like LSD, and
working at these very high
doses, which, by the way, I
don't recommend, I truly do not
recommend that people do what I
did. I wouldn't do it the same
way if I did it today. But
basically, when you're working
with opening consciousness that
radically music has a
tremendously powerful effect, I
would maybe estimate it has
concentrating, amplifying effect
by five or 10 times, doing it
without psychedelic but without
music. So I remember I started
using music only in the fourth
session, and the jump that
happened in that fourth session
was just enormous. So I think
it's very important.
Kyle Buller: Yeah, it's a topic
that keeps coming up, I guess,
within the psychedelic
community, especially when
talking about putting playlists
together for therapy. And I just
recently recorded an episode
with a fellow who composes music
and ended up taking his
experiences and making music out
of it. So, yeah, I think the
music piece is just really
interesting. It's a huge part of
Breathwork as well.
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah, and
Helen Bonnie, of course, are
early work plotting the various
stages of an LSD journey and the
characteristics of music that
support each of those stages as
we go important work. Yeah. So
where
Kyle Buller: did this idea come
from of wanting to engage in
this, these high dose sessions?
Like, did you start off saying,
I'm going to do, you know, X
amount of sessions and really
dive in? Or did you go in
saying, I'll have a few and then
see where it goes? Or did you
have this idea kind of mapped
out of doing X amount of
sessions, or had a goal with it
at all?
No, I did not have any
trajectory or any goal. I saw
the range of experiences that
Stan described in realms of the
human unconscious. I saw since I
had a pretty good grounding in
western philosophical thought
and theological thought, I had a
good sense of the significance
of these states of consciousness
that he was describing. And I
believe that the people who
would be making the most
important contributions in my
discipline would be speaking out
of an experiential basis in a
matter of years, not out of a
theory, simply a theoretical
basis. This was common in my
time. So I just, I knew that to
do that, you just had to get in
and do your work. And I had no
idea how long the work would be.
I was still thinking in the
early years that, you know, you
basically go through ego death,
and then you get unrestricted
access, you know, to the deep
consciousness of existence. What
I found, of course, is that it's
not a matter of simply, of
shattering the ego and going
through ego death. The universe
has many, many layers. And while
it's all holographically
integrated, in a sense, if you
engage the universe
systematically with a carefully
defined kind of methodology, the
universe takes you in by
degrees. It takes you in by
layers. And as you move into a
new layer of consciousness, and
your consciousness stabilizes at
that new layer sooner or later,
if you keep pushing it, the
method you're using has
sufficient power to take you to
the very edge of that new layer,
you're going to go through yet
another death and rebirth
process that's different than
ego death that builds upon that
process. And you go through a
series of death and rebirth
processes as you explore
progressively deeper levels of
consciousness, at least. That's
how it happened for me. It may
be different for other people
and different substances, but
how it happened to me that there
was a systematic progression,
entry into communion with the
universe, and that's where I
laid out the book. I just
basically took it in, start at
the beginning, try to I tried to
distract, recognize the levels
of consciousness that I went
into, consolidating the story to
make it as efficiently conveyed
as possible, and then each
chapter basically goes into
another level of consciousness,
or another level of engagement
with the universe.
Unknown: How would you, I guess,
define that layer of
consciousness, like, like, What
do you mean? Mean by that of
getting to these next layers.
You know, sometimes you hear in
like, the New Age, like, oh, you
ascend to 3d to 5d and maybe
that's how, you know, some
people are making sense of that.
But how would you describe that
moving through layers?
Kyle Buller: Well, I adopted the
working vocabulary that Stan has
developed in his books between
psychic level, subtle level and
causal level consciousness, it
differentiates low and high,
psychic low and high, subtle and
low and high, causal. And that's
a vocabulary that works for me.
Of course, the universe is so
deep and has so many hundreds of
levels, those are just
approximations, and I don't have
any vested interest in a
particular model of the
universe, or model of how many
levels of consciousness there
are when I was going through and
writing a book and looking back
retrospectively at where this
journey went and how many core
Death and Rebirth cycles. There
were, there many sub cycles of
death and rebirth, but four
fundamental death and rebirth
cycles, and therefore different
levels of consciousness. One
moves into, I found I
differentiated five levels. The
first takes place at the
personal mind, the level of
personal mind, and that
culminates in ego death, where
you lose your egoic or time
space identity. The second takes
place, or took place, for me, at
the collective mind. It's
dynamics fundamentally at the
early, subtle levels of
consciousness. It has to do with
the species mind, dimensions of
species existence. The third
level is archetypal mind, where
one is moving into the highest
subtle level, moving beyond
simply the collective
consciousness of the species,
moving into different levels of
archetypal reality. The fourth
for me, is causal mind, causal
oneness, where you're moving
into profound states of non dual
reality, causal reality. And
then the fifth is, I call
diamond Luminosity, a
particularly deep, clear
experience of ultra clear,
particularly clear dimension of
life. And there are many, many
different, you know, degrees of
light that one encounters. The
closest I could find in the
conventional spiritual
literature to this was in the
Buddhist concept of Dharmakaya,
the clear light of absolute
reality, the light that pre that
exists prior to the Big Bang,
right?
Unknown: Stan even kind of talks
about that with his first LSD
experience, right? Yeah. He's
talking about, you know, the
proceeding and
Kyle Buller: way out, yeah,
yeah,
Unknown: thinking about these
levels of consciousness and
thinking about this, like kind
of new psychedelic Renaissance
with psychedelic therapy. How
important do you think it is for
therapists to kind of understand
these, these levels of
consciousness when working with
clients,
Kyle Buller: if you're going to
be a psychedelic therapist? Of
course, because there are many
different levels of
consciousness. As a therapist,
one works at different levels of
consciousness. So I don't think
a therapist has to have deep
familiarity with all the levels
to work at the early levels, but
I think conventional wisdom,
it's a good wisdom that if
you're going to be working with
clients going into deep,
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness. You must be
personally familiar with those
states. Otherwise. How can you
be the stabilizing factor in the
room when someone is losing
their mind and is terrified of
losing everything they know to
be real, if you haven't been
there yourself, if you haven't
learned to let go, how can you
help someone else let go at
those deep levels? So I think
it's very important, and that
poses a challenge, of course, in
training psychedelic therapists,
because we're in this great
period now, but that's going to
be changing. We're going to be
moving into a different legal
environment soon. I hope the
work that you guys are doing,
and other people are doing is
really creating new
possibilities. But I think, you
know, personal experience is
really important in this area.
Unknown: Yeah, thanks for that.
It's been a hot kind of topic. I
guess that people have been
exploring, should therapists
really understand this, this
these layers of consciousness
and these experiences to be a
guide,
Joe Moore: which is interesting,
this whole idea of, yes, you can
get this training, but you don't
necessarily need a session. But
then there's this whole vast
realm of religious and
philosophy like this material
that discusses all of these
states in kind of a literature
form. Or we can go experiential
with it, too. And I, my problem
lately is I really want a very
strong argument for this, and I
haven't really personally been
able to come up with one,
Kyle Buller: a strong argument
for the importance of personal
experience
Joe Moore: here, at least
personally, at least personal
experience. But the point I
think, that you made, which is
unique, is there's these very
complex spiritual experiences
you can have, Transpersonal
experiences you have, and that's
not really discussed in the
literature, as far as I can
tell, in terms of the, at least
the recent literature, like, how
do you talk to somebody about
this? You know, yes, you became
Buddha for a millennia, and now
you're trying to, you know, work
at your day job again. What?
What do you do? But, yeah, any
comments on that kind of thing?
Kyle Buller: Well, I think it's
important for people to have a
good, solid theoretical
grounding. I mean, I think it's
important to read deeply in
Transpersonal psychology, and
works like Stan Grof and the
various people who have been
guiding people or taking people
into these domains, and have
compiled a large database,
experiential database. But if
you don't have personal
experience of these realities,
you're always working at a
disadvantage, and you can have a
verbal understanding of what it
means to go through into certain
territories. But if you haven't
some personal exposure of this
territory, you're going to make
mistakes. You're going to draw
inferences where an experienced
journeyer would not draw those
inferences. You're going to find
correlations where there aren't
correlations. You'll miss
correlations where there are
correlations. These are very,
very complex experiences. I
mean, my journey lasted from 79
to 99 right, covering a 20 year
spread. I didn't publish this
book for another 20 years, and
partly that was because of the
legal complications I had to
retire from the university
before I did this. But partly it
took me years during the
sessions and years after the
sessions to work out the
complex, overlapping
phenomenology of these states of
consciousness. And you know, if
I were, I mean, I think the word
guide is maybe not the best
word. I mean that implies a role
of active guidance, of active
direction, which is not really
the case for I think, working
with much of this work, doing
much of this work, but to be a
sitter, to be able to hold the
ground, to be able to help
somebody go to the edge of
everything they know to be real
and true about themselves and
about the world, and help them
jump over the edge, to give them
the support that they need to
lose their mind, to really let
go of everything they know To be
real and true, I don't know how
one could really do that without
having first hand experience of
those domains. And so to that
extent, the I think the
effectiveness of therapists are
sitters will be limited to their
own depth of experience. They
can be very, very good and
skillful at levels one, two,
perhaps, but maybe not so much
at levels three, four or five,
or whatever you get the sense of
Unknown: it, right? That's
that's kind of interesting to
think about, even like practical
stuff, like going to different
people for different like
sessions, maybe, I mean,
obviously you have no idea what
the hell is going to come up,
right? But somebody focusing
more on personal dynamics,
right?
Kyle Buller: Yeah, and I think
it's good right now, we're
proceeding very slowly, very
methodically. We're using
gentler psychedelics. There's no
federal protocol that's
suggesting using LSD and the
quantum, the high levels that I
used it, and I think that's
that's good, that's important.
It's important that we proceed
methodologically carefully. We
have a window. You know, we lost
our window 40 years ago. Yeah,
the window is back. And it's
important that we move very
judiciously as we expand that
window, but sooner or later,
we're going to find what we
found in the early years of
psychedelic work, and that is
healing the personal unconscious
is only the first step of a long
journey into the universe, into
the deeper dimensions of
consciousness which take us into
the I don't know what do you
call it? I think of it as the
mind of the universe, the mind
of the cosmos. I hesitate to
call it the divine mind, or the
mind of God, because that
language has very strong
cultural overtones that I don't
really want to import. But when
one dissolves. Evolves when one
completely dissolves time space
level and just dissolves into
increasingly comprehensive
fields of experience that open
realities to you that you've
never even dreamed possible. And
if you go back again and again
in a methodical way, levels of
consciousness that at first
swallow you up whole, and it's
very, very hard to stay
consciously aware at these new
levels. And that's why I think
we often call them ineffable,
but right if you go back
consistently over and over
again, what happens is, you
acclimate, you learn how to stay
conscious at levels of
consciousness that previously
were not able to stay conscious
in and that's a pattern that
repeats itself as you go deeper
and deeper.
Joe Moore: Yeah, I find that to
be really true. Are you familiar
with this gentleman, Kalin de ai
from Detroit, I'm not. He is a
very strong proponent of these
high level doses. And I, I
struggle with his arguments
around it, but, but yours, you
know, seems quite sensible.
It's, you know, how do we
approach it?
Kyle Buller: I'm not a proponent
of high doses myself. I mean, I
did this work. I came through
it. See, in the early years, the
early high dose work done at
Spring Grove Hospital with
terminally ill patients. Well,
it's limited to three sessions.
Low dose psychedelic work, open
ended, high dose work was
limited to three sessions. And I
thought, going into it, I
thought, well, if you could do
it safely three times, you could
do it safely more time. But what
I found was that by doing it as
systematically as I did, and
pushing that edge as hard as I
did, it required that issues
arose, challenges arose which
had not been discussed in the
early levels of the work,
opportunities for insights and
understanding emerge, but also
challenges navigating these
increasingly intense levels and
large levels of consciousness
and what it does to your body
and mind and as you go into
these realities and how It
affects people around you, I
found that my students never
knew about my work. I mean, I
kept my work completely isolated
from anyone on campus, but I
found at a certain point, my
students began to be activated
by my psychedelic work. There
was a natural contagion that was
happening because consciousness
at these deeper levels is open
ended. It's like a lake. You
throw a rock in the lake and
ripple spread out. So when one
person goes very, very deep,
people around them are naturally
going to be impacted. And I had
to learn how to take care of the
activations that my my students
were experiencing. That's I
wrote the book living classroom,
Sri, that came out of years and
years of trying to understand
this dynamic between my mind and
their mind and our minds
together in the context of, you
know, consciousness at large. So
it's not just a matter of taking
care of your own body and your
own emotions and your intimate
relationships, and taking care
of everyone who's touched by
your work at a larger collective
level. I wouldn't push it as
hard if I were doing it again. I
would. It's not that I would
avoid working with high doses,
but I would balance it working
with lower doses, and I would
balance working with LSD, which
pushes a high cosmological
ceiling with Psilocybin work and
Ayahuasca work is much more kind
of embodied psychedelic states.
Unknown: Yeah, man, there's a
couple questions I want to ask.
Much direction I want to go
into, but I want to come back to
the this idea, the ripples,
right? Because I've thought
about this a lot, and I'm kind
of curious what your take is on
this, of having some of these
experiences. And I've even had
it in Breathwork sessions, where
it's like tapping into, I guess,
how you describe it, like this,
this lake, you know, you kind of
toss it in and there's like,
ripples and time wave or
something like that, where all
these kind of synchronistic
things might start happening.
And I'm wondering, from your
perspective, you know, you're
talking about your students
changing, do you think that was
more in the sense of your
presence and the way that you
were showing up, or do you think
it was kind of more in that
subtle realm, world where you're
going into these states and it
is having more of a ripple on
some other sort of level.
Kyle Buller: I think it's a
both, and I think it does as my
work changed me, certainly my
presence in the classroom
changed. But the more
interesting aspect, I think, is
working at the subtle level. I
mean, I began, for example.
Example. I found that when I was
lecturing and just just looking
for a random example, looking
for an example to illustrate
some concept that I wanted to,
you know, was bringing forward,
and I would pause, I would just
stop, and my mind would go
blank, and I this idea would
come to me to give this example,
I would use that example. And
students began to come up to me
after class and began to say,
very quietly when they were sure
no one was listening. You know,
it's funny, you use that example
today, because that's exactly
what happened to me this week.
And this first, I thought this
was just, you know, an
interesting accident, but it
kept happening. It happened
repeatedly. And not only was it
happening frequently enough that
I knew it was it had to have
some significance, but the
deeper I went in my own work,
the more the students were being
touched in very, very deep,
private, personal areas of their
life, lies places where they
needed healing, places where
they were blocked, places where
they needed some help getting
through to the next stage of
their own development. So as I
was kind of facing my blocks and
entering into deep communion
with the intelligence of life,
it was as if the very fabric the
intelligent fabric around me was
being activated and triggering
these kind of aha moments with
my students and their own
confrontations with their
blocks. And the students knew
that something unusual was
happening. I couldn't exactly
explain what it was, but I had
to, you know, we all knew
something was happening, so I
would have students taking my
courses, partly for the
intellectual content, partly
because they wanted to be in the
energy of the room. But I found
it wasn't just that there was a
resonance spontaneously
occurring between my energy and
their energy. There was a second
phenomenon that I discuss in the
living classroom, and that is
the effect of group fields. That
is that just like morphogenetic
fields, Rupert sheldrakes,
concept of Morphic fields,
except these are smaller. These
are not species wide field.
These are more specific fields,
I found that there was, there
were psychic fields growing
around my courses that were
getting stronger year by year,
the more students studied with
me in these courses, and it was
a field that was being generated
by their learning. So hundreds
and hundreds of students
learning over many years creates
a field that was impacting and
accelerating and deepening the
learning of subsequent students
in subsequent semesters. So
there were multiple factors
going into this phenomenon.
Unknown: Yeah, it's super
fascinating, and I don't know
how to make sense of it at
times. So yeah, thanks for
sharing that.
Kyle Buller: But you know, it
turns out that once you let go
of an atomistic psychology, once
you and it's not that atomistic
psychology is really true. That
is the psychology which treats
our individual consciousness as
the individual, standalone
phenomenon. We know that that's
true, but underneath that is a
quantum reality. It's a quantum
psychology, and once you let go
of this idea that everything
that happens around us can be
explained in terms of the of the
aggregate of simply individual
awareness and open to this
larger participatory Cosmos
where there is a deeper context.
It's like a deeper tide that's
always moving in and out. It's
always flowing. It actually
becomes very coherent. It's very
easy to understand. It says that
you have to shift your
metaphysical basis, right?
Unknown: Yeah, that makes sense.
That makes sense.
Kyle Buller: It's like plate
tectonics. You know, in the
early years, it was very, very
hard to see that just looked
ridiculous. But once we began to
see it, then a whole lot of data
began to make sense, and it was
elegant and simple and
transparent.
Unknown: Yeah, I'm curious also
to kind of go back to that idea
of kind of incorporating
mushrooms in Ayahuasca. You kind
of said that it seems to be a
little bit more body medicine.
Could you talk about the
difference between your
experiences with LSD and the
more plant based psychedelics.
This is a question that we've
been asked a lot, and I think we
even chatted about in our course
last two nights ago, of like,
you know, what is the difference
between like, LSD? Is that a
little bit different that like?
I've always like somebody said,
I always heard it's like, more
psychological than say, you
know, more kind of like
biographical and doesn't have
this, like spirit, right? Where
you Albert Hoffman said, right?
He said, Psilocybin seems to be
something in there, right? So,
yeah, I wonder what your take
is.
Kyle Buller: Well, inevitably,
my take is based on my own.
Personal experience, and so it's
always dangerous to generalize
on an end of one. So I just
don't want to over generalize
psychedelics, which have been
used historically, have fields
associated with them. So we've
been using mushrooms for 1000s
and 1000s of years, and I think
there's a certain sense in which
around the biochemistry of this
substance, there are fields of
human experience of human beings
engaging the deeper dimensions
of their own consciousness and
consciousness at large using
this substance. And when one
takes this substance, you don't
just introduce a chemical into
your body, which then you have a
private experience of this
substance. But there is a sense
in which how this substance
affects you is mediated, in
part, by the history of your
species with this substance. And
I think that's also true with
Ayahuasca. There's a multi 1000
year history surrounding
Ayahuasca with LSD, we don't
have those fields. I mean, LSD
is a new substance, and I don't
think the difference is
fundamentally organic versus
synthetic. I don't find that
discussion terribly
illuminating. I mean, our
experience in the 60s and 70s,
that's a few decades, that's not
a whole lot of experience when
it comes to these types of
fields that I'm talking about.
So in my experience, that living
quality, that kind of living
intelligence quality, I'm sure
that there are spiritual
agencies on the other side which
may account for part of that and
but part of it, I think, has to
do with humanity's living
experience with these substances
and all the experiences I've had
with them. LSD strikes me as
kind of cleaner in that respect.
It doesn't have that same kind
of programmed quality. Now I
don't know what it would have
been like if I had been working
with low doses of LSD. If I'd
been working with low doses, I'm
sure it would have activated my
experiences would have been much
more personal and
psychodynamically oriented. But
working with the very high doses
that I worked with, after the
first 15 sessions or so, when
the sessions were at their peak
hours, I was not working in
relationship to my personal
psyche at all. In fact, pretty
much in the book, I drop out the
personal story as much as
possible, because the personal
story kind of showed up at the
beginning of a session and at
the end of a session. And these
were very meaningful experiences
to me. They were very healing.
They were very, you know,
helpful and giving me insights
to relevant things in my life.
But during the peak hours, I was
usually operating far beyond the
range of personal psyche. When
I'm working with Psilocybin, I
don't have that experience of
being so far removed from my
personal reality. I don't have I
only have limited experience
with Ayahuasca. I like the
medicine very much. It's a very
powerful medicine. It's been
given me some extra ordinary
help and extraordinary clarity
here and there, but I don't have
enough experience with it
comparable to my 70 some high
dose LSD sessions to do a
careful AB my basic sense is
that Psilocybin tends to be less
evocative, less disruptive, less
opening up to the deep, deep
levels. Ayahuasca is more
disruptive, opening up to deeper
levels still. And at least for
me, LSD, working with it as I
did, opens up to very, very deep
cosmological levels. Eventually,
I don't know of people I have
not seen, though I haven't tried
to do an exhaustive search in
the literature, but I have not
seen people having experiences
with Psilocybin and, for the
most part, even Ayahuasca, that
correlate to the experiences I
was having in the last 10 years
of my work with LSD. But again,
that's just my personal
experience. It's, you know, it's
not a scholarly person, right?
Unknown: Yeah. And what were
some of your experiences like
towards the last 10 years? Like,
I guess, yeah. Could you give us
some examples of, like, those
big themes that you're working
through, if it wasn't so
personal or psychodynamic?
Kyle Buller: Well, you know,
that's that's a hard question,
because there's so many levels,
and there's so many of some it's
always tricky to kind of jump
in. To the later stages, because
every state builds upon earlier
stages. But right one of the one
of the barometers I would
mention, for example, would be
time when I went into subtle
level reality. I for a year, I
had a consistent set of
experiences where I experienced
the totality of my life from
beginning to end as
simultaneously present in
immediate now. So I not only had
insights into my old age, and I
didn't experience my age in a
sort of abstract, theoretical
way I experienced, the distilled
essence of my entire life boiled
down to right now, and all of
the data of my life was present
at this particular moment in
time. This was such a mind
shattering possibility that when
I first came back out of this
experience. I couldn't remember
it. It took me entering into it
multiple times to be able to
really be able to hold on to all
of those experiences, which I
write about in the chapter
called deep time in the soul.
Going beyond that, I began to
enter into archetypal dimensions
of archetypal reality. I began
to have experiences of something
like the Platonic domain of the
reality behind time, space
reality, except it wasn't
archetypes like Plato conceives
of them. Plato conceives of
archetypes as unchanging ideas
in the mind of a transcendent
intelligence. My experience,
these were vast, huge beings
that were so huge I couldn't
wrap my mind around them. The
best my mind could do in imaging
them was to sort of see them as
galaxies. I think was simply my
mind's attempt to image
something that one would measure
in hundreds of 1000s of light
years of scope. But these were
beings that were responsible for
creating time and space and
orchestrating the unfolding of
reality in time and space I went
into, into what I call deep
time, which is not eternity, it
isn't timelessness, but it's
different magnitudes of time
experienced within a
simultaneous or broader frame of
reference. So I had many
experiences, and became one of
the overarching themes of my
book of my sessions, and
therefore the book of humanity's
future, where humanity was
going, what our moment in
history was, what the archetypal
trajectory of humanity was, what
was happening behind the scenes
in this global sustainability
crisis that we're entering into.
What I have a chapter in the
book called The Birth of the
future human lots and lots of
going into deep time, going deep
into humanity's future,
experiencing what is attempting
to be born in this period of
History. What how evolution
works on this larger, broader
scale, and then eventually going
deep into various episodes of
causal oneness, Shunyata,
emptiness, the experience of
primal void, you know, the void
that's behind physical manifest
existence, experience of cosmic
love, cause of just being
overwhelmed with and I think
love is basically a kind of
characteristic of the inherent
oneness of life. When you
experience the deep, deep
oneness that existence is, then
you know the emotional
counterpart of that is love.
It's compassion, the emotion of
oneness, and then eventually
going beyond oneness, beyond the
void, into this diamond
Luminosity state which, once I
touched the diamond Luminosity,
this occupied the last five
years of my work. Once I touched
it, it was a state of state of
being, state of consciousness so
incredibly clear, so exquisitely
clear that once I touched it, I
wasn't interested in exploring
any of the other dimensions of
consciousness that I had been
exploring for years. Returning
to that condition became my sole
objective in the next in the 26
chapter, 26 sessions, covering
four years of work, I only
touched that condition four
times, and in between those four
sessions were tremendous
cleaning, tremendous
purification, tremendous
detoxification, so that I could
return to that condition.
Conversation and experience it
more clearly, more completely.
So this, there's a lot of
levels, and yeah, that's what
makes the story a complex story
to tell.
Unknown: Yeah, well, and people
should check out the book and
read through all this. So, yeah,
yeah.
Kyle Buller: Well, it's nice now
that the book is out, you know,
they don't have to get it from
me speaking. You know, I've done
my best to tell the story as
cleanly and simply as I can with
without a lot of the
philosophical baggage that may
have been in some of my earlier
works.
Joe Moore: Right? Is there a
story that you'd like to tell
the most about your project,
that that maybe you could share
here, or any, any kind of
specific gem you like to share
the most.
Kyle Buller: You know, it's a
story of a journey, and every
phase of the journey was an
exciting adventure in its own
right. At the time when I was
entering into that territory.
And each one was absolutely
fascinating and captivating to
me when I was going through this
material. And so I don't have a
favorite, per se. I mean, I
think, of course, the diamond
Luminosity is from my own
personal heart. That is the
deepest dimensions of the story,
the deepest aspect, I think the
story of the birth of the future
human, where reincarnation is
taking humanity, is an important
component of the story, because
I what happened to me in one
particular session, in the 38th
session, without this cutting
down to the important piece here
is that I began to experience
all my lives coming into me, all
my former lives were kind of
being integrated. And I've done
a lot of other work, hypnotic
regression work, to familiarize
myself with some of my deep life
history, but I experienced all
my former lives coming in very
quickly. It was like wrapping
string on around a kite spool.
And there came a moment when all
of that energy with all those
living experiences, they fused.
And when they fuse, they
ignited. And there was a
tremendous explosion of diamond
light from my chest, and it
threw me into a completely
different state of consciousness
and and I think what I was being
shown in this experience, what I
was being given was an
understanding of where
reincarnation is taking us,
because, classically,
reincarnation, you know, leads
to a gradual, hopefully a
sustained, development of more
compassion, more understanding,
developing our qualities of our
deep essential nature, more and
more richer and richer levels.
We make mistakes, we go back, we
learn, we go forward in this
process. But I don't think the
process is really about taking
us incrementally to eventually
producing a better life, which
is incrementally plus one from
where we were previously. I
think eventually, if we die and
we expand in the after death
condition, we're born and we
contract into an immediate one
life focus, we die and we
expand, and we're born. We go
back and forth. And if we keep
this up, just for hundreds and
1000s and 10s of 1000s and
hundreds of 1000s of years, if
we keep this up, sooner or
later, the totality of our
consciousness, which most people
would experience only after they
die, the deep soul, sooner or
later, that soul consciousness,
I think the evolutionary
trajectory is for this
consciousness to wake up inside
our physical incarnation, and
that's what I call the birth of
the diamond soul, when you wake
up and we are not tempted to
identify with simply egoic this
body, mind, kind of structure
that we know ourselves to be, an
internal being. We know
ourselves to be in relationship
with other eternal beings. We
have a felt sense of history
with many, many of these beings,
and the compassion that comes
with that history and a sense of
open transparency to the cosmic
intelligence at large. I think
that's basically where we're
going. And I don't know, I think
this is not a private
experience. It's a collective
experience. The universe doesn't
work in small numbers. The
universe works with whole
species. And what's happening is
really an evolving of our entire
species in the direction. If
there are one thing, I guess, to
keep, I would come back to one
thing which I wish I could tell
of reach into my heart and
communicate to people it would
be to let go of this terribly
constricting fear of death.
Because if we're afraid of
dying. We've got it all
backwards. You know, here's
where the hard work is done.
When we die, we have all this
Hollywood bullshit about what
happens to us when we die, and
most of it, most of it's just
trash. When we die, we enter,
you know, we go back home, we
enter. The vast majority of us
enter, pretty, very easily,
straight into the depth of where
we come from. And there are many
layers of that reality. So
there's a lot of work to do, but
there's absolutely nothing to
fear of death. And one of the
things that's come out of my
work is I just, I don't have a
fear of death. I mean, dying is
pain in the ass, but being dead
has absolutely no fear for me.
In fact, it's something I look
forward to very much.
Joe Moore: Kyle, how do you
respond to that
Unknown: that resonates a lot
with me, of what you're saying,
like, kind of gave me a little
bit of chills. So I don't know
if you know my my story.
Listeners probably know this, if
you've been following us for a
while, but when I was 16, I had
a Near-Death Experience, and so
rupture my spleen when I was in
the MRI or the CAT scan machine,
I was overwhelmed with this,
this blissful feeling of love
and beauty that I was going back
home, and there is a sense
something came over me and said,
You're going back home, you're
going to you're going back to
the stars, where we all come
from, and this, you know,
physical life is going to cease
to exist, but you're going to
continue on. And that was really
beautiful, and it wasn't scary
when I when I first heard I was
dying in like they said, you
know, you have internal
injuries. You're losing massive
blood. I thought, you know, I
was pretty terrified. But in
that moment, as I was drifting
away, total acceptance, and so I
actually had a really hard time
coming back here, right? Because
it was, and I could probably
resonate with that idea, the
diamond Luminosity of wanting to
return there, because I
definitely resonate with that
feeling of wanting to return to
that oneness that I felt on that
night. And that's what got me
into like exploring
psychedelics, is having very
similar experiences with
psychedelics and correlating
that to my Near-Death
Experience, and wanting to get
back there and over time. And
maybe you'll resonate with this
is like the period in between of
stopping and actually focusing
on the integration. And I keep
coming back to this idea that
the work is here. This is where
all the magic happens. And how
do we really embody that and
show up.
Kyle Buller: Yeah, yeah. To
complain about the restrictions
of time and space is kind of
like a weight lifter complaining
about the weights. This is
where, this is where the work is
done. Time space is an extremely
demanding environment, but
progress made here has
exponential import for what
we're what's available to us
when we die. Of all the various
populations, people I feel the
closest affinity from my own
psychedelic work are the near
death episode people. I've
taught near death episode
research for years at my
university in one of my courses,
and so I've really read deeply
in the near death literature,
and that's the closest
correlation I find with the
deepest of the psychedelic
experiences, very strong
correlations. And Ken ring was
one of the near dev episode, you
know, one of the founders of
that movement, and I have, we've
written together and dialog
together. He's a good friend
around that.
Unknown: Yeah, yeah. It's, it's
a powerful topic, something I
think about often, right? And I
guess my early experiences got
me really on this path. Was just
like I entered into this space
where just felt so similar with
like this. I had an experience
with Psilocybin, or just so on
par with dying, and just
captivated my attention of how
could a substance like this? I
mean, I guess in a sense, you
know, if you take it from the
psychotherapeutic like lens,
it's like reliving trauma,
right? I'm kind of, my psyche is
processing that experience, and
I'm going back there to kind of
reprocess it, but that plenty of
other experiences where it still
felt pretty similar and on par
with that original Near-Death
Experience.
Kyle Buller: Yeah, I've died
many times, and I feel like and
that was the whole impetus in
the early work at Spring Grove,
was to give people a foretaste
of where they're going and they
die. And, you know, I've gone
through that in shamans. This is
very familiar territory, so
there's nothing unique to me
there, but I've gone through
that death process so many times
it feels very comfortable and
very natural, and coming back is
sometimes challenging. I mean,
the hardest chapter for me to
write in this book. Was the last
chapter coming off the mountain.
It basically tells a story of
what happened after I stopped my
sessions and I basically entered
into a period, eventually, of
deep, deep existential
loneliness. I found that I had
really worked very hard in
integrating my sessions. I did
all of Albert very carefully. I
wrote them down, I studied them,
I tried to incorporate their
teaching into my life. I really
thought I had it, you know,
locked down pretty well, and I
thought therefore that I could
stop my sessions and I would
just be able to kind of collect
and ponder the many gifts that I
had been given through the
years, but what I learned was
that integrating an entire
journey is different than
integrating individual sessions,
and that by repeatedly going
deeper and deeper and deeper
into the universe and experience
The exquisite ecstasy of
dissolving into sheer light
repeatedly and entering into
dissolving into the crystalline
body of the Divine. When, for
various reasons, I made the
decision that it was time for
this work to stop, I found that
I had a I was suffering from a
loss of communion, a deep, deep
existential sadness, and
eventually, years down the road,
I found that I was really just
waiting to die, that I could
return to the light. And I
realized, you know, that wasn't
right. That's not the way this
work is supposed to end. You
know, my entire body was
screaming, failure to integrate.
But because I had been so
careful trying to integrate. It
wasn't clear what the where the
imbalance had come in. What I
found eventually is that there
was an imbalance that had I had
cultivated, inadvertently,
between Transcendence and
immanence. It's all the divine.
The physical universe is the
divine. I knew that it was the
divine. I knew that we're never
absent from the Divine for any
moment. It's only our own
illusions to keep us in that
sense. But I had pushed so
deeply into Transcendence that
in this to a certain degree, I
had lost my footing in the
imminent divine, and I had to
make a conscious choice and
undertake specific practices to
really kind of ground myself
back in the imminent divine for
the remainder of my years on
this earth. It took about 10
years for me to really get
solidly, comfortably back inside
my time space suit.
Unknown: Wow, I can imagine,
after 20 years of deep
exploration. I mean, that's a,
I'd say that's probably a pretty
long integration process, yeah,
yeah.
Kyle Buller: And that's, I
think, you know, in this
respect, my story is sometimes
described as a hero's journey,
but it's not the hero's journey
the way it's usually thought of.
It's not simply going and
experiencing something and
bringing back, you know,
something valuable for your
culture, for yourself. It's all
it's tempered by, it's tempered
by a kind of lesson that comes
from dealing with not the
failure of some aspect of the
journey, but actually of the
success of the journey, of being
wounded by the sheer beauty of
what one experiences. You
literally are wounded by the
beauty of the universe, by the
experiencing the extraordinary
intelligence of the universe,
extraordinary love of the
universe. And if you're not able
to create a container inside
your historical existence where
you can breathe this
intelligence in and breathe the
compassion in, then you know
it's like it literally can kind
of become painful. So it my, my
story is in part of it's a
cautionary tale. It cautions
against and even though I tried
to be as methodical as possible
and do it as carefully as
possible and integrated as
deeply as I could, it cautions
against going too deep, too
fast. If you can call 20 years
too fast, going too deep or
deeper than you can actually
productively use, I think my
memories have changed not only
the rest of the years of my
life, but my memories have
changed the trajectory of my
soul's entire evolution. So I
don't think of the results of my
journey as necessarily coming to
fruition in just, you know, the
next few decades, I think they
come to fruition over life.
Times it's changed the entire
trajectory of my deep
evolutionary project. And I
think that's true for anyone who
enters into this. You know, when
you enter into deep intimacy
with life in this way, you
purify, and you're purifying,
you offload a lot of, you know,
painful trauma, whatever,
whatever, but you also open up
to a different a different
relationship with the universe.
So right now, my primary way of
being with the universe in this
intimate way is not working with
psychedelics. That time of my
life is largely over. I'm 70
years old, and this is, you
know, somewhat of a young man's
game, young person's game, but I
do a lot of contemporary of
classical contemplative
practice. I do a lot of
Vajrayana practice, which I find
to be very complementary to deep
psychedelic work. I don't feel
any cross purposes between the
two different work methods of
working. I should mention in
this context, though, I think it
would be a mistake to hold to
sort of evaluate the the the
value of psychedelic feed
psychedelic work by holding it
accountable just to the
Enlightenment project. I started
this work with an agenda of an
enlightenment project. What
happened was my personal
Awakening was completely
eclipsed eventually by a project
of a collective awakening. All
my work began to be focused on a
type of healing of the
collective psyche that went
beyond my personal healing, and
an awakening of the collective
psyche that went beyond my
personal awakening. And then it
became just a radical adventure,
a cosmological adventure going
so deep that it would be
impossible to bring those
experiences back and stabilize
them in some kind of spiritually
awakened state. It's just a
different project, the
Enlightenment project and
cosmological exploration
project. These are two different
projects that have to be
evaluated on their own terms. My
two cents,
Unknown: no, yeah, I would agree
it sounds
Joe Moore: Yeah, Hmm, yes, this
is quite the interview.
Certainly like a much, I knew it
was going to be a big topic, but
I'm always impressed by how big
some of these things become. And
yeah, I I do think some people
are doing similar projects
nowadays, though. Yeah, I want,
I wonder if LSD is still in
vogue in this context. I don't
know.
Kyle Buller: I don't know. I
worked with LSD primarily
because that was the work that
Stan had done most of his early
work with, and I trusted what I
saw in Stan's research, and I
trusted the history there and
the methodology he developed. I
only began to work with other
psychedelic substances pretty
much after my LSD work was done.
And so the mind that I brought
to my Psilocybin experiences and
my Ayahuasca experiences and
solvia Dip and arm so on so
forth, the mind was that the
mind that had been transformed
by all my previous psychedelic
work, which is the other thing
to you know, important to take
account of that the mind, the
experiences that we have,
reflect the entire history of
our working in Non-ordinary
states of consciousness. So if
we've done this work only a few,
a few, two or three times, well,
then we have that kind of depth
of experience to bring to it.
But if we've been doing this
work for years and years and
years, naturally, these
substances are going to have a
different kind of effect,
because we've been transformed.
The way I think of this is that
list, in my experience, the
universe is an infinite ocean of
possibilities, just an infinite
ocean of we'll never, ever get
to the end of it. I used to
think, and we'll get to an end
state. That was the project to
get, to get to the end condition
that was taken away from me
along the journey, I began to
understand it's an infinite,
infinite progression. I get
distracted from my original
point by that particular,
particular image. Yeah, I'll
just stick with that. I lost my
train of thought.
Joe Moore: But that works for
us, because it's our orientation
is. This Grof Ian meets
Whitehead and John Cobb kind of
synthesis. And, yeah, you know,
largely this, that's at least
the project of the company here.
But yeah, it's, it's good to
hear that, you know, in it, it
rhymes, in a sense, with that
Bodhisattva vow of, let's keep
going like there's not this end
point of Nirvana until
everybody's there, and it's
going to be a long, long, long,
long time, if time even enters
into that discussion,
Kyle Buller: it's a long time,
except, of course, it's speeding
up. You know, it's kind of like
our collective karma as a
species is coming at us hard.
You know, the whole history, you
know our culture is basically a
culture that's been built by
ego, and for all the many
virtues and values of the ego,
it's basically, it's
fundamentally a fragmented
condition, and therefore it
creates a world which is deeply
imbalanced with between
ourselves and between other life
forms. And you know that world
is coming to a radical and
accelerated breakdown. And I
think this is actually part of
the evolutionary pivot that we
are coming into a time where we
literally will not be able to
continue operating out the same
not just an economic or
industrial or technological
basis, but we will not be able
to continue functioning out of
the same psychological basis
that we go at consciousness. So
how fast we might make this
transition? If we use historical
projections from the past, we
probably deeply underestimate
how fast this could happen. In
fact, in that chapter on the
birth of the future human, where
I talk about particularly one
session, session 55 it took me
deep into the death and rebirth
of humanity. The message that
kept coming through over and
over and over again was, this is
going to happen much faster than
anyone could have is imagining
it's going to happen much
faster, you know. So I think
we're the game is getting very,
very intense. We're being driven
into non linear dynamics. Feels
that way, conscious that yeah,
dynamics, the collective psyche
is being hyper stimulated by the
trauma that we're going into.
And when systems, we know from
physical systems, when physical
systems enter into non linear
conditions, they can do things
that they could not do when they
were in lower energy linear
conditions. And I think that
something similar happens with
psychic fields, the integrated
psychic field that holds all of
our individual minds, and that
psychic field is hyper
stimulated by the suffering that
we're going into. But it's hyper
stimulated, it moves, will
eventually move into a non
linear condition. And the rules
of non linear conditions of
dynamics apply to psychic fields
as well as physical fields.
Small changes can elicit huge
outcomes, latent connectivity,
which was kind of invisible at
the linear level, becomes
suddenly active and visible at
the non linear level. Things can
happen much faster at the non
linear level than at the linear
level. So, you know, we're going
into a trial by fire, and I
think this trial is actually
part of the conscious intention
of the creative intelligence
itself. I don't think it's
accidental, and I don't think
there are any victims here. You
know, personally, my own
personal belief is we all chose
to be here. We chose to be part
of this time in history. It's an
extraordinarily important time
to be fully conscious and fully
active.
Unknown: Makes give me chills
thinking about that. It's
interesting. It does feel like
things are really kind of
speeding up. And you know,
sometimes I'm like, oh, you
know, you always kind of hear
that as you get older, time
seems to be speeding up. But
even, you know, talk to people
that are older, like, things
just seem to be happening
quicker and quicker. It is
really interesting. Feel like I
can't, like, hold on to
anything, you know? It's like,
once you kind of grasp onto it,
something else has already
changed form, you know,
Kyle Buller: yeah, yeah. So many
of our, not only our technology
is driving this way, but our
social customs, you know, just
They're dissolving right out
from underneath us. The
standards of truth are changing.
And it's a confusing time, and
it's a it's a dangerous time and
it's a hard time. Wow, it's an
extraordinarily exciting time.
It is.
Unknown: Do you see psychedelics
aiding in this
Kyle Buller: in any way? Yeah,
absolutely. I think that the
ways in which psychedelics have
come back into our culture, both
from the Central American and
South American cultures, which
have kept this tradition alive
the. The new psychedelics, you
know, LSD is often compared to
the atom bomb, right? They were
discovered at the same time this
exponential, this opportunity to
explore dimensions of
consciousness that previously,
previous generations, for the
most part, and classically, have
had to spend lifetimes
meditating in order just to get
access to some of them, and now
people of even modest spiritual
capacities can have temporary
experiences of these realities,
which have a profound they
require a profound redrafting of
our existential assumptions
about how life works, and that
we can do this. We can engage
these, these dimensions of
consciousness, not for
recreational purposes and not
even for healing purposes, but
we can engage them
systematically for educational
and deep, transformational
purposes, not only for our own
personal transformation, but we
can. We can work on behalf of
the collective in these states
of consciousness. I mean, I
think psychedelics are just they
have that's, that's what I saw
when I first read Stan
Grossberg. I thought, wow, this
is going to change everything.
It's going to be a true before
and after development. We're
going to it's like the invention
of the as he said, the
microscope for biology and the
Telescope for Astronomy, it just
increases the quantity of data
we have access to, so that it
changes, it forces a radical
revision of our theoretical
understanding. I think
psychedelics are part of it, and
just in time, because we have
very little time. Yeah, it feels
that way. Yeah, it's coming at
us very fast, very fast. Cool.
Joe Moore: So I hate to end the
podcast, but we're at over an
hour, and I don't I want to be
respectful of your time, and I
really appreciate this. This is
a very enlightening episode. Can
you tell us a little bit about
where people can find your book
and perhaps the upcoming audio
book,
Kyle Buller: they can find the
book on Amazon. I'm just putting
the final edits on the audio
book. I'm not sure that will be
released through inner
traditions. I'm not quite sure
what the vehicle will be for
that, but it should be out,
hopefully by the beginning,
beginning of the year, I will
have a website up. Hopefully by
the first of the year, I'm way
overdue in revising this website
and getting it posted, but
eventually, within a month or
so, people will be able to find
me@chrisbache.com that's going
to be the easiest way right now,
most of my written work and some
tapes are collected@academia.edu
under my name, You can find them
listed there. But right now, I'm
not as good on social media as I
should be.
Unknown: It's hard to keep up
with Yeah,
Joe Moore: only do one. It's not
worth being everywhere,
Kyle Buller: yeah, but the most
what's really exciting is the
book is finally out, and it's as
clear a presentation of this
material as I've been able to
take me five years to put it
together and bring it forward,
and it's as it's as good as I
can tell the story.
Joe Moore: Well, thank you for
all your work, and really
appreciate you joining us on the
show today.
Kyle Buller: Thank you guys.
It's been a real honor. I really
appreciate the work you're
doing. Keep it up. Thank you.
Keep getting the word out. You
know, you guys are social
Catalyst. We need all the social
capitalism we can get these
days.
Unknown: Thank you, yeah, well,
we'll keep plugging along.
Joe Moore: Thank you for tuning
in to psychedelics today, this
interview with Dr Chris Bache
was super interesting for me,
and I really can't wait to dig
into his work more. It sounds
super fascinating, and I really
hope you enjoyed it, if you did
or didn't, let us know.
Psychedelics today,
email@gmail.com We'd really like
to hear feedback if you want to
support the show, we accept
small monthly donations over
patreon.com/psychedelics, today.
If you want to do it at no
charge, you can just tell a
friend and also leave us a
review on Facebook or iTunes or
your podcast app, any of those
places help a ton. So please.
You know, just take a quick
minute to help us out, and it
would be much appreciated. We
also have a course called
navigating psychedelics for
clinicians and therapists coming
up. Class starts February six,
and we are very excited about
it's an eight week course goes
through the end of March, and it
is extraordinary. Narrate tons
of pre recorded content. Class
time with Kyle and I to discuss
ideas. We'll also have guest
teachers. There's master classes
and much more. We facilitate the
class on zoom as a kind of web
platform. So it's video. You get
to see our faces. We can see
your faces if you want to let us
see your faces, and we get to
chat and work through a lot of
this material together. So hope
you are interested. If you are,
check it out psychedelic
education center.com or
psychedelicstoday.com to find
the link for this course for
clinicians and therapists. And I
think that's it for now. Thank
you all for tuning in to
psychedelics today. This is Joe
signing off from Colorado, see
you on the next Episode, bye,
Bye. You
Unknown: Hey, you