Unknown: Connecting minds is a
space dedicated to honoring the
amazing authors, researchers,
clinicians, artists and
entrepreneurs who are
contributing to our collective
evolution or simply making the
world a better place. These
thought provoking conversations
are intended to expand our
horizons. So come with an open
mind and let us grow together.
Here is your host, Christian
yordanov, hello
Christian Yordanov: and welcome
to the connective minds podcast.
My name is Christian Jordan of
and thank you so much for
joining me today on this 11th
episode of the podcast. Today I
have Christopher M Bache on. We
had a two hour conversation,
almost. It was a wonderful
conversation, relished every
single minute of re listening to
it while I was typing up the
show notes. So much depth to it,
you're in for a treat.
Basically, the focal point of
the conversation will be Chris's
latest book, LSD and the mind of
the universe, diamonds from
heaven, where he it's basically
an account of his 20 year
journey of high dose LSD
sessions between 1979 and 1999
where he undertook deep
exploration of his consciousness
and into the mind of the
universe. As the title of the
book suggests, we also discuss
his first book, briefly, life
cycles, which is about
reincarnation. So you're about
to hear some amazing stuff from
Chris. Really awesome guy. So
glad he agreed to get on the
podcast. He was actually the
first guest that I approached,
way back in September. So he was
the first interview I conducted.
So I was extra nervous. I did a
ton of preparation. I really
immersed myself into his work,
you know, His books, His videos,
etc. It was a very enlightening
and illuminating experience. He
really opened my eyes to so many
concepts and authors and thought
leaders and pioneers in various
different fields, and I have a
reading list from here till the
end of I don't know what it's
that long, you know, but, um, so
I really think you enjoy this
episode. I don't want to offer
too many spoilers. I think the
best thing to do is to just let
Chris speak for the experiences
of you know, hear it from the
horse's mouth, as it were, even
though we will only be
scratching the surface in this
interview. Of course, he has a
rather large body of work that I
highly recommend you check out
the of course links and to the
books and to to his website,
some YouTube videos, etc, will
all be in the show notes and on
the website. So yeah, please get
in touch with me. Let me know
how you like the episode, and
thank you once again for joining
me today. Really appreciate you
investing your time in this
podcast. So without further ado,
I present you Christopher M
Bache. Alrighty, today on the
connecting minds podcast, we
have Christopher M Bache PhD.
Christopher Bache, or Chris is
professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he
taught for 33 years. He is a
fellow at the Institute of
Noetic Sciences. He is also a
junked faculty at the California
Institute of integral studies
and on the advisory board for
Grof Transpersonal training and
the Grof foundation. He's an
award winning teacher and an
international speaker. He's the
author of four books, and he
lives in North Carolina now. He
has written several books today
will one of the topics of our
discussion will be his latest
book, LSD and the mind of the
universe, diamonds from heaven.
Chris, thank you so much for
taking the time out to join us
today.
Chris Bache: It's a pleasure to
be with you, Christian.
Christian Yordanov: All right,
so we have a lot of ground to
cover in a relatively short
space of time. So what I would
like to do is to start with, I
would like if you could please
tell us what were you up to
between the years of 1979 and
1999 and maybe introduce us to
your journey. Uh, into uh,
exploration of your
consciousness, but also in
parallel. If you could kind of
tell us how your career
progressed during this time. So
if you could kind of tell this,
I know it's a parallel story
that you lived almost two lives,
if you could kind of show I must
there,
Unknown: yeah, be glad to I came
out of graduate school in 1978 I
was trained as a philosopher of
religion. I was raised in the
Deep South, got my PhD from
Brown University. I had finished
my dissertation, had done some
published part of my
dissertation, and I was looking
for where to take my research
next. As a young academic, I had
no experience in psychedelics
whatsoever. At that time, I was
30 years old, and I encountered
the work of Stanislav Grof. I
read his book, realms of the
human unconscious, which was
published in 76 and as soon as I
saw his work on psychedelic
research, I immediately
recognized that this was an
important development, not only
for psychology, but for
philosophers as well, that he
had a method for giving us
experiential access to
dimensions of mind and
dimensions of the Universe that
many people have talked about
and theorized about, but not
many people have had direct
access to so i made a choice at
that point. I was not
comfortable with the choice, but
because LSD was illegal, and his
work was primarily centered on
LSD, at the time, because it was
illegal, I divided my life into
into two parts. In my daytime
job, I worked as a philosophy as
a professor in the Department of
Philosophy and Religious
Studies. I taught courses on
world religion, psychology of
religion, Buddhism, comparative
mysticism, Transpersonal
studies. And in my personal
life, I began a 20 year journey
exploring working with LSD in a
systematic, rigorous manner,
using Stan Grof protocols. I
over the course of the next 20
years, as I progressed through
the academic world, I did 73
high dose LSD sessions,
completely internalized,
completely protected with the
sitter using the traditional
formats, private, safely
protected from the world with
the assistance of a sitter who
kept me safe and secure during
this process, and I basically
began across this process and
found that it engaged me
systematically into a deepening
and ever deepening exploration
of my own consciousness, and
eventually into a consciousness
that was so large, so vast,
where some people, where I you
could describe it as the the
consciousness of the Divine, but
I often just refer to it simply
as the the mind of the universe.
So while I continue to teach,
and I love teaching, I love
being with the students teaching
in these areas, I basically
developed this second life, and
it wasn't until after I retired
from the university and after I
was passed the statute of
limitations for working with
these what our culture deserve
called illegal substances, that
I was really able to begin to
share the full scope of the
experiences that I had had on
this substance and To extract
some of the philosophical
implications of these
experiences,
Christian Yordanov: right? And
so that was a 20 year journey
that ended in 1999 How did your
career progress over those 20
years?
Unknown: Oh, in a very
traditional manner. I mean, I
was progressed, I mean, promoted
up the ladder as one's does. I
published through the process. I
won two awards at the University
for my teaching. I love
teaching. Love being with the
students. I did the things that
an ordinary professor does. I
worked on committees. I did all
the things that you do at a
university in a department. My
department is a comp. Was a
complex department filled with
philosophers and Religious
Studies professors whom I became
dear and close who became my
dear and close friends over the
course of time. Yeah, it was
just kind of a traditional
academic career,
Christian Yordanov: and you had
three kids along the way, yeah.
So we could say you led a
productive life, contributing to
society. So which I think is
important, because I think
there's still this stigma.
People recoil when they hear
someone, even a learned person,
an academic is. You know, did
stuff with psychedelics. They
recoil. And think of this
person, you know, they'll never
be a productive member of
society. And it's quite the
contrary. So along the way
around, I think 1990 you
published your first book, life
cycles. Could you please tell us
what life cycles is about?
Unknown: Life cycle is about
reincarnation. When I was on my
first sabbatical and I could
only write books during my
sabbaticals, I had been
researching reincarnation when I
when I met Stan grofs work. I
also met the work of Ian
Stevenson, professor at the
University of Virginia, and his
work convinced me that there was
he had collected empirical
evidence that reincarnation was
a simple fact of life. It's
simply something nature is
doing. This completely jarred
me, because reincarnation had
not been a serious part of my
academic training. It was not
part of my education in western
religions, which is where I
spent most of my academic life
training, nor in philosophy of
religion or the scientific study
of religion. But here it was,
this massive body of evidence
collected. He's collected
evidence from children all over
the world, from different
cultures who have spontaneous
recall of their previous
lifetime. 90% of the cases he
never publishes because they
don't meet the highest standards
of scientific investigation, but
about 10% of his cases are very,
very important and substantive
cases, indicating that these
children have an accurate and
documented recall of their
previous life. So I wrote life
cycles, after teaching about
this material for years and
introducing it into my students
for years, I wrote this book
basically which begins with a
review of the evidence for
reincarnation coming from Ian
Stevenson and supplemented by
the research coming from past
lives therapists who were
writing a number of very
important works at the time.
Then I explored, once we had
that evidence in place, I
explored what the implications
of the evidence were. What What
difference does it make if we
are growing up in a universe
where reincarnation is a simple
fact of life, so that was the My
First Project. It ruffles some
feathers in my department,
because they weren't expecting a
book like this, but it's gone on
to be published in six
languages, and it became a
staple in my courses, and it's a
very easily accessible and yet
academically sound investigation
of reincarnation.
Christian Yordanov: Yeah, it was
sold out. I've been trying to
get it from Amazon for a while,
but you in your book, I believe
you published in 2001 dark
night, early dawn in chapter I'm
actually got that book a couple
of weeks back, I've been slowly
going through it. It's, you
know, it's, it's definitely,
yes, it's not the kind of book.
It's not a light reading book. I
read it in the mornings when,
you know, my brain is still, you
know, optimal. But um, in
chapter two, you you nicely
summarize the, you know, the
stuff you talk about in life
cycles, which I really
appreciate, guys like you that,
judging from the books behind
you, you know, you read books
and then present the information
to us in a digestible manner,
which I really, really
appreciate. But what was
interesting is that in the cases
of the children who remember
their past lives, it seems like
the average period between lives
is something around two and a
half years, but when people do
past life regression therapies,
it was some somewhere more
around 4050, years, which I
think was Pretty fascinating,
because to consider the
implications of your soul or
your being being in between
bodies for such a long period of
time in these dimensions, It's
unfathomable the amount of
learning and development that
could be going on. So that's
just really fascinating. And I
was actually aware of Ian
Stevenson's work before that, so
you know, you don't have to
convince me. But for folks that
are just kind of hearing this
for the first time, Chris has a
really good YouTube video that
I'm going to link in the
description of this episode
where he talks about, I think
it's about 35 minutes that you
basically present Ian Stevenson
work and then some past life
therapists, accounts of that,
and some books. So there's a
really good resource there on
YouTube.
Unknown: And thank you. And the
important, really
philosophically, the important
aspect of reincarnation
research, I think, is that it
invalidates our dominant
paradigm about consciousness
and. Our dominant thinking in
our culture, university culture,
is that our minds are produced
by our brain. So our brain is
the core reality, and it gives
off a glow, which is our mind
and reincarnation. It
invalidates that, because if
there is any period of time
before, between the death of one
personality and the birth of a
second personality, and there is
an organized transfer of
memories from one life to
another. Then there has to be a
dimension of reality where
consciousness can exist
independent of a physical
substrate of the brain
underneath. And that tells us
that the universe is much more
complicated. Has many more
layers to it than where we have
traditionally thought up to this
century.
Christian Yordanov: Exactly that
is beautifully said. So this is
where things like LSD,
Psilocybin, certain other
entheogenic compounds,
psychedelics, if we want to call
them, they seem to be able to
allow us to tap into these
dimensions. They seem to like
open up the gates. So with that
said, Can you, Chris, can you
tell us? You give us an
overview, I suppose, of Stan
grofs work, what he contributed
to the Transpersonal field. He,
in a sense, you know, is one of
the founders of the
Transpersonal field. But can you
tell us what happens to an
individual? What happens when
one takes a normal dose of LSD,
let's say, and what happens when
a person consistently brings
themselves into that state, and
what happens when someone takes
high doses consistent? Can you
basically tell us, you know,
discuss the phenomenology,
talking about psychodynamic,
Transpersonal, perinatal, as
Grof laid it out. And then the
contributions you added on top
of Grof s paradigm generally,
and then what you experienced in
your journey, please.
Unknown: Yeah, well, Stan
differentiated in his work. Stan
Grof differentiated between low
dose and high dose psychedelic
therapy. First, we have to
understand in psychedelic
therapy, you're not taking a
psychedelic and engaging the
world. You're not taking a
psychedelic and going to a
concert. You're going into a
highly protected, sheltered
environment, protected from the
outside world, completely
focused internally. You're
wearing eye shades. You're
listening to very carefully
selected music, the whole focus
is on and confronting whatever
is emerging in your mind and
letting it take you where your
mind wants to go. Our
understanding is that LSD and
other psychedelics basically are
amplifiers of consciousness.
They don't take our
consciousness in a particular
way. They simply amplify
consciousness. And so they make
dimensions of our mind which are
far removed, more available to
us. And so when you amplify your
consciousness, and then you sit
in a contemplative manner, and
you focus on what's emerging in
your mind, what often happens is
that your consciousness will use
this opportunity to cleanse
itself, to purify itself, to
empty itself of problematic
experiences that it's carrying.
So we would describe this as
confronting the shadow.
Basically one begins to confront
all the things that worry you,
that scare you, that terrify
you. One confronts things coming
from earlier in one's life, from
childhood, things that have
happened, traumatic experiences,
all the way back to your to your
infancy, all the way back to the
womb. If one continues this
process, the mind reveals that
this is working with low dose
therapy somewhere on the order
of 50 to 150 maybe 200
micrograms. So if you keep this
process up, and you go back into
deeper and deeper levels of your
life. Eventually, one gets into
what Stan calls the perennial
level of consciousness, where
you begin to confront the
deepest fears that all of us
share. They're not personal,
they're kind of universal, the
fear of death, the fear of what
happens to us when we die, the
anxiety over whether there is
any ultimate meaning or purpose
to our life since we die, since
everyone we love to dies,
everything that we care about is
destroyed. Is there any larger
purpose or project? And one goes
through the Death-Rebirth
process, which often. Involves
curiously reliving one's birth,
and what emerges over time is
that you are transcending the
limits of your physical
consciousness. So we get here by
being born. We leave the
physical world by dying, and so
the birth and death are all
complexly intertwined in the
psyche, so when one is pushing
beyond the limits of your
physical memory, of your
physical being, physical
consciousness, one is involved
in reliving how you got here, as
you transcend out of here, going
into states of consciousness
which transcend physical
reality. And a critical piece of
this is going through what Stan
calls ego death, which is to
say, your physical personality,
your body, mind, ego dissolves,
and you experience a loss of
control and a death at that
level. And then when that
process has completed itself,
one awakens inside a spiritual
reality, inside a deeper level
of existence. And then, if you
go, if you continue this
process, one begins to go deeper
and deeper into that spiritual
reality through the various
levels of Transpersonal
consciousness, which stand
identifies as the psychic,
subtle and causal levels of
consciousness. Now, a different
protocol was developed later for
working with terminally ill
cancer patients. This is these
are patients that were not
trying to be healed. These are
people who are going to die. And
they developed a high dose
strategy working with LSD in
high doses, somewhere between
305 100 micrograms. And the goal
here, this was at the Spring
Grove Hospital in Maryland. The
goal here was not to digest all
the different aspects of one's
personal shadow and personal
consciousness, but to break
through that, and to give these
people an experience of
Transcendence, essentially to
give them a glimpse of where
they were going to be going when
their body dies. And it was very
successful, it had a tremendous
impact, a positive impact on
death anxiety. So what I did, I
came along, and I'm not a
psychologist, and I wasn't
really interested primarily in
the clinical aspects of this
work. I was a philosopher, and I
was interested in exploring the
deeper dimensions of
consciousness that this work
made possible. So I and in the
early high dose therapy, the
sessions were limited to three
sessions. That was the maximum
that any one person could do. So
I thought, Okay, if you can do
three high dose sessions safely,
then you should be able to do
more than three safely. After
three sessions of working with
lower doses, I chose a regimen
of working with high doses of
LSD, partly for efficiency,
partly because it was a dual
career marriage, it was hard to
find time to schedule one
sessions, and so I I was still
thinking in terms of this being
a personal transformational
process. Was thinking in terms
of clearing out my personal
karma so I could get to
enlightenment faster. I thought
if you worked with higher doses
and you really confronted your
shadow conscientiously, you
would basically be able to
dissolve your karma. It was like
eating a meal, taking bigger
bites out of your karma in every
session. Eventually, this whole
model exploded as my work
continued to deepen, because
after about three years of work,
I was entering dimensions of
consciousness and was
confronting levels of shadow
which far transcended my
personal shadow or anything
related to my personal life, I
was tapping into the collective
unconscious. So what I did to
back up a little bit. What I did
was to do 73 high dose sessions
extended over 20 years. I worked
for four years. I stopped for
six years for reasons that I
give in the book. And then I
continued for another 10 years.
I was doing about, on average,
about five sessions a year. So
every two and a half months or
so I would be doing a session.
And what I found was that
I went through repeating cycles
of death and rebirth, about four
or five cycles of death and
rebirth. And I found that every
that the deep spiritual reality
or Transpersonal reality has
levels to it, many layers to it,
and every time you enter a
deeper level of spiritual
reality or Transpersonal
reality, you have to go through.
Another act of surrender. You
have to let go of your identity
at a deeper and deeper level. So
you go through a series of death
and rebirth experiences. I also
found that each level of
consciousness operates at a
higher level of frequency, so to
speak, it's a much more intense,
energetic level. So it's like,
if you're climbing a mountain,
you have to adjust to higher and
higher levels of altitude, and
you have to acclimate
systematically to that higher
altitude. In this in in mountain
climbing, you're adjusting to
less and less oxygen. In
psychedelic work, you're
adjusting to more and more
energy. So you have to
acclimate, literally, for your
consciousness to stabilize and
have coherent experiences at
these deep levels of reality.
You have to go through not
simply a death experiences, but
experience but you have to go
through a purifying purification
process, you have to empty
yourself of different levels of
your being that in a sense, or
operate at a lower level of
frequency. And if you don't do
this, your experiences at these
deep levels will not be
coherent. They will be
fragmented. You can touch into
these levels, but you won't be
able to maybe recall them. You
won't be able to remember them
consistently, and you won't have
coherent experiences of these
levels. But if you engage them
conscientiously, if you gave
engage them with focus and
determination, my experience has
been that your consciousness
goes through this self
purification process, and your
your awareness at each level of
consciousness gets clearer and
clearer and clearer, so that you
become operational at a deeper
level of reality. And if you
keep pushing the boundary,
sooner or later, you're going to
reach the border of that deeper
level, you'll go through another
purification process, another
death and rebirth process, and
they'll be thrown into yet
another level of reality that
operates by different
principles. It's governed by
different physics, so to speak,
and the process continues. So
basically, that's what I did as
a philosopher. This was the
philosophical adventure of a
lifetime, the opportunity to
explore the the universe or the
mind of the universe, through
exploring, through using the
vehicle of my own consciousness.
Because what I discovered, in
contrast to contemporary thought
that our consciousness is not
individualized. It's not like we
are a an atom, that everything
in my mind is simply a result of
the experiences of my personal
body. What I discovered is what
many spiritual traditions have
taught and many Transpersonal
explorers have discovered is
that the bottom of our mind,
that there actually is no bottom
to our mind, that when you go
deeper and deeper and deeper in
your individual mind, you open
up into the ocean of
consciousness. You open up into
an infinite ocean of
consciousness. So it truly is
the case that our individual
mind is like a wave that arises
out of an ocean of
consciousness, and if you
penetrate this wave, you will
drop into this infinite ocean,
which doesn't dissolve you
immediately into oneness, but it
dissolves you into the ocean,
and the exploration continues.
Christian Yordanov: That's
awesome. Now, just to go back to
the, let's say, the more
beginning parts of the journey,
and this is something that Grof
talks about a lot, is the
initial stage of working with
LSD people generally explore or
go into the perinatal level, and
this is where various traumas
surface all the way, including
all the way back to birth
trauma. But you, in your in your
in dark night, early dawn, and
in LSD and the mind of the
universe you make you have a
great analogy of explaining the
COEX systems as the dialog or
the emotions of a protagonist in
a novel. So with that said, Can
you give us a deeper overview of
what the perinatal level
actually is, because generally
this is kind of the first thing
that people you know had get
head on with in their LSD work.
What is the perinatal level?
What are the what are coax
systems? What are the four
phases that Grof. Discusses and
what is the therapeutic
potential of allowing yourself
to kind of getting that level
and we experience those, let's
say emotions,
Unknown: a coax system, is a
system of condensed experience.
So what we find is that, you
know, the psyche organizes its
memories in many different ways,
but one of the ways it organizes
them is that it groups all of
our life experiences according
to its emotional content,
according to its emotional
themes. So the analogy I give in
the book is imagine if you took
a novel and you underlined all
the passages that have to do
with fear in yellow, and all the
passages having to do with the
protagonist experience of greed
in green, say, and anger in red.
And then you cut up the book,
and you took the protagonist
experiences and all you grouped
all the green in one pile, and
all the yellow in another pile,
and so on so forth, that you
would have all of their
experiences of fear clustered in
one pile. And something like
that happens in the psyche, that
when you when you encounter your
shadow, you encounter your
shadow in these clusters of
condensed experiences. So you
often get into it feels almost
like a tornado. There's just so
many layers and layers to it,
and the outer layers are the
most recent versions of those
experiences. And as you get into
the center of the coax system,
you get into the more and more
elemental layers, until
eventually you get to the
fundamental core, the original
trauma, the original
disturbance. And when you in
going through this process, you
peel these Coex systems over
time, and then eventually, when
you get to the core, you relive
the core trauma. And when that
happens, the entire Coex system
has been dissolved, and so its
influence on your life has
basically been emptied. So you
can, you melt all your
experiences related to fear, you
melt all your experiences
related to anger, so on and so
forth. Now what Stan found is
that there are Coex systems that
relate to things that happen to
you after you're born, but there
are also Coex systems that seem
to be rooted in the very act of
birth itself, so that the act of
being born is a traumatic
experience. Here, the fetus is
floating very peacefully and
comfortably in the womb,
assuming that the mother is
taking good care of herself and
her child in the gestation
process in pregnancy, but then
all of a sudden, that
environment becomes hostile. The
water breaks, and the womb
begins to contract, and the
child begins to be put under
enormous pressure, which bills
and bills, until eventually it
climaxes, and the child being
released from this pressure into
a new environment with its
mother and father, that and Stan
broke this process. He found
that there were kind of four
stages of this process, and he
labeled these the four perinatal
matrices, which are coax systems
that are rooted in the perinatal
level of consciousness. And so
they're the the first one that
usually appears. They appear in
different orders, but often the
one that usually appears could
be correlated with the beginning
of labor, where there is
contractions, but no place to
go. The cervix hasn't been
dilated. Then there is
intensification of these
symptoms of contraction, but the
cervix is now opened and there
is a place to be to go. The
Death-Rebirth struggle begins.
This culminates in the final
expulsion from the Mother, the
experience of death and
liberation, and then the
experience of beatific bliss,
perinatal matrix, one of oceanic
bliss and ecstasy. And so what
we find is, if you kind of step
back and look at many people's
experiences who have gone
through this level, what we're
finding is is that people are
basically confronting and
digesting their entire life as a
physical being, their entire
life as a human being. They are
digesting the experience that
brought them from another
reality into time and space, and
so this is part of the process
of basically allowing your
consciousness to expand beyond
the limits of your physical
identity. So you shatter your
physical identity, but you
dissolve all the constant.
Relations of stress and
traumatic experiences and
anxiety that are involved in
being born at the physical
level, and then you open up into
the world that lies beyond the
physical level. But then the
process doesn't stop there. It's
not simply a matter of getting
into physical into spiritual
reality, but then it's a matter
of going deeper and deeper and
deeper into what appears to be
an infinite and unlimited ocean
of possibilities.
Christian Yordanov: Yeah, you
really, really described that
really well. So it's a very
obviously, the experience of a
psychedelic is a very complex
but we have what you just
described as the perinatal
level. So we also can consider
the psychodynamic level. So you
know, lower doses psycholytic
therapy may elicit more
psychodynamic experiences where
you know the people in your life
and your own emotions, so you
this perennial level goes
deeper. So what then happens
when you, I guess, overcome or
dissolve these coax systems or
these kind of this birth trauma,
when you actually overcome all
of that, what happens then?
Unknown: Then you open up into a
process of remembering who you
are, really, who you are,
underneath your physical
incarnation, who you are,
underneath all your physical
experiences, there is a process
of engaging what you might think
of as the deep structure of the
universe. Now, of course, one
way of in order to understand
what really happens in these
sessions, you have to understand
what's happening in life,
normally, naturally, and that is
reincarnation, for me, is a
simple fact of life. So
reincarnation tells us that when
we die, we expand into another
universe, and then when we're
born, we contract into our egoic
identity. At the end of that
life, we expand into another
universe, and then we contract
into a smaller egoic identity.
And this process goes on over
and over again, century after
century, millennia after
millennia. What seems to happen
when you work with an amplifying
substance like LSD is that you
accelerate that process and you
deepen the process. So in a
sense, you when you go through
ego death in this process, you
go through a death experience,
which is truly terrifying. It
really does feel like you are
physically dying. It feels like
you are absolutely losing
control. You've lost control of
your life, and you're going to
die. And there is a fundamental
way in which you do
psychologically. You do die, but
when you die, you don't simply
cease to exist. You actually are
reborn into the deeper
landscape, into the deeper
tapestry of of consciousness,
and so you begin to explore the
world that you enter when you
die physically. So that's why
there's a it's a strong
correlation between people's
experiences with deep
psychedelic work and people who
have near death episodes. So
people who sort of suddenly have
a heart attack or something
happens and their body stops, or
their body almost dies, and
their consciousness explodes
into a deeper dimension for
minutes at a time, and then they
come back talking about this
other world that they had
contact with. And something like
that happens with LSD work that
you basically more slowly shake
off your physical identity and
open into this deeper, spiritual
universe. And if you return to
that over and over again, again,
working with very, very I mean,
I worked at 500 to 600
micrograms every session, very,
very high doses of LSD. Now this
is not a protocol that I
recommend. I do not recommend
that people do this for reasons
I give in the book, but that's
what I did. And those
experiences kind of replicate
the the entry, the experiences
that people who have near death
episodes have you enter into
this deeper dimension. You see
yourself. You see your life on
earth from the spiritual
dimension you you begin to have
contact with the way the world
is organized in spiritual
reality, that there is a
structure. Culture to it, that
there is an organization to it,
and there is a there is a
relationship, actually kind of a
it's almost like a relationship
of physics. There is a
relationship between the way the
spiritual world is organized,
and it is the spiritual world
which gives birth to the
physical world. I mean the Big
Bang, everything that exploded
into existence 13.7 or 13 point
8 billion years ago, the entire
intelligence and all the energy
and all the power and the
unfolding which takes place, all
of that came from somewhere. It
came from some reality that is
not physical. Physics stops at
that point and says, We can't go
any farther. But in deep states
of consciousness, you can go
farther. You can enter into the
reality that gave birth to the
physical universe. Okay, that's
when you begin this. I think of
it as a, first of all, a
communion. It's because when you
enter this reality, you don't
take your ego, you know, cleaned
up, buffed up. You don't take an
ego into this reality and have
an experience of that reality.
You literally dissolve into that
reality. You lose your sense of
a small reality, and you
dissolve into this larger
reality. And for the hours that
the session takes place, you are
dissolved into that reality. And
then, of course, the drug wears
off, and slowly your
consciousness shrinks back into
your ordinary state. And if
you've worked well, if you've
really created optimal
conditions for this engagement,
you come back with accurate
memories, with strong recall of
where you've been. And it's
important to write down your
notes from your session. Within
24 hours, I had followed a very,
very strict procedure that
within 24 hours of every
session, I wrote a detailed,
accurate description of exactly
what happened in this session,
because this window closes, and
if you wait five days, a week, a
month before you write it down,
you're not going to remember
everything as exactly as you can
when you first come back. And
then, if you do this over and
over again, you begin to get a
very coherent travelog of your
experiences in this deeper
reality. And what I found was
that when you approach the deep
the mind of the universe in this
systematic fashion with the
desire to know, a desire to
understand. And you're asking
it, teach me. Show me what is
real. Show me what is there that
literally, this consciousness is
massive, infinite consciousness
takes you in, and it begins a
systematic process of initiating
you of teaching you what's going
on in this deeper reality.
Christian Yordanov: There was a
couple of questions that came
into my head as you started
speaking, but I think what is
clear is that drugs like LSD can
certainly accelerate one's
spiritual practice, but it's
also very easy to as you write
in your work, it's very easy to
think you have accomplished more
than you have in a single
session. What would you say are
some of the most important
practices that, other than
keeping meticulous notes, of
course, and analyzing your
sessions, what other practices
allowed you to contain these
experiences and embody them on a
day to day basis?
Unknown: Yeah, that's an
important question, and it's a
very important issue, because
stabilizing these states of
consciousness and integrating
your experiences in your earthly
life are a real challenge. What
we're finding is that it's not
that difficult to break through
into these dimensions, but to
hold on to them and to integrate
them, first of all, just to
remember them, and then to try
to integrate them and to
incorporate the teachings into
your life is a very, very
important part of the work. So
it's like half of the work is
getting out, and then half of
the work is getting in and
holding on to one of the ways
that this was expressed in my
sessions, that spirit said,
there's the dying of seeing and
the dying of keeping. The dying
of keeping is the integrating of
these experiences. So during all
the years when I was doing this
work, I was doing spiritual
practice. I mean, I was
basically doing meditation. I
was doing spiritual practice in
different traditions.
Eventually, my spiritual
practice centered in the vara
Ian. A Buddhist tradition. But
it began. I began with
Transcendental Meditation. I did
Vipassana meditation. I was
raised in a Christian tradition.
The teaching of Christianity
influenced me very deeply. I was
actually studying to be a priest
for four years when I was in
high school and early college.
So I absorbed deeply the values
of Christian compassion, self
sacrifice, so on, so forth. And
I also incorporated elements
from Eastern traditions. But
it's really very important for
lots of reasons, to have a
strong spiritual practice in
order to integrate and stabilize
the experiences that you have in
these short, very intense days,
because these psychedelic
sessions open you to vast fields
of awareness and knowing, but
They also open you to vast
fields of energy. And a daily
practice is really important to
be able to assimilate these huge
fluctuations, these tidal waves
of energy and tidal waves of
knowing that sweep through you,
and you have to have a context
to digest them, and slowly, you
know, roll them over in your
mind and hold them in your heart
and really digest them. So
grounding is really important.
So the grounding of a spiritual
practice, but other areas of
grounding, I mean, as I didn't
quite appreciate it so much at
the time, but when I got, you
know, at the end of my journey,
and was looking back, I really
appreciated that the stability
of my career and the stability
of my marriage and my
responsibilities as a father,
you know, every week I was in
the classroom, teaching my
courses, every day I was with my
children. Every day I was within
a primary relationship, a
relationship with my wife. So
these are very, very stable
grounding activities. I was
grounded as a homeowner. I was
grounded in my weekly lifestyle,
and that really provided me the
foundation that allowed me to
open up into these radically
Transcendence states and then
come back and hold them in a way
which didn't cause me to be
fragmented or didn't cause me to
be inflated, because one of the
great dangers of working with
psychedelics is psychic
inflation. You can think because
you've had a deep experience,
that you must be a very deep
person, or because you've had an
experience where you've touched
the divine, that you must be a
holy person, but that, of
course, is an illusion that's a
fool's delusion. What's because,
what's important in a
psychedelic session, in this
respect, is not what happens to
you on the day of your session,
it's what you can do in the days
following your session, when
you're back in your ordinary
state of consciousness. So you
may experience profound wisdom
in the day of your session, but
how much of that wisdom can you
really concretize and embody in
the weeks following your
session. So when you're raising
children, when you're married,
they really keep you grounded
and keep and they protect you
from being in having an inflated
sense of your value in the
universe. You know, in the end,
you're just a human being,
shoulder with shoulder with all
the other human beings in the
world, getting by in the world,
trying to do the best you can.
Christian Yordanov: Yeah,
that's, that's what I really
like about you. Seem to have
like zero kind of ego inflation,
despite the fact that you know
you've touched dimensions that
most folks, you know, they have
to live incarnate, many, many
lifetimes to get to that state,
you know, but I'm curious, if
you didn't have that many
responsibilities and that
weren't so busy with this and
that, how often would you have
gone into sessions if you could
have
Unknown: that's an interesting
question. Never never thought
about that.
I probably would have been
tempted to go more often, but
I'm glad I didn't, because I
found that going when you
completely blow your mind apart
and drink deeply from the power
and the knowing of the deep
universe, it's an extremely it's
not only a psychologically
demanding experience, but it's a
physically. Demanding
experience. It makes tremendous
demands on your body and on your
subtle energy system, on what
the on your the Chinese would
call your qi, or the Indians
would call your Prana. It's a
very, very demanding process to
open up your entire system and
close it down, open it up and
close it down. And that's one of
the reasons I really don't
recommend this particular
protocol. If I were starting
over again, I would do it very
differently. I would work with
lower doses. I would only
occasionally you work with high
doses of LSD. And because LSD is
a kind of psychedelic that tends
to push the cosmological
ceiling. It tends to sort of
push to the stars. I would
balance that with working with
other psychedelics like
Psilocybin or Ayahuasca, which
are much more kind of body
grounded, kind of states of
consciousness. They open your
system up, but you're much more
kind of grounded in your
emotional body, in your physical
body. So working with the
Psilocybin or body grounded
psychedelics, and occasionally
with the cosmic, logical kind of
high ceiling psychedelics, that
is, I think, produces, overall,
a more solid and secure journey.
But these are things that I
understand now. I didn't
understand these things when I
was doing this work. When I was
doing the work, it was like
pedal to the metal. Let's blow
it out, go as far as you can,
go, drink as much of it as you
can. And i think i i Not only
I'm glad I didn't do more
frequently than I did, because
it really takes time to
assimilate these material but I
think probably I went farther
than was healthy for one person
to do. Even though I followed
all the precautions, I really
paid a lot of attention to my
physical body, to stabilizing my
my my world, keeping everything
on an even keel, even so, I
think I bit off a bigger piece
of the apple than is wise to
chew. You know, it's just it
took me years and years after I
finished my sessions to fully
internalize them. And I don't
really think I've finally
internalized them, even now, I
think I'll be absorbing them for
the rest of my life. And I think
in deep ways, they have impacted
not only the remainder of this
incarnation, but they've
impacted the entire trajectory
of my soul's future
incarnations.
Christian Yordanov: Yeah,
talking about the toll that it
can take, just reading what a
session day was like for you, no
breakfast because of, you know,
the potentially impending
vomiting all day at it, and then
as soon as you're done, you're
up all night, documenting
everything, because you need to
get it on paper as quickly as
possible. So that sounds like
more demanding than partying out
on the weekend, going to, you
know, clubbing so very It's good
that you took good care of
yourself. Yeah, it is
Unknown: very demanding. And
what happens is when you start
to go past the early levels that
you might touch in parting and
you go into the deep levels, and
you don't start again at the
early levels. You start where
you stop. So it's like climbing
a mountain. You establish base
camp one, base camp two, base
camp three. You're working at
base camp three and above, these
are extremely high energy
experiences I found over the
years I had to take more and
more precautions. I had to take
more care of my body. I really
made sure that my body was in
good condition. I watched my
diet very carefully. I would
even I would have massage to get
my body nice and soft and
pliant, or do I'd go to the
chiropractor to make sure that
my body was aligned? Because if
you, if you take a body that's
out of alignment into these
states, you're going to feel the
pressure, pressures and pains
that are living within your
body. And in addition to that, I
was doing spiritual practice, of
course. And I would do very,
very intense practice for days
before my session, and I would
do very intense extra spiritual
practice in the days following,
because this opening is so huge,
you're tapping so deep into the
universe, it's, it's extremely
demanding, and so the demands
are not only on the weekend when
you're doing it, but on the week
before and the week after. And I
found that it took, you know,
the closing of that window. It
closes in stages. It closes
within 24 hours, but then it
closes at a deeper level within
three. Days, and it closes over
several weeks, and it really
takes about a month before it's
completely, absolutely closed
again. That doesn't mean you're
you're having psychedelic
flashbacks or anything like
that. It just means that your
entire system opens and closes
organically, and therefore
there's a there's an underlying
deep structure to that rhythm.
So you really, really have to
take care of your life at all
the different levels. And it's
not just, and I learned and that
it's not just impacting you,
because consciousness is like an
it's an ocean consciousness. You
know your life is like a
vibration within an ocean, and
are maybe thinking of it as a
lake. And when you do deep work
like this, when you engage and
set a deep ripple like that in
motion, it ripples out around
you in 360 degrees, and it
touches and influences the
people that you have karmic ties
to. So that I found that even
though my students never knew I
was doing this work, even though
you know, I never talked to them
about it, never shared this with
them, I found that some of my
students began to be activated
in ways that were directly
related to what was happening to
me personally in my session, and
that was what's happening, not
because I was consciously
willing it or I was letting I
was talking about it or
triggering it. It's hap was
happening simply because that's
the nature of consciousness. All
spiritual traditions teach this,
that when you engage these deep
dimensions, you don't just
influence your personal life.
You influence the lives of
reality around you, the people
around you. So I found that
integrating my sessions, taking
care of my person in the
sessions, was only one phase of
it. I also had to take care of
anyone around me who is being
impacted by this work. So there
is a social dimension to working
responsibly with psychedelics.
Christian Yordanov: I like I
like that you took it in this
direction because I was just
about to quote something from
your book, LSD and the mind of
the universe, right? So, just,
it's a So, basically, this is a
quote you cite from Marie Louise
von Frantz, a lifelong
collaborator of Carl Gustav
Jung. Jung had come to a similar
conclusion about the collective
import of deep, transformative
work, she wrote, whenever an
individual works on his own
unconscious, he invisibly
affects first the group, and if
he goes even deeper, he affects
the large national units, or
sometimes even all of humanity.
Not only does he change and
transform himself, but he has an
imperceptible impact on the
unconscious psyche of many other
people. So that's perfect. How
you describe consciousness as a
lake or an ocean, and we
literally send ripples, waves,
invisible waves that reach
potentially the ends of the
universe, if there ever were
such a thing. So with with this
in mind, could you take us
through what the say mid and
later stages of your journey
were like, What did you What
experiences did you start
having?
Unknown: Well, it took me about
two and a half years and 10
sessions to go through the
psychodynamic and Perinatal
levels and to go through my
first deep ego death experience.
And I was quite surprised at
what happened next. First, let
me back up in every session, as
this energy bills inside of you,
there are two phases to every
session. There's a cleansing
phase, which is then followed by
ecstatic phase. So there's a
purification stage, where you
begin to encounter really deep,
deep disturbances. And if you
surrender to that process, if
you don't flinch and back away,
but if you let yourself be drawn
deeper and deeper into this
pain, whatever it is, without
understanding it, you just go
into it. Eventually, this will
reach a peak, a culmination, and
you'll go through some type of
deep surrender, eventually into
another level of death. And when
that happens, you're drawn into
a very spacious place, a
transcendent place, where you
move into the ecstatic portion
of the session, where you have a
very positive and. And the
teaching continues at that
level. So what I was surprised
after I went through ego death
and I thought, Well, okay, I've
I've reassimilated much of my
own personal shadow, what
happened is that I entered a
period that lasted two years of
what I came to call the ocean of
suffering, I began to have
experiences of vast collective
suffering, and I was
systematically taken into the
suffering, stage by stage by
stage, deeper and deeper, until
eventually I was experiencing
hundreds of 1000s of human
beings, or stretched over 1000s
and 1000s of years, all of them
in massive pain and anguish and
anger and killing and
destruction. At first I thought
this represented a deepening of
my personal ego death. But
eventually, this kept on for so
long and involved so many people
that I began to understand that
what I was doing was engaging
some aspect of the collective
psyche of humanity, that not
only do individuals have Coex
systems where they consolidate
many, many years of experience
in these thematic clusters, but
that also applies to the
collective unconscious, that the
collective psyche, or the mind
of our species, has an
unconscious in which it stores
all of its unintegrated life
experiences. So all the trauma
of war, all the trauma of
droughts and famine, all the
trauma of the terrible things
that human beings have been
doing to each other, those
register and collect, not only
at the individual level, but
they register and collect at the
at the collective level. And so
eventually I came and it took me
a long time to accept this idea,
because it sounded like ego
inflation, even to claim it, but
I think Marie Le vow France is
right. When we do deep work,
personal transformation opens
into collective transformation.
We're working on behalf of
humanity. We're working on
behalf of the entire species,
and the healing which is taking
place as we were literally
draining the pain, not out of
the personal psyche, but we are
draining the pain out of the
collective psyche. And remember
that it's not like Chris Bache
is private. Ego is draining this
pain, but by this time, Chris
Bache has been shattered. My
consciousness is vast, and I'm
it's like the collective psyche
is draining the collective pain
out of the collective psyche.
This went on for two years. On
the positive side, when I went
through each session, I went
through a series of ecstatically
beautiful, powerful experiences
in one whole year, I began to
have experiences of experiencing
my life from beginning to end as
a completed whole, as a totality
that was finished. It was both
going to happen and had already
happened, and it gave me a deep
understanding of what my life
was about. And then for another
year, I was taken in a series of
initiations deep into the
universe, taken back into what
appeared to be the very
beginning of the universe, and
was given a teaching about the
evolutionary dynamic, which
eventually culminated in a
series of experiences about
where humanity is going, where
humanity is in its historical
development, what is the next
stage in its evolutionary
progression? But eventually the
ocean of suffering came to an
end. I went through this
profound final death experience
there, and I was catapulted into
what I came to recognize as what
I would call archetype of
reality. So there was a personal
reality, death, ego death, and
there was a collective reality
death. At this level, I was
catapulted into archetypal
reality, and I began to have
experiences which are very
unnerving in the beginning,
because I had the experience
that there is a level of reality
that is more real than time and
space, over and over again, when
I went back to this reality, I
was in a domain that was more
real than time and Space, and in
some ways, which was the
generative matrix, which
produces time and space. It was
like Plato's cave. You know the
man in Plato's cave, where he's
chained and he only sees the
shadows of reality reflected on
the cave, but eventually he
leaves the cave and encounters
the reality that's producing
these. Shadows. It is as if I
had entered a reality that was
producing the reality that we
know of as time and space, and
then I spent about a year and a
half exploring this dimension of
reality and having many
experiences of the collective
psyche, learning how the
collective psyche works,
learning how it is that all of
our individual minds are cells
within this larger tissue of the
mind of the species, and that
the species is part of the
larger tissue of the mind of the
planet, the mind of the
universe. I spent about a year
and a half exploring these
dimensions. And then I went
through another Death-Rebirth
process, and was catapulted into
what you might call the domain
of causal oneness. I was
catapulted into a level of
reality where all boundaries,
all divisions, all all divisions
became permeable, and I began to
experience the universe as a
singularity, as a single entity,
living and breathing As one, so
that everything taking place
inside physical reality were
simply small life forms that
were basically transparent to
the fundamental life of the
universe that's living within
it. It's like being experiencing
a forest where there are 1000s
of trees and hundreds of
different species of trees, but
you're experiencing the life
that flows through all of the
trees, the sun and the moisture
trees, and doesn't care whether
it's nurturing a pine tree or an
oak tree or, you know, doesn't
care. It's only the one. And I
had so I had many experiences of
oneness, experiences of what the
Buddhists would call a Shunyata,
emptiness of self, because when
you're experiencing the world as
one, you know that your
individual life doesn't have
private existence. Your
individual life, it is
individual, but it's open and
it's porous, and it it is a
you're breathing in and
breathing out constantly, the
larger reality of oneness. I had
experiences of the primal void,
the the primal matrix out of
which all reality emerges, over
and over again, microsecond by
microsecond from there, after
about a year in that reality, I
know I'm going very fast through
this material, but I went
through yet another death and
rebirth experiences, and I was
catapulted into a reality of
light. I had experienced cosmic,
cosmic light many times, but I
was catapulted in a domain of
light that was exceptionally
clear, just hyper, hyper, clear
dimension of consciousness that
was clear, crystalline, clear
beyond imagination. It is the
domain that Buddhism calls
Dharmakaya, the clear light of
absolute reality. I called it
the diamond Luminosity, the
domain of diamond Luminosity, an
absolute ecstatic.
Transcendent reality in that
over the last five years of my
work and 26 sessions, I made
contact with this reality, I
dissolved in this reality only
six, only four times, four times
in five years, in 26 sessions.
In between those four times, I
was going through again deep,
deep, intense purifications,
deep catharsis around just
purifying and purifying and
purifying in order to allow to
be allowed to enter back into
these hyper clear, hyper, pure
states of awareness. So I guess
I would differentiate five
different levels of reality that
I went through over all this
time. There's the personal
level, which culminated in ego
death, the collective level
where you're working basically
cleaning portion, some portion
of the collective psyche of
humanity, the archetypal level,
then the level of causal
oneness, and then the level of
the diamond Luminosity. It was a
long journey
Christian Yordanov: that is
absolutely fascinating, and I
would highly encourage folks to.
To check out the book or at
least some of your videos where
you discuss this in a little bit
more depth. Because, you know,
when we, when we look at folks
that have experienced near death
experiences, when we, you know,
we see what the what the Tibetan
Buddhists when they talk about
entering the Bardo of death.
They do discuss that we see a
light, but most of us are not,
say, developed enough to realize
that's our own essential nature.
So do you think this could be a
part of what the Buddha
experienced under the body tree,
this kind of experiencing this
light. What do you think these
experiences are something the
Buddhist, the Tibetan
meditators, these guys are
experiencing, getting into these
states after, you know, years
and years of meditation. Do you
think it's possible without?
LSD,
Unknown: it sounds arrogant, I
know to even suggest touching
into that which the Buddha
touched into, but I think it, I
think it is the cosmology of the
understanding of the universe
that emerges in psychedelic
states is basically the same
cosmology that emerges in the
great mystical traditions of the
world, the understanding of the
Bardo, the understanding of the
post death domain, the
understanding of the fundamental
union and oneness that underlies
all existence. We're tapping
into the same reality. And it's
really important to understand
first that when you're working
with psychedelics, you're
tapping into this reality in a
temporary manner. When you're
working with meditation and the
sort of slower contemplative
methodologies which take longer
to mature, you gain access in a
more abiding fashion to these
realities. So I don't want to
suggest in any way that my
experiences of these realities
were were comparable in terms of
their significance to the
experiences the of the great
spiritual masters of our
different spiritual lineages,
not at all, but even to have
temporary access to these
realities. Change forever. They
change your life forever. They
completely banish your fear of
death. They allow they revise
your complete understanding of
the world that you live in, of
how the world works. And also
these experiences are very
useful to use in your daily
meditation practice. That even
have temporary access to some of
these dimensions of real, of
reality, then can be used to
deepen and accelerate your daily
contemplative meditation
practice. So I think there is a
correlation there. I would place
the diamond Luminosity
experience in what the Buddhists
call extra Samsara reality that
is Samsara, is the world of
individual existence, the world
of cyclic existence. And so that
includes everything in the
physical universe, where
everything arises and falls,
arises and falls, but also in
spiritual reality. When you die,
you enter the Bardo, multiple
levels of reality where
everything is temporary.
Everything is it's much longer
than physical reality, but
still, everything is temporary.
That's part of the world of
reincarnation. But then it's
possible to go outside that
entire system, outside the
system of death and rebirth,
outside the reality of Samsara,
and I think that's what I was
tapping into in the diamond
Luminosity work, and that's what
is held as a possibility in all
the deepest spiritual
traditions. Dharmakaya is the
highest level of reality that
one taps into in the varana
Buddha's tradition, again, I do
not I'm not a mystic. I'm not an
enlightened being. Temporary
access is different than
permanent access all honor to
the great masters who have
abiding, permanent access to
these realities, but even just
to touch them temporarily is a
profound life changing
experience.
Christian Yordanov: Agreed,
agreed to know, and I like, I
like again that you're very you
know you exercise humility. But
I. I think it's, it's what they
do say, we all have the Buddha
nature, like the core of mind is
our, you know, our essential
nature. Yeah, I think the
Tibetans also call it Rigpa. But
we, if we, if we are all part of
this universe, which is, like
you say, it's all the divine, we
must have the spark of the
divine within us. So to be able
to access it, whether it's for a
second or a lifetime, is
certainly significant,
especially with with our current
egoic minds that have so many
layers, so many layers of of
complexity that obscure this
essential nature. So I think
it's, yeah, it's good that
you're humble, but these are
very important experiences. And
we know, we know there are some
research being done that
Psilocybin can induce a mystical
experience in people. And these
are very important things in our
especially in our world today.
And this is actually maybe,
let's go a little bit back from
the diamond Luminosity in terms
of you didn't make some before
we go
Unknown: quite there. Let me add
something that you just said in
my own sequence of experiences,
after getting contact with the
diamond Luminosity domain and
that extra Samsara reality, my
experiences actually pivoted and
began to lead to a deeper
internalization of that reality,
so that eventually it brought me
back into right here, right now,
my present life, my present
mind. And it uncovered this
Buddha nature, this essential
nature, which is right at the
very center of my mind and at
the center of all of our minds.
It is a hyper clear, transparent
reality, out of which all
emotions arise, out of which all
sensation arises, out of which
all thought arises. It neither
begins nor ends. It doesn't it's
not private. It's universal. It
is our essential nature. When we
tap it, we know that we're
tapping into the essential
nature of all beings. It, it
doesn't change. It doesn't
become better. It neither begins
nor ends. It has no boundaries,
and yet it is the most
fundamental level of our own
being, and to tap into it is
like finding diamonds in your
pocket. I mean, it's just the
most precious thing in the
world, and here it is, right in
the center of our own mind. And
it's impossible to be without
it. We don't pay attention to
it. Usually we don't rely on it,
but there it is. It's always
waiting for us. It's always
there. It's always nurturing us,
and it's patiently waiting for
us to turn our attention away
from the world outside of us,
back into the world that's
within us. And when we go deeply
enough, we find this extra
ordinary truth waiting for us.
And I want to differentiate you
don't have to go through all the
experiences that I went through
in order to find this. You know,
I differentiate the use of
psychedelics for spiritual
awakening, which is what we're
talking about here, and using
psychedelics for cosmic, logical
exploration, you don't have to
go through archetypal reality.
You don't have to go back to the
birth of the universe. You don't
have to explore the deep
structure of Bardo reality in
order to clear your life in a
way that allows you to have
immediate, daily access to this
fundamental nature that's living
inside of you that is what you
are at the deepest level. And so
I just want to make clear
Christian Yordanov: that getting
goosebumps,
Unknown: yeah, you don't. You
know it's like what I did really
is best described in terms of
the project of cosmic logical
exploration. I wanted to
understand the deep structure of
the universe. I wanted to
understand how things work. But
you don't have to go through
that in order to rest in your
own essential nature. That is a
much more kind of targeted
project in one spiritual
practice.
Christian Yordanov: Well, you
are, you know, a scholar,
academic philosopher, so it's, I
think most humans cannot
undertake what you did, even if
they wanted to. I'm sure there's
a few guys out there that will
follow, attempt to follow in
your footsteps. Steps, and you
know, God bless them, and best
of luck to them, you know, but I
don't think most people will
have the resolve to go through
to because a byproduct of your
experiences as as beneficial
they are to your souls.
Evolutionary trajectory. You've
also contributed a significant
amount of thought to, you know,
the Transpersonal field,
critical appraisal of the you
know, the near death literature,
the the reincarnation work. So
there's a lot of you've made a
great contribution as part of
your work, right? But, um, what?
There's a couple of there's
actually quite a few directions
I want to take it, but I'd like
to actually go back, because we
will definitely come back to the
light and the diamond
Luminosity. I feel like this is,
this is a topic that needs a
little bit more discussion
before we finish up. But let's
just go back to a little bit
earlier in the journey. So in
the book, I believe the chapter
was called The Birth of the
future human. So you did mention
a little bit about that. But can
you, can you tell us what
visions you had about the
trajectory of our human
evolution.
Unknown: Well, what I'm going to
describe now, I know sounds
fantastic, I know it sounds
seemingly arrogant to even
suggest that a human being can
have these kinds of experiences,
but I have no recourse except to
simply describe what happened.
And I think that chapter, the
birth of the future human, is
probably the most important
chapter in the book, and it's
the most surprising to me and
unexpected, because when I began
this work, I thought this was
about my personal
transformation, my personal you
know, whatever, whatever. But
what I found was as the work
deepened, once I reached a
certain point, once I about 23
sessions into the process, when
I would move into the ecstatic
portion of the session, I began
to be shown things. And what I
was being shown was consistent
session after session, starting
from the 23rd session, going all
the way to the 70th session.
Periodically, from time to time,
I would be drawn deep into what
I would call deep time. Deep
time is a level of of reality
where time behaves differently
than it does inside time and
space. I was taken outside
linear time into deep time, into
a not into eternity, not where
there is timelessness, but into
a deeper dimension of time
itself. And I was shown things
about where humanity had come
from and where it's going first,
I was shown that the entire
evolutionary project is rooted
in a profound cosmic love, and
that everything that's happening
to us inside time and space is
part of this process of
creation. And creation emerges
out of love, and it's always
suffused with love. And that, I
was shown over and over again
that humanity is coming to a
significant shift in its future,
a profound catharsis point, a
bifurcation point in its
history, and that we were on the
on the verge of a profound
spiritual awakening, a profound
transition in our history as a
species. It really was I began
to realize that nature simply
isn't trying to awaken
individual human beings. Nature
is in the process of awakening
the entire human species, that
there is something taking place
at the very core of our
collective psyche. And then,
once again, we're looking at a
species which is reincarnating
over and over again every 100
years or so every just you know
life pulsating with life,
pulsating with life, and that we
were evolving, not only
individually, but we were
evolving collectively. And I
kept being shown we're coming to
a turning point, a major turning
point, a profound awakening of
the human of spirituality within
the human heart, a profound
tapping into the oneness that
underlies all existence. Because
the ego is a magnificent thing.
The ego is beautiful. The ego is
individual awareness, but the
ego lives in. A divided reality.
So there's your reality, my
reality. Everybody's in separate
realities, but oneness is the
reality that we all emerge out
of. Oneness is our common core
reality. And there was coming.
It showed an explosion of
oneness within the human heart
and a society which is rooted in
oneness, in the experience of
oneness creates a different
social structures and different
social forms than a society
which is rooted in the Division
of ego. So I kept being shown
that there is this turning point
coming, that there was this
spiritual awakening coming, but
it never explained to me how it
was ever going to happen, how
this was going to take place.
And then in 1995 in my 55th
session, I went through what was
to me, a seminal experience. I
went through into deep time. I
went into the deep future, and I
went through the death and
rebirth of our species. I went
through, instead of ego death or
collective death, I went
through, I experienced a major
global crisis that was being
driven by ecological crisis
being driven by global climate
change and all the derivatives
of global climate change, but
which triggered a crisis in all
of our governing structure, all
of our economic structures, all
of our political structures that
basically this was a crisis that
was putting enormous pressure on
the human species and causing
enormous suffering for the human
species. I was experiencing
this, not as Chris Bache, but I
experienced it as the species
itself. I had dissolved into the
species mind. I experienced a
period of increasing loss of
control, inability to control
the outcome of circumstances,
inability to control the
circumstances of one's life.
Families being torn apart, just
a crushingly painful experience.
And what I saw, what I
experienced, or what I was
shown, was these experiences
were so widespread, it wasn't
like any other period of history
before. If there is a hurricane
that impacts one country or one
part of the world, it doesn't
touch the other parts of the
world, but this was an
experience that was touching all
the people on this planet,
wherever they live. And that
means it was registering not
only in their individual lives,
but it was registering in the
collective psyche itself, and it
was hyper energizing the
suffering that we were going
through was hyper energizing the
collective the field of the
collective psyche, and driving
it into what physicists would
call non linear conditions. So
physicists differentiate between
systems that are operating in a
linear mode. And then systems
which become so highly
energized, they operate into a
non linear mode. And when
systems are in non linear modes,
things can happen that can't
happen in linear conditions.
Small changes produce large
outcomes. Things can happen
very, very fast, and nature
pulls out from within it, higher
forms of integration, higher
forms that did not that were
always potentially present but
weren't there. Before I mention
this, because what happened in
the session is that as this pain
got worse and worse, we came to
a point where it looked as if we
were going to die. This was a
massive extinction event for the
species. But just when we had
gotten to that breaking point,
the storm as it were, passed and
we survived, and when we began
to pick ourselves up off the
ground, so to speak, and rebuild
our lives. We were different. We
had been changed. There was
something about this profound
catharsis, this profound
inheriting and shedding of the
karma of our past as a species,
something about the way this
trauma had broken us down and
forced us into
into a new openness of heart,
into a new depth of mind, into a
new depth of sharing with other
human beings. The way that
happens in a crisis. You know,
when there is a huge social
crisis, suddenly people are
helping each other, they're
working together. This was
happening, and it opened up a
future. I saw a future emerging.
I experienced a future emerging
where human nature had been
changed. Changed. It wasn't just
that our political system had
been changed, our industrial
system had been changed, but the
fundamental core of human nature
had gone through a pivot, and we
were now operating out of a
different collective psyche. We
were operating out of a
collective psyche that knew
things that previously only
advanced spiritual beings knew
we had access to the universe,
which paralleled the access that
the great saints and saviors of
history had had, but now it had
been sufficiently internalized
that had become part of our DNA.
So to speak, we were, we were
literally spiritually awakening.
We had awakened into oneness.
And when we began to move
forward, we built a different
society. This is what I came to
call the birth of the future
human. That's, I think, what's
happening in history we have
entered now the labor of
birthing the next iteration, the
next formation of the future
human. This future human has
been gestating inside us for
1000s and 1000s of years as we
live and die and live and die
and reincarnate again and again,
we have been growing and
developing and growing and
developing, but the ego still
tends to dominate our lives and
our choices. But it was as if in
this crisis, something
shattered, Something opened and
our our deep consciousness, our
soul consciousness, exploded
forward in the human psyche, and
we began to live out of a
different psychological basis,
and we began to create a
different world. And then later,
after this 55th session, in the
70th session, again, I was taken
deep into the future and was
given the experience of the
future human. I dissolved into
this archetype of the future
human. And if I try to describe
this being, I'll probably end up
crying, just because this being
is so magnificent. We are giving
birth to a new child in the
universe. This being was extra
ordinary, magnificent, a heart
that had been healed of all the
traumas of all the wars and all
the terrible things we've been
doing to each other at our lower
level of development, a heart
that was profoundly encompassing
and encompassed the whole
breadth of the human family, and
a mind that was profoundly
clear, able to download
information from the cot, from
the mind of the universe,
capable of knowing things, the
sustaining levels of awareness
that previously only great
geniuses and great spiritual
beings had been able to sustain.
This was an awakening which is
changing the very foundation of
life on this planet. This is, I
think, what we have entered. I
mean, I think the covid 19,
perhaps, is simply the overture
of a crisis which is going to
deepen as global climate change
impacts us at deeper and deeper
levels. We know we're going into
a hard time. We're nowhere.
We're going into a time of deep,
deep disruption. What's
important to understand, I
think, from a spiritual
perspective, is what's actually
taking place. What's actually
taking place is that we're in
the process of burning off a
huge amount of personal and
collective karma. We are burning
off the consequences of the
choices that we have been making
as a species, while we have been
operating out of a private
consciousness, out of an
individual consciousness, where
I can make my life better if I
push off the same pain and
suffering onto other persons.
But now we are beginning to
create a profound sense of
oneness consciousness, where we
are beginning to build a world
which truly does work for all.
This is a spiritual,
transformational process. It's
an evolutionary process, and
it's a process which is being
driven, not so much at the
individual level, individuals
are cooperating with it, but
it's being driven by the
intelligence of the universe
itself, just as it has driven
all the other quantum jumps that
have taken place in the
evolutionary process, it's
likewise now Taking humanity
into this deep jump in its in
its archetypal structure. We are
living in hard times, but we are
living in extraordinarily
important and times which will
lead to a magnificently
beautiful outcome if we do our
jobs well, if we really dig deep
and do our jobs well.
Christian Yordanov: Like you. I
think you like to say that we
chose to be here. Yes. When we
do more, we chose Yes. I think
Unknown: every human being on
this planet before they
incarnated in spiritual reality,
they could see what we were
getting into, they could see
what they were getting into, and
they chose to be part of it. So
there are no victims here. There
are just people, actors in a
place, so to speak, who made
conscious choices to be on this
planet during this time when it
is going through this
convulsion, convulsive period in
the end, when we die, we don't
die. I mean, we die clearly, and
there is mourning to be done.
But at a deeper level, the soul
doesn't die. And in a deeper
level, we come back, we keep
coming back, and we continue to
participate. And this is, this
is how life works. I mean, we
are going through a process, and
humanity will be here for
another, for millions of years,
for billions of years. Yet, I
mean this, we are evolving in
the life of the universe. We are
being taken somewhere extra
ordinary. And even though my
personal Chris Bache won't live
to see it, my soul will
participate it in sub in later
reincarnations, as we all will.
It's a it's a deep and because
we all chose to be here, I think
we can get we should get past
quickly the anxiety of being
here. We can simply roll up our
sleeves and get to work doing
the work that we chose to do
before we incarnated,
Christian Yordanov: and this is,
you know, perfect again, you set
me up perfectly for what I
wanted to discuss next. I've
been thinking about, you know,
death a lot lately, which for
many of my peers, it would be
like, what's wrong with you? Are
you depressed? But I think this
is such a such an important
thing to think about and even
more importantly, get over so
you can get on with your
mission, your intent that you
came with here. So I know you've
said this on in other places,
but I would like to share this
with my audience. What I and you
already kind of mentioned some
stuff. But how do you when you
think about your own personal
death as Chris Bache? How do you
think about that?
Unknown: Well, one of the
consequences of doing this work
is that I have no fear of death
whatsoever. In fact, death is
something I'm looking forward
to. I'm not eager to push it.
I'm not going to run off and
kill myself, but I have no fear
of it because I have already
tasted the world that I'm going
into when I die, and to be
afraid of death is to be trapped
inside the physical world, and
to be trapped in the illusion
that the physical world is the
only world that's real. When so
many areas of research are
showing us that this is just
simply not true. The physicists
have shown us that 96% of the of
the universe is invisible, dark
matter and dark energy. So only
4% of the universe is physical
matter is manifesting as
physical matter near death.
Episode. Research is showing us
again and again that when we
die, we enter an extra ordinary,
beautiful dimension we enter, we
return home, so to speak, to the
reality that we were in before
we incarnated. Reincarnation
research is showing us that we
go back and forth over and over
again between the spiritual
reality and the physical
reality, not because we're being
punished, but because we are
choosing to participate in the
conscious creation of this
species, in this conscious
universe, I'm not afraid of
dying. I look forward to it in
the sense that, of course, I
look forward to graduating. I
look forward to returning to the
domain of bliss. It's kind of
like when we're born. The hard
work begins when we die, we
graduate into into returning to
a deeper level of knowing, to a
deeper spiritual reality. Now,
of course, if you go through a
deep enough spiritual death and
rebirth in your physical life,
then you don't have to die in
order die physically, in order
to die psychologically. There
are beings, great beings, who
are in their physical body, but
they are complete. They are
already living the bliss of
spiritual. Reality inside their
physical existence. And I think
this is where we're going. We
literally are creating heaven on
earth in that by going through
our own developmental process,
we are physically alive on
Earth, but inwardly,
spiritually, psychologically and
even physically. In some ways,
we become so transparent to the
infusion of the spiritual world
that we are literally mingling
Heaven and Earth inside the
vessel of our physical body. So
that when we speak about someone
who is spiritually awakened or
spiritually liberated. Another
way of thinking about that is
they have simply become
transparent to the energies of
the spiritual universe. They
don't have to die in order to
die spiritually. They are
already living in the spiritual
world inside their physical
body. And when you have enough
of these experiences, when you
go through death and rebirth,
often enough, one of the things
you learn is that you can't die.
You're the essence of what you
are. Can't die. Chris Bache will
die. The shell, the shell of
Chris Bache will die. The
physical form will die, but the
essence of the individual does
not die. The essence of the
individual continues to live in
an even greater and more
luminous and more love soaked
reality. So if there were any
one thing that I wish I could
bring from my work and and give
it to people, it would be the
loss of the fear of death
Christian Yordanov: that's so
important. I think, yeah, now,
when you enter the Bardo and you
see the light, what do you maybe
this is an A question that you
cannot answer at the level of
Chris Bache. But what do you
think you will do when you see
the light, when you merge with
the light, when you become the
light you think you will ever
come back in human form?
Unknown: Well, I've decided to
put that decision in the hands
of the being that I will be
after I die. I have spent so
many days exploring the beauty
of that spiritual universe at so
many levels that naturally,
there is, in me, a profound
desire, even a need to explore
that universe more. And there is
a longing to enter more deeply
into this magnificent universe.
So naturally there is I would
rather be there than be here,
but I basically trust that when
I'm there, I'll know better than
I could know here. What would be
the best thing for me to do and
how to support our collective
developmental process than I can
know here. So I just have rolled
that decision into my into my
soul, into the consciousness
that will hold Chris's life and
merge it with all the other
lives that this soul stream has
had. And I'll let that decision
be made then twice.
Christian Yordanov: So just as
we wrap up, maybe let let the
listeners know why you decided
to stop your sessions in 1999
please.
Unknown: Well, as I explained in
the book, I stopped for two
reasons, one was pain and one
was heartache. Basically, as
I've mentioned, these
experience, these states of
consciousness are so intense,
they involve so much of a
increase of our energy, I found
that my my physical system was
was running very hot, my subtle
energy system was running very
hot. I was having more and more
difficulty integrating the the
sheer energy that it takes to
enter these states in my
physical incarnation, and I did
lots of spiritual practice that
helped. But in the end, I began
to understand that I was really
running too hot, and I need to,
needed to stop and let my my
body calm down, to let my subtle
energy system calm down. There
was no pathology. I was not.
Having any flashbacks or
anything like that, but I needed
to sort of cool down some, so to
speak. But that's not the main
reason I stopped. The main
reason I stopped was heartache.
Once you have known the joy of
dissolving into light, of
becoming light once you've known
the joy of dissolving so deeply
into the crystalline body of the
Divine, coming back into time
space, at least into the
incarnation that I have the
limitations of my present
incarnation, coming back into
this time space, reality it's
just painful. It's it's so
difficult to go from such
exquisite intimacy with Infinite
Being back into private, finite
existence. The going out and
coming back was getting was
becoming too hard, and
eventually I asked the universe,
and I called my beloved, I asked
my beloved never to take me back
this deeply until I could stay
with her forever. And that's
when I stopped the sessions. I
was surprised by what happened
next. I found that it took
years. I thought I had had so
many I'd been given so many
gifts, I'd had so many blessings
given me, that I could simply
stop my session step back, and I
had a wealth just to digest for
the rest of my life. But what I
found instead, well, that's true
that that's part of it, but the
other part of it was that I
found I had in me a deep and
profound longing to return to
these states of diamond
Luminosity, and I knew I I
couldn't return to them. I it
wasn't good for me to return to
them anymore in this
incarnation, I knew I would not
go back there again until I
died, and I could, if I took a
massive dose of LSD today, I
would not return to these
dimensions. It takes years and
years and years of sustained
work to develop the energy and
the momentum to enter these
states of being. So I knew I was
waiting until I my physical life
died before I could really
return. And there was a
tremendous unfulfilled kind of
longing for more communion as
long as I was returning to these
states periodically, once a year
or so, this imbalance had not
manifested. But once I stopped,
I realized that I was there was
an imbalance that I had created
between too much Transcendence
and not enough imminence. Now,
the entire physical universe is
the body of the Divine. It's not
like I was going into the divine
and coming out of the Divine,
but I was going into the
transcendent divine and coming
back into the physical divine,
into the imminent divine. And it
took me about 10 years to really
make my peace with this and to
really get completely
consolidated to being
comfortable and to be at peace
living inside the physical
universe again in my physical
condition. But I also discovered
that part of the sadness that I
experienced in ending my
sessions was that my culture did
not allow me to talk about these
things. I just, you know,
because psychedelics are
illegal, I couldn't talk about
it at the university. I'm a
philosopher, and I love to
teach, but I wasn't allowed to
do philosophy drawing from these
very important experiences. I
could not share them. I could
not talk about them. And if
you're not allowed to talk about
these deep and profoundly
important things, it tends to
make you sick inside. So for me,
finally giving myself permission
to tell the story of this
journey, to share it with other
people, not because, not because
I'm special in any way, but
simply that these experiences
might be useful to other people
in their own spiritual journeys
and their own social journeys,
that actually represented a
process of putting together the
two halves of my life that I had
separated. I had separated my
academic life from my spiritual
life, and now I was beginning to
put them together and to and to
bring myself into wholeness
again. So the heartache that I
experienced when I stopped my
sessions has begun to be
soothed, and as this integration
process has deepened in. Writing
of the book, and in the
beginning to have conversations
like the one we're having,
something interesting has been
set in motion. It is as if the
Divine is not waiting for me to
come back to it when I die, but
it is as if the Divine is
beginning to come for me here so
there is a deepening sense of
peace, a deepening sense of
permeability to the ever present
divine dimension of life, even
inside the nuts and bolts of our
physical existence.
Christian Yordanov: Beautifully,
said, Chris, I want to thank you
for your work.
Just I was going over LSD and
the mind of the universe over
the weekend, just I have almost
every third page in this book is
dog eared and the top is double
dog eared in certain places
where it's really important for
me to go back. I have a list of
probably a couple of dozen
authors whose work I need to
investigate that came out of
you. I want to thank you for
bringing them all to our
attention, for synthesizing
their work, for undertaking this
exploration of yours and
bringing it to the world. I
really want to thank you for
that, and I really appreciate
your time just before you can
tell us where to find you and
your work. Can you tell us, do
you what do you what in terms of
continuing your teaching? What
is your plan for the future? Do
you want to plan to run more
books, or you were saying
something about workshops?
What's your kind of plan for
next, whatever, few years?
Unknown: Well, I'll tell you
when I wrote LSD in the mind of
the universe, or, as I prefer,
the title diamonds from heaven,
I had a deep sense of closure. I
felt like I had finished my
life's work. I had done what I
was came here to do in sharing
this information, but I love to
teach. I love to be with the
people. Covid 19, of course, has
interrupted all of those things,
but I love to be with the
people, and I love to explore
these topics and conversations.
So I hope opportunities will
will occur. I look forward to
entering into retreats, to do
retreats with people, just to
have to open up the thought of
psychedelic conversations and
circle so that I can not only
talk about the experiences that
I have, but that other people
can have the opportunity to talk
about the experiences that there
have had, because clearly, all
of our experiences together are
more important than any one
person's experiences by
themselves. So I hope that to be
doing retreats, you know,
shorter retreats, longer
retreats, week long retreats.
I'm not sure how this is going
to materialize, but I hope that
after the pandemic kind of
eases, there will be
opportunities. I mean, I've
been, I don't I'm not very good
at self promotion, and I'm the
I'm kind of adverse to self
promotion, so I don't even have
a website developed yet, but if
people want to contact me, they
can contact me at the email
address. It's on the back of my
book. It's cm Bache, my initials
and my name@ysu.edu which is my
university email address, and
within a couple of months, my
website should be up, and the
name of that website will be
Chris bache.com so if someone
wants to reach me, they'll be
able to reach me there, and
they'll be able to keep in touch
with what teachings I'm doing,
where or what talks I'm giving
at Chris bache.com
Christian Yordanov: Awesome. And
your books can be found. Can you
briefly just summarize your
books? I know we touched on a
couple of them, but can you just
briefly see if we can pique
people's interest to explore on
their own?
Unknown: Well, there, there are
four books. Yeah, I hope there's
not more books coming. You never
know. The first book is life
cycles on reincarnation. The
second book is a book called
dark, night, early dawn, which
was published by the State
University of New York Press and
Academic Press. And it's a. So,
you know, it's a challenging
book. I mean, I'm really kind of
using all my academic muscle,
but I'm also beginning to share
my psychedelic experiences, and
I'm trying to integrate
psychedelic research, near death
episode research, and out of
body research, out of body
research, the work of Robert
Monroe. So I'm really kind of,
it's a major kind of exploration
of the implications of
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness. And then I wrote
a book called The living
classroom, because, as I
mentioned, my students were
being impacted by my own
psychedelic work, and I began to
understand that there are fields
of consciousness that grow up
around groups, and that it
wasn't simply that they were
having resonance experiences
with me, or that somehow I was
triggering these experiences in
them, but the groups of
learning, there were fields of
learning that were growing
around my courses and that were
influencing the learning of new
students as they entered these
courses. And so I wrote a book
called The living classroom,
which was also published by SUNY
press. And all these books are
available on Amazon. And then
finally, I've written LSD in the
mind of the universe, which
really is kind of coming out of
the psychedelic closet and
really laying out what has
really been the driving source
of inspiration behind all of my
work. Because even though I
don't talk about psychedelics in
life cycles, and I don't talk
about psychedelics in the living
classroom, once you know the
full story of my psychedelic
work, you can understand how
those books came out of that
work, and express that work, and
even though I integrate it with
all of the scientific research
and the philosophical research
that's present in those books,
experientially, the driving
inspiration came out of my
psychedelic work. There is an
academic work. Thank you.
Academia.edu. Is basically where
all of my articles that I've
published are can be found at
that website. It's so if you go
to academia.edu and just punch
in. Chris embache, you'll get to
a page where you have access to
all of my research.
Christian Yordanov: Yeah, we'll
have all the links in the
episode show notes. Um, yeah,
actually, just to in terms of
your, just to go back to your,
it's a great body of work,
because, like I said already,
you've synthesized so much. And
what we were saying before we
started is that bookcase behind
you, you actually gave away more
than half, I think two thirds of
your books after you retired. So
I said it to my girlfriend
earlier today. Said this guy I'm
interviewing today, not only is
he twice my age, but he's you
the books you and me have read.
This guy's probably right, like
100 times more books, right? So
it's, it's truly, truly an honor
to converse with you over the
last couple of hours. Thank you
so much for spending the time
with us, Chris and yeah, God
bless. Thank you.
Unknown: Thank you, Christian.
It's a pleasure, a deep pleasure
and an honor to be with be with
you and to be with your
listeners today, truly.
Thank you for listening to
connecting minds. We hope you
enjoyed this conversation and
found it interesting,
illuminating or inspiring for
episode show notes, links and
further information on our
guests, please visit
christianyordenov.com if you
found this episode valuable,
please share it with someone who
might also enjoy it. Thank you
for being here. You.