Joe Moore: You. Good. Hello,
everybody. Welcome back to
psychedelics today. Today on the
show, we have Chris Bache,
retired professor and Professor
Emeritus at Youngstown State
University and author of the
recent book LSD and the mind of
the universe. We're also going
to be doing a giveaway. So stay
tuned on that, Chris. Thanks for
joining us. Glad to be here,
guys. So I, I had been talking
about you, I think even a couple
years ago when I found out about
your, your kind of long term
project, before, probably the
book, was even with a publisher,
and I was really excited by the
idea, and then I just totally
forgot, and then all of a
sudden, we got connected, I
think, through the publisher.
And now I'm very excited to
record with you, because this is
quite the project you've
undertaken, and you've got some
very unique insights to share.
How do you how do you like to
start this story? Like, how did
maybe, maybe we can start with
psychedelics? How did
psychedelics come on your radar
initially.
Chris Bache: Well, I had just
finished graduate school. I was
publishing a few articles out of
my dissertation. I was looking
for where to take my research. I
was a brand spanking new
university professor, and I met
the work of Stan Grof, and
that's what really snapped my
head to attention. I did not
have a psychedelic history. I
was I finished graduate school
in religious studies as a pretty
deeply convinced atheistically
inclined agnostic, but I read
Stan's work, and light bulb went
off inside of me, and I said,
this is important, not just to
psychology, but it's important
to philosophy religion, which
was my training, and I wanted to
get involved. I wanted to do it,
but, of course, it had been made
illegal. So I split my life. I
in my ordinary day job, I
continued to function as a
professor of Religious Studies
in the Department, taught
conventional kind of courses, or
semi conventional courses. And I
began a 20 year, what became
eventually a 20 year journey,
working with LSD, following Stan
grofs paradigm, and then pushing
the limits of that paradigm
pretty far, much farther than I
appreciate it at the time. And I
was trained in philosophy of
religion, and so I kept careful
records, careful notes. Tried to
make the engagement as clean and
as productive as possible, and I
knew there would come a time,
sooner or later, when I would
share the experiences or share
the insights from the
experiences with a broader
audience. And after I retired
from the university, that time
finally came,
Joe Moore: perfect and what was
the first Did you have any kind
of previous, spontaneous,
mystical experiences or anything
before that? That kind of clued
you into how important these
things might be.
Chris Bache: I've always been
envious of people who have had,
you know, I was 12 years old, I
had my first spontaneous
mystical experience. That's not
the way it's been for me. I've
always been kind of deeply
locked into my body and my
physical experience. You know, I
I was reasonably well educated
in Western religious thought. I
became educated in Eastern
religious thought, in a broad
spectrum of contemporary
thought, but no, I had no
background. In many ways, I'm
the last person you would have
expected to write a book on deep
psychedelic states of
consciousness. It just, I mean,
I grew up in Mississippi. I got
a degree in theology from the
University of Notre Dame before
going on to graduate school. So
this wasn't part of my
background at all.
Kyle Buller: I'm curious. How
did you stumble across Stan's
work by not having any exposure
to psychedelics beforehand?
Chris Bache: Well, I was reading
widely in different areas. I was
reading and kind of emerging
Transpersonal psychology. It
interested me two people whose
work I met my first year out.
One was Ian Stevenson, whose
work at the University of
Virginia convinced me that
reincarnation is a simple fact
of life. And that was a jolt,
because it hadn't been part of
my education anywhere. And then
I met Stan's work, and he had
just published two years before,
realms of the human unconscious,
and that was the book that
really did it for me. And so Ian
gave me kind of empirical
evidence that there had to be
another dimension of reality,
other than the physical world,
because there, if there is any
time interval between the death
of one personality and the birth
of the second personality, there
has to be a place for them to.
This during that time, and Stan
gave me the methodology that
allowed me to the prospect of
exploring that reality. So I
just decided to go for it.
Joe Moore: So maybe next, like,
what? What did the protocol look
like to you? Like it to me, it
looks like a very clearly looks
like the work being done at
Hopkins and by maps now. But was
it any different in your
perspective at this point?
Chris Bache: No, I think it's
pretty much conventional in that
respect, you're always working
in complete isolation. You're
always working with a sitter,
you're always working with a
very carefully curated playlist
of music. The difference is,
after I did three medium dose
LSD sessions and then shifted to
working with very high levels of
LSD. So I worked at 500 to 600
micrograms. At first, I did it
simply for efficiency, because
it was hard to get time in a
dual career marriage for, you
know, arranging a session day,
and I wanted to make the most
out of every day. I also thought
it would get me to my early goal
of enlightenment faster, if I
could kind of chew through my
karma in bigger bites that
eventually is a project that
just dissolved along the way,
and the whole concept of a
personal spiritual journey, or
strictly personal evolutionary
project that fell out along the
way. So the difference, I think,
is the quantity, the part that
first the psychedelic used, very
different than Psilocybin or
mvma, working with very high
doses, which changed the whole
trajectory of the experience.
And then I basically began to
curate a much more aggressive
playlist with the music. I used
a lot more indigenous music. I
didn't use classical western
music. I use a much more
aggressive approach in the music
itself, but otherwise, very much
like contemporary therapeutic
approaches to psychedelics.
Kyle Buller: Yeah, huh, that's
interesting. I guess backtrack a
little bit too. So your book
really kind of covers these,
what is it? 73 high dose
session. So the like your book
is covering all these insights
of your experiences and some of
your philosophical work, and
really understanding
consciousness from these
experiences. So I don't know if
I forget if we gave that little
intro there. So that's just to
get some context of what we're
talking about and what Joe meant
about protocol of how you're
setting that up. And I'm curious
why did the music change over
time?
Chris Bache: I happened upon
some indigenous chanting music,
and I threw it into my session
on the next day or the next
week, and it had such a profound
impact on the intensity of the
session. It basically rattled my
cage much more aggressively than
some of the more even aggressive
classical music. I like the
effect I recognize that it's
sort of more disorienting, more
giving me stronger support for
going deeper into consciousness,
so I just began to cultivate and
collect that type of music.
Kyle Buller: Yeah, that's really
interesting. And from your
perspective, how important is
music when you're doing high
dose psychedelics or just
psychedelic kind of therapy and
that self discovery format, I
Chris Bache: think it's very
important. Now, I've done
sessions without music
eventually, after long down the
road, and I've done Psilocybin
sessions with and without music,
but in working with a very
strong psychedelic like LSD, and
working at these very high
doses, which, by the way, I
don't recommend, I truly do not
recommend that people do what I
did. I wouldn't do it the same
way if I did it today. But
basically, when you're working
with opening consciousness that
radically Musik is a has a
tremendously powerful effect, I
would maybe estimate it has a
concentrating, amplifying effect
by five or 10 times, doing it
without psychedelic but without
music. So I remember I started
using music only in the fourth
session, and the jump that
happened in that fourth session
was just enormous. So I think
it's very important.
Kyle Buller: Yeah, it's a topic
that keeps coming up, I guess,
within the psychedelic
community, especially when
talking about putting playlists
together for therapy. And I just
recently recorded an episode
with a fellow who composes music
and ended up taking his
experiences and making music out
of it. So yeah, I think the
music. Piece is just really
interesting. It's a huge part
of, you know, Breathwork as
well. Yeah, yeah.
Chris Bache: And Helen Bonnie,
of course, her early work
plotting the various stages of
an LSD journey and the
characteristics of music that
support each of those stages as
we go important work.
Kyle Buller: Yeah. So where did
this idea come from of wanting
to engage in this, these high
dose sessions? Like, did you
start off saying, I'm going to
do, you know, X amount of
sessions and really dive in? Or
did you go in saying, I'll have
a few and then see where it
goes? Or did you have this idea
kind of mapped out of doing X
amount of sessions, or had a
goal with it at all?
Chris Bache: No, I did not have
any trajectory or any goal. I
saw the range of experiences
that Stan described in realms of
the human unconscious. I saw,
you know, since I had a pretty
good grounding in western
philosophical thought and
theological thought. I had a
good sense of the significance
of these states of consciousness
that he was describing. And I
believe that the people who
would be making the most
important contributions in my
discipline would be speaking out
of an experiential basis in a
matter of years, not out of a
theory, simply a theoretical
basis. This was common in my
time. So I just, I knew that to
do that, you just had to get in
and do your work. And I had no
idea how long the work would be.
I was still thinking in the
early years that, you know, you
basically go through ego death,
and then you get unrestricted
access, you know, to the deep
consciousness of existence. What
I found, of course, is that it's
not matter simply of shattering
the ego and going through ego
death. The universe has many,
many layers. And while it's all
holographically integrated, in a
sense, if you engage the
universe systematically with a
carefully defined kind of
methodology, the universe takes
you in by degrees. It takes you
in by layers. And as you move
into a new layer of
consciousness, and your
consciousness stabilizes at that
new layer sooner or later, if
you keep pushing it, the method
you're using has sufficient
power to take you to the very
edge of that new layer. You're
going to go through yet another
death and rebirth process that's
different than ego death that
builds upon that process. And
you go through a series of death
and rebirth processes as you
explore progressively deeper
levels of consciousness. And at
least that's how it happened for
me. It may be different for
other people and different
substances, but how it happened
to me that there was a
systematic progression, entry
into communion with the
universe, and that's where I
laid out the book. I just
basically took it in, start at
the beginning, try to I tried to
describe, recognize the levels
of consciousness that I went
into consolidated the story to
make it as efficiently conveyed
as possible. And then each
chapter basically goes into
another level of consciousness,
or another level of engagement
with the universe.
Kyle Buller: How would you, I
guess, define that layer of
consciousness, like, like, What
do you mean by that, of getting
to these next layers? You know,
sometimes you hear in like, the
New Age, like, oh, you ascended
to 5d and maybe that's how, you
know, some people are making
sense of that. But how would you
describe that moving through
layers?
Chris Bache: Well, I adopted the
working vocabulary that Stan has
developed in his books, between
psychic levels, subtle level and
causal level. Consciousness
differentiates low and high,
psychic low and high, subtle and
low and high, causal and that's
a vocabulary that works for me.
Of course, the universe is so
deep and has so many hundreds of
levels, those are just
approximations, and I don't have
any vested interest in a
particular model of the universe
or model of how many levels of
consciousness there are when I
was going through and writing a
book and looking back
retrospectively at where this
journey went and how Many core
death and rebirth cycles. There
were, there many sub cycles of
death and rebirth, but four
fundamental death and rebirth
cycles, and therefore different
levels of consciousness. One
moves into, I found I
differentiated five levels. The
first, it takes place at the
personal mind, the level of
personal mind, and that
culminates in ego death, where
you lose your egoic or time
space identity, the second takes
place, or took place, for me, at
the collective mind, its
dynamics, fundamentally at the
early, subtle levels of
consciousness. It has to do with
the species mind dimensions of.
Species existence. The third
level is archetypal mind, where
one is moving into the highest
subtle level, moving beyond
simply the collective
consciousness of the species,
moving into different levels of
archetypal reality. The fourth
for me, is causal mind, causal
oneness, where you moving into
profound states of non dual
reality. Yeah, causal reality.
And then the fifth is, I call
diamond Luminosity, a
particularly deep, clear
experience of ultra clear,
particularly clear dimension of
light. There are many, many
different degrees of light that
one encounters. The closest I
could find in the conventional
spiritual literature to this was
in the Buddhist concept of
Dharmakaya, the clear light of
absolute reality, the light that
pre exists prior to the Big
Bang, right?
Kyle Buller: Stan even kind of
talks about that with his first
LSD experience, right? Yeah. I
was talking about, you know, the
ladder proceeding and way out,
yeah, yeah. Thinking about these
levels of consciousness, and
thinking about this like kind of
new psychedelic Renaissance with
psychedelic therapy. How
important do you think it is for
therapists to kind of understand
these, these levels of
consciousness when working with
clients,
Chris Bache: if you're going to
be a psychedelic therapist, of
course, because there are many
different levels of
consciousness. As a therapist,
one works at different levels of
consciousness. So I don't think
a therapist has to have deep
familiarity with all the levels
to work at the early levels. But
I think conventional wisdom,
it's a good wisdom, that if
you're going to be working with
clients going into deep,
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, you must be
personally familiar with those
states. Otherwise, how can you
be the stabilizing factor in the
room when someone is losing
their mind and is terrified of
losing everything they know to
be real, if you haven't been
there yourself, if you haven't
learned to let go, how can you
help someone else let go at
those deep levels? So I think
it's very important, and that
poses a challenge, of course, in
training psychedelic therapists,
because we're in this great
period now, but that's going to
be changing. You know, we're
going to be moving into a
different legal environment
soon. I hope the work that you
guys are doing and other people
are doing is really creating new
possibilities. But I think, you
know, personal experience is
really important in this area.
Kyle Buller: Yeah, thanks for
that. It's been a hot kind of
topic, I guess that people have
been exploring, should
therapists really understand
this, these layers of
consciousness and these
experiences to be a guide?
Joe Moore: Yeah, right, which is
interesting, this whole idea of,
yes, you can get this training,
but you don't necessarily need a
session. But then there's this
whole vast realm of religious
and philosophy, like this
material that discusses all of
these states in kind of
literature form, or we can go
experiential with it too. And I
my problem lately is I really
want a very strong argument for
this, and I haven't really
personally been able to come up
with one,
Chris Bache: a strong argument
for the importance of personal,
Joe Moore: at least personally,
at least personal experience.
But the point I think that you
made, which is unique, is
there's these very complex
spiritual experiences you can
have, Transpersonal experiences
you have, and that's not really
discussed in literature, as far
as I can tell, in terms of the,
at least the recent literature,
like, how do you be about this?
You know, yes, you became Buddha
for a millennia, and now you're
trying to, you know, work at
your day job again. What? What
do you do? Yeah, good. Any
comments on that kind of thing?
Chris Bache: Well, I think it's
important for people to have a
good, solid theoretical
grounding. I mean, I think it's
important to read deeply in
Transpersonal psychology and
works like Stan Grof and the
various people who have been
guiding people or taking people
into these domains and have
compiled a large database,
experiential database. But if
you don't have personal
experience of these realities,
you're always working at a
disadvantage, and you can have.
Have a verbal understanding of
what it means to go through into
certain territories, but if you
haven't some personal exposure
of this territory, you're going
to make mistakes. You're going
to draw inferences where an
experienced journey or would not
draw those inferences. You're
going to find correlations where
there aren't correlations.
You'll miss correlations where
there are correlations. These
are very, very complex
experiences. I mean, my journey
lasted from 79 to 99 covering a
20 year spread. I didn't publish
this book for another 20 years,
and partly that was because of
the legal complications I had to
retire from the university
before I did this, but partly it
took me years during the
sessions and years after the
sessions to work out the
complex, overlapping
phenomenology of these states of
consciousness. And you know, if
I were, I mean, I think the word
guide is maybe not the best
word, I mean, that implies a
role of active guidance, of
active direction, which is not
really the case for I think,
working with much of this work,
doing much of this work, but to
be a sitter, to be able to hold
the ground, to be able to help
somebody go to the edge of
everything they know to be real
and true about themselves and
about the world, and help them
jump over the edge, to give them
the support that they need to
lose their mind, I mean, to let
go of everything they know to be
real and true. I don't know how
one could really do that without
having first hand experience of
those domains. And so to that
extent, the I think the
effectiveness of therapists or
sitters will be limited to their
own depth of experience. They
can be very, very good and
skillful at levels one, two,
perhaps, but maybe not so much
at levels three, four or five,
or whatever you get the sense of
it, right?
Kyle Buller: That's really
that's kind of interesting to
think about, even like practical
stuff, like going to different
people for different like
sessions, maybe, I mean,
obviously, you have no idea what
the hell is going to come up,
right? But somebody focusing
more on personal dynamics,
right?
Chris Bache: Yeah, and I think
it's good right now, we're
proceeding very slowly, very
methodically. We're using
gentler psychedelics. There's no
federal protocol that's
suggesting using LSD and the
quantum in the high levels that
I used it. And I think that's
that's good, that's important.
It's important that we proceed
methodologically carefully. We
have a window. You know, we lost
our window 40 years ago. The
window is back, and it's
important that we move very
judiciously as we expand that
window. But sooner or later,
we're going to find what we
found in the early years of
psychedelic work, and that is
healing the personal unconscious
is only the first step of a long
journey into the universe, into
the deeper dimensions of
consciousness, which take us
into the I don't know what do
you call it? I think of it as
the mind of the universe. The
mind of the cosmos. I hesitate
to call it the divine mind, or
the mind of God, because that
language has very strong
cultural overtones that I don't
really want to import. But when
one dissolves, when one
completely dissolves at the time
space level and just dissolves
into increasingly comprehensive
fields of experience that open
realities to you that you've
never even dreamed possible. And
if you go back again and again
in a methodical way, levels of
consciousness that at first
swallow you up whole. And it's
very, very hard to stay
consciously aware at these new
levels. And that's why, I think
we often call them ineffable.
But if you go back consistently
over and over again, what
happens is you acclimate, you
learn how to stay conscious at
levels of consciousness that
previously were not able to stay
conscious in and that's a
pattern that repeats itself as
you go deeper and deeper.
Joe Moore: Yeah, I find that to
be really true. Are you familiar
with this gentleman, Ken Lindy,
ie from Detroit. I'm not. He is
a very strong proponent of these
high level doses, and I, I
struggle with his arguments
around it, but, but yours, the
you know, seems quite sensible.
It's, you know, how do we
approach it? I'm
Chris Bache: not a proponent of
high doses. By. Stuff. I mean, I
did this work. I came through
it. See, in the early years, the
early high dose work done at
Spring Grove Hospital with
terminally ill patients. Well,
it's limited to three sessions.
Low dose psychedelic work, open
ended, high dose work was
limited to three sessions. And I
thought, going into it, I
thought, well, if you could do
it safely three times, you could
do it safely more times. But
what I found was that by doing
it as systematically as I did,
and pushing that edge as hard as
I did, it required, issues
arose, challenges arose which
had not been discussed in the
early levels of the work.
Opportunities for insights and
understanding emerge, but also
challenges navigating these
increasingly intense levels and
large levels of consciousness
and what it does to your body
and mind and as you go into
these realities and how it
affects people around you, I
found that my students never
knew about my work. I mean, I
kept my work completely isolated
from anyone on campus, but I
found at a certain point, my
students began to be activated
by my psychedelic work, there
was a natural contagion that was
happening, because consciousness
at these deeper levels is open
ended. It's like a lake. You
threw a rock in the lake, the
ripple spread out. So when one
person goes very, very deep,
people around them are naturally
going to be impacted. And I had
to learn how to take care of the
activations that my my students
were experiencing. That's I
wrote the book living classroom
as to read that came out of
years and years of trying to
understand this dynamic between
my mind and their mind and our
minds together in the context
of, you know, consciousness at
large. So it's not just a matter
of taking care of your own body
and your own emotions and your
intimate relationships. It's
taking care of everyone who's
touched by your work at a larger
collective level. But I wouldn't
push it as hard if I were doing
it again. I would. It's not that
I would avoid working with high
doses, but I would balance it
working with lower doses. And I
would balance working with LSD,
which pushes a high, cosmic,
logical ceiling, with Psilocybin
work and Ayahuasca work is much
more kind of embodied
psychedelic states.
Kyle Buller: Yeah, man, there's
a couple questions I want to
ask. Much direction I want to go
into, but I want to come back to
the this idea, the ripples,
right? Because I've thought
about this a lot, and I'm kind
of curious what your take is on
this, of having some of these
experiences. And I've even had
it in Breathwork sessions, where
it's like tapping into, I guess,
how you describe it, like this,
this lake, you know, you kind of
toss it in, and there's like
ripples and time wave or
something like that, where all
these kind of synchronistic
things might start happening.
And I'm wondering, from your
perspective, you know, you're
talking about your students
changing, do you think that was
more in the sense of your
presence and the way that you
were showing up, or do you think
it was kind of more in that
subtle realm, world where you're
going into these states, and it
is having more of a ripple on
some other sort of level?
Chris Bache: I think it's a
both, and I think it does as my
work changed me, certainly my
presence in the classroom
changed. But the more
interesting aspect, I think, is
working at the subtle level. I
mean, I began, for example, I
found that when I was lecturing
and just just looking for a
random example, looking for an
example to illustrate some
concept that I wanted to, you
know, was bringing forward, and
I would pause, I would just
stop, and my mind would go
blank. And this idea would come
to me to give this example, and
I would use that example. And
students began to come up to me
after class and began to say,
very quietly when they were sure
no one was listening. You know,
it's funny you use that example
today, because that's exactly
what happened to me this week.
And this first, I thought this
was just, you know, an
interesting, you know, accident,
but it kept happening and
happened repeatedly. And not
only was it happening frequently
enough that I knew it was it had
to have some significance, but
the deeper I went in my own
work, the more the students were
being touched. It very, very
deep, private, personal areas of
their lives, lives places where
they needed healing, places
where they were blocked, places
where they needed some help
getting through to the next
stage of their own development.
So as I was kind of facing my
blocks and entering into deeper
communion with the intelligence
of life, it was as if the very
fabric, the intelligent fabric
around me, was being activated
and triggering these kind of aha
moments with my students and
their own confrontations with
their blocks and the students
knew that something unusual was
happening. I couldn't exactly
explain what it was, but I had
to, you know, we all knew
something was happening. So I
would have students taking my
courses, partly for the
intellectual content, but partly
because they wanted to be in the
energy of the room. But I found
it wasn't just that there was a
resonance spontaneously
occurring between my energy and
their energy. There was a second
phenomenon that I discuss in the
living classroom, and that is
the effect of group fields. That
is that just like Morphic
genetic fields, Rupert Sheldrake
concept of Morphic fields,
except these are smaller. These
are not species wide fields.
These are more specific fields.
I found that there was, there
were psychic fields growing
around my courses that were
getting stronger year by year,
the more students studied with
me in these courses. And it
wasn't a field that was being
generated by their learning. So
hundreds and hundreds of
students learning over many
years creates a field that was
impacting and accelerating and
deepening the learning of
subsequent students and
subsequent semesters. So there
were multiple factors going into
this phenomenon.
Kyle Buller: Yeah, it's super
fascinating, and I don't know
how to make sense of it at
times. So yeah, thanks for
sharing that.
Chris Bache: But you know, it
turns out that once you let go
of an atomistic psychology, once
you and it's not that atomistic
psychology is really true. That
is the psychology which treats
our individual consciousness as
the individual stand alone
phenomenon. We know that that's
true, but underneath that is a
quantum reality. It's a quantum
psychology, and once you let go
of this idea that everything
that happens around us can be
explained in terms of the of the
aggregate of simply individual
awareness and open to this
larger participatory Cosmos
where there is a deeper context.
It's like a deeper tide that's
always moving in and out. It's
always flowing. It actually
becomes very coherent. It's very
easy to understand. It says that
you have to shift your
metaphysical basis, right?
Kyle Buller: Yeah, that makes
sense. That makes sense.
Chris Bache: It's like plate
tectonics. You know, in the
early years, it was very, very
hard to see. It just looked
ridiculous. But once we began to
see it, then a whole lot of data
began to make sense, and it was
elegant and simple and
transparent.
Kyle Buller: I'm curious also to
kind of go back to that idea of
kind of incorporating mushrooms
in Ayahuasca. You kind of said
that it seems to be a little bit
more body medicine. Could you
talk about the difference
between your experiences with
LSD and the more plant based
psychedelics? This is a question
that we we've been asked a lot,
and I think we even chatted
about in our course last two
nights ago, of like, you know,
what is the difference between
like, LSD? Is that a little bit
different that like, I've always
like, somebody said, Oh, I
always heard it's like, more
psychological than say, you
know, more kind of like
biographical and doesn't have
this, like spirit, right? Where
you Albert Hoffman said, right?
He said, you know, Psilocybin
seems to be something in there,
right? So, yeah, I wonder what
your take is.
Chris Bache: Well, inevitably,
my take is based on my own
personal experience, and so it's
always dangerous to generalize
on an end of one. So I just
don't want to over generalize
psychedelics, which have been
used historically, have fields
associated with them. So we've
been using mushrooms for 1000s
and 1000s of years. And I think
there's a certain sense in which
around the biochemistry of this
substance, there are fields of
human experience of human beings
engaging the deeper dimensions
of their own consciousness and
consciousness at large using
this substance. And when one
takes this substance, you don't
just introduce a chemical into
your body, which then you have a
private experience of this
substance, but there is a sense
in which how the substance
affects you is mediated, in
part, by the history of your
species with this substance. And
I think that's also true with
io. Ayahuasca with is a multi
1000 year history surrounding
Ayahuasca with LSD, we don't
have those fields. I mean, LSD
is a new substance, and I don't
think the difference is
fundamentally organic versus
synthetic. I don't find that
discussion terribly
illuminating. I mean, our
experience in the 60s and 70s,
that's that's a few decades.
That's not a whole lot of
experience when it comes to
these types of fields that I'm
talking about. So in my
experience, that living quality,
that kind of living intelligence
quality, I'm sure that there are
spiritual agencies on the other
side, which may account for part
of that and but part of it, I
think, has to do with humanity's
living experience with these
substances and all the
experiences I've had with them.
LSD, strikes me as kind of
cleaner in that respect. It
doesn't have that same kind of
programmed quality. Now I don't
know what it would have been
like if I had been working with
low doses of LSD. If I'd been
working with low doses, I'm sure
it would have activated my
experiences would have been much
more personal and psycho
dynamically oriented, but
working with the very high doses
that I worked with after the
first 15 sessions or so, when
the sessions were at their peak
hours, I was not working in
relationship to my personal
psyche at all. In fact, pretty
much in the book, I drop out the
personal story as much as
possible, because the personal
story kind of showed up at the
beginning of a session and at
the end of a session. And these
were very meaningful experiences
to me. They were very healing.
They're very, you know, helpful.
They're giving me insights to
relevant things in my life. But
during the peak hours, I was
usually operating far beyond the
range of personal psyche. When
I'm working with Psilocybin, I
don't have that experience of
being so far removed from my
personal reality. I don't have I
only have limited experience
with Ayahuasca. I like the
medicine very much. Is a very
powerful medicine. Has been
giving me some extra ordinary
help and extra ordinary clarity
here and there, but I don't have
enough experience with it
comparable to my 70 some high
dose LSD sessions to do a
careful AB my basic sense is
that the Psilocybin tends to be
less evocative, less disruptive,
less opening up to the deep,
deep levels. Ayahuasca is more
disruptive opening up to deeper
levels still, and at least for
me. LSD working with it, as I
did, opens up to very, very
deep, cosmic, logical levels.
Eventually, I don't know of
people I have not seen, though I
haven't tried to do an
exhaustive search of the
literature, but I have not seen
people having experiences with
Psilocybin, and, for the most
part, even Ayahuasca, that
correlate to the experiences I
was having in the last 10 years
of my work with LSD. But again,
that's just my personal
experience. It's, you know, it's
not a scholarly comparison,
Kyle Buller: right? Yeah. And
what were some of your
experiences like towards the
last 10 years? Like, I guess,
yeah. Could you give us some
examples of, like, those big
themes that you're working
through, if it wasn't so
personal or psychodynamic?
Chris Bache: Well, you know,
that's that's a hard question,
because there's so many levels,
and there's so many of some it's
always tricky to kind of jump
into the later stages, because
every stage builds upon earlier
stages. But right one of the one
of the barometers I would
mention, for example, would be
time when I went into subtle
level reality. I for a year, I
had a consistent set of
experiences where I experienced
the totality of my life from
beginning to end as
simultaneously present in
immediate now. So I not only had
insights into my old age, and I
didn't experience my age in a
sort of abstract, theoretical
way, I experienced the distilled
essence of my entire life boiled
down to right now. Now and all
of the data of my life was
present at this particular
moment in time. This was such a
mind shattering possibility that
when I first came back out of
this experience, I couldn't
remember it. It took me entering
into it multiple times to be
able to really be able to hold
on to all of those experiences,
which I write about in the
chapter called deep time in the
soul. Going beyond that, I began
to enter into archetypal
dimensions of archetype reality.
I began to have experiences of
something like the Platonic
domain of the reality behind
time, space, reality, except it
wasn't archetypes like Plato
conceives of them. Plato
conceives of archetypes as
unchanging ideas in the mind of
a transcendent intelligence. My
experience, these were vast,
huge beings that were so huge I
couldn't wrap my mind around
them. The best my mind could do
in imaging them was to sort of
see them as galaxies, which I
think was simply my mind's
attempt to image something that
would measure in hundreds of
1000s of light years of scope.
But these were beings that were
responsible for creating time
and space and orchestrating the
the unfolding of reality in time
and space. I went into into what
I call deep time, which is not
eternity, it isn't timelessness,
but it's different magnitudes of
time experience within a
simultaneous or broader frame of
reference. So I had many
experiences, and became one of
the overarching themes of my
book of life sessions, and
therefore the book of humanity's
future, where humanity was
going, what our moment in
history was, what the archetypal
trajectory of humanity was, what
was happening behind the scenes
in this global sustainability
crisis that we're entering into
what I have a chapter in the
book called The Birth of the
future human. Lots and lots of
going into deep time, going deep
into humanity's future,
experiencing what is attempting
to be born in this period of
history. What how evolution
works on this larger, broader
scale, and then eventually going
deep into various episodes of
causal oneness, Shunyata,
emptiness, the experience of
primal void. You know, the Void
is behind physical, manifest
existence, experience of cosmic
love, cause just being
overwhelmed with and I think
love is basically a kind of
characteristic of the inherent
oneness of life, where you
experience the deep, deep
oneness that existence is. Then
you know the emotional
counterpart of that is love.
It's compassion. That's the
emotion of oneness, and then
eventually going beyond oneness,
beyond the void into this
diamond Luminosity, state which
once I touched the diamond
Luminosity, this occupied the
last five years of my work. Once
I touched it. It was a state of
state of being, state of
consciousness, so incredibly
clear, so exquisitely clear that
once I touched it, I wasn't
interested in exploring any of
the other dimensions of
consciousness that I had been
exploring for years. Returning
to that condition became my sole
objective. The next in the 26
chapter, 26 sessions covering
four years of work. I only
touched that condition four
times, and in between those four
sessions were tremendous
cleaning, tremendous
purification, tremendous
detoxification, so that I could
return to that condition and
experience it more clearly, more
completely. So there's, there's
a lot of levels, yeah, that's
what makes the story a complex
story to tell.
Kyle Buller: Yeah, well, and
people should check out the book
and read through all this. So,
yeah, definitely.
Chris Bache: Well, it's nice now
that the book is out, you know,
they don't have to get it from
me speaking. You know, I've done
my best to tell the story as
cleanly and simply, as I can
with without a lot of the
philosophical baggage that may
have been in some of my earlier
works. Right? Is there a
Joe Moore: story that you'd like
to tell the most about your
project that maybe you could
share? Are here for any any kind
of specific gem you like to
share the most. You know,
Chris Bache: it's a story of a
journey, and every phase of the
journey was an exciting
adventure in its own right at
the time when I was entering
into that territory. And each
one was absolutely fascinating
and captivating to me when I was
going through this material. And
so I don't have a favorite per
se. I mean, I think, of course,
the diamond Luminosity is from
my own personal heart. That is
the deepest dimensions of the
story. The deepest aspect, I
think, the story of the birth of
the future human, where
reincarnation is taking
humanity, is an important
component of the story, because
I what happened to me in one
particular session, in the 38th
session, without this cutting
down to the important piece here
is that I began to experience
all my lives coming into me, all
my former lives were kind of
being integrated. And I've I've
done a lot of other work,
hypnotic regression work, to
familiarize myself with some of
my deep life history, but I
experienced all my former lives
coming in very quickly. It was
like wrapping string on around a
kite spool. And there came a
moment when all of that energy,
with all those living
experiences, they fused. And
when they fuse, they ignited.
And there was a tremendous
explosion of diamond light from
my chest, and it threw me into a
completely different state of
consciousness and and I think
what I was being shown in this
experience, what I was being
given was an understanding of
where reincarnation is taking
us, because, classically,
reincarnation, you know, leads
to a gradual, hopefully a
sustained development of more
compassion, more understanding,
developing our qualities of our
deep essential nature, more and
more richer and richer levels.
We make mistakes, we go back, we
learn, we go forward in this
process. But I don't think the
process is really about taking
us incrementally to eventually
producing a better life, which
is incrementally plus one from
where we were previously. I
think eventually, if we die and
we expand in the after death
condition. We're born, and we
contract into a immediate, one
life focus. We die and we
expand. We're born. We go back
and forth. If we keep this up,
just for hundreds and 1000s and
10s of 1000s and hundreds of
1000s of years, if we keep this
up, sooner or later, the
totality of our consciousness,
which most people would
experience only after they die,
the deep soul, sooner or later,
that soul consciousness, I
think, the evolutionary
trajectory is for this
consciousness to wake up inside
our physical incarnation, and
that's What I call the birth of
the diamond soul, when you wake
up and we are not tempted to
identify with simply egoic this
body, mind, kind of structure
that we know ourselves to be an
internal being. We know
ourselves to be in relationship
with other eternal beings. We
have a felt sense of history
with many, many of these beings,
and the compassion that comes
with that history and a sense of
open transparency to the cosmic
intelligence at large. I think
that's basically where we're
going. And I don't know, I think
this is not a private
experience. It's a collective
experience. The universe doesn't
work in in small numbers. The
universe works with whole
species. And what's happening is
really an evolving of our entire
species in the direction. If
there are one thing, I guess, I
keep, I would come back to one
thing which I wish I could kind
of reach into my heart and
communicate to people. It would
be to let go of this terribly
constricting fear of death,
because if we're afraid of
dying, we've got it all
backwards. You know, here's
where the hard work is done.
When we die, we have all this
Hollywood bullshit about what
happens to us when we die, and
most of it, most of it's just
trash. When we die, we enter,
you know, we go back home, we
enter. The vast majority of us
entered pretty, very easily,
straight into the depth of where
we come from. And there are many
layers of that reality. So
there's a lot of work to do. Uh,
but there's absolutely nothing
to fear and death. And one of
the things that's come out of my
work is I just I don't have a
fear of death. I mean, dying is
pain the ass, but being dead has
absolutely no fear for me. In
fact, it's something I look
forward to very much.
Joe Moore: Kyle, how do you
respond
Kyle Buller: to that? That
resonates a lot with me. Of what
you're saying, like kind of gave
me a little bit of chills. So I
don't know if you know my my
story. Listeners probably know
this, if you've been following
us for a while, but when I was
16, I had a Near-Death
Experience, and so rupture my
spleen. When I was in the MRI or
the CAT scan machine, I was
overwhelmed with this, this
blissful feeling of love and
beauty that I was going back
home. And there is a sense
something came over me and said,
You're going back home, you're
going to you're going back to
the stars, where we all come
from, and this, you know,
physical life is going to cease
to exist, but you're going to
continue on. And that was really
beautiful. And it wasn't scary
when I when I first heard I was
dying, and like they said, you
know, you have internal
injuries, you're losing massive
blood, I thought, you know, I
was pretty terrified, but in
that moment, as I was drifting
away total acceptance, and so I
actually had a really hard time
coming back here right because,
and I could probably resonate
with that idea, the diamond,
loose Luminosity of wanting to
return there. Because I
definitely resonate with that
feeling of wanting to return to
that oneness that I felt on that
night, and that's what got me
into like exploring
psychedelics, is having very
similar experiences with
psychedelics and correlating
that to my Near-Death
Experience, and wanting to get
back there and over time. And
maybe you'll resonate with this
is like the period in between of
stopping and actually focusing
on the integration. And I keep
coming back to this idea that
the work is here. This is where
all the magic happens, and how
do we really embody that and
show up?
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah, to
complain about the restrictions
of time and space is kind of
like a weightlifter complaining
about the weights. This is where
the work is done. Time space is
an extremely demanding
environment, but progress made
here has exponential import for
what we're what's available to
us when we die. Of all the
various populations of people I
feel the closest affinity from
my own psychedelic work are the
near death episode people I've
taught near death episode
research for years at my
university in one of my courses.
And so I've really read deeply
in the near death literature,
and that's the closest
correlation I find with the
deepest of the psychedelic
experiences, very strong
correlations. And Ken ring was
one of the near to so, you know,
one of the founders of that
movement and I have, we've
written together and dialog
together. He's a good friend
around that,
Kyle Buller: yeah, yeah, it's,
it's a powerful topic, something
I think about often, right? And
what I guess my early
experiences got me really on
this path. Was just like, you
know, I enter this space where
it just felt so similar with
like this. I had an experience
with Psilocybin, where it's just
so on par with dying, and it
just captivated my attention of
how could a substance like this?
I mean, I guess in a sense, you
know, if you take it from the
psychotherapeutic like lens.
It's like reliving trauma,
right? I'm kind of, my psyche is
processing that experience, and
I'm going back there to kind of
reprocess it. But I have plenty
of other experiences where, no,
it still felt pretty similar and
on par with that original
Near-Death Experience.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I've died
many times. I mean, I feel like
and that that was the full
impetus in the early work at
Spring Grove, was to give people
a foretaste of where they're
going and they die. And, you
know, I've gone through that in
shamans. This is very familiar
territory, so there's nothing
unique to me there, but I've
gone through that death process
so many times. It's It feels
very comfortable and very
natural, and coming back is
sometimes challenging. I mean,
the hardest chapter for me to
write in this book was the last
chapter coming off the mountain,
because it basically tells a
story of what happened after I
stopped my sessions, and I
basically entered into a period,
eventually, of deep, deep
existential loneliness. I found
that I had really worked very
hard in integrating my sessions.
I did all of all my very
carefully. I wrote them down, I
studied them, I tried to
incorporate. Or teaching into my
life. I really thought I had it,
you know, locked down pretty
well, and I thought therefore
that I could stop my sessions
and I would just be able to kind
of collect and ponder the many
gifts that I had been given
through the years. But what I
learned was that integrating an
entire journey is different than
integrating individual sessions,
and that by repeatedly going
deeper and deeper and deeper
into the universe and experience
the exquisite ecstasy of
dissolving into sheer light
repeatedly and entering into
dissolving into the crystalline
body of the Divine, when for
various reasons, I made the
decision that it was time for
this work to stop, I found that
I had a I was suffering from a
loss of communion, a deep, deep
existential sadness. And
eventually, years down the road,
I found that I was really just
waiting to die, that I could
return to the light. And I
realized, you know, that wasn't
right. That's not the way this
work is supposed to end. You
know, my entire body was
screaming, failure to integrate.
But because I had been so
careful trying to integrate, it
wasn't clear what the where the
imbalance had come in, what I
found eventually is that there
was an imbalance that had I had
cultivated inadvertently,
between Transcendence and
imminence. It's all the divine.
The physical universe is the
divine. I knew that it was the
divine. I knew that we're never
absent from the Divine for any
moment, it's only our own
illusions that keep us in that
sense. But I had pushed so
deeply into Transcendence that
in this to a certain degree, I
had lost my footing in the
imminent divine, and I had to
make a conscious choice and
undertake specific practices to
really kind of ground myself
back in the imminent divine for
the remainder of my years on
this earth. It took about 10
years for me to really get
solidly, comfortably back inside
my time space suit.
Kyle Buller: Wow, I can imagine,
after 20 years of deep
exploration, I mean, that's a,
I'd say that's probably a pretty
long integration process,
Chris Bache: yeah, yeah. And
that's, I think, you know, in
this respect, my story is
sometimes described as a hero's
journey, but it's not the hero's
journey the way it's usually
thought of, it's not simply
going and experiencing something
and bringing back, you know,
something valuable for your
culture, for yourself. It's all.
It's tempered by, it's tempered
by a kind of lesson that comes
from dealing with, not the
failure of some aspect of the
journey, but actually of the
success of the journey, of being
wounded by the sheer beauty of
what one experiences. You
literally are wounded by the
beauty of the universe, by the
experiencing the extraordinary
intelligence of the universe,
extra ordinary love of the
universe. And if you're not able
to create a container inside
your historical existence where
you can breathe this
intelligence in and breathe the
compassion in, then you know
it's like it literally can kind
of become painful. So it my, my
story is in part of it's a
cautionary tale. It cautions
against, and even though I tried
to be as methodical as possible
and do it as carefully as
possible and integrate it as
deeply as I could, it cautions
against going too deep, too
fast. If you can call 20 years
too fast, going too deep, or
deeper than you can actually
productively use and I think my
memories have changed not only
the rest of the years of my
life, but my memories have
changed the trajectory of my
soul's entire evolution. So I
don't think of the results of my
journey as necessarily coming to
fruition in just, you know, the
next few decades. I think they
come to fruition over lifetimes.
It's changed the entire
trajectory of my deep
evolutionary project. And I
think that's true for anyone who
enters into this. You know, when
you enter into deep intimacy
with life in this way, you
purify, and you're purifying,
you offload. A lot of, you know,
painful trauma, whatever,
whatever, but you. Also open up
to it a different a different
relationship with the universe.
So right now, my primary way of
being with the universe in this
intimate way is not working with
psychedelics. That time of my
life is largely over. I'm 70
years old, and this is, you
know, somewhat of a young man's
game, young person's game. I do
a lot of contemporary of
classical contemplative
practice. I do a lot of Vadnais
practice, which I find to be
very complementary to deep
psychedelic work. I don't feel
any cross purposes between the
two different work methods of
working. I should mention in
this context, though, I think it
would be a mistake to hold to
sort of evaluate the value of
psychedelic, deep psychedelic
work by holding it accountable
just to the Enlightenment
project, I started this work
with an agenda of an
enlightenment Project. What
happened was my personal
Awakening was completely
eclipsed eventually by a project
of a collective awakening. All
my work began to be focused on a
type of healing of the
collective psyche that went
beyond my personal healing, and
an awakening of the collective
psyche that went beyond my
personal awakening, and then it
became just a radical adventure,
a cosmicological adventure going
so deep that it would be
impossible to bring those
experiences back and stabilize
them in some kind of spiritually
awakened State. It's just a
different project, you know, the
Enlightenment project and cosmic
logical exploration project.
These are two different projects
that have to be evaluated on
their own terms. My two cents,
Kyle Buller: no, yeah, I would
agree it sounds Yeah, hmm.
Joe Moore: Yes, this is quite
the interview. Certainly, like a
much, I knew
it was going to be a big topic,
but I'm always impressed by how
big some of these things become.
Yeah, you know, I do think some
people are doing similar
projects nowadays, though, I
want I wonder if LSD still in
vogue in this context. You know,
Chris Bache: I don't know. I
worked with LSD primarily
because that was the work that
Stan had done most of his early
work with, and I trusted what I
saw on Stan's research. And I
trusted, you know, the history
there and the methodology he
developed. I only began to work
with other psychedelic
substances pretty much after my
LSD work was done. And so the
mind that I brought to my
Psilocybin experiences and my
Ayahuasca experiences and salvia
div and arm so on so forth, the
mind was that the mind that had
been transformed by all my
previous psychedelic work, which
is the other thing to you know,
important to take account of
that the mind the experiences
that we have reflect the entire
history of our working in
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness. So if we've done
this work only a few, a few, two
or three times, well, then we
have that kind of depth of
experience to bring to it. But
if we've been doing this work
for years and years and years,
naturally, these substances are
going to have a different kind
of effect, because we've been
transformed. The way I think of
this is that, listen, my
experience, the universe is an
infinite ocean of possibilities,
just an infinite ocean that will
never, ever get to the end of
it. I used to think that we'll
get to an end state. That was
the project to get to hold, to
get to the end condition that
was taken away from me along the
journey, I began to understand
it's an infinite, infinite
progression. I get distracted
from my original point by that
particular, that particular
image? Yeah, I'll just stick
with that. I lost my train of
thought, but I'll yeah, that
works
Joe Moore: for us because it's
our orientation is this Grof Ian
meets Whitehead and John Cobb.
Kind of. A synthesis, and, you
know, largely this, at least,
the project of the company here.
But yeah, yeah, it's, it's good
to hear that, you know, it
rhymes, in a sense, with that
Bodhisattva vow of, let's keep
going like there's not this end
point Nirvana, until everybody's
there, and it's going to be a
long, long, long, long time, if
time even enters into that
discussion,
Chris Bache: it's a long time,
except, of course, it's speeding
up. You know, it's kind of like
our collective karma as a
species is coming at us hard.
You know, the whole history. You
know, our culture is basically a
culture that's been built by
ego. And for all the many
virtues and values of the ego,
it's basically, it's
fundamentally a fragmented
condition, and therefore it
creates a world which is deeply
imbalanced with between
ourselves and between other life
forms. And you know that world
is coming to a radical and
accelerated breakdown. And I
think this is actually part of
the evolutionary pivot that we
are coming into a time where we
literally will not be able to
continue operating out of the
same, not just an economic or
industrial or technological
basis, but we will not be able
to continue functioning out of
the same psychological basis of
egoic consciousness. So how fast
we might make this transition?
If we use historical projections
from the past, we probably
deeply underestimate how fast
this could happen. In fact, in
that chapter on the birth of the
future human, where I talk about
particularly one session,
session 55 that took me deep
into the death and rebirth of
humanity. The message that kept
coming through over and over and
over again was, this is going to
happen much faster than anyone
could have is imagine it's going
to happen much faster, you know.
So I think we're the game is
getting very, very intense we're
being driven into non linear
dynamics. Feels that way.
Conscious dynamics, the
collective psyche, is being
hyper stimulated by the trauma
that we're going into. And when
systems, we know from physical
systems, from physical systems,
enter into non linear
conditions, they can do things
that they could not do when they
were in lower energy linear
conditions. And I think that
something similar happens with
psychic fields, the integrated
psychic field that holds all of
our individual minds. When that
psychic field is hyper
stimulated by the suffering that
we're going into, but it's hyper
stimulated, it moves will
eventually move into a non
linear condition. And the rules
of non linear conditions of
dynamics apply to psychic fields
as well as physical fields,
small changes can elicit huge
outcomes, latent connectivity,
which was kind of invisible at
the linear level, becomes
suddenly active and visible at
the non linear level. Things can
happen much faster at the non
linear level than at the linear
level. So, you know, we're going
into a trial by fire, and I
think this trial is actually
part of the conscious intention
of the creative intelligence
itself. I don't think it's
accidental, and I don't think
there are any victims here. You
know, personally, my own
personal belief is we all chose
to be here. We chose to be part
of this time in history. It's an
extraordinarily important time
to be fully conscious and fully
active. I of
Kyle Buller: it's give me chills
thinking about that. It's
interesting. It does feel like
things are really kind of
speeding up. And, you know,
sometimes I'm like, oh, you
know, you always kind of hear
that as you get older, time
seems to be speeding up. But
even, you know, talk to people
that are older and like, things
just seem to be happening
quicker and quicker. It is
really interesting. Feel like, I
can't, like, hold on to
anything, you know? It's like,
once you kind of grasp on to it,
something else has already
changed form. You know, it's,
Chris Bache: yeah, yeah. So many
of our, not only our technology
is driving this way, but our
social customs, you know, just
They're dissolving right out
from underneath us. The
standards of truth are changing,
and it's a confusing time and
it's a it's a dangerous time and
it's a hard time, but it's an
extraordinarily exciting time.
It is.
Kyle Buller: Do you see
psychedelics aiding in this
Chris Bache: in any way? Yeah,
absolutely. I think that the
ways in which psychedelics have
come back into our culture, both
from the Central American and
South American cultures, which
have kept this tradition alive,
the the new psychedelics these,
you know, LSD is often compared
to the i. The atom bomb, since
they were discovered at the same
time, this exponential this
opportunity to explore
dimensions of consciousness that
previously, previous
generations, for the most part,
classically, have had to spend
lifetimes meditating in order
just to get access to some of
them. And now people of even
modest spiritual capacities can
have temporary experiences of
these realities, which have a
profound they require a profound
redrafting of our existential
assumptions about how life works
and that we can do this. We can
engage these, these dimensions
of consciousness, not for
recreational purposes and not
even for healing purposes, but
we can engage them
systematically for educational
and deep transformational
purposes, not only for our own
personal transformation, but we
can. We can work on behalf of
the collective states of
consciousness. I mean, I think
psychedelics have just, they
have that's, that's what I saw
when I first read Stan grofberg.
I saw, this is going to change
everything. It's going to be a
true before and after
development. We're going to it's
like the invention of the, as he
says, the microscope for biology
and the Telescope for Astronomy.
It just increases the quantity
of data we have access so too,
so that it changes, it forces a
radical revision of our
theoretical understanding. I
think psychedelics are part of
it, and just in time, because we
have very little time, yeah, it
feels that way. Yeah, it's
coming out. It's very fast, very
fast. Cool.
Joe Moore: So I hate to end the
podcast, but we're at over an
hour, and I don't I want to be
respectful of your time, and I
really appreciate this. This is
very enlightening episode. Can
you tell us a little bit about
where people can find your book
and perhaps the upcoming audio
book,
Chris Bache: they can find the
book on Amazon. I'm just putting
the final edits on the audio
book. I'm not sure that will be
released through inner
traditions. I'm not quite sure
what the vehicle will be for
that, but it should be out,
hopefully by the beginning,
beginning of the year, I will
have a website up. Hopefully by
the first of the year. I'm way
overdue in revising this website
and getting it posted, but
eventually, within a month or
so, people will be able to find
me at Chris bache.com that's
going to be the easiest way
right now, most of my written
work and some tapes are
collected@academia.edu under my
name, you can find them listed
there. But right now, I'm not as
good on social media as I should
be. It's hard to keep up with
Yeah.
Joe Moore: Only do one. It's not
worth being everywhere,
Chris Bache: yeah, but the most
what's really exciting is the
book is finally out, and it's as
clear a presentation of this
material as I've been able to,
took me five years to put it
together and bring it forward,
and it's as it's as good as I
can tell the story.
Joe Moore: Well, thank you for
all your work, and really
appreciate you joining us on the
show today.
Chris Bache: Thank you guys.
It's been a real honor. I really
appreciate the work you're
doing. Keep it up. Thank you.
Keep getting the word out. You
know, you guys are social
catalyst. Do we need all the
social catalysts and we can get
these days?
Kyle Buller: Thank you. Yeah,
we'll keep plugging along. You
you.