Unknown: Like a smile, another
side I truly live. All right,
are you doing good? Nice to meet
you.
Frank McCaughey: Frank,
likewise. All right. Well done
on the book.
Chris Bache: Thank you. Thank
you, pleasure.
Frank McCaughey: Not only
because obviously writing a
book, in and of itself is an
achievement, but the nature of
this particular book, yeah,
yeah, I'm almost exhausted
reading some of us, if you know,
I've read a good bit. I'm
exhausted because of the the
journeys. Yeah,
Chris Bache: yeah. It was quite
a journey. Always hard to
summarize in any meaningful way
in a one hour podcast or
whatever, but, but certainly a
message that I'm looking forward
to bringing into the world.
Frank McCaughey: Yeah, where do
you begin? I mean, you can begin
at the start, which is always
the easiest way. But I suppose,
well, actually, you know what we
but I might just ask it, because
it's, it's ongoing this before
we even get into the book, I
suppose ask you is, in a way, I
feel it's, it's a big part of
the book, just anyway. But how
are you now? How are things? How
is life now?
Chris Bache: Life is very good
now, especially now that I've
finally written the book and
finally I've gone public with
this, him going public with
this, that has been a very
healing and deepening
experience, actually, to claim
my memories, to claim those
experiences, and to begin to
speak about them without
inhibition, has has deepened my
integration of those experiences
in my life. And I don't know
where it's going, I suspect in
three years, I may be in a very
different place than I am now,
and I'm in a good place now.
Frank McCaughey: Okay, yeah, and
what we're talking about is, so
the title of the book is LSD and
the mind of the universe, and
it's basically a documentation
of 73 high dose LSD sessions,
trips, and everything that comes
with that, and all your
insights. So maybe let's begin
at start, because it's I think
anybody who's taken a
psychedelic will know,
especially one, if you've gone
on one big trip, you know, yeah,
73 is like 73 babies. 73
childbirth, you know, yeah. So
maybe let's start at the start.
Yeah, what? Okay, you didn't
know at the start that this is
what you what was going to
happen. It just you took a trip
and you documented it, but you
didn't know you're going to keep
going and going over this long
period of time.
Unknown: What happened was,
fresh out of graduate school, 29
years old, in the middle of my
Saturn Return. Didn't know that
yet, at the time, had finished
my dissertation. Was looking for
where to take my research. I was
a brand new professor of
religious studies at Youngstown
State University, and I read
Stanislav Grof realms of the
human unconscious had just been
published. To read it in 1978 I
saw that I thought, I got to get
in on this. This is just
fantastic. It's not only extra
ordinary for psychology, but
it'll have enormous implications
for philosophy of religion as
well. So I, I felt the draw. I
felt like I had found my life's
work. I started the work. I knew
that you had to, you know, to
write truly out of an
experiential basis. First you
had to do your work, and that
meant doing an unspecified
number of sessions. I started
with three low dose sessions. Me
about 200 micrograms, got my
bearings, got my feet wet, and
then I shifted in the fourth
session to high dose sessions. I
started I worked at 500 To 600
micrograms consistently all the
way through, which is not a
protocol that I recommend. And
yes, you know in the book, I
strongly do not recommend this
protocol for reasons I explained
in the book, but basically
recorded, documented as
carefully as I could, kept all
the variables as consistent as I
could. I think one of the things
that makes this story unusual is
not just the depth of where it
went, but the stabilization of
the variables in 20 years.
Always the same sitter, same
sentence, setting, same physical
location, Northeast Ohio, couple
places within Northeast Ohio,
same medicine, same dose, same
protocol for recovering memories
of the session. So I think that
established a very unusually
stable listening post as I
entered into this dialog with
the universe.
Frank McCaughey: Yeah, I always
admire works of patience. And 20
years is, is a work of is, yeah,
is patience. And I I like, in a
way, how, when you're
approaching the psychedelics at
the moment, obviously, you get a
huge amount of coverage there. I
suppose if you're into the
subject at all, it seems to be
everywhere, and in especially in
the last six or seven years,
it's in mainstream media, all of
the work, and then you have all
these conferences. But the harsh
side of, let's say, the dark
side of psychedelics are not
spoken about. Maybe they are. I
feel that they're not as well
documented in terms of the
levels to which the mind you,
the places you can go. And I
feel you really have captured
that so because that really
comes across very early on, and
we don't want to give away the
entire book, obviously, and
going through it, but it does,
you do capture the, yeah, I
mean, this is not like somebody
is going and getting high with
friends for 73 times. Obviously,
you've just said that you go
through your, you had your
rigorous sort of process, but
you are going into the depths of
suffering, living and being
suffering, and how to go, how do
you go back into that every time
knowing it's like, you know
you're getting suited and ready
for war, almost,
Chris Bache: yeah, in a way. I
mean, you have to go through the
same type of mental preparation
that a soldier does before
battle and a mother does before
labor, you just really be
focused, internalized and ready
for whatever the day may bring.
You know at the end of the first
chapter, I said the single
greatest concern I have about
bringing the story of my journey
forward is the amount of
suffering that it contains. And
so I take some time to try to
explain to the reader to prepare
the reader for what this
suffering, suffering represents,
and specifically the suffering
of death and rebirth. This is,
this is one of the natural
components of deep work with
psychedelics that in order to
move into a deeper state of
consciousness, a state of
consciousness where you can
experience things that the
physical consciousness cannot
experience. You must surrender
deeply your attachment to your
physical consciousness, to your
embodied identity, and you go
through a Death-Rebirth process.
It's that first level of death
and rebirth around ego. Death, I
think, is frequently discussed
and honored in the therapeutic
discussion. But what I think is
less attended to is the fact
that when you go into still
deeper levels of consciousness,
beyond the early levels and
beyond the middle levels, you
have to go through the same
process of radical surrender of
everything you've known to be
true up to that point in time.
So you have to surrender even
your own LSD experiences, your
psychedelic experiences, in
order to go through yet another
round of death and rebirth in
order to wake up to yet another
deeper dimensions of existence.
So if you're going to press the
journey hard or long as I did,
you're going to go through a lot
of purification, a lot of
detoxification, and a lot of
death and rebirth. And the
reason I think you go through so
much purification is I think
every time, every deeper level
of the universe operates at a
higher level of energy. So if
you're going to break through to
a deeper level of consciousness
and a deeper level of the
universe, you have to go through
a purification process so that
your consciousness can stabilize
effectively at that deeper level
of consciousness, so that you're
in. Awareness can remain
coherent there, and otherwise,
if you don't, your awareness
will always remain fragmented.
You won't be able to bring back
the coherent experience. But
there is a lot of suffering.
It's not like there's suffering
in the universe, but if you want
to explore the universe, you
must be willing to go through a
deep series of purifications,
purifications unto death, in
order to enter into that dialog,
that communion,
Frank McCaughey: and what do you
what do you think death is?
Chris Bache: Well, as I say in
the book, eventually you come to
a point. If you've gone through
many cycles of death and
rebirth, you come to a point
where the death loses its
meaning, because you've learned
from experience that you can
die. You can lose all your
reality reference points,
everything you know yourself to
be can be shattered and
destroyed, but the Phoenix
always rises. You always wake
up. You a changed you always
awakens in a deeper capacity and
a deeper level of reality. So
from this perspective,
eventually you learn that there
is no such thing as death. There
is only the shedding of one
particular set of parameters
within which awareness operates,
shedding those parameters and
letting consciousness expand to
a deeper experience of reality.
What we usually mean, and I
think death of the physical body
is something very similar what
you go through in an LSD
session, deep one that type of
death approximates what happens
when you go through physical
death. The body dies, you lose
your physical reference points.
Consciousness expands into a
deeper and broader universe, but
eventually the very concept of
death loses its meaning in this
respect.
Frank McCaughey: Yeah, yeah, it
was two ways I was going to go,
some I'll come back. I'll come
back to the way I was going to
go on that, the grueling impact
of that on like I spoke to
somebody, and in a way, it's
existent. It can be
existentially violent, a
psychedelic experience. Yes, is,
and there's moments. I mean, I
think that's a good it's a good
description, existentially
violent, fair description. And
what's like, and that, I don't
think also that you ever get
comfortable. It's not like you
suddenly go, Okay, I've done 50,
and this is going to be no
problem, because there's bigger
levels. Is that fair to say that
I
Chris Bache: thought that you
would go through a period of,
you know, Death-Rebirth and
purging and whatnot, and you
would get to a stable place, and
all all entries from that point
on would be clearer and easier.
I found that that's not true,
that the in the universe is
infinitely deep with an infinite
number of levels. And as long as
you keep pushing the outer edges
of your experience, if you're
willing to go farther, the
universe will keep taking you in
deeper. And it always will
require some deep surrender,
some death and rebirth process,
to move deeper into it.
Frank McCaughey: And when you
when you say, universe, what?
What do you? What's that to you?
What is the nice? What's that
word mean to you?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, my
experience is, of course, when
you let go of consciousness at
the physical level, you enter
into a deeper dimension of
consciousness, and then later is
still a deeper dimension, and
it's all coherent from top to
bottom, and it is all
fundamentally unified. For me,
it never took a face. It never
showed an identity as such. It
was always open ended and
perpetually fluid and invisible
and yet very deeply felt. So
what do we call this thing? What
do we call this consciousness,
which we dissolve into at
successive levels. Some might
call it the infinite, the
absolute. I call it both of
those things. I call it the
creative intelligence of the
universe. It feels to be the
creative intelligence that's
inside the universe and behind
the universe, different aspects
coming forward at different
times. In the end, in my heart
of hearts, I call it my beloved
because you do once you enter
into it, once you dissolve into
it, once you recover your true
idea. Entity within its
identity. Then it opens up
dimensions of love within you,
and it pours dimensions of love
within you that it becomes my
beloved. Sometimes I call it the
great expanse, something to
suggest the vastness, its
vastness, its power, its
creativity, its intelligence,
and of course, since compassion
is a mark of oneness, its
inherent oneness, so that
compassion is a spontaneous
manifestation of its innate
oneness.
Frank McCaughey: Yeah, it's
funny. I think he quoted some an
Indian guru who used the word
the beloved, and was the guy in
England he would refer to
oneness. So he would refer to
the Beloved. Tony Parsons would
talk about unconditional love,
that that it's, but not the love
that we would know it's, it's
love beyond conditions beyond
it's not a personal it's the
allowance of all things.
Chris Bache: Yeah, it's, it's a
deeper love than human love, but
I think it is alive in the best
of us when we experience love.
But it is. It is. It's a radical
love. It's a It's the love that
the Dao has for the 10,000
things. You know, it's, it is
the love that being has for its
own self, for its own being.
Because, in the end, from its
perspective, all of us and all
of creation is a manifestation
of its being. So how could it
not love itself? And therefore,
how could it not love us?
Frank McCaughey: So let's see,
can we? I'm going to go this
route. Let's see where it goes.
Say the idea of my beloved and
who do you think is describing
when you say it's my who is
describing the beloved? You know
this sort of perspective,
because there is a perspective
that it cannot see itself, only
in reflections, and it because
it is already what's happening.
The Beloved is already what's
happening there. Yeah, it can't.
It can only ever appear as,
yeah, you know where I'm going
with that. Or do you have your
sense? Yeah, I'm going with
that? Yeah, I do. It's very hard
to objectify in a way, when that
objectifying is almost what is a
part of the Beloved is that
happening already? It's fresh
already. Yeah, it's already
complete. In other words, what
you're saying there, whilst
we're kind of talking about
experience that you've had and
you've written a book, it's, it
gives the impression of being
Once removed, but obviously it's
a part already.
Unknown: Yeah, you know, we have
all sorts of ideas and stories
we tell ourselves about what
this totality consciousness is
and isn't and what it can know
and can't know. And I think a
lot of that is just cultural
scripting. It's our best guess.
It's our best cultural guess,
and our best cultural guess is
not very old at this juncture,
we've been kind of making these
metaphysical guesses or
intuitions for 5000 years, but
this intelligence is 13.7 plus
billion years in the making and
unfolding, and we're just kind
of getting to the stop place in
our evolution where we can
really begin to engage it. So my
sense is I don't know whether
this intelligence is not self
aware, except through us that
seems kind of outrageously puts
enormous privilege of place on
us as to be the mirror of the
Divine Eye. Why should we assume
that this intelligence is not
self aware as it unfolds itself
with seeming pointed accuracy
through time and space? So what
I can say is this, when I lose
my boundaries as Chris Bache,
when I allow myself to dissolve
as Chris Bache and enter into
these deeper layers. There's
many, many layers of this
phenomenon. So some of the early
layers have to do with my
species consciousness, the mind
of the collective unconscious,
the mind of my species. Other
layers have to do with the mind
of our planet, Gaia
consciousness. And there are
multiple layers going right
through species mind, the
archetypal mind, archetypal
dimensions, the root causes of
some of the patterns inside time
and space, the root cause even
of time and space itself, moving
even deeper into dimensions of
oneness. Permutations of
oneness, even entering into the
primal void that appears to be
the formlessness out of which
all form emerges with the Big
Bang and subsequently, and then
entering beyond even that. And
at each level of entry, entering
into clearer and clearer and
clear states of being, states of
awareness. Now, yeah, that and
so it's hard for me to imagine
that the being or dimension of
being that I have been in it for
hours at a time, would not also
be self aware in its unfolding.
Now, it's also been the case
that I've had the experience
that this creative intelligence,
or an aspect of creative
intelligence, met me in my
sessions, took me on a cosmic
tour, you know, in that chapter,
initiation into the universe,
and it seemed to want to show me
its work. It seemed especially
pleased to have evolved
consciousness to the point where
some of that consciousness could
come back and be shown what has
actually been being worked on
for billions and billions of
years. So it seems to delight in
being known. But I wouldn't say
necessarily that it didn't know
itself before I knew it. You
know what? I mean. Yeah.
Frank McCaughey: And did you get
a sense of do you still have a
sense of the despite having
spent so much time that, in a
way, you're still only it's
impossible. It's so the
vastness, the extra, the
scraping the surface, the
enormity of the all of
everything.
Chris Bache: So this was a major
change in my thinking. It took
place in the 50th session. So,
so my background is I did four
years of work. I stopped for six
years, and then I did 10 years
of work, so 14 years of active
work over 20 years, when I was
entering into the last five
years of work, or those years of
what I call the diamond
Luminosity work. And this was 26
sessions out of 26 sessions,
that's about a third of all the
sessions in the book. Four of
those sessions took me into this
diamond Luminosity, an
unbelievably beautiful,
ecstatic, empty consciousness
that was just clear, just clear
beyond imagination, just so
clear, so hyper clear, that once
you touch it, nothing else
matters except returning to it.
Nothing else I had entered in
earlier stages mattered in the
least compared to connecting
with this. And this is what the
Buddhists call, I think the
closest thing I could find is
what they call Dharmakaya. You
know, they have three
dimensions, or three modalities
of existence, Dharmakaya,
sambhogakaya and Nirvana, Kaya
Dharmakaya being the deepest,
and Dharmakaya the absolute, the
light of the clear light of
absolute reality, just kind of
the light out of which existence
emerges. I'm sorry I got so
involved in the description. I
lost track with the the original
question, focus.
Frank McCaughey: Well, I think I
know we are going though,
because we were talking about
the vastness and scraping the
surface. And you said, yeah,
yeah.
Unknown: So I was 50 sessions
in. I was in the second of the
four diamond Luminosity
sessions, I was as deep into
ecstatic diamond consciousness
as I had ever gone and would
ever go. It was the deepest
penetration in that way. And
toward the end of the session, I
had this experience where my
visual feel flipped 90 degrees.
A huge space opened up. And
beyond where I was, there was
another reality, worlds upon
worlds beyond me. And there was
a light there, and a beam of
this light hit me, and it
shattered me. And I called the
light the absolute light, just
to give it a differentiating
name from the diamond Luminosity
light. But what it showed me was
that there were worlds and
worlds beyond where I was, as
far beyond where I was as the
diamond Luminosity was beyond
time and space. So that told me
that an idea that I had taken
into this work, that the purpose
of this work was to get to an
end point, an end stage, a
destination to go home,
something like this that that
was just not an accurate
assumption. You do repeatedly
have a sense of going home. You
do enter into deep, deep
experiences of Homecoming. And
for me, the diamond. Luminosity
was my actual practical
destination. I did not go deeper
than that. It totally satisfied
me in all respects. I continued
to do the session work, but for
the next 23 sessions, it wasn't
going deeper into the diamond
Luminosity, but it was
internalizing diamond
Luminosity, soaking deeper and
deeper into my physical and
psychological being. But it's an
infinite ocean. And I don't I
gave up completely the idea of
ever getting to the end of it
Frank McCaughey: unfathomable.
It's unfathomable everything.
Unknown: Well, in a sense, I
mean, I have a tendency that,
you know, what is the term we
use for not being able to
ineffable? You know, we like to
say the mystical is ineffable.
And I don't necessarily agree
with that. I think that's that's
true. I understand, you know,
language falters, but I think
making ineffability a primary
characteristic of mystical
experience. I think it cuts off
rather than opens up. I think we
should exhaust ourselves trying
to describe what lies at the
edges of our awareness, rather
than surrendering to the silence
so unfathomable in one sense,
but not unfathomable. In another
sense, I think I fathomed what I
entered. I mean, I went back
again and again and again, and I
stabilized consciousness and I
understood it, but there are
dimensions beyond which I
understood, and even my
understanding of what I
experience is admittedly
limited, okay, but I wouldn't
want to say that the reality
itself is innately unfathomable.
I think we can fathom, but it
takes hard work and discipline.
Okay?
Frank McCaughey: There's a part
of the book and it's, I think it
kind of describe the it's the
royal we. Let's just say, you
kind of describe it's us. You
say us creating everything the
royal us. No, you haven't used
the word the royal, but that's,
that's the sense of me. It's
kind of that, it's a generic
feeling of usness, but in that,
yeah, I was just curious a
little bit. What does that bring
back to you when I when I
mentioned that, that creation,
what does that say? Yeah, what
does that remind you of?
Unknown: First of all, this
reminds me to mention that this
book is not primarily a
therapeutic story, and it's not
a story about my personal
healing or my the work that the
advice or the counsel that I got
from the universe at a personal
level, for my personal life.
It's not that I didn't receive
those things. I did receive
those things, but I've dropped
them out for the most part, in
the story. In the story, I'm
focusing on what took place
during the peak hours of these
high, intense sessions. And it's
a fundamentally, a cosmic,
logical story. It's a story
about the universe and about the
aspects of these sessions that
have generalizable significance,
where we're touching dimensions
of reality, that are dimensions
that all human beings share in
one way or another. So sometimes
I speak about the we in the book
because I'm basically
acknowledging that what's
important in these experiences
is not that I experience them.
That's not the important thing.
The important thing is that
these dimensions are available
for all of us to experience if
we use sufficient technologies
and techniques to get into these
territories, including non
psychedelic techniques,
meditation, contemplation,
silence, so on, so forth. That's
the important story. So when,
when you enter these profoundly
expansive, encompassing states
of consciousness, you're, you're
not an eye when you go into it,
you're, you're, there's an eye
in the sense that you have
continuity of memory when you go
in and you come back, you can
remember it. So there is a sense
in which I is present in order
to facilitate recall. But what
this i has become in the point
of entry, you have ceased to
function as an individual. In
some of these, I cease to
function as a human being, per
se, when you're operating beyond
the species mind at archetypal
reality levels, you have to
cease to function as a human
being and you left. Have to
learn how to be conscious and.
Not as a human being is
conscious, but in a totally new
and unprecedented way, and the
universe will take you in and
teach you it mean you literally
will give you exercises and
disciplined exercises, which you
repeat. It repeats over and over
inside the sessions, and you
have to take the set the
assignments you're given in the
sessions after the sessions and
do your homework in order to
kind of enter fully consciously
into subsequent sessions. Yeah,
I've meander a bit on your
question, but you
Frank McCaughey: get, I mean,
it's kind of interesting,
though, even though you didn't
mention the personal journey
really in the book, like you say
it was the bigger, let's say or
the but it's funny how the
psychedelics seem to always
remind that element. And it's
kind of like, you know, it'll
give you this list of things.
Let's say ace will get but there
will be that will come up every
time. Yes, it's almost like,
have you been doing this, this,
this, this, or, you know, but
it's kind of like, your de,
your, I don't know what it is
exactly. Maybe it's eating well,
being nicer. It's all kind of
very personal things. Yeah,
Chris Bache: it's personal.
Yeah. I mean, I own the journey.
It was my journey, and it has
all my limitations into it, in
it, and what's important is
whatever I experience, that it
be placed on a table beside
other people's experiences. And
we look at lots of people's
experiences simultaneously to
find how they fit together.
What's the common ground, what's
idiosyncratic. You know, if from
a philosophical perspective, I
want to know what's real, and
one of the best ways to know
what's real is, you know,
compare lots of people's
experiences of this reality, so
we can see it through that
prism. But within my own
experience, I I own that it is
my journey. It's a personal
journey, and yet the most
important parts of the journey
didn't really involve me. In a
sense, let's say the filter of
Chris Bache was highly polished
away, shattered, deconstructed
at the most important parts of
the journey.
Frank McCaughey: And do you
think, in a way, the you know,
when you went through this
suffering, the humongous amount
of that suffering, the ocean of
suffering, the ocean suffering,
he called it, yeah, an ocean is
pretty big. And do you just talk
about the ego death a little bit
there, within that ocean of
suffering? Do you think that you
were there in that or there was
just the suffering, if you know
what I mean, there was Yeah. Or
were you in that suffering? Or
then every time it felt like
it's almost, I had to go through
all that to be it's like the
dying on the cross, that kind of
symbology of all that suffering
is almost to kill the
resistance, and then within that
the expansiveness can happen.
Yeah, is that true?
Unknown: Well, my understanding
of the ocean of suffering
deepened and changed over the
years. What happened is, after
about two years, two and a half
years of work, first 10
sessions, I went through what
Stan Grof describes as the
perinatal level of
consciousness, I felt like a
poster child for the perennial
severe seizures, existential
crisis, confronting the
meaninglessness of life so on so
forth, reliving aspects of my
birth and eventually went
through a deep and shattering
ego death experience, where
everything I knew myself to be
was turned inside out, and I was
forced to become the opposite of
what I knew myself to be. I I
was a male, highly educated,
white academic obsessed with the
meaning of life. I became women,
lots of women, women of color,
women who had no philosophical
interest whatsoever, and and
basically it just shattered me,
just shattered my identity and
then took me into a deeper
spiritual dimension. After one
transition experience, I went
then from that condition into
the ocean of suffering, which
was an expanding landscape that
was systematic, expanded year by
year for over two years of
active session work, 14
sessions, just horrendous planes
of human suffering, opening to
1000s and 1000s of beings, 1000s
of years, just unimaginable,
brutal, brutalities. And at
first I thought this. Was a
deepening of my ego death. I
didn't understand why I had to
go through this, but based on
the information that I was
working on at the time, I
thought it was a deepening of
ego death. But over time, I
changed my mind on that, and
that is now I understand that
there are different levels of
the universe, and what's
happening differs according to
which level you're operating on.
At this level of the universe, I
was operating in subtle level
reality. I was operating in the
context of the species mind, and
that these tremendous
purification processes, this
encounter and an opening to the
pain, and letting the pain in
that it moved through me was not
really aimed at my personal
transformation, but was aimed at
transforming some aspect of the
collective psyche, so that the
healing being generated here was
Gen was aimed at my species, not
at me personally. And this built
up for two years. Actually,
there was one year I stopped.
For six years I started, then
six years later, and the ocean
of suffering started exactly
where I had stopped six years
before. And it continued to
deepen and deep, and eventually
reached a crescendo of an orgy
of suffering and pain, and then
I was spun into archetypal
reality, and the ocean of
suffering never returned. So I
think that just as there was a
process of cleaning out the
personal unconscious leading an
ego death, there was a cleaning
out or healing of some aspect of
the collective unconscious, and
then being spun beyond the
species mind into archetype
levels of reality. The what,
what prevents this suffering
from being internalized in your
system is trauma. Is that when
you do this work, if you
surrender completely and let the
session take you wherever it
wants to take you, even though
it doesn't make sense at the
time, it will take you to a
culmination, a breaking point,
and then you will be spun
through that. You'll go through
to a point of reconciliation, of
ecstatic embrace. And then what
you internalize and love, what
you internalize then is the
whole cycle, the trauma, the
physical violence, or the
psychological violence,
breakthrough and reconciliation
harmony so that it doesn't
internalize as trauma. You learn
the cycle. You trust the cycle.
I was willing to go back into
the pain for two reasons. One,
because I felt a calling to it.
I felt a destiny calling me to
engage this pain for in ways I
explain in the book. But the
other one is that I really
wasn't a glutton for pain. I
hated the pain. I was a glutton
for what lay on the other side
of pain, or the insights and the
ecstasy that I got on the other
side one I started going through
on the second year of this ocean
of suffering, and I broke
through into these series of
sessions that I summarized in
that chapter, initiation of the
universe. One of the first
things it did was take me deep,
deep, deep in time back to what
felt to be the font of creation.
And there I was. I experienced
the beginnings of creation, the
Big Bang type of experience, and
I experienced it as a choice
that in some strange way, I and
all of us had participated in
that we chose to participate in
creation, we chose to
participate voluntarily in the
act of creating a universe,
galaxies, solar systems, the
human species, that the
suffering that we've encountered
on this agenda, on this
adventure, is not being
inflicted on us. It's something
we chose as kind of a passage, a
rite of passage to participate
in the creation, or the self
expression, the self
manifestation of our universe.
Chose, chose, yeah, hard to say
what that means at the level of
soul that we're talking about,
but we're, but there are no
conscripts here we are
volunteers
Frank McCaughey: during the
book. There is a part you
mentioned. Think he's, I think
you said the sense of no
beginning,
Chris Bache: no beginning. Have
to think about that. I you know
that doesn't ring a bell. I'd
have to,
Frank McCaughey: yeah, well,
say, say this. Idea, it does
explode time.
Psychedelics, explodes the sense
of duration, or, let's just say,
this idea of the infinity or
eternity or timelessness, maybe
more. So
Unknown: there's different
modalities in which time exists
that you experience in
psychedelic states. There is an
experience of timelessness, or
moving beyond time, moving
outside of time and space.
That's I've had that experience.
I've gone there. But there's
another more subtle dimension of
time, experience that I call
deep time. Deep Time is moving
into temporal envelopes, where
different spans of time can be
experienced as simultaneously
now, so in one of the early
sessions and teens, I
experienced stably in seven
consecutive sessions my life
from beginning to end, all the
experiences of my life as
simultaneously taking place now.
So I experienced what it felt
like to be old in a distilled
essence kind of way. Later on, I
was taken into larger segments
of deep time, what I would call
collective deep time, where I
was being taught or shown
aspects of human evolution that
required a larger time landscape
in order to show them to me,
maybe a landscape of 100,000
years or so, and at the very end
of the journey, in The 70th
session, and what I call the
final vision, I was taken into a
temporal landscape. Who knows,
hard to describe the scale, but
somewhere on the order of maybe
a million years. So what I've
come away with is the conviction
that there, there are different
modalities of time operating
within the universe, and I don't
be begin to understand how this
is possible. I've had some
interesting conversation with
some physicists who are
exploring different temporal
dimensions within the universe.
I'm not a physicist. All I know
is that I've been taken in and
out of time multiple ways, in
multiple frames of reference,
only one of which is a negation
of time in itself. Most
frequently it allowed to
experience different modalities
of time or different
aggregations of time.
Frank McCaughey: Yeah, I suppose
the answer, the idea, if I said
to you, there is no time, what
would
Unknown: you I would I would say
there are dimensions of
existence in which that's true.
Time comes into existence with
space. Time and Space is a sort
of a fundamental unit. So when
one moves, in a sense, to the
edges of space, you move into
domains where time behaves
differently. So within space,
time, this time is very
convenient. You know, the arrow
of time is generally true. But
that doesn't seem to exhaust the
whole of the universe with
respect to time. We now know
that what 96% of the universe is
dark matter and dark energy,
which we don't know what the
hell is going on there. So we're
now getting used to
understanding that time space is
really just like the skin of an
apple. There's a lot going on
underneath the skin of the
apple. That's true for space.
It's also true for time, I
think.
Frank McCaughey: And do you
think time is related to the
sense, this sense of, I an ego
would say, or a sense of this
that when there is a center in
the universe, let's just say,
you know, when you're location
based, and then sometimes during
the trip, you can be exploded.
It can be just gone, gone gone,
gone, gone, gone.
Unknown: And
Frank McCaughey: in that even
this idea of any time, that it's
almost a requirement of a
separate human who lives in
time, and is certain amount of
finite. And who knows the world
knows this is earth, and this is
2019 and all these pillars of
knowledge, and that's what's the
little piece in the center of
all of that is that holds it
together, this little me and
this world, and that when that's
say gone, that there's just
timelessness and in that it's
whatever appears. So, yeah,
whatever is appearing here in
this conversation is all of
everything. And whatever appears
in the vastness of one of those
trips is all of everything.
Yeah. Yeah, yeah,
Chris Bache: you describe very
nicely. I like your description
of how individual awareness kind
of anchors our sense of time,
and when individual awareness is
shattered or blown out, then our
sense our experience of time
changes. Now I don't know
whether for everybody, when
individual awareness becomes
transparent, or Shunyata
emptiness or is blown out. I
don't know whether everybody
necessarily flips into pure
timelessness. My sense, I'd
rather say there are different
modalities of time that we can
move into when we are don't are
not so heavily grounded in our
physical body, sense of
identity, okay, but yeah, time
becomes porous. Times becomes
well, becomes porous, and we can
experience we can have insights
that have to do with future, so
called future time. We can have
insights of what's going on that
violate the patterns of space.
We can know something that's
going on that's outside of our
physical senses, that's
happening now, but far away in
space. We can have experiences
of something that's happening
far away in time. So time does
get permeable,
Frank McCaughey: yeah, yeah. And
not, you did speak a bit, a bit
about this, somehow being able
to see futures, and I'd be
familiar with that, and I've
heard it in a good few places
too. It's, yeah, it does
collapse a lot of things. What
was I going to ask? You the I
suppose,
yeah, in that kind of say, Yeah,
I'll just describe something to
you. One thing that I and I
think you've definitely you
touched a big bit in the book is
this idea that you come out of
this trip having, let's just
say, tasted the infinite, and
then you're gone from that's
gone, and you're back to being
Chris In the world, having to
get up and do taxes, whatever,
and that sense of loss, that it
wasn't a feeling of it, not for
you now, it wasn't ever present,
or was that true is there's a
big bit about that kind of loss,
of the Feeling that you lost,
the beloved, that Sacramento is
almost coming back.
Chris Bache: Yeah, when one
does, allows one's egoic reality
or Body, Mind identity to
dissolve and experiences that a
deeper landscape of the
universe, some aspect of the
universe, it's a it's an awfully
exciting and affirming and
empowering experience, just to
have that experience of some
aspect of the intelligence that
runs through all things, that is
alive in all things, to have
insights that convince you that
you yourself participate in that
intelligence, and you yourself
are alive in time in a way that
expands beyond your traditional
ways of thinking. In my case, I
press so hard and so deep into
the fabric of existence into the
fabric of the creative
intelligence I pushed into the
diamond body of I'm hesitant to
speak about God and the divine
because that has those words
have so much cultural baggage
around them I don't Want to
import. But inevitably, I you
have to speak about a purified
or cleaned up vision of the
divine in order to that's the
closest vocabulary our culture
has for pointing to these
extreme facets of existence. I
pushed so deeply into that
touched it so intimately that
when I stopped my sessions, not
until I stopped my sessions, as
long as I was going back and
touching this reality
periodically through the years,
I didn't have this sense of a
deep sadness that took came over
after I stopped my sessions, I
stopped my sessions, and in the
years following, I began to miss
this dimension of existence.
There were good reasons, which I
explained in the book, why I
felt I had to stop my work, but
the consequences of stopping the
work was not being able to. Have
even a few hours at a time, a
few times a year, of exquisite
intimacy with this reality. Now
there are beings who, because of
their spiritual practice, are
able to maintain some type of
version of this intimacy with
Transcendence, with the divine
in their daily life, and I
understand that all power and
honor to the great masters,
they're my heroes. They're my
guiding lights. I knew that in
my case, I did not have the
capacity at this stage in my
life to stabilize these extreme
states of consciousness. It
would take not only years and
years, but lifetimes of
spiritual practice to succeed in
doing that. So there was a sense
of true sense of loss. I had to
content myself with having had
these experiences, but not being
able to abide continuously in
those experiences. And that
took, that took a while. I mean,
I basically went into a sadness
that was so deep that I found
that I was just waiting to die.
I was I was taking care of my
children, I was lecturing, I was
doing my my work, but in my
heart, I was just waiting to die
so that I could return to the
light. And that, over time, I
began to realize, you know, that
was really not a good way to
live. I really had to see what
was at the bottom of this, and
what was at the bottom of this,
I think, is an imbalance that I
allowed to develop between
Transcendence and imminence.
It's all the divine. The
physical world is the divine,
but there's a transcendent
divine and the imminent divine.
And I had plunged so deep into
the joy of the transcendent
divine that to a certain degree
I lost my footing inside the
imminent divine, and I had to
really recommit myself to
grabbing my physical existence
and being what I was as I was
here, incomplete, as I was for
the remainder of my life. And I
did, and I have kind of I'm
fully grounded here, and I do my
spiritual practice, and I hope
that my sessions will continue
to absorb themselves into my
body. And my transformation is
not over yet. It's work in
progress.
Frank McCaughey: And so if I was
you mentioned about the Masters
having arrived almost or can I
ask you what what
do you think that would look
like at that place of arrival,
that in daily life?
Chris Bache: Well, again, there
are many, many levels
Frank McCaughey: to say, these
masters that you mentioned, the
masters that you mentioned,
Chris Bache: but even the
Masters, I mean, there are many
levels of the gradients of
masterhood, and which these
traditions articulate with great
detail. I think the first kind
of point of entry into this
spiritually transformed
existence is one second. Let me
take care of something that's
just popped up on my screen,
which is getting in the way.
Okay, we'll have to let it be
one of the love the point of
entry is, I think, transparency.
We become transparent, we dis we
let go of our ego
identification, and we are able
to be transparent to the larger
flow of life, the larger matrix
of cause and effect, and to the
sheer immediacy of presence
inside the physical existence.
And then from there, they're
just degrees of deepening and
deepening and deepening, so that
some masters have exist in such
a deep intersection of time,
space, reality and spiritual
reality, that they can literally
leave their fingerprints in
stone. I mean, that's how much
energy they're carrying. That's
the level of consciousness that
they're living in. 24/7, so
they're they're very beings. Are
surrounded by what we would call
miracles. But they don't call
them miracles. They call them
the natural consequence of
integrating spirit, reality and
physical reality into their
physical into their precious
body. So there are levels and
levels of mastery I can envision
and imagine what the lower
levels might look like. I mean,
I've taught courses and
comparative mysticism. I've
studied the mystics, but what it
would be like to actually
stabilize what I call the
diamond Luminosity, to live in a
perpetual awareness of diamond
Luminosity, that's hard for me
to. Imagine, likewise, it's hard
for me to imagine being living
in conditions which have
radically transcended time, as I
have experienced for a few hours
at a time here and there. I
mean, that's just a radical
state of consciousness. So I
think in my psychedelic work, I
started it with an eye towards
spiritual awakening,
accelerating my spiritual
enlightenment, personal
transformation, things like this
that quickly fell away as a not
worthy goal for the work that I
was doing. Collective
transformation, collective
enlightenment took its place,
and then later the journey
became a cosmic, logical
adventure, an adventure in
exploring the deep fabric of the
universe its successive levels.
It did not become, did not
retain its role as just trying
to awaken spiritually, awakening
spiritually was is a perfectly
good goal and agenda, but what
happened in my sessions was
about something different than
just awakening spiritually. It
was about exploring the deep
fabric of the universe. And you
don't have to explore the deep
fabric of the universe, to
awaken spiritually and even to
be God realized, even to be kind
of fully saturated with divine
awareness, this is a different
agenda,
Frank McCaughey: Okay, and you
see a part of me when I've I
didn't like the idea that there
was here, and there this idea in
psychedelics, that there was
this realm, and this was not
this realm and that. And so I
always felt a sort of a
dissatisfaction, one way or
another for a period of time,
anyway, that it was kind of
okay. It was hugely
experiential, humongously. But
it's almost it could become
another path. And the path is
endless, in a way, yeah, the
path of this idea of becoming
now that seemed to all fall away
this and in the end, yeah, I
suppose what I'm trying to say
is that, I suppose in the end,
I'm just curious about the first
question I asked at the Start,
and back to here, back and in
your book, during the trips, it
felt like everything was during
the trips, bringing you back to
this every time it seemed to be
this, which I kind of liked
that, because I felt, well, has
to be this, has to be completely
what's happening as well as
anything else. And I'm curious
what's your sense of that,
because it did seem to go full
circle in everything. And I like
that you went to the depths of
hell and the highest heavens.
But every time at the end of the
trip, always you returned. But
even during the trip, it felt
like, towards the end of your
journeys, it felt like you were
brought back to what's
happening. Yeah, and I liked, I
really liked that, because for
me, it has to be, this has to be
within the grasp of a child.
Can't be ugly. It has to be,
this has to be what's happening.
And I kind of liked that in the
book that to give it felt like
everything brought you back to
this is that
Chris Bache: you catch the arc
of it well, and you describe it
well. In the early sessions, the
early years, there was an acute
sense of going out, experiencing
a universe that was sense going
out, coming back, always coming
back to right here, right now,
learning the lessons, but going
out deeper and deeper into the
universe. And then late in the
sessions that changed. There was
less of a sense of going
anywhere, and more of a sense of
being here, right here, right
now. Clear, clear, cleaning,
cleaning, cleaning, right here,
right now. It was as if, after
taking me, excuse me so deep,
and giving me the sample, deep
into the universe, deep into the
diamond Luminosity, and then
showing me that there was a
world among world upon world
beyond that, even still, at that
point, everything shifted in the
last 23 sessions or so, we're
really about cleaning, cleaning,
cleaning, right here, right now.
And the arc of the sessions arc
back towards something alike
classical spiritual awakening to
the here and now, to the
consciousness, which is the ever
the ever pure. Effervescent
source out of which your moment
to moment awareness springs, out
of which the universe springs
moment to moment, bringing back
to here and now, here and now.
Yeah, in the end, I think
everything we do in all
spiritual practice, and
including all psychedelic
practice, is all about
purification. In the deepest
sense, we end up where we
started, except that where we
started our mind was encumbered
by all sorts of conditioning and
obscure obscurations. And in the
end, hopefully those
obscurations are gone and you
have the opportunity to
experience what the Buddhists
call the nature of mind, or your
mind in its natural condition,
or Atman, our Satchitananda,
Frank McCaughey: yeah, and on
that. Then if I said to you that
the beloved never left you, that
this is the beloved happening.
And it's never left,
Chris Bache: never left. Oh, the
physical, the physical world is
the body of my beloved I know
that. It's just that on some
days, I can experience her more
completely than on other days,
and on the days when I can't
experience her completely, and
it's all my fault, only my
fault, only my limitations. I
missed the days when I could
experience her it in complete
transparency and her complete
beauty.
Frank McCaughey: Always say,
it's my fault. That's an
interesting they're interesting
words to say, it's my fault.
Chris Bache: Well, it's my
limitations. It's only my
limitations, you know? So the
limitations are not the
limitations of the substance
itself. They're not the
limitations of reality. It's
only the limitations of my
ability to experience the truth
of what is at any point in time.
Yeah.
Frank McCaughey: I could ask a
couple of sort of questions. You
allude to Alan Watts? Oh, you
can hear me. Sorry, you've got
wireless you allude to Alan
Watts and hanging up the phone,
yeah, this is what happens when
you don't hang up the phone,
which I think is a great, it's a
great way to describe the book,
Kid essence, this is what
happens when you don't hang up
the phone. Yeah. What's your
sense of that? Not really a
question, but it's, well, that
was a big thing like
Chris Bache: it is, I mean,
Huston Smith, when he wrote his
book cleansing the doors of
perception, which is his
collected reflections on a
lifetime of scholarship as a
professor of religious studies,
and one that I'm very close to,
because I taught out of Huston
Smith's books For decades in my
world religions course. So I've
internalized his mind a lot, but
when he wrote that collection of
essays, he had only taken LSD
six times, and he said at that
point, the bummers increased and
the benefits decreased, and he
took Alan watches adage
seriously, when you get the
message, hang up the phone. And
I said, this book is about what
happens if you don't hang up the
phone, and if you don't hang up
the phone, a long journey
begins, a journey that goes
deeper and deeper and deeper.
And I understand where the
bummer is increased. That's part
of the Death-Rebirth cycle. But
if you're willing to submit to
those bummers, or you're willing
to submit to that purification
process. The adventure begins.
The adventure deepens, and
you're just taking on layer
after layer this following the
cycle of death and rebirth into
deeper levels of initiation. As
a philosopher that was
extraordinarily valuable to me.
Now, when you say we get if you
get the lesson, hang up the
phone. What were they referring
to? I would assume that they're
referring to the lessons of
oneness, which is comes up often
early in the work, the truth of
oneness, the teachings of
oneness, the compassion of
oneness, the ethics of oneness,
the identity that one realizes
one, one realizes that the
entire world is one at its core,
all those things are very, very
good, but there's just so much
more that we can experience if
we if we jump into So my sense
is it's a subtle, interactive
dance between the mind doing the
exploring and the mind being
explored. So small mind, big
mind, and when we that the mind
being explored, that the
Universal Mind is an infinite
mind capable of infinite
experiences. So the mind we drop
into, it acts as a seed,
catalyst. A seed crystal that
cradle catalyzes a certain set
of experiences from its infinite
potential. Those experiences
change us. They illumine us,
they purify us. They help us
face our conference, confront
our restrictions, so that the
next time we drop that mind into
the infinite ocean, it's a
different seed, tree seed
crystal, it's a different mind,
and it elicits a still deeper
set of experiences out of the
infinite potential. And if we
keep this up, we keep this up,
we are changed by the journey.
We the journey deepens. We're
changed. The Journey deepens
that the universe reveals itself
multiple multiple layers of the
universe will systematically
reveal itself in an organized
fashion. My experience, at
least, was that it paid a great
deal of attention to making sure
that I understood every lesson
as it was being given me. There
were some sessions which were
retroactive and really kind of
going back in the past to
explain what I had experienced.
There were some sessions which
were more showing me where we
were going, but they were always
in conscious dialog with this
creative intelligence. So the
journey to me is it's much more.
I mean, right now we're just
getting started on the
psychedelic Renaissance. You
know, very important work. So
important. The ambitions right
now are modest. Get us getting
it legal, learning the biology
of psychedelics more clearly
they're how they do, the work
they do, and healing, healing
the personal psyche, healing
from post traumatic stress,
healing from depression, healing
death anxiety, really, really
important work, but healing the
personal unconscious is just the
first stage, or the early stage
of a much, longer journey of
exploration,
Frank McCaughey: yeah, yeah,
that's for sure.
It's huge. I suppose what I'm
saying and that, I think, in a
way, the person that a lot of
you see, for me, the first of
all, this idea of the hang
hanging up the phone, or not
hanging up the phone, I think
that's just a it's just a
sentence. It oneness is doing it
73 times, and oneness is doing
it once. So that's to me, it's
all happening and anyway, and I
suppose I what I'm in, I think
the message is this, that it's
a, it's, it's, it is doing the
trip 55 times, 73 times. And
it's, it's in the doing, and
that the hanging up the phone is
that it's, it's, you can't hang
up really, because that's who's
going to hang up, in a way, and
that, that this is the only
message is that this is it, but
it's not a kind of A fixed it.
Yeah, yeah. That's
Chris Bache: the things. It's
things, it turns out, is when
you go in and out of
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness repeatedly, you in
this way, you just, you really
have to face that terrible
moment when you realize that
everything you've experienced in
your sessions is taking place.
24/7, you're just not tuned into
it. So the joy, the beauty, the
work, the clarity, all of that
is taking place continuously.
Oneness does not stop being
oneness just because you start
being amount of paying attention
to it. It's all taking place
seriously, so that you begin to
realize, my God, I'm living in
heaven. If I pay attention, if
I'm if I'm not paying attention,
then I'm living in the hell of
Samsara, where where we are just
pieces bumping around in a
meaningless universe. But if I'm
paying attention, the innate
oneness of the world springs
into flower around us.
Frank McCaughey: So, yeah, well,
you see, I think that's that
shimmering line between what's
happening and stories from the
past and from the future, but
within what's happening there's
no room for it's almost
objectifies the universe by
creating that separation that
I'm here and I can pay attention
to the world out there, and
that's that reinforces the
separation that really it isn't
separate anyway, there is no
separation. I. Away.
Unknown: Yeah, yeah. And in
these sessions, you don't study
the universe as if through a
microscope. You open up to that
part of your being where you are
already that part of the
universe. So it's always a
matter of dissolving boundaries
within your own awareness that
allows you to experience, as you
say, what is right here right
now. So you dissolve the part
that keeps you separate from it,
and when you then dissolve
completely into what's here
right now, you then experience
different aspects of what's here
right now. And so then
Frank McCaughey: beyond stories
and beyond thing, do you know
what you are?
Chris Bache: If I if I don't
know what I am right now, it's
not because the universe hasn't
beaten it into my head
repeatedly and just showed me
mercilessly the truth of my
being and the truth of all of
our being. So I'd say, Yeah, I
know what I am. That doesn't
mean I can always hold that in
my awareness. 24/7, but I've had
ample experiences of of what I
am, and that my identity is
essentially the identity of the
totality. And with that
experience, there's tremendous
relief, tremendous release. All
judgments are dissolved. All
judgments good or bad are
dissolved. There is just the
infinite joy of one's true
nature, one's true reality, and
then the joy of living
consciously in that reality,
rather than living unconsciously
in that reality, if we live
consciously in that reality, our
life gets better and better. If
we live unconsciously in that
reality, then we're subject to
the fluctuations of karmic
conditioning. We get caught in
all these scenarios. So the
trick is to stay mindful, to be
aware that we are always in
subtle ways, creating our
reality, and we can always
create a better reality if we
are more transparent to our
nature, which turns out to be
the same nature which is
bubbling up inside every Living
Thing, inside around us, every
person, every object, it's all
one nature, and in that, there
is tremendous relaxation.
Frank McCaughey: I think that's
a nice way to finish. I think
that's keep talking to you, but
we have so the book. Have a
couple of it's available. Is it
online? Now? I'll put a link.
You can send me a link.
Chris Bache: Amazon, I can send
you a link. Amazon.com, in the
United States has it on. They'll
be releasing it November 26 I'm
told that England, Amazon will
not be releasing theirs until
January 2. I would assume that
Ireland probably is more linked
to Amazon com, so either
November 26 in America or
January 2 in UK.
Frank McCaughey: Okay, very
good. And it's on, is it on
Kindle? Also it's, it's both
obvious,
Chris Bache: and there will be
an audio book that will be
released. I just finished
recording, and it's going to be,
I recorded it for inner
traditions, yeah, yeah.
Frank McCaughey: I mean, it's,
it's an epic journey. Epic is
the only way you've gone. And I
like how, like I said, very
start. Also, I like how you
haven't, not necessarily
glamorized. You haven't. This
isn't a prescription. It's a
description of what you have
gone through and experienced and
you've managed. It's like you
when I was a kid, I used to go
into dreams, and I used to try
and take sweets out of the
dreams and bring them home, and
I'd wake up disappointed that I
couldn't bring the sweets out.
But in this book, I think you've
managed to bring a few diamonds
from heaven. So well done, fair
play. And I put the links up,
and I'll do a short version of
this, and then I'll do a longer
one great.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Frank,
thank you for helping me bring
the book forward. I really do
appreciate it. Excellent
questions. I enjoyed our
conversation a lot.
Frank McCaughey: Yeah, likewise.
Thanks for the chat. Thank you
and good luck with this. I hope
it does well.
Chris Bache: Thank you. Thank
you very much. Bye, bye. You.
Day,
Frank McCaughey: hi, if you like
the conversation that I just had
and you'd like more, please hit
the subscribe button. Thank you.
Unknown: Where to take it. Here.