Jef Baker: Author and
psychedelic explore. Chris Bache
meticulously documented the
insights from 73 high dose LSD
sessions conducted over the
course of 20 years, drawing upon
his training as a philosopher of
religion and following protocols
established by Stanislav Grof,
Chris went on a life changing
journey to explore his mind.
What he discovered drew him into
deep communion with cosmic
consciousness. Chris Bache is
professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he
taught for 33 years. Chris is
also adjunct faculty at
California Institute of integral
studies and a fellow at the
Institute of Noetic Sciences, an
award winning teacher Chris
work. Chris's work explores the
philosophical implications of
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, especially
psychedelic states. Chris has
written four books, life cycles,
a study of reincarnation in
light of contemporary
consciousness. Research. Dark
Knight, early dawn, a pioneering
work in psychedelic philosophy
and collective consciousness.
And the living classroom, an
exploration of teaching and
collective fields of
consciousness. And his new book,
LSD and the mind of the
universe, which I must say, is
absolutely brilliant and seems
to be getting really good
reception with everyone I know
that's that's reading it. It is
a different foam of, as you
said, the deepest states that
LSD gives us access to. It
Chris Bache: was a quite an
adventure, quite a long and
interesting journey.
Jef Baker: How long did it take
you to write? Because there's
obviously years of notes, and
well,
Chris Bache: yeah, I had years
of notes, and all the in the 20
years that I did the work, and
then I digested that material
for more years, and then i i
condensed my sessions, took
notes and condensed them and got
prepared, and once I actually
started writing, it took five
years. Okay, so it's a long
project.
Jef Baker: I think it really
highlights the importance of
some type of integration. You
being a writer, obviously that's
your modality of integration.
For others, it's art. For
others, it's music. But yeah, it
really highlights the importance
of finding a way of making sense
of these experiences after the
facts. And I remember reading in
the book that you would take the
time to write as soon as
possible after such an
experience, and to use the music
that you had played during the
sessions as a trigger, as a
memetic device to or a mnemonic
device to those emotions which
can often get lost in the cloud
of the intensity of I guess,
Chris Bache: yeah, let me just
mention something about the
method. Just give a context,
because that was an important
aid in solving a problem. A
challenging with work. Doing the
work the way that I did, what I
did was to work after three
medium dose sessions, always
following Stan Grof protocol. So
I was always totally isolated,
always working with the sitter,
always working with eyeshades
and music. Totally internalized
sessions. After three
preliminary sessions, I did all
the rest of the session. 73
sessions, total, high dose
session. So I was working at,
essentially, I aimed at 600
micrograms, so between 506 100
micrograms. So when you're
working with doses that high,
and you're going as deep in
serial sessions over many years,
recall becomes a serious issue,
because you're just pushing the
boundaries of consciousness so
deeply. So I found that to
record the sessions, it was
important to record them within
24 hours, and recording them
often had me writing at the very
edges of my comprehension,
because I was trying to describe
experiences that were deeply
mysterious to me at the time, so
I found it was a help if I
listened to the music that was
played in the session in exactly
the order in which was played.
And I would play a piece of
music over and over again while
I was trying to record the
session after the day after, and
then when I was done with that
section, I'd go on to the next
piece of music all the way
through, and that really, you
know, because the day after a
session, you're kind of horse
around the edges, but your
verbal functions are back, so
you're one foot in, one foot
out. And I found by listening to
the music, I could get into a
state where. I called it
standing at the edge of the
well, where I would basically
get back in the edge of it and
enough that I could get it down
on
Jef Baker: paper. Yeah, still a,
still a liminal stage. Yes, I
remember. I remember you writing
that some of the things you'd
written down during the session,
it might have been like reality
is, which, at the time, can be
so profound and meaningful, and
you read it back later, and you,
of course, it is safe, is
obviously sifting through that
stuff to to get your teams that
can really
Chris Bache: be applied. And in
general, General, I didn't try
to make notes or record anything
during the session itself,
because I was so far removed
that, you know, I just wasn't
even in touch with my own body,
let alone with anything going on
in the room
Jef Baker: interesting. Because
that's, that's something I've
been thinking a bit about
recently, is recording sessions
in the moment, particularly with
five Meo DMT and Toad medicine,
because people seem to be
channeling stuff. Things are
coming through languages and and
vocalizations that are the quite
simply out of this world, which
there is almost no way of
recollecting afterwards. And so
there does to be some merit in
recording in the moments to
catch up things that might come
through when your vessel is
empty and universal.
Chris Bache: Maybe it may vary
by substance and agenda the
course. The tricky part about
the five Meo experience is how
fast it is. It's short and it's
incredibly fast. And the LSD
experience is very, very long.
It's an eight hour window. So it
each of them pose distinct
challenges for recall and
integration
Jef Baker: as and as generally
applicable across all all
psychic medicines, I think they
all have their own unique
challenges. Defines Grof
protocol, what's I guess, the
key question to begin with is,
what made you decide to do such
large doses, given that Dan's
general in his protocol,
Chris Bache: yeah, well, you
know, in Stan's early work, he
clearly differentiates between
psycholytic or low dose therapy
and psychedelic high dose
therapy. And the protocol for
psychedelic therapy was, they
developed this in Spring Grove
Hospital, and they were trying
to trigger a near death episode
experience with patients who
were terminally ill. So and it
was limited to three sessions, I
thought, well, if you could go
into high dose session space
three times, you could do it
more times. If you could do it
safely three times, you could do
it safely multiple times. And I
guess in the beginning I did
high dose sessions simply
because it was hard to find time
to do sessions in a dual career
marriage. And soon there were
children involved, just to get
in both of our schedules, to get
a day where we could give the
entire day over to this work.
And so I thought I was still
thinking in terms of a personal
model of therapeutic engagement.
So all the Eastern sources that
I had, you know, I'm professor
of religious studies, teaches
religion, psychology of
religion, and these eastern
sources basically said your
karma is ultimately finite, over
even with many lifetimes, your
karma is finite. And I thought
that I could just work through
mine faster by working with high
doses. I knew the sessions would
be hard, but I thought if I
could just stay grounded and
stay focused and confronting the
shadow, I could just work
through my shadow faster that
way, eventually that that whole
protocol was shattered when I
began to realize that what was
happening in my sessions went
far beyond anything that
concerned only my personal
psyche and my personal karma, my
personal soul,
Jef Baker: even after that
point, sorry that would be At
the point of the ocean of
suffering that you experienced
where, yeah, was quite honestly
hard to read that that
experience of the entire
collective human pain throughout
all of history,
Chris Bache: yeah, yeah, it is
hard to read. I had to really
give some careful thought of how
much to expose that because I
know it's challenging for
readers to go into that
material, but just to finish
that other topic, even once I
let go of that personal model, I
found that I developed I liked
where the high dose work took
me. Me, and it took me farther
than I imagined, and I developed
a taste for it. Now I don't
recommend this protocol. I
really don't. I would do it
differently if I were doing it
over again today, I would be
much gentler on myself. I would
balance high dose work with low
dose work. I would balance LSD
with Psilocybin, Ayahuasca, more
organic psychedelics. But at the
time, I mean, this was really, I
started in 79 so I did this work
between 79 and 99 when I was 30
to 50 years old. So at the time,
Ralph, I just, I ended up
pushing myself harder than I
would recommend other people to
push themselves. It's really not
necessary.
Jef Baker: I also got in the
book too, which is good, yeah,
Chris Bache: yeah, yeah. I
thought that the goal was to get
somewhere, you know, to get to
some end point that would be
enlightenment or oneness with
God or the primal void, and I
came to realize that that was a
naive expectation late, I mean,
50 sessions in, I had
experiences which convinced me
that the universe is infinite
and the Divine is infinite.
Well, it's not a matter of
getting to the end or some
ultimate state. It's a matter of
opening ourselves as deeply as
we can to the intelligence of
the universe or to the
intelligence of the Divine,
letting as much of it into us as
possible, and stabilizing it as
deeply as possible.
Jef Baker: So you would have
known that, at least on a
theoretical level, from Eastern
Studies, that that
enlightenment, you know, is,
isn't a destination, it's it's a
journey, as cliche as that may
sound. So you would have gone
into into the sessions with
that, at least in mind as a
conceptual
Chris Bache: Mm, hmm.
Conceptual, yeah, but I found
even even the Eastern models
that I was familiar with and
working with did not
encapsulate, or did not profile
the full scale of the
experiences that opened in this
journey, because I found that,
yes, you can work through
multiple layers of the Bardo,
the inter the after death
states. You can go into extra
Samsara reality, into spiritual
dimensions beyond the Bardo. But
whereas Buddhism, particularly,
which is kind of the the Eastern
traditions that I was most
familiar with and most
comfortable with, even that
tradition sort of stops at that
point and says it invokes the
grand silence. You know, when
the Buddha was asked the
ultimate questions, he invoked
the grand silence. He wouldn't
describe it, and I found that
there were realities that would
open at that dimension that were
just well so beyond that
Jef Baker: grand silence is
correlated with ineffability,
which is often thrown about in
The psychedelic world,
particularly in relation to
these large doses. And I
remember noting the concept of
ineffability in the book that,
yeah,
Chris Bache: well, as I say in
the book, I think ineffability
is overrated, as it's a
category. I mean, it really
comes from William James in
discussing this talk, one of the
qualities of mystical experience
is ineffability. And I of
course, ultimately our rational
mind and our verbal mind fall
silence when confronting the
infinite. But I work very, very
hard to put language to things,
and I believe in pushing
language as far as humanly
possible repeatedly before
surrendering to the ineffable.
So because if we, if we
prioritize ineffability as one
of the primary features of
mystical experience, it almost
as is, is as if we're saying the
divine wants to be not known.
And my experience is that the
divine wants to be known. And so
ineffability, I think, often is.
It's a symptom of hitting our
experiential limits. But if we
it, when we break into a new
level of consciousness, we can't
bring all of it back. There are
gaps in my notes. We just can't
bring it all back. But I found
that if you go back to that same
level of consciousness again and
again and again, I. The
experiences that were
undigestible or unrecognizable
or ineffable in the beginning
become comprehensible with
repetition and with experience.
So to me, if you can't say where
you went, this a little harsh,
but if you can't say where you
went, you probably just got
lost.
Jef Baker: And it reminds me of
McKenna's saying about bringing
back a middle sized fish that
bring something back for the
community. You know, you've been
living in the realms of, you
know, extraordinary
consciousness. You need to bring
back something useful.
Otherwise, what's it for? At
least you can I go bring it back
and articulate it and express
it. And particularly for me,
that's creative. And Devon seem
to have a real sort of purity
about them, that you can create
something beautiful, the
painting or a sculpture, that
others can see and appreciate.
It's one of the it's a true gift
to be able to articulate this
like experience and a creative
manner. Yeah, writing certainly
falls into that category. Yes,
yeah,
Chris Bache: I found it just
takes time. I mean, I've really
had to sit with my experience
for years and years to
understand, in fact, it's a
general rule of thumb, I would
never talk about an experience
till five years after I'd had
it, because it just takes a lot
of time to fully digest and to
understand. In fact, I had the
narrative. Man had recorded my
experiences all the way through,
but I was still learning things
about the journey in the process
of writing the entire journey
down.
Jef Baker: Yeah, I've noticed
that too, when you start to
write things down, other things
fall in it so like, it creates a
space for those perhaps
otherwise forgotten aspects to
drop back in and there's even
aspects of this Amazon shamanic
tradition that say you shouldn't
speak like sharing circles are
not a thing simply because you
by sharing your experience the
next morning, it dilutes it.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I had to
really in Buddhism also, one
does not speak about one
spiritual experiences except to
one's teacher. And I had to sit
with that for a long time,
because Buddhism is, you know,
an important tradition for me,
as all the traditional spiritual
traditions are, but particularly
Buddhism, and I really had to
ponder whether I should even be
talking about these experiences,
but in the end, my experience
was that the universe wanted me
to share what it was that she or
it had allowed me to experience.
I didn't I didn't program my
experiences. I didn't choose
what I experienced. Something
else. Was entirely in control of
my experiences through the
entire journey, and at the end,
you know, the universe made it
clear that said you didn't give
yourself those experiences. We
gave you those experiences.
Those experiences were never
meant for you by yourself. They
were always meant for you to
share with others, and I think
we it's basically no one
person's experiences are really
important, but when all of our
experiences are shared together
in the circle, then we begin to
have a deeper understanding of
this mysterious universe that
we're Exploring. Yeah, and
Jef Baker: can build a cultural
picture that then yeah as a
context for it, yeah. Just to go
back with what you said earlier
about if you were to do it
again, differently, that you
would use different plants,
almost like, and, you know,
different compounds, almost like
building a house. You use
different tools for different
parts of the construction. Do
you work with other plants now?
Or did you end your experiences
at that 73 photos sessions, if
they saw much personal
questions?
Chris Bache: Yeah, no, not at
all. No, I still use medicines
from time to time, though, much
less than I used to. I mean,
somewhat, it's a young man's
game, a young person's game. I'm
70 years old now, so if I
haven't learned by now, yeah,
yeah. So you know, after I
stopped my work, the LSD work in
99 and after that, from time to
time, I would do light sessions,
or I would do Psilocybin
sessions, and a few times
Ayahuasca sessions, or salvia
divinorum. So I, you know,
broaden my experience by working
with those substances. But the
LSD work was in a category unto.
Itself, and I found one of the
things I found was that my body,
my system, was storing energy
over time. So when I was doing
multiple sessions, my system was
storing energy of those sessions
and then using that stored
energy periodically to trigger
breakthroughs into new levels of
consciousness, so that I if I
were to even take a massive dose
of LSD today, I would not be
able to get back to where I was
working regularly when I
finished my work in 99 it would
take years for me to develop the
energy, the power, to be able to
access those deeper dimensions
of of the universe. My
understanding over time that
developed was every step into a
deeper level of consciousness is
a step into a higher energy, a
higher energetic
Jef Baker: state really stood
out that line, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Chris Bache: And it just takes a
long time to develop the power
to access these very, very
highly energized states of
consciousness.
Jef Baker: And I think that's um
working with, with integration,
particularly with five Meo, I
noticed this, a lot of people
can be quite depersonalized,
disassociated after a very high
dose toe session. And one of the
things we advise as embodiment
is to bring that energy back
into the body and to ground it
through the earth, not to go
into meditation, which is going
to get you more into the
ethereal realms, to bring it
back and into the earthly realm,
almost to discharge it. It's
like your body becomes a
capacitor for this energy. Yeah,
it's been an empty vessel to
accept it. You're right. I think
it was a good, good point to
jump into the three other two
phases. You spoke about the
cleansing and the ecstatic
phase.
Chris Bache: Yeah, basically
working the way I did, I found
that my sessions basically had
two phases. Though, at the
beginning of every phase there
was some type of intense
cleansing or purification
process. And if you surrender to
that, if I surrender to that
completely, that would
eventually come hit a peak
threshold, and then there would
be some type of Death-Rebirth
process, and then the rest of
the session was sent in an
ecstatic state, in some type of
transcendent experience of some
form or another. And that
process kept repeating itself
over and over through the years.
Jef Baker: You know, you think
goes all down to the nature of
the compound itself. I guess
just the way LSD works is a
turnaround point halfway at
those days?
Chris Bache: No, I don't think
so. I think we're looking at
it's one of the dynamics of
consciousness that when you are
opening to deeper levels of
consciousness. These deeper
levels of consciousness require
a just to enter them triggers a
purification, a spontaneous
purification of your of your
system, purification of your
thoughts, of your emotions,
purification of your body. And
so just when you're when you're
entering into these very, very
intense, very, very pure states
of consciousness, you just start
a spontaneous detoxification
process. And there's so many
concepts and belief systems and
emotional complexes that we all
carry that have to be taken
apart, have to be undone, if
we're going to experience the
universe at that deeper level.
Jef Baker: On Ayahuasca as and
then obviously the Purge is very
much associated with Ayahuasca,
but as you point out it, it's
applicable to all psychedelic
medicines in which you need to
remove the blockages in your own
system, be they psychological,
emotional, energetic, before you
can open up and then be open to
those levels. And so you
extrapolated three factors from
those two phases to
Chris Bache: refresh me on which
particular ones are you plugging
into there?
Jef Baker: So there's the
cleansing and ecstatic phase
with a sliding line between two
functions of the larger whole
which was influenced by three
factors that related to each
planetary setting,
Chris Bache: yeah, and the and
then first, the depth of the
ecstatic portion of the session
would be was influenced by
several. Factors as I came to
understand it. One of them was
the depth of cleansing that had
taken place in the first part of
the session. So usually, the
deeper the cleansing, the deeper
the ecstatic revelation,
ecstatic entry. The second one
was the depth of cleansing that
had taken place in all of the
sessions up to that point in
time. So naturally, I say in the
book, you expect a deeper
experience 50 sessions into a
journey than on the first couple
of sessions into a journey. And
the third has to do with this
energy quality, the quality of
the massive amounts of energy
that's involved. So when you
work in serial sessions, and I
was doing, on average, about
five sessions a year. So I
worked for four years, I stopped
for six years, and then I worked
for 10 years, and on average, I
was doing about five a year. So
when you're working
systematically like that, you're
taking your body and your mind
into those states. It you build
up this energetic momentum. It's
like an athlete in training. You
know, the more you train, you
build up this, this energy,
which then carries you through
new performance levels. And I
think that happens with the
universe too. It just, it
carries you into deeper levels
of consciousness. I found that I
because these sessions were so
intense and they were so
demanding, psychologically and
demanding physically, I really
had to prepare myself for days
before every session physically,
yoga wise, chiropractic wise,
making sure my body was
carefully aligned, and then
spiritually, dietarily,
spiritually, I would there were
certain practices that I would
do before a session and other
practices that I would do to
integrate the session
afterwards. So yeah, because
it's just so extremely intense.
Jef Baker: It was interesting.
You use the term breadth there
as well, not only depth, but
breadth like width, like a
bandwidth, which is first time
I've heard it sort of referred
to that way.
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, in
certain specific experiences,
the breadth has is a is a
metaphor that describes the ways
in which we connect with
humanity, we connect with other
persons, we connect with nature.
We can enter into states of
consciousness who are extremely
wide. So to speak. Depth is
something different. Depth is
entering into contact with
deeper levels of reality, other
systems of reality, other
beings, archetype of reality,
void, the pure void, cosmic
void, types of reality. Those
are different, different
categories of experience.
Jef Baker: Okay, that might be a
good point to talk about
archetypes.
Chris Bache: Hmm. Well, let me
just kind of lay out some of the
sequences the categories when I
when I got to the end of the
journey, well, I went through
what I experienced as a series
of punctuated death and rebirth
experiences. So I would break
into a new level of
consciousness. I would then
stabilize at that level over
multiple sessions, and I'd
become more familiar with that
level, and I'd get to understand
it more and become more
cognitively how it works and
energetically. Would be purified
by the process of engaging that
level of consciousness. And then
over time, if I kept pushing, I
would come to a threshold, and I
would go through another death
and rebirth process, and that
would drive me into yet another
level of reality, and it would
start all over again, having to
stabilize my consciousness at
that level, having to learn how
to manage the factors at level.
So when I got to the end of the
journey, and I was looking back,
I asked myself, well, how many
levels of consciousness did I
enter, how many fundamental core
platforms did I go through? And
I basically boiled them down to
five. So there was a level of
work at the personal level of
consciousness, and then there
was a level of work at the
collective level of collective
mind, which is where the, you
know, the ocean of suffering,
work, and where the purification
was really aimed at the
purification of the collective
psyche, more than the personal
psyche. And after that, there
was the archetypal dimension of
consciousness, entering into
archetypal consciousness, and
then entering into oneness, or
causal consciousness, and then
entering finally, into what I
call the diamond Luminosity.
Which is what Buddhism would
call Dharmakaya, the clear light
of absolute reality. So for me,
after I went through death and
rebirth at a personal level, and
then after I went through that
took about two years. And then
after two years of work at the
collective level, working at the
in the purification part,
working in the ocean of
suffering work and then
experiencing successive deeper
initiations into the universe,
and a chapter that I call
initiation of the universe. Then
I was spun into archetypal
reality. My experience was when
I entered archetypal reality, I
had the extraordinary sensation
that I was entering a level of
reality that was more real than
time and space was. It was more
real than our lives here was,
and it took me a long time, you
know, several sessions, to
stabilize and to be able to
enter that level of reality. And
the nature of death that was
required to enter that reality
was different than ego death. I
had to literally die as a human
being in order to enter
archetype of reality. So I found
that there was a level of
identity that we all have as
human beings. It's our it's our
humanness. It's our human
identity that's deeper than our
personal identity, and the human
identity had to die in order to
function at a level of
consciousness that allowed me to
have access to levels of reality
beyond human consciousness,
beyond the collective psyche
began the and entering into
archetype of reality. And there
I basically, I only spent about
a year and a half at that level,
I mean, which is not much time.
That just the tip of the
iceberg, in a way, but I
experienced sort of two levels
of archetype reality, one which
you might think of as a more of
a platonic level, I encountered
beings phenomena that were vast.
I mean, they were just huge. I
could not wrap my mind around
them. I mean, I just they were
just staggering that they are,
they were the forces of nature
that were responsible for
creating time and space and for
orchestrating the events that
were taking place in time and
space, and then at a lower level
of consciousness, at what I
would call a Union level of
consciousness, I entered into
repeated experiences of
experiencing the the psyche of
the human species, or the
literally the collective
unconscious, how, how the system
works, that the human species
lives as a single entity,
psychologically, even
physically, that our minds are
cells within our collective
mind, and our bodies are cells
within the collective body of
humanity. I learned that our
healing of our individual
diseases contributes to a
healing of those conditions
within the body of humanity as a
whole. So it was just over and
over again being taken into the
dynamics of wholeness, the
wholeness of our species. And I
think these these experiences,
which were always there, it was
like I was being educated one
after another, first stabilizing
at this level, going to another
level, going to another level.
And I think these experiences
were teaching me what I needed
to know in order to receive the
visions that came later on,
where humanity is going, the
birth of the future human, the
crisis that we're coming to in
history. What that's all about?
Jef Baker: Great, yeah. I think
what that really shows too, is
the fractal nature of of
reality, describe the different
levels as being parts of the
whole. And it's interesting you
mentioned entities, because it's
something that we tend to
associate with DMT more than
anything, even though we know
from those experiences that,
yes, you have to die and there
has to be death of the self, in
order to open up to those, those
larger realms, I just wanted to
acknowledge things I just
noticed in my notes. Um, Kalin
de e, were you aware of
Chris Bache: his work? I'm sorry
say again we. Were you
Jef Baker: aware of Kalin D E,
who was a large advocate for 30
grams of dried mushrooms, plus,
and he was entering some very,
very deep realms of Psilocybin.
He passed recently. Last week, I
just started my notes and then
shooting logic there before I
forgot.
Chris Bache: Um. No freight.
Jef Baker: Now, did you have a
teacher during all of this? You
give me no practice
Chris Bache: a spiritual
teacher. Are Well, no, I
consider the universe my only
teacher. See one of the things
that maybe is a little unusual
about my experiences compared to
other people I've talked to is
that I didn't have a lot of
contact with individual beings,
which are so common in the DMT
experience. And I, over time,
I've really pondered why that
was the case, and basically, I
kept being dissolved into levels
of being, and then being
dissolved into deeper levels of
being, and kind of opening up
into vast expanses of
consciousness and vast
dimensions of and learning how
the universe works, but not in a
way which engaged, involved
engaging individual beings who
live on those levels. And about
the closest I could come to
encountering beings as such,
like that is when I described
archetypal reality. But these,
these realities were so large, I
the best my mind could do to
image them was to image them as
galaxies. I saw them as
galaxies, billions and billions
of light years wide. They were
so foreign. But in general, I
mean, I have had contact with
beings, with Psilocybin, or with
Ayahuasca, things like that, but
the LSD work just kept
dissolving me into deeper and
deeper into being itself, so
that there was always I would
encounter an intelligence, and
an intelligence would guide me
and orchestrate and teach me and
talk to me. And it was an ever
deepening, cascading deepening
of this intelligence, but I
never had the sense of
encountering or experiencing
discrete intelligences. So to
me, the universe is a is an
infinite potential, and I
experience a dialog or rapport
or dissolving into deeper and
deeper and deeper layers of this
infinite ocean. And so I
consider, I mean, I consider the
universe, my teacher and the
universe was always there
articulately at the other end,
but the nature of the
intelligence that I was
encountering kept changing, kept
deepening as it went, as it took
me deeper. So it's, I think
Jef Baker: there's a little
different lots about LSD itself
in relation to the other
compounds. I think that there is
a kind of resonance between the
form of the subs or compounds or
plants, and the experience, to
me, LSD has always been a very
human centric experience from,
you know, the therapeutic levels
of the individual self and the
cleansing right through to our
place in the largest Cosmos we
can imagine. But as you noted,
it's not about sort of beings
from other realms or other
realities or other dimensions.
It seems to be very grounded in
the human psyche and what it's
infinitely capable of. And I
don't know, I'd love to get your
thoughts on this, whether that
has anything to do with the
synthetic nature of it being,
you know, discovered by Hoffman
in a laboratory, as opposed to
occurring in the deep jungles or
Daniel bush. Yeah.
Chris Bache: Well, you know,
people, a lot of people, have a
lot of convictions around the
difference between synthetic
psychedelics and organics. Yeah,
and I don't really have a big
investment in that distinction.
I don't have enough data points
to really draw a lot of
conclusions, but I would do have
this observation substances. The
longer humanity has worked with
a substance, I think there are
energetic fields like Rupert
sheldrakes, morphogenetic fields
that develop around a substance.
So when people have the
experience of encountering the
Ayahuasca deity or the
Psilocybin deity, I cannot but
think. That in some ways, the
substance, the experience we
have with Psilocybin or with
Ayahuasca, which humanity has
been using for 1000s of 1000s of
years, that there's a certain
way in which all of humanity's
experiences with this substance
create a field surrounding this
chemical. So when I take this
chemical, it's not just putting
a chemical into my body, in some
sense, I am opening myself to
the field of humanities
experience with this substance.
LSD is basically a new
substance. It's only a few
decades old, and 60s and 70s is
nothing compared to the length
of time that human beings have
been using Ayahuasca. So I have
always experienced LSD to be a
very clean substance in that
respect, without a lot of
cultural baggage around it,
using it the way that I did, and
to me, it just, it just shatters
me. It dissolves my
consciousness over and over and
over again at deeper and deeper
levels, and takes me into
territory which felt kind of
from an evolutionary
perspective. It felt fresh. It
there were places that I went
that did not feel like there
were many footprints on them
from other human beings, and I
don't have that experience when
I worked with Psilocybin or with
Ayahuasca, where the those
territory feel more frequently
traveled, so to speak.
Jef Baker: Well, it's
interesting that you also note
the experience of perceiving the
universe as feminine.
Chris Bache: Yeah, for a couple
of reasons, two reasons that I
talked about in the book. The
first reason is simply because
of the tremendous love that the
experience of the universe
triggered in me and just awoke
within me, and the deep heart
felt opening and the the depth
of passion that I felt for the
universe that was taking me in
that love, which for me, had a
feminine quality to it. But the
other reason was because of the
specific cosmology that emerged
in my sessions. And this
cosmology surprised me. It
wasn't one that I had
internalized or taken in from
any of the sources that I had
read. And the cosmology
basically there was an
experience, a series of
experiences, that took me back
to the beginning of creation,
back before the Big Bang, and I
experienced the universe as
basically emerging out of this
primal oneness, which you know,
the oneness becomes the two yin
yang. And the experience was
that out of that primal two, one
of those consciousness stayed
outside of time and space and
stayed intact. And the other
consciousness began a journey of
manifesting time and space and
manifesting everything that has
evolved in time and space since
the Big Bang. And so the
consciousness that stayed
outside of the entire
evolutionary or creation project
felt more to me, felt more,
quote, masculine, and the
consciousness which created felt
more feminine, so that it's felt
congruent with me, To in to I
had, I just had repeatedly the
experience of the universe
itself as more feminine than
masculine. And I mean, I just
has that quality to me. So the
Great Mother lineage is very
strong in me. I've always
understood myself to be deeply
connected to the Great Mother
lineage
Jef Baker: as what I consider in
many cultures around the world.
As you would know, no, yes, of
the earth being the great
mother. Yeah, yeah.
Chris Bache: I consider my work
always in service of the great
mother.
Jef Baker: Yeah. So as I noted
earlier, I got to, I'm just up
to the point of deep time in
your book, yeah, perhaps you
could give us a little insight
into the nature of deep time,
yeah, and well,
Chris Bache: early on in my
work, when I entered into the
ocean of suffering during the
cleansing part is really, really
intense, collective cleansing,
when I would come through each
session, I would be spun into a
reality that was so foreign to
me that in the beginning I came
back from the My 11. In session,
and I couldn't remember it. I
mean, I I couldn't remember
where I had gone. Took me months
to begin to fully remember it.
And what had happened is I
entered what I later came to
call deep time for year and
seven, a total of seven
sessions, I experienced my life
as a completed whole, start to
finish, all the days of my life
as a simultaneously present now
and I experienced the totality
of my life beginning to end that
require that was so hard for my
mind to hold on to, because my
mind is trained to operate
within linear conditions where
time flows one moment at a time,
but to experience all of the
moments of my life as a
simultaneous present. It took
literal It took me an entire
year to learn how to stabilize
consciousness at that condition,
I kept going back and back and
back into the same condition. So
the universe was teaching me how
to be conscious at that
condition. In that condition,
later, I began to enter more
radical dimensions of time. I
entered not personal deep time.
I entered evolutionary deep
time. I had experiences of it
wasn't eternity, it wasn't
timelessness. That's a different
experience. It was different
swaths of time. It was I would
experience different patterns
within time on a scale of
100,000 years, or within a scale
of a million years, either
simultaneously present or in an
accelerated fashion. So I could
sometimes I would experience
centuries going by in seconds,
but I was experiencing life in
terms of the rising and falling
of way of generations, just
generations coming and going,
generations after generations in
order to understand or to be
taught, what was happening
underneath the evolutionary
dance. So I just experienced so
many variations on time that I
came to call it deep time,
different. The deep time is
entering into a different
modality of time consciousness.
I do think that there in the
universe, there are multiple
envelopes of time, multiple
modalities of time. Linear time
is how the world behaves inside
time space. But as you move to
the edges of space, you move to
the edges of time, and they're
between linear time and
timelessness, where you're
outside of time altogether. In
that intermediate domain, there
are multiple modalities of time,
and you can learn to stabilize
consciousness at those levels of
time. And it seemed that the
universe wanted to teach me
certain things. And the only way
it could teach me certain things
was to teach me how to stay
conscious in these unusual
temporal modalities. In fact,
the last of the what I consider
the great visions. The last of
the great visions took place in
the 70th session, and it was one
of the most extreme strip down
that I went through in any of my
sessions, and it moved me into
the most radical experience of
deep time in all of my sessions.
In fact, after this vision, the
universe basically wrapped it up
the next three sessions that
kind of wrapped up our work
together. This was the dominant
vision, and it took me far, far
into the deep future, into
humanity's evolutionary future?
Jef Baker: Yeah, yes. I was just
going to ask you, what that that
window of deep time into the
evolution of the human species?
What? What insights that gave
you about our future direction?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well,
starting at around the 23rd
session and repeating itself in
a punctuated way over the years,
the universe kept on taking me
into giving me teachings about
the human story. It was
basically giving me the outline
of you, what you might call the
master story. And I apologize
for the arrogance of that
concept. I don't mean it as
such, but it just kept taking me
over and over again, showing me
certain things about humanity.
It kept emphasizing that we were
coming to a crescendo. Our
evolutionary journey. We're
coming to a turning point, a
true before and after point, and
we after 1000s and hundreds of
1000s of years of struggling and
of course, with reincarnation. I
believe in reincarnation. My
first book was on reincarnation.
I've had lots of experiences
around reincarnation. So when I
talk about humanity evolving for
100,000 years, this within a
reincarnational framework, not
just a genetic but a
reincarnational development, it
kept emphasizing that humanity
was growing, coming to a turning
point in its larger evolutionary
story. And it was a turning
point that was so decisive that
we would mark history in terms
of the before and after of this
point. And then in the 55th
session, it, it took me it. It
kept showing me that there was a
profound opening that was in the
process of emerging in the human
heart, a profound change in the
human psyche that was taking
place in history. But it didn't
show me how it was going to
accomplish this. It never showed
me how, until the 55th session,
and at that session, it took me
deep into the future, deep into
deep time, and it took me into
the death and rebirth of our
species. It literally gave me an
experience, not as Chris Bache,
but by this time, the boundaries
of Chris Bache had been
shattered so many times in so
many ways. It took me into how
the species as a whole was going
to experience this death and
rebirth, so that just as
individuals go through death and
rebirths, and a mystic goes
through the dark night of the
soul, and then the birth into
spiritual reality. The entire
human species was going to go
through a death and rebirth
process. And it it gave me that
experience where we it just we
went through a series. This is a
process that takes generations
to actualize, but a process
where we it got so bad, where
there was a falling apart, a
loss of control, a an unraveling
of the assumptions that we make
in life and we just broke us
down, just like in a psychedelic
session when you die and are
reborn, the entire species was
going through a loss of control,
a breakdown. And just when it
looked like we would all be
dead, just when it looked like
we were coming to an extinction
event, the worst of it passed,
and we began to emerge and pick
ourselves up and go forward. And
when we emerged, a different
humanity was in its place.
Something happened in this
Death-Rebirth process and this
collective Death-Rebirth
process, we were changed
profoundly, a tremendous opening
of the heart, an opening of the
mind, so that the humans that
were coming out of the other
end, this was a shift that took
place in the depths of the
collective psyche. It wasn't
taking place at the surface of
the individual psyche. This is a
pivot at the core of the
collective unconscious, and when
this pivot takes place, all
other all subsequent human
beings will be born within the
contracts or the matrix of this
changed collective psyche. And
it really was literally, I
think, an enlightenment of our
entire species, a death and
rebirth and a spiritual opening
of our entire species. Later, I
came to understand this in terms
of what I call the birth of the
diamond soul. My understanding
of reincarnation is when we die,
our consciousness expands into
deep spiritual reality. And when
we're born, we get small, we
become male female. This that
you know, and then when we die,
we get big. When we're born, we
get small. It's like going to
college. When you go to college,
you choose specific courses for
the semester. That's your
semesters work. Then at the end
of the semester, you go on
spring break, summertime, then
you get back small again. So you
just over and over, over and
over, we get big, we get small,
we get big and we get small. And
if we keep this up for a few
100,000 years, sooner or later,
the large consciousness, which
is the consciousness of the
soul, the consciousness. It
holds all of our experiences for
all of our lifetimes. That
consciousness, which we
naturally return to when we die
in the Bardo condition, that
consciousness, I think, awakens
inside time and space. And this
is what I call the birth of the
diamond soul. We literally wake
up to our entire identity and
our entire history inside time
and space, so that we're no
longer even tempted to think
that our present body and the
little bitty consciousness of
ego is our true identity. The
soul wakes up on Earth. And I
think that's what's happening
for the entire human race, the
crises that we're experiencing
that and we're moving into with
global systems crisis and the
global ecological crisis, we're
we're experiencing the ending of
a world that was built by the
ego. And the ego is a
magnificent like a magnificent
phenomenon, but ultimately it's
it's cut off from each other.
It's cut off from itself. It's
cut off from the other beings.
The culture that we're living in
is a culture that was built by
the ego, and in order to solve
the problems which we are
confronting in this generation,
this century, we have to
transcend egoic consciousness.
We can't solve these problems at
the level of egoic
consciousness. And I think
there's a tremendous
evolutionary drive for us to
give to wake up to our soul, to
that soul reality, and literally
give birth to soul consciousness
inside time and space, and if we
can imagine what it would be
like to have an entire species
that is awake to their soul
reality. Now we're talking about
a turning point in history, and
that's what I think is
happening. I think we are
entering a process of labor, and
labor is a, you know, a
gestation last a long time.
Labor is fast and short, very,
very intense, very, very painful
Day. Humanity has been just
dating, developing this capacity
of soul for 1000s and 1000s and
1000s of years. I think we are
entering labor now, this
tremendous unraveling, this
tremendous pain of history that
we are entering and will
continue to enter for decades,
still is not an end an
apocalypse. It's not an end of
existence, an end of life, but
it's giving birth to the future
human. And I think the future
human is the diamond soul.
Jef Baker: Yes, well, Apocalypse
is revelation that's to lift the
veil and to reveal the hidden,
the unseen, the new. So you get
the feeling that this time is
now, that this rebirth takes
place. I mean, when we look out
of what's going on at the
moment, it certainly feels like
a dramatic catharsis is taking
place. And either go it's like
the forces of freedom and
control are dominating the
battle. And we can either go in
two directions, you know,
increasing control and
totalitarianism, or increasing
freedom and autonomy and
sovereignty. And it's
interesting, because I wonder
how much of that is a sort of a
grand narrative, collective
story in the spiritual world
that, because I hear it a lot
from many different circles that
you know, we are birthing into
the new age, into the new man.
And yeah, and that would be
absolutely beautiful if that was
the case, and indeed is the
case, that the painful birth
that we need to go through in
order to transition into a
better, more functional, more
balanced species. Elaborate on
that?
Chris Bache: Well, there's a
chapter in the book called The
Birth of the future human. And I
discussed this in a chapter
called The Great Awakening in
dark night, early dawn, this
book that I wrote in in 2000 and
I go into a deeper in LSD, in
the mind of the universe, the
birth of the future human. And I
was first very uncomfortable
going into this territory,
because I'm not comfortable with
what some would call think of as
historical speculation, and I
had begun this work really
thinking in terms I was doing
this work for my individual
healing, my individual
transformation, my individual
enlightenment. And that just got
blown away. You. Within a few
years, and everything,
everything the work, the
purification, the accessing the
information, the knowledge,
everything seemed to be in
service of the species as a
whole. That's it's like, that's
what the Divine is really
interested in right now, not
that our species is special in
the universe, but but the scale
of what the Divine is focused in
on this planet is species wide.
It's not so much individual
species wide. And so this was
repeated so many times and so
strongly that the entire gist of
my 20 year journey ended up
being focused on this collective
story of death and rebirth. So
every I mean, I have deep
convictions about I think we've
entered the dark night of our
collective soul. We've entered
the dark night, which is a
period of purification we
basically are confronting in a
very accelerated manner, the
sins of the past, we would say,
the sins of our fathers, except
we were our fathers. We are our
mothers. You know, so
reincarnation wise, we're
confronting our history. We're
confronting the choices that
we've made and the consequences
of those choices, and we are
purifying ourselves of the
toxins left over by those
choices in order to open
ourselves up into new dimensions
of our being. Because when we
when we open to our soul, it
opens. It has two immediate
effects, an enormous expansion
of compassion, because we, we
have relationships. I mean, we
haven't met each before, right?
You and I are new to each other,
but how many times has your soul
and my soul, you know, in
different times in history, made
contact and the people that we
have, our friends and our
enemies, and we have such a
deep, deep history on this
planet. So when, when you wake
up as a soul, in a sense, you
wake up to that history, and it
has the effect of unleashing an
enormous compassion for not only
human beings, but all being, for
all life forms. And then there
is when you wake up to that kind
of depth, it also opens up a
deeper experience of communion
with cosmic intelligence,
because it's like the ego is
operating under a cloud of
obstruction, but when the soul
awakens, then It's easier to
enter into conscious rapport
with the consciousness of the
universe itself. So there is
literally an awakening to trans
to transcendent consciousness,
as well as awakening to
tremendous breath of
consciousness. That's where I
think we're heading,
Jef Baker: yeah, and I think
your your, um, your description
the ocean of suffering, of
experiencing the pain of every
woman that it every that it ever
existed, exemplifies that, that
when you experience
empathetically emotionally with
all the beings that you have
been in this model of
reincarnation, then it by
accident, has to lead to
something larger. It has to, you
know, resolve into a higher
level. So when did you when did
you write dark night early dawn?
In relation to to this book,
Chris Bache: I wrote dark night
early dawn. I wrote it in 9596 I
stopped my work in 99 when I had
already entered the diamond
Luminosity years. The last five
years of my work were centered
on what I call the diamond
Luminosity work. But I
deliberately when I wrote dark
night early dawn, I deliberately
restricted myself, for the most
part, to analyzing only the
sessions that emerged in the
first half of my journey. I did
not discuss what was happening
in the second half. I needed
more time to digest them. So in
LSD, in the mind of the
universe, I go back to the very
beginning. The whole structure
of the book is just start in the
first session. Take it all the
way through. Every chapter deals
with a certain number of
sessions. Just do it layer by
layer. This is where it started.
This is where it went. This is
where it ended. So dark data
Ladon was written basically
about three quarters of the way
through the journey itself.
Jef Baker: Okay, that's
interesting because I had not
read it, and so I asked one of
our team members Andre to just
throw some questions out about
that book, which, which he had
read. And he asked him a few,
actually, um. One that stands
out to me here is, um. As a
teacher of comparative religion,
your take on the problem of
theodicy, the problem of
reconciling a beneficent
intelligence with the radical
examples of evil in history, in
present day. Is there a solution
to the destructive phenotype
within human minds,
Chris Bache: the problem of
suffering and or some people
would say, the problem of evil.
I don't use that category
because that's just a
theological interpretation of of
the experience of suffering and
pain. You know, I think
Ramakrishna was right.
Ramakrishna said, if you want to
understand God, you must be
willing to look suffering in the
face, because suffering doesn't
come from any secondary source.
It's not a demonic you know,
agency that you have to you have
to look deeply into the logic of
the universe and the logic of
creation, if you want to
understand how to reconcile the
intelligence of the universe and
the compassion of the universe
with the fact that existence
hurts so much. There's so much
pain and suffering here. And I
think the key is understanding
that creation or evolution or
the manifestation of life, we
are very It's incomplete. We're
not finished. We are we're
building something and and the
what we are building is
something which is evolving and
developing over billions and
billions of years. So the
universe, as we find it now and
as we measure it in the last
10,000 years, say, is just a
drop in the bucket compared to
the billions of years that
preceded it and the billions of
years that come after it. So
it's clearly, there's a great
deal of pain and suffering in
life as we experience in its
current form, but we are
evolving and developing and
becoming more consciousness.
We're learning from our choices.
We're getting more and more
control over our bodies and our
mind, and we're going to keep
this up, not for another couple
of decades, or a few more 100
years, or even a few 1000 years,
we're going for millions and
millions and billions and
billions of years. So to me,
suffering, the scale of
suffering has to be understood,
or the logic of suffering has to
be understood, not necessarily
in terms of just what has been
accomplished up to now, but we
have to understand that we are
in a process. We are in
developmental process, and it's
an incomplete process, and so
it's kind of like when you're
building a house and you just
have the stud walls up and you
have the trusses up, but you
don't have the roof on, and the
rain comes and it gets wet
because there's no roof, because
you haven't built the roof yet.
But humanity hasn't achieved
levels of capacity that would
allow us to stop the suffering,
and it's and it's not because
we're bad and it's not because
we're being forced or
manipulated by dark and demonic
forces. It's just a radically
incomplete process. We're trying
to continue the process as fast
as we can
Jef Baker: now. Do you? Do you
believe within this sort of
model of yin and yang, of there
being perfect balance and dual
forces throughout the universe,
that that suffering is balanced
equally by pleasure and good in
the world, that for every you
know starving child experiencing
the pain of hunger, there is a
person experiencing the beauty
of a sunset. Do you think it
exists in that kind of balance?
No, I
Chris Bache: don't think so. I
don't think so, because that
would mean if, in the long term
wise, if we were ever going to
continue or deepen our joy, we
would be deepening and
continuing our suffering. And I
don't think that's where we're
going necessarily. I think we
are. You know, I asked my
classes sometimes, when I was
teaching, if I draw a line on
the board and the evolutionary
line, and so I would ask, how
far are we on the evolutionary
line? Are we, like, 90% along
this line? Well, and if you're
90% along the line, then we have
a certain set of conclusions
that would seem to follow when
we look at life and try to
understand it. But what if we're
only 1% on this line? What if
everything that we've developed
is really just a little bitty,
bitty bit of this entire
process? Then that opens. Up the
picture enormously, up until
just a few decades ago, a few
100 years ago, yeah, it opens up
hope. We used to think the
universe was 6000 years old
because we added up all the age.
Yeah, now we understand it's
billions and billions of years
old just since this first Big
Bang. And we don't know whether
they had been bangs before. If
it's an expanding and
contracting universe, it may
have been there may have been
other universes that feed into
the intelligence of this
manifestation of this universe.
So the challenge here is to is
to engage and comprehend the
scale of the project that we are
involved in, or to put it a
different way, if you want to
speak within divine terms, is to
understand the scale of the
agenda of the Divine. It's like
we're literally just children.
We only became self conscious a
few 1000 years ago. We only
dropped beneath the level of our
individual consciousness to
discover the dimensions of our
mind which are universal. Well,
maybe four or 5000 years ago,
we're just beginning to wake up
on this planet, and this planet
has been four and a half billion
years in the making, 13 point 7
billion years in the galactic
scale of things, and we're just
waking up. We're just getting
started here. And so it's not
surprising from that
perspective. And of course,
suffering is the great, great
challenge. I mean, as you say,
the children who are dying, the
children who are suffering from
hunger, the injustices that that
surround us completely. I'm not
making light of any of those
things in saying this. We have
to address those things. We have
to expand and continue to work
on those things. But
philosophically, we have to sort
of understand that we're just
beginning to wake up to the
scale of the universe that gave
birth to us and is continuing to
give birth to us. From that
perspective, we have a lot of
work to do, but we have a lot of
hope. I really do think we're
becoming a species of Christ, a
species of Buddhas, a species of
the Prophet. We are becoming an
entirely higher order of species
over time, and this is going to
be what we're doing. Is
extraordinarily important this
time in history, but very, very
hard work. But when we go
through this process, when we
give birth to the future human,
like a mother who gives birth to
a child, when she holds her
child, she doesn't forget the
pain, but she knows that the
pain was worth it in order to
deliver this child. And when we
give birth to the future human,
we will look back at all of the
suffering of all of history, and
we will say it was worth it for
where we are and where we're
going.
Jef Baker: So so if I'm to
redirect the balance, the
balance of Yin and Yang and pain
and joy is laid out on this
scale of deep time, which which,
I recall you, you referring to
Bakti in relation to that
concept of, you know, loving
devotion and, you know, yeah,
leaving all beings of pain and
suffering, yeah,
Chris Bache: Yin Yang. Yin Yang
is a an attempt, by a particular
culture to articulate some of
the deep structure of the
universe and to point to this
primal duality which then
divides into the 10,000 things,
becomes the 10,000 things the
complexity of the evolving of
life. But I don't think, I think
we have to be careful not to
hang too much on the primary
polarity, good, bad, male,
female, things like this. But
the bhakti is a different issue.
And this was a surprise to me.
In Hinduism, there are four
systems of spiritual work, four
yogas, this, Yana, yoga, the the
yoga of meditation, Karma Yoga,
the yoga of action. Blanking on
bhakti is the is the yoga of
emotion. It's loving. God is
becoming awakened through love.
I had always been attracted to
more the mental forms of
spiritual practice of all the
various yogas in Hinduism. I was
least attracted to bhakti, the
emotions, the cultivation of
emotional relationship with the
divine, and yet I found in the
psychedelic work of. Well,
Bhakti was activated. Bhakti was
very powerfully activated, so
that I had not only a mental
relationship with the universe
and a cognitive experience of
the universe, but an
overwhelmingly powerful
emotional connection to the
universe and experience of the
universe so that it just it
became a love relationship. And
that's why, for me, I mean,
everybody has to develop their
own vocabulary for the ultimate
reality, but my vocabulary for
ultimate reality, I call the
absolute My beloved, the
beloved, just because it that's
the bhakti quality
Jef Baker: touches my heart.
Yeah, I've noticed that with
with five Meo, when, when
everything is stripped away, and
there is that zero point
singularity, that everything is
fused into one point, the only
thing left is love. Yeah, the
only thing that can exist, or
the only thing left to exist, is
this universal love. And it's,
it's quite interesting. I mean,
I guess from a neuro
reductionist perspective, you
can say that's because your
serotonin receptors have been
completely flooded. Yeah, it's
love.
Chris Bache: Love is the quality
of the the experiential quality
of oneness. Oneness and love are
two different sides of the same
coin, because when you dissolve
into oneness, then instantly,
love is the experience that the
universe has for itself. There
is no division in oneness. So
oneness is all embracing. So we
might experience this as
compassion or love, but the
logic of love is the logic of
oneness. Everything short of
oneness is fragmented.
Jef Baker: Okay, so would you
agree with this perspective that
I see a lot in the psychedelic
community, that the universe
creates separation in order to
experience itself, in order to
experience the you know, the joy
and the pain, because one cannot
experience itself alone. Do
Yeah,
Chris Bache: it's, you know,
that it really presses the
question. I mean, when we're
asking the question, why
existence? Why is there anything
went when there was the primal
void, when, let's say, to use
God language, when the divine
was whole and complete in
perfect equanimity within
itself, why did it manifest the
universe? Knowing what would be
involved, knowing all the pain
and suffering that was involved.
What was that about? And one of
the proposals is, well, this is
a way of the Divine knowing
itself. This is a way of
learning itself. Personally,
I've always I've never found
that very persuasive. I mean, I
understand it, and I think this
is a truth to it, but to me, to
make creation an exercise in
self knowledge, I think this
that never, had never, was very
satisfying to me. Another aspect
of it, I think, is that creation
is a way for the divine to share
its being. So all of us, from my
cosmology, all of us are sparks
of light that emerge out of the
primal light. So all of us are
aspects of the Divine, little
bitty pieces broken off out of
the primal one. And those little
bitty pieces grow and grow and
grow and grow. And as they grow
and grow, they're actualizing
their innate potential. They're
actualizing their divinity. And
in the end, it is as if you have
a one light, which is growing
millions and billions of light
out of its own one light. So
it's sharing of its being, a
cascading of the sharing of its
being, which I'm sure is an
inadequate model by itself, but
I've asked the universe
Jef Baker: simile and in the
form of the universe, being this
diamond with infinite facets
each face, yeah, being an
individual human, you know,
showing a piece of light that is
part of The whole, yeah, yeah.
Chris Bache: And we always, of
course, always have to remind
ourselves that what has emerged
up to this point in time is just
the tip of the iceberg. It's
just getting started. So we have
to kind of imagine ourselves a
million years from now, which is
nothing in evolutionary time but
a million. Years from now, what
we might be envisioning the
answer to this question to be,
what is the purpose of creation?
Why is why is this happening? A
million years from now, we're
going to understand it and have
a much deeper answer to that
question, and a million years
after that, we're going to have
a deeper answer to that
question. So I just there's a
certain way in which I caution
closure on these questions. I'd
rather be agnostic, somewhat
open ended. I do think it has to
do with self knowledge, self
expression. I think it has to do
with sharing nature open up
opportunities for life to breed
life, life to grow life.
Jef Baker: We're seeing so much,
particularly the moment. We've
seen a lot of people fall into
the trap of certitude, of
knowing that there's some grand
design behind it all, whether it
be, you know, hidden, sinister
cabals, but in this time of
uncertainty, people seem to be
really struggling with with
that, and looking for answers
that that resolve some kind of,
you know, provide some kind of
strategy,
Chris Bache: good luck. Yeah,
exactly when we dissolve into
the universe, when we just die
and die and die and dissolve
into the universe, we tap into
this. So many of us tap into
this condition where we
experience the intendedness of
it. We experience the
meaningfulness of existence, and
we walk away, come away with it,
saying, there is a plan, there
is a purpose, there is a project
here. But then when we try to
describe exactly what is the
plan, what is the purpose, I
think we very quickly reach the
limits and and it's the limits
are simply the limits that are
built into our evolutionary
condition of this moment, for
this species, in this planet, in
this evolutionary period. Mean
we literally, I don't think we
have a brain big enough to begin
to comprehend mystery scale,
yeah. So a certain we can feel
it, we can affirm it, we can
assert it. But closure is
Jef Baker: it steps to our
fingers, our nation, our sort of
drive to to find the answers and
pin them down. Yeah, it's, it's,
you know, rather futile. Perhaps
that is what gets us into so
much trouble.
Chris Bache: Yeah, certainly one
of the things
Jef Baker: you mentioned in dark
night, early dawn, Homo
noeticus, yeah, and, and the
widespread use of antigens, as
you know, a condition for the
evolution of humanity.
Chris Bache: Well, the concept
of Homo noeticus is simply a way
of putting language and and if
different people have different
ways of languaging homo
spiritualist, the future human,
the diamond soul. This is just
different ways of articulating
what I think is a very, very
widespread collective intuition,
perception, and that is that
that humanity is growing into
something new, that there is an
evolutionary development. So we
go from Homo habilis to homo
whatnot, Homo sapiens, and
there's something after what we
are now. There's something
coming, and we generate
different words for it, but the
and certainly this is so strong
in psychedelic experience that
we are an unfinished species,
that we are developmental
species, and we're not just
getting we're not just getting
smarter or more compassionate in
incremental ways. I think there
are major turning points where,
like, the rules change. When we
go through these thresholds,
we're coming into a bifurcation
point in history. We either make
it across this threshold or we
probably go extinct. I
personally believe that we will
make it across this threshold.
We will make this jump. And when
we make this jump however long
it takes us, 1000s of years,
hundreds, whatever, however long
it takes us, that's not going to
be the end point. That's just
going to be the new platform,
and we will eventually reach the
end of that platform, and we're
going to make a jump into yet
another because that's the scale
of what we're engaged in, of
what we're involved in.
Jef Baker: So how do you how do
you see psychedelics as a
catalyst? In this moment,
obviously, there's a huge push
for them to be used only within
the medicalized model as
therapeutic tools for trauma.
And then there's, you know, the
proposal of modern day Mystery
Schools, which I personally
think is greatly under, under
focused, yeah, where do you see
psychedelics playing a role in
this evolution?
Chris Bache: Well, I understand
the in the psychedelic
community, the very strong
emphasis on demonstrating the
therapeutic effectiveness of
psychedelics. I think it's
really important that we that we
not blow this opportunity we
have. We kind of blew it in the
60s, you know, it blew up in our
faces. We lost the right to use
these things. We had to go
underground to use them. And
it's really important that we
have this new opportunity, that
we document things, that we
demonstrate their effectiveness.
And right now, their
effectiveness is being
demonstrated in their
therapeutic potential. But if we
do this, if we keep going, it's
only going to be a matter of
time before mainstream thinkers
begin to understand that the why
is it that psychedelics are so
therapeutically effective?
Because they open up a communion
with the deeper, with the deeper
dimensions of mind, and in the
early stages, this encounter
with the deeper dimensions of
our own, of our consciousness,
unconsciousness, is very
cleansing. It's very healing.
It's very therapeutically
efficacious. Can be
demonstrated, but if we but
that's just the tip of the
iceberg. We go deeper. We go
deeper. We go deeper. It opens
up our relationship to each
other. It opens up our
relationship to the to the
planet, other life forms. It
opens up our relationship to
spiritual reality. Personally, I
was trained as a philosopher of
religion. It's always been the
philosophical import of
psychedelics which has
interested me. I'm not a
clinician, I'm not a therapist.
I've always interested in the
philosophical or cosmological
opportunities, and I think in
that perspective, we're coming
to a critical moment in history.
And it's not enough just to heal
us at this moment in history. We
have to heal not simply the
personal unconscious, though
that's important, it's very
important. But we have to heal
the soul. We have to heal the
fundamental human condition we
have, and that means recovering
an understanding of what we are,
who we are, where we are, what
existence is about. And I think
psychedelics are coming at a,
you know, the rediscovery of
psychedelics in Western
industrial cultures, because
indigenous cultures have had
them, you know, long time. But
in this culture where we have
lost contact with the deeper
levels of our own psyche, we've
lost contact with the
consciousness of the earth.
We've lost contact with the
consciousness of the creator of
galaxies. Psychedelics have this
opportunity to awaken us quickly
jar us into an awareness of this
deeper dimension at exactly the
time when we need it, because we
can't get through this period of
history with the limited
understanding of ourselves that
have grown out of 19th century
science, this materialist,
mechanistic, reductionistic
understanding, which is just an
absolutely devastating worldview
to try to live in. You know that
you that existence comes into
exist. We come into existence by
accident. It's all random. It
has There's no meaning to it.
There's no meaning to our
individual challenges. There's
no meaning to history. That is
an absolutely devastating
worldview, and it leads to the
kind of planet that we've
developed now where we just
basically try to eat it all
alive and get as many
experiences and as much of
experience as we can possibly,
because when we die, it's all
over, and it was all an exercise
in futility anyway. Well,
psychedelics and help us
understand that that's not true.
It's a very different agenda.
Jef Baker: It's almost like they
are the perfect tools for the
human condition at this point in
time. They really are. And yeah,
it feels like you know, there is
a grander scheme playing out
with the Renaissance. How do you
think we get psychedelics? Or
what do you think is a good,
pragmatic way to get
psychedelics and field of
philosophy more
Chris Bache: Well, I think the
therapist have to do their work.
You know, they have that. That's
what's really going to open the
door. They have to do their
work. They have to study the
physiology of psychedelics. They
have to de. Demonstrate the
therapeutic efficacy of
psychedelics, but the Mystery
School aspect, the philosophical
aspect that's there,
I think that the key to opening
to this deeper dimension in
mainstream society. If you're
working at the fringes of
society, the edges of society,
we're already open to the
mystery school use of
psychedelics, but for mainstream
culture to begin to open to this
dimension of psychedelic work, I
think the therapists have to
lead the way into it. Once we
see that that's being
demonstrated, then I think
society will be more open to the
more exotic qualities of
psychedelics. But we have a lot
of maturing to do there. We have
so many psychedelics which
unleash so many different
experiences. It's an
overwhelmingly complex maze. If
you go from five Meo to salvia
divinorum to Psilocybin in Iowa,
so many different experiences,
it takes a huge expansion of our
cosmology to understand even to
begin to understand how all of
these experiences can co exist
within a meaningful framework of
a deeper understanding of
existence. Even just to begin
that understanding, we have to
be highly motivated. And I think
the therapists are the ones that
are opening that door for us.
Jef Baker: I think a good way to
understand it is that these are,
these are plants that have, for
whatever reason, Evolved Human
neurotransmitters. And the
plants being much older than us
and the evolutionary scale of
things are almost trying to
teach us,
Unknown: yeah, a
Jef Baker: simpler way of being
one of a better description, but
to to look back throughout, you
know, historical lineage, and to
perhaps examine where we went
wrong,
Chris Bache: yeah, yeah, where
we went wrong again, we don't
blame a first grader for being
first, being six years old, you
know, it's just like, you know,
they didn't do anything wrong.
They're just six years old, you
know. And humanity, you know,
we've made mistakes. We've done
dumb ass things. We've done this
and that the other terrible
things. But in a larger sense,
we're just young, inexperienced,
not understanding, and because
we didn't all understand, we
make mistakes. You know, in
Eastern traditions, they say the
core problem, the core problem
is not that we're evil, the core
problem is that we're ignorant.
We literally don't know, and
because we don't know, we make
bad choices. And because we make
bad choices, those have bad
consequences. But the more we
understand and
Jef Baker: they sell, we can
make them too. Yeah, I like the
analogy to get you. I like the
analogy of people don't judge a
tree because it grew a little
bit this way because it didn't
get enough light from the other
side. It just is. It's just, you
know, we accept it much more
easily than we do with people,
yeah,
Chris Bache: yeah, yeah,
exciting times we live in. I
want to ask, I know we're coming
sort of towards the end of the
discussion. So I want to mention
something at the end. The last
chapter of my book is called
coming off the mountain, and I
basically discuss what happened
when I stopped my sessions in
the years after I stopped the
sessions. And I just want to
mention that, because I think
we're it's getting easier and
easier with the substances that
are available to us to break
through consciousness, to break
into intimacy with the universe,
to break into Transcendence, you
know, to access information. My
experience was when I stopped my
sessions in the years that
followed, I thought that since I
had been given so many gifts,
and since I had been had so many
mystical experiences, and so
many experiences of intimacy
with the being of existence and
dissolving into, you know, the
primordial light of existence. I
thought that would be easy to
stop my sessions and just step
away and I would be able to be
nourished by those experiences.
And what I found was that in the
end, there was such a deep
existential. Longing to return
to those dimensions of
existence, and I knew that I had
to stop for reasons I explained
in the book I had to stop this
work. I came to a point where it
just I knew I needed to stop and
slow things down, and I knew
when I stopped that I would
never go back into such intimacy
with the divine during my
lifetime. It would only happen
with death that I would return
to such depth of place, and I
found myself slowly entering a
condition where I was just
waiting to die. I was, you know,
taking care of my children,
teaching my classes, doing the
things that I do. But in my
heart of hearts, I was just
waiting for this life to be
over, so that I could return to
the full intimacy of the Divine.
And in time, I began to realize
this, this is not right. This is
not the way this work is
supposed to end. And I had been
so careful to integrate every
session, to integrate all of my
work as I went, and not get
ahead of myself, that I It
wasn't clear to me what, where I
had gone wrong. My life was
screaming failure to integrate,
but it wasn't clear how I where
I had failed to integrate,
because I had paid so much
attention to integration, and I
learned that integrating a
session is different than
integrating an entire journey.
And my journey had taken me so
deeply into Transcendence that I
sort of lost my footing in the
world of imminence. It's all the
divine. The physical world is
the divine. But I had entered so
deeply into the transcendent
divine that I had become I was I
lost my footing inside the
immanent divine, and it took
years. It took me about 10 years
to get really grounded back in
space, time reality, so that I
could live the remainder of my
years within the joy of space
time reality. And I mentioned
this because I think many
people, as we have more
experience of Transcendence, we
naturally want to go there or
let there come in here more
completely, I think it's really
important to address the issue
of integration. While we are
going into these states to
integrate, integrate, integrate.
And integrating a journey is
different than integrating
individual sessions. It's a
really delicate process. And so
I mentioned my own mistakes in
order to encourage other people
not to make those mistakes,
right?
Jef Baker: And thank you for
mentioning that. That's that's
quite pertinent. After this goes
to air, the Australian
psychedelic society is running a
large integration workshop. And
as saying before, with people
having difficulty integrating,
say, such a peak experience like
five Meo, that embodiment, that
eminence, that experience of the
divine in everyday life and the
small things and being in
nature, you know, eating clean
and just looking after the
presence rather than constantly
seeking these transcendent
experiences. Yeah, that's a
beautifully pertinent way to
perhaps around the interview.
Off there's a couple of quotes
that really jumped out at me
from the book. And I think one
that fits quite well here too,
is you said, it's all too easy
to think that because we have
had a deep and profound
experience, we have become deep
and profound ourselves. This is
a false delusion, I think I may
never Yeah, describe that right?
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah. The
greatest danger, I think, of
working with psychedelics is
psychic inflation, and we can,
we can overvalue the temporary
experiences and undervalue and
undervalue the stable platforms
of our day to day consciousness.
It's in Maslow's terms, we can
overestimate the value of our
peak experiences and
underestimate the value of
plateau experiences, so we can
have a very, very profound
spiritual experience on Saturday
and still be an asshole on
Monday.
Jef Baker: Yeah, it's certainly
visible within, you know, some
aspects of this community,
certainly. But yeah, we're all
growing and we're learning,
yeah, yeah, if you're, if you're
happy to leave it there. Chris,
thank you so very, very much. On
behalf of the Australian society
and everyone that's viewing
this, thank you for your time.
Chris Bache: Pleasure to have
the Congress. Thank you. Good to
have this conversation.
Jef Baker: Yeah, I recommend
everyone. Do you read? Read your
latest book,
Unknown: and you very much. Let
us
Jef Baker: know where, where
readers can people get hold of
the book?
Chris Bache: Well, I've just
been told that Amazon isn't
delivering to Australia now, so
probably the easiest way is
through digital forms. Amazon
will, you know, deliver digital
forms. I I'm very late in
getting my website up. I don't
it isn't finished yet, so it'll,
it'll be there within a couple
of months. I hope so. Easiest
way to get it is through inner
traditions, or through Amazon or
other booksellers and get it
digitally if it's not being
mailed in a hard copy. Great.
Jef Baker: Thank you for that.
And stay safe. And these strange
and interesting times,
Chris Bache: they say, Thank you
for your work. One day, I hope
maybe I'll be able to get to
Australia and person, yeah, and
look forward to having
conversations with your larger
psychedelic society. Be a
pleasure.
Jef Baker: Absolutely, yeah. And
we'd love to have you speak it.
You know, when the larger
conferences here, if you're so
inclined and believe you come
Chris Bache: out. Be great. Be
great. Thank you, Chris, all the
best. Yeah.