Unknown: Ryan,
Ryan Kemp: Okay, welcome
everybody to the naked guru
experience. I'm Ryan Kemp, just
as a little forward. This
discussion is part of a series
in tribute to the American
ethnobotanist Terence McKenna,
and is sponsored by the
psychedelic society as ever. It
really helps in the production
of these discussions, if
listeners subscribe to our
YouTube channel, today's guest
is Christopher M Bache. Chris is
an emeritus professor in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he
taught for 33 years, an emeritus
fellow at the Institute of
Noetic scientists. He is also a
junk faculty at the California
Institute of integral studies
and on the advisory board for
the Grof Transpersonal training
and the Grof foundation. An
award winning teacher and
international speaker. He is the
author of a number of books,
including life cycles, dark
night, early dawn, and the book
we'll be discussing today, LSD
and the mind of the universe,
diamonds from heaven, in which
Chris catalogs his epic journey
over 20 years, where he engaged
in 73 high dose LSD sessions,
working at 500 to 600
micrograms. Chris, welcome to
the podcast, and thank you so
much for agreeing to this
discussion. Hi, Ryan. It's a
pleasure to be here with you
today.
So we have a lot to cover in
just a small amount of time. And
I just wanted to say from the
start that your book has been
profound in my life, and it's in
huge discussion all around the
world and multiple groups I know
the feedback from many others,
it's been life changing for many
others. So thank you for your
work. Thank you. I'd just like
to start with a little
introduction to you and your
background and influences, if
you will, please. Chris,
Chris Bache: well, I'm the last
person you would expect to have
written this book. I was raised
in the Deep South, who grew up
in Mississippi. I studied
theology at the University of
Notre Dame. I was actually in
the seminary for three years in
high school and one year in
college. I did my masters at
Cambridge in New Testament
criticism. I was going to be a
New Testament scholar. Shifted
out of that, got my PhD from
Brown University in philosophy
of religion. But when I came to
ISU and I was looking for the
next area to focus myself. I was
trained in philosophy of
religion. I encountered the work
of Stanislav Grof, who was it
was life changing. I also
encountered the work of Ian
Stevenson, whose research on
reincarnation was life changing.
But it was Stan's work
particularly that seemed to set
the course for my life. I was I
understood immediately the
implications of his research
for not only psychology, but for
philosophy, the opportunity to
develop a new philosophical
methodology, the systematic
exploration of consciousness
through the disciplined use of
psychedelic states. Now, of
course, the United States had
made psychedelics illegal at
that time, so I divided my life
in half. In my daytime job, I
was a professor at the
University teaching courses in
Eastern religion, psychology of
religion,
comparative mysticism, a course
called Transpersonal studies.
And then I began in my personal
life, a very private exploration
of the my deep psyche, using
Stan Grof protocols for
psychedelic therapy, and then
pushing those protocols to their
limits to explore my
consciousness. And through that
exploration, what I came
eventually to understand was the
consciousness of the universe
itself. Brilliant, brilliant.
Now, a lot of what we're going
to discuss in this talk,
there'll be people within the
psychedelic and psychological
and even spiritual community
that will be very familiar with
what we're going to talk about
and our terminology, but there
is a good I'd say, probably even
a majority of human beings on
our planet that that are not
aware of these kind of
psychological landscapes and the
terminology. So for me, I think
it would be helpful if you could
please frame for us the context
that we're talking about when we
discuss LSD, a lot of people
will see this as a discussion on
drugs, when actually it's a
discussion far from it, from
something far more profound.
Yes, yes, yeah, we all kind of
suffer from the carry over of
our experience with
psychedelics, our culture's
experience in the 1960s and all
the negative press that
psychedelics generated or were
generated around psychedelics,
when the true story is really
very different. Psychedelics in
general and LSD in particular,
Fung.
Function as non specific
amplifiers and catalysts of
consciousness. They don't give
you a particular experience.
They don't
what they do is hyper amplify
your consciousness, and if you
use these hyper these hours of
hyper amplified consciousness
carefully and conscientiously,
if you shut out all outside
stimulus and focus your
attention completely from
within, you can use those hours
to explore and to, in a sense,
excavate the deep architecture
of the psyche. Now,
nature of consciousness itself.
I should say that when I was
doing this work, just to be
clear, I was always working
privately. I was always working
in very controlled
circumstances, either at my
house or at my wife's office. My
sitter for all the years of my
work was my wife, my first wife,
who is a clinical psychologist.
So I was always protected from
the world. I was isolated. I was
lying down. I was surrounded by
pillows. I was wearing
headphones, listening to a very
carefully curated playlist of
music which is designed to
facilitate a deepening of the
experience and wearing eyeshades
so I was completely protected.
Someone was taking care of my
body, taking care of the musical
selection. My job was simply to
focus on what was emerging at
the center of my experience, and
to allow that experience to go
wherever it would go if you do
that, what begins to happen in
the early stages is you begin to
confront your personal shadow.
You begin to front confront all
those aspects of your life which
you are ashamed of, are
embarrassed by, are intimidated
by, or uncertain about, the
deepest fears of your life,
including when you get down to
it, the fear of death, the fear
of extinction, the fear of the
meaninglessness of life. And
then, as you if you keep that
process, these fears kind of
come to a crescendo, a peak
expression. And if you will, can
confront that peak expression
and let it take you where it
wants to take you. It will take
you through some crisis, which
eventually becomes some form of
death and rebirth, some absolute
shattering of your life as you
had known it, of reality, had
you as you had known it. And
then you fall into a deeper
level of reality. You die at one
level and awaken within a deeper
level of reality. And your
session shifts from purification
to
an ecstatic phase of the
session, and you basically are
given you enter into an intimate
dialog with the universe, an
inter intimate initiation into
successive layers of the
universe. This is what working
critically, therapeutically with
psychedelics is all about.
Ryan Kemp: And would you
describe that Chris is what Jung
would term the collective
unconscious.
Chris Bache: Well, the
Collective Unconscious is a
stratum of consciousness that
lies below the personal
unconscious. So in Jung's model,
every we first encounter when we
go below our conscious mind, we
encounter our unconscious mind,
our personal unconscious. But if
you can go deeper than your
personal unconscious, you enter
into a stream of awareness,
which seems to be a collective
stream shared by all human
beings of your species. So this
is Jung's collective psyche,
right? Then, if you go deeper
than that, you enter into still
deeper streams of consciousness,
entering into what some would
call global consciousness. But
you can enter into levels of
consciousness that go beyond
space, time, reality altogether.
Enter into archetypal levels of
consciousness enter into
complete states of dissolving
into Non-duality and what might
be called causal oneness, and
you can enter deeper states of
consciousness even than that. So
it's it's a long journey with
many.
Ryan Kemp: Levels of exploration
along the way. So in your view,
like the view of Jung and in
many spiritual texts and very
many religious texts, we have
our personal, individual mind,
but the universe itself is a
mind, a oneness of its own. It
would that be correct?
Chris Bache: Yes. And our as I
experience it, at least, our
individual mind is a fractal
embodiment, a fractal
manifestation, of this larger
cosmic mind. So at one level,
there is a functional duality,
which we might think call a
small mind and the big mind, but
at a deeper level, there really
isn't a duality. There is a
continuum of awareness that we
are a small actualization, a
fractal manifestation of this
larger cosmic consciousness.
Ryan Kemp: Now, just while we're
discussing about your technique
and what you were, what you're
up to in these sessions, one of
our questions from, from, from,
from the Terence McKenna guys
was about the music you were
listening to. So you described
the area where you were and that
Carol, your lovely wife was ex
wife currently was sitting for
you. But what? What about the
music you were listening to the
I know this changed over time,
but could you tell us a bit
about that?
Chris Bache: Well, here I was
drawing upon Helen Bonnie's
work, early work in the study of
the stages of psychic of
psychological opening, and it's
like an LSD session. I learned
about her work through Stan Grof
work, and she differentiate five
stages of opening and closing in
an LSD session. LSD session is a
long session. It's, you know,
it's a six to eight hour
session. And there is the early
stages of latency, then the the
medicine begins to kick in. Then
there is an acceleration of an
opening of consciousness. One
begins to encounter resistances
and fears as one moves deeper
the the energy continues to
build exponentially. There is a
peak period, and then there is
you hit the long, kind of steady
plateau of the experience. And
then there is a long, slow,
gradual return. So each of those
stages of consciousness are best
paired with particular types of
music. In the early stages, you
want music to calm you and relax
you before the session actually
gets underway. And then when the
session begins, you want music
that gives you a sense of flow
and continuity, music that can
support your support your
letting go of your fears and
resistances, shifting gradually
to stronger music with more
climactic cadences and themes to
support You really letting go
into the deeper turmoil that
rises in your consciousness,
eventually leading to the
moments of great breakthrough.
And then as you move into the
breakthrough, you want music
that supports the vast expanse
and the opening of horizons that
can open after you go through a
Death-Rebirth process, and in
the return you want music which
is very gentle. Increasingly
gentle gives you a lot of space
in which to process your
experiences. Now, again, I want
to mention that all of this is
contingent on the type of
psychedelic you're using and the
dose at which you're working
with now, I chose to work with
very high doses of LSD. I worked
with 500 to 600 micrograms. I
started working I did three
sessions with about 200
micrograms. Chose to work at
five to 600 micrograms in a
sustained protocol of this sort.
And this generates enormously
powerful experiences. I mean,
the process of of your
consciousness. It's not like
taking 150 micrograms and
relaxing on a Sunday afternoon
sun, a sunny afternoon under the
trees. It's it's a much more
powerful, hyper stimulation of
your consciousness that just
challenges and shatters all the
limitations of your known mind,
and the music accordingly is I
found it I was important to have
very strong music, engaging
music. I found quickly that.
That indigenous chanting and
music from foreign cultures was
more effective for me than
classical music. It's very
foreign nature made it easier
for me to surrender to the
foreign territory that I was
entering into. It gave me gave
my ego less room for anything to
hold on to, and therefore it was
more challenging, but it was
more productive in that it
helped me get into the deep
material more quickly, more
easily,
Ryan Kemp: right? And the
indigenous music you were using,
were these kind of Ayahuasca
shaman chants, or were they were
from worldwide, different
different tribal chants.
What in particular
Chris Bache: I have used the
escaros from Ayahuasca
ceremonies late in in my
psychedelic life, mostly after
my LSD years. I mean, I did this
work between 1979 and 1999
between when I was 30 and 50.
I'm 70 now, but in the primary
years, I didn't really encounter
the Ayahuasca music until much
later in this process, the music
tended to come from a lot of
African music, a lot of Tibetan
music, Indonesian music,
Japanese music, South American
music. I basically just was
always looking for music that
would give me a supportive but
challenging context against
which I would allow myself to
enter into these deep states.
And I found that I could only
use a piece of music
approximately about about three
times after I'd used it three
times the music became encoded
with the experiences that I had
had with the music. And in order
to allow to avoid being kind of
repetitiously encoded or
programmed by the music, I
always had to be looking and
using fresh music,
Ryan Kemp: right? Okay, so the
mind had, had taken the music
and you kind of knew it, and it
was, it was then program along
with the previous experience. So
that's if you re listen to it,
you would go back to the same
experience, or,
Chris Bache: well, it would tend
to pull you in that direction.
Or at least there was some
potential for it to pull you in
that direction, maybe not the
second time you listen to it.
But if you listen to the music
repetitively repeatedly, it can,
it can narrow your conscious
experience instead of expanding
and opening it
Ryan Kemp: right so as you just
touched on there as well you saw
this, or what you came to learn,
that what you were doing was a
series of iterated deaths and
rebirths in one body, which is
also quite in the other
literature with Stan grofs work
and whatnot. So could you talk a
little bit about how you view
that, and what is it
relationship to actual death and
rebirth as we know it, the
leaving of this form and coming
back into a new form? Perhaps
your views on that?
Chris Bache: Yes, well, it took
me a long time to understand the
patterns of my sessions, because
in some ways, they started as I
expected them for drawing upon
Stan's map of consciousness that
he gave us in his early
writings. But then after a few
years, they seemed to diverge in
some ways and enter into new
territory. But one of the things
that
I've come to understand over
time is that consciousness has
many levels, many tiers,
operational levels, and the only
way to and when you enter, each
time you enter into a new level
of consciousness, there is
required a surrender of
everything you had known before,
everything you had learned and
assumed before, in order to
enter into a level of
consciousness that operates by
completely different rules. Now
it's it's not that Chris Bache
is ego, even a softened ego, can
be catapulted out in some
reality and have an experience.
It's more that
Then you transition to a deeper
level of reality. You enter
spiritual reality, which
operates by different rules than
physical reality, but in the
early years, often at least also
speak for myself, I my
experience of this reality was
still colored by my experience
of time and space. So the
assumptions of time and space
kind of place limits on your
experience of that spiritual
level of reality. And there
comes a time if you keep pushing
that eventually there is an
invitation extended or a
breakthrough which you come to
where you have to let go even
deeper, let go to something even
deeper than your physical
identity, which shatters you yet
again and takes you into yet
another level of reality which
is deeper, a deeper level of
spiritual reality than the
earlier level you had been
experiencing. And this process
repeats itself multiple times if
you, if you use your sessions in
a focused way and always pushing
to explore the deepest dimension
of consciousness, that's
possible. Now I want to say, I
don't advise that people do what
I did. I mean really, I if I
were doing it over again, I
would not adopt such an
aggressive strategy as I, as I
adopted, always pushing so hard
with such high levels of LSD, I
would be much gentler on myself.
I would balance high dose
sessions with low dose sessions.
I would balance working with
LSD, which is a kind of a high
ceiling psychedelic, with
Psilocybin or Ayahuasca, which
are much more body grounded
psychedelics. So I'm describing
something without recommending
it to be followed or be used by
other people. Truly, I don't but
doing what I did and learning
how to navigate these waters and
surviving my own foolishness.
I'm just in the book. I'm just
trying to tell stage by stage
exactly what happened as best I
could on this deepening
immersion into the universe.
Ryan Kemp: And when you say
pushing forward, that suggests a
kind of active,
Unknown: an active role in the
in the experience. Was it? Was
it a process of pushing outward
into these kind of further
landscapes, these further
psychedelic and psychological
VISTAs, or was it a process of
surrendering into them, or maybe
a combination of the two? It's
really a matter of surrendering
the only pushing is by the
repeating of the circumstances
of availability. You
Chris Bache: you create a
completely quiet and safe
container. You detach yourself
from all the circumstances of
your daily life, you take a
powerful medicine, you surrender
yourself to the care of another,
and then you open. You allow
yourself to open. What happens
next is beyond your control. At
least working with this
substance at this higher dose,
is beyond your control. You
surrender to a. Larger
consciousness. And I've the
longer I work with this this
material, the more it became
clear that there was a larger
consciousness that was guiding
my sessions, guiding my
education in the sessions, that
was meeting me, breaking me
down, loving me, caressing me,
breaking me down some more,
forcing me to face certain
things, challenging me to face
certain things, and then
thrilling me, taking me into
deeper and deeper intimacy with
what I would come to describe as
the creative intelligence of the
universe, the cut. It's hard to
describe when you enter so
deeply into states of
consciousness that so far
transcend your physical
consciousness. How do you
describe it? What? What
categories do you have to
describe it? We could call it
the cosmic mind, the universe's
mind, the great expanse in my in
my heart of hearts, I've came to
call it My beloved, because
returning to such intimacy with
the very source of your
existence, with the source of
all existence, awakens such a
deep passion of embrace and
being embraced that it well, I
call it my beloved. Yes.
Ryan Kemp: I mean, what I really
love about your work, for me and
somewhat Stan Grof work, is it
reconciles psychology,
psychedelics, religion and
spirituality in a way can be
read in a way that reconciles
that when you discuss
terminology and you discuss it
as your beloved Jesus may have
called that the kingdom of
heaven within Buddha may have
called that Dharmakaya, the
Hindu Atman. And so there exists
kind of a spiritual terminology
that to a lot of people, is very
alien and dogmatic and separate,
but once viewed in the context
of your work, through through
the psychedelic where one can
experience this as a direct
contact with the trans person or
the transcendent, it all fits
very, very nicely, and You all
of a sudden become to understand
what those human beings were
trying to describe. It's not
something abstract, it's
something that can be
experienced in a number of ways.
Would you agree?
Chris Bache: Yes, it can. And
certainly, once these
experiences become part of our
cultural story, they are subject
to all the distortions that
culture can bring so they can be
subject to the distortions of
historically limited
perspectives, to patriarchy, to
all sorts of cultural
constrictions. But I had the
advantage of I was teaching
world religions, and I was
teaching courses in comparative
mysticism and so over and over
again, year after year, I was
studying some of the great
spiritual teachers from around
the planet. And if you do this,
you very quickly outgrow the
limitations of your own religion
of birth, and you begin to enter
into this collective
perspective, where you begin to
recognize a deeper, fundamental
core overlap of many of the
teachings of the different great
religious teachers, what what is
often called the perennial
philosophy, the perennial
tradition, and at the same time.
So there is a sense which
recognizing what people have
been talking about when they
when they talk about the divine,
what they talk about when they
talk about Transcendence or
Atman and Brahman, these
categories become alive for you
as as an essential vocabulary to
articulate what is becoming your
natural experience of the world.
And at the same time, at least
in my experience pushing as
deeply into the universe as I
did, I was shown over and over
again that all the religions of
the last four or 5000 years are
radically and profoundly
incomplete. They are noble
initiatives in history which
reflect a certain state of human
evolution. But the landscape of
human evolution the landscape of
the Divine initiative, and I
even hesitate. I don't talk
about God very much, and I
hesitate to even talk about the
divine, because those words are
so heavily laden with
theological presuppositions that
I don't necessarily want to
affirm or buy into. But
basically, when you when you
begin to experience the
magnitude of the intelligence.
Presence that suffuses existence
and the magnitude of the
compassion and an intimate love
that the creative impetus, the
creative intelligence has for
all of its manifestation, all of
its manifest beings. It just it.
It just opens worlds within
worlds within worlds. So there
is a both an affirming and a
humble recognition of the
greatness of the great teachers
and saints of history, and at
the same time, a sense that even
they, even they have not
captured, perhaps, the vastness
of the great expanse of the
world, of the world as it is,
the world of, you know, our 13
point 7 billion year old world,
and the scale of the
evolutionary project. You know,
Sri Aurobindo said that humanity
was a transitional being, and if
we don't understand what we're
transitioning to, it's hard to
understand what we are. Even
right now, everything we're
doing is taking us. It's not
we're not only the culmination
of everything that has been in
our evolutionary story, but
we're also laying foundations
for what we are in the process
of becoming. And what we're
becoming is something, at least
from my experience, is not
something that results in a
culmination of a few 1000 years
out, but hundreds of 1000s,
millions of years, millions of
years coming. So it's just that
radical expansion of existential
horizons that that qualifies my
relationship to the world's
religions
Ryan Kemp: and your journey in
particular. I mean, what? What I
really enjoyed in the book as
well, was your journey hasn't
necessarily being one of just
love and light and bliss and
divine unfolding. As many have
the kind of presupposition of
the spiritual path to use, for
lack of a better word, the
spiritual path they think is
some kind of love and light,
blissful path, but actually it
can be very difficult, very
isolating, very lonely and very
nightmarish in some, some sense,
many people that are on the
path, whether it be through
psychedelics or whatever
spiritual, spiritual practices
they may be involved in, to be
on that individual path can be
Very difficult. And what you
mentioned in your book was some
of the dark side of what you've
been through very openly and
honestly, voyaging, especially
in the in your early sessions,
through the hell realms, and in
your sessions 11 to 15, you
mentioned the hell realms. I
mean, could you? Could you talk
about those a little bit,
Chris Bache: yeah, I had, I had
to think a lot about how to
present the different types of
suffering and the different
types of challenges that I faced
on the journey because, and in
fact, it was my greatest concern
in beginning to Share my the
story of my journey with the
world, with others, because I
did not want them to become
scared of the unseen universe,
and I did not want them to
prematurely misjudge the
psychedelic method itself. And I
really had to think about this.
And eventually I decided just to
tell, to tell what happened, to
lay it out and to tell what
happened. And there is great joy
and great beauty and great
ecstasy. And just, I mean, I
wouldn't trade these 73 days for
any treasures on earth. I mean,
they just, they showed me so
much and they gave me so much
that whatever purification
processes I went through and
whatever pains I went through, I
paid them gladly to have been
and had been rewarded more than
fairly for what happened along
the way, but the what you
mentioned the hell realms? Well,
this is the kind of scenario I
basically after about two years
of work, I went through a really
crushing ego death, where my
historical existence was just
turned inside out and shattered.
And I thought, Okay, I've gone
through ego death, then I won't
have to go through that anymore.
I won't have to go through ego
death. Everything's going to get
better and better now. But what
happened was that very quickly,
within a couple of sessions, I
began to enter into. Realms of
collective suffering that were
just much, much worse than
anything I went through. In ego
death, I entered into what
Buddhism calls the hell realms.
I called it an ocean of
suffering. I was systematically
over two year period, and I was
taken deeper and deeper and
broken down at deeper and deeper
levels into realms of collective
anguish involving 1000s and
1000s and 1000s of beings, human
beings, and 1000s of years of
history and very detailed
patterns of configuration. And
at first I thought, This must be
a deeper iteration of ego death.
I must be going through a deeper
form of ego death. But
eventually, by the time this
ended, I realized that this
wasn't about my personal ego
death. It wasn't about personal
healing at all that somehow the
universe or something was using
my sessions to facilitate a
healing of my species, of my
people, that in somehow, in
opening myself or allowing into
my conscious awareness the
unresolved trauma of history,
all the terrible things we've
done to each other, all the
killings and maimings and rapes
and just that gave terrible
scars in the collective psyche
that somehow, when a person
opens this deeply, if you are
willing to let This pain and
suffering in, it has a
clarifying effect, a healing
effect, a transformational
effect that heals a certain
portion of the collective psyche
of humanity. Now I wouldn't dare
try to estimate how large a
portion or what its impact is,
but I was just taken repeatedly
through these hell realms, into
these hell realms, and
eventually they culminated. I
was about four years, four and a
half years in, 24 sessions in,
and they culminated an
extraordinary kind of orgy of
the ocean of suffering. And then
I was spun out into a deeper
level of reality that lay beyond
the hell realms into archetype
of reality. And at that point,
all the collective suffering
stopped, just as the ego death
suffering stopped when I went
through ego death, the ocean of
through this culmination and
entered into archetypal reality,
but later at deeper levels, as I
went into still deeper levels,
there were still challenging
periods that I would go through,
just periods where I entered
into patterns of chaos, patterns
of psychological dismemberment,
patterns of just different
subtle, subtle forms or ordeals
that were hard to understand
because, you know, we're
charting some territory that
lies far, far deep into the into
the collective fabric of Things,
into the not the collective
fabric. This is beyond the
collective fabric, into into the
dimensions of the Divine, into
the dimensions of the cosmic
mind itself. But every time I
came into one of these sort of
patterns of ordeal, or patterns
of clarification, I came to
recognize that these were all
some form of purification, that
if I allowed these things to
take place, something was being
lifted from my system, something
was being broken open, and
eventually it would culminate
and take me into yet a new
stunning level of discovery and
a deeper intimacy with the body
of the Divine.
Ryan Kemp: I mean many, many
people at these points where
they're going into an ocean of
suffering, and in your book,
describes also your experiences
were sometimes violent and
vomiting. And many people would
say, well, that's enough of
that, you know, I understand.
I'm going to start what, what
was it that drove you forward,
in particular, into this? I
mean, what was that drive to?
Because it could have
hypothetically been that they
would never end. He would just
continually. You didn't know
what was was over the horizon, I
guess. Or did you intuit that?
Chris Bache: I didn't know what
was in the horizon, over the
horizon, but it is something
that I perhaps the most profound
gift that Stan Grof gave me was
a trust in the universe.
Universe, they trust that you
could surrender yourself to
whatever was asked of you, and
if you did so completely the
your the universe would in the
end, it would take care of you.
You would go through ordeals
that you may not understand, but
in the end, you would understand
them. You would get large enough
and enter deeply enough into the
universe that, with hindsight,
you would get a deeper
understanding of what was going
on. But absolute trust, if you
surrender completely, it will
lead to breakthrough. It will
lead to a deepening initiation.
So and I think you know,
everybody has different measures
of tolerance and different
circumstances, and again, I
don't think it's wise to push
even though I did this as
responsibly as I could, and
really taking very good care of
my body throughout and in
between my sessions, I was doing
about five sessions a year. I
worked for four years. I stopped
for six years, and then I worked
for 10 very intense years. So
over the 14 years, or 14 and a
half years when I was actively
working, I was averaging about
five sessions a year. So I had
months in between every session
to digest my experiences, to
write them down, to think about
them, to reflect upon them, and
I was doing a lot of yoga in
between. I was doing a lot of
meditation, a lot of spiritual
practice. But even doing all of
those preparatory practices, I
found myself pushed to my
absolute limits in going as
deeply as I did. And ironically,
in the end, it wasn't the pain
that was the most difficult
thing to manage in my work. It
was the ecstasy. It was the
intimacy with the fabric of
existence. It was entering into
what I came to call the diamond
Luminosity, what Buddhism calls
Dharmakaya, the absolute, the
clear light of absolute reality,
entering into such dissolving
into the light that precedes the
physical universe as
manifestation, dissolving into
the crystalline body of the
Divine, that ecstasy, that joy,
became more difficult to manage
than the pain of getting there.
And the reason it became
difficult to manage was not
because of the joy itself, but
because it was a temporary
condition. I could not stay in
that condition. Now there are
great masters and Great Beings
who can stay in that condition
and all honor always to the
great ones. But in my condition,
in my circumstance, I could only
gain temporary access to these
realities, and when I would come
back out of them, I was
simultaneously deeply and
profoundly spiritually satisfied
and gratified, and I was left
with an aching sense of
bereavement because I could not
stay. I had to leave.
Ryan Kemp: Yeah, it reminds me a
little bit of what Baba Ram Dass
used to talk about. He used to
say, We're all walking each
other home. And a little bit
about what you're you're talking
about, it, it one necessarily
doesn't require psychedelics in
order to go to this place. There
are people that seem to be able
to do it without the use of
these tools. And life itself is
an analogy for what you're
talking about we go through on a
day to day basis, forms of
suffering, of which we tolerate
and overcome for the good of
ourselves and the community and
the society and the human race,
and we also experience periods
of bliss. So we are interfacing
with our reality on a day to day
level, independently of these
kind of cosmic experiences.
Would you agree that's the case?
We're all walking together. I
mean,
Chris Bache: yes, absolutely,
absolutely. I mean, once again,
what happens in these sessions
is that your consciousness is
temporarily amplified. That's
all your consciousness is
tearing, temporarily amplified.
So if you want to understand
what truly happens in a session,
you must have an understanding
of basically what happened,
what's happening in life outside
of a session. So in that
context, my understanding of
life, which I draw from my
philosophical studies and
psychological studies, and then
in addition to that, my
psychedelic experiences. For me,
reincarnation is a simple fact
of life. It's just this is how
life works. We incarnate.
There's a narrowing of our
conscious experience with an
incarnation, we take on a
particular persona, male,
female, rich, poor. We. We
incarnate in a particular
historical period, social
conditions. We live our life as
best as we can, and then we die,
we expand back into our deeper
soul consciousness, back into
spiritual reality. When we die,
our consciousness expands. We
return to the light when we
incarnate, there is a
contraction into the specificity
of our next learning exercise,
different gender, different
social circumstance, different
historical period, we live and
learn, and then we expand.
Because I'm an academic, I tend
to see this as like a semester.
You know, we choose our courses
for the semester, and then we're
locked in. And then at the end
of the semester, we get some
breathing space expand, so we
keep this up. And we're always
kind of, we're in the dance of
learning to create learning the
consequences of our choices,
making good choices, making bad
choices, you know, just learning
and growing and becoming more
and this is the dance of life.
This is taking place, and it's
been taking place for hundreds
of 1000s of years, when we begin
to meditate without
psychedelics, just when we begin
to meditate and focus on the
consciousness which is living
through all of these lives, one
of the things that happens is we
speed up what is taking place
when reincarnation, if you want
to speed up your spiritual
evolution, then focus on the
fundamental inner experience of
your being. And if you do that,
you begin to confront themes and
issues and choices, which, if
you didn't do that, would
eventually manifest in some
conditions in the outer physical
world. But if you don't want to
wait for them to manifest in the
outer physical world, you can
confront those conditions in
your inner psychological world.
So you you actually you speed up
your evolutionary process when
you focus in your your inner
being, in the sort of the inner
flow of your being. And
psychedelics is simply another
form of spiritual practice which
very intensely, for temporary
periods of time, focuses on that
fundamental core stream of your
being and so there is a
detoxification process, an
accelerating process that takes
you eventually deeper and deeper
home. I mean deeper and deeper.
There are just so many levels of
home, so many levels of return.
But yes, this is simply we are
simply dancing the dance of
life, just doing it in a
slightly different form. And you
can stop anywhere along the way.
And just as you can stop your
meditation practice, you can
stop your psychedelic practice,
and you continue to dance the
dance in life. It is the dance.
Ryan Kemp: I mean, we touched
upon this briefly in a private
conversation, but we discussed
the idea of moving outward from
the kind of collective egoic
mind, what a car Tolle would
call the collective egoic mind,
and moving into a process of
what Jung would term a process
of individuation, becoming an
individual. And that that
process can be a very lonely
process, too, if you, if you're
not within the community that
understand you, like, like Jung
said, loneliness is not, not,
not from comes from having
nobody around. It comes from not
being able to express the ideas
that are important to you or
that others find it invisible.
This, this idea, the journey of
individuation can be a lonely
one, and the road to that, as
you're discussing it now, is
this process of evolution and
meditation. And I'm sure you've
been through experiences like
that, like many of our listeners
and and people that are on these
journeys, I'm sure you've been
through those experiences you
know, through this book and
through your life. Would that be
correct in saying,
Chris Bache: Yes, I think
basically the deeper I've gone
into this, on the one hand, like
I feel more deeply my
fundamental common ground with
all human beings. I don't feel
unique or separated or set aside
in any way. I resonate more and
more deeply with the human
condition and with the dance
that human beings are dancing
across the globe, around the
world, and you know, in many
spiritual traditions, if we
address this issue of
individuality, in my book, Dark
naturally dawn. The last chapter
of that book in which I am
discussing there a number of
things, but one of the things
I'm discussing is my own
psychedelic history. In the last
chapter, the fate, the name of
that chapter is the fate of
individuality, because many
spiritual. Definitions basically
say the individual is an is an
illusion. Individuality is
basically a it's just an
illusion. And the goal is to
transcend individuality and
return to the one. And you, the
drop returns to the ocean.
Vedanta thought in India
basically that the drop returns
to the ocean you dissolve into
the divine, and that is coming
home. And any kind of holding on
to, any kind of sense of
separate existence and
individuality is basically it's
it's not a fully mature
spiritual understanding or
experience. And I disagree with
that. My experience has been
that individuality is one of the
great gifts of creation.
Individuality is one of the
great manifestations of
existence. And what we don't
want to do is live in an
isolated individuality, to think
that somehow our individuality
is makes us separate
ontologically in with respect to
the core of our being separate
from other beings in the world,
unique in the world, or that our
individuality is a permanent,
abiding individuality which
never changes. I mean,
basically, I agree with Buddhism
in their teaching of anata or no
self, or emptiness of self, that
there is no private self in the
sense of a separate self, that
all our experience is part of
the matrix of cause and effect
manifesting in a continual
arising and falling away. And
there is no unchanging Self.
There is no absolute, unchanging
Self over time. But if you can
let go of that small sense of
self, that ego which sees itself
separate and unchanging and open
and grow into a deeper
experience of individuality,
which is in continuous exchange
with all living beings, and in
continual expansion and Growing
and development. And I think
that basically the maturation of
that individuality over time.
The maturing of that selfless
kind of individuality is one of
the great spiritual gifts of our
time space experience. So the
two truths, one is the truth of
wholeness, the truth of oneness,
the truth of interconnectedness,
of inner penetration, another
truth is the truth of the
learning system, which
experiences all these things,
learns from it, internalizes it,
and becomes more because of it,
Ryan Kemp: which is also one of
The things that I grappled with
within your book and wasn't
quite sure about was, are we
talking about we have one soul,
which is known as God to many
people. Is the term linguistic
reductionist terminology that we
have to kind of use, is God or
the divine? What I was thinking
about many individual souls.
Which is it, or is it both?
Chris Bache: Well, we can choose
to use language any way we want.
We can. We can define our terms
as we go, as long as we're
careful and we know what we're
doing. So one can talk about God
as the one soul of which we are
all drops within that one ocean
of soul, and that's perfectly
fine. We can also use the term
soul to refer to the accumulated
experience of all of my former
lives integrated in a unique
individual consciousness, which
is as unique as a fingerprint
within a still larger matrix of
the collective species mind and
a larger matrix within the
planetary mind and within a
larger matrix of the Galactic
mind, but a true individual, an
individuality which she emerges
so we can determine, we can use
the word soul any way we want,
as long as we're clear what
we're doing with it. In my
experience, about halfway
through my journey, in session
38 which is a session I discuss
in the chapter on the
benediction of blessings, I had
a very interesting experience
previously, 11 years previously,
I had the experience when I was
coming through the ocean of
suffering. I had a series of.
Sessions which repeatedly took
me back into the same
experience, taking me deeper and
deeper into it, which was
experiencing the totality of my
life, from birth to death, as
simultaneously present as a
completed whole. It was, it was
like looking down my life from
beginning to end, and seeing it
and experiencing it as a
totality, complete and finished
with on within itself, which was
a mind shattering experience.
And it, and I discuss it in the
in the chapter, deep time in the
soul. But 11 years later, I was
given, I was a very deeper stage
of the work, I was working at
causal level, reality, a little
reality of oneness. And in this
time, I had the experience of
seemingly integrating all of my
former lives. They were coming
in quite quickly, from different
centuries, different periods,
and it was like wrapping a
filament of white light around a
kite spool. Just wrapping these
lies were coming in and were
wrapping themselves around this
kite spool. And at one point
they hit critical mass, they
fused, and when they fused,
there was an explosion of
diamond light from within my
chest, and I was catapulted into
a state of consciousness that
was unlike any I had experienced
before. I was an individual, but
beyond any category or any
experience of individuality that
I had ever known before, and I
came to language this in terms
of the birth of the diamond
soul. And they gave me, I was
given a series of teachings in
this session that all focused
upon reframing my understanding
of what the goal of
reincarnation is about, because
much of our teaching of
reincarnation comes from
cultures and times in history
where the pattern of the
teaching seems to be we are
mired in illusion. We grow
slowly, slowly through multiple
incarnations, eventually, we
come to a discovery of our
essential divine nature. We
awaken to our divine nature, and
when we achieve that awakening
breakthrough, we leave time
space. In Hinduism, the earliest
term for reincarnation was
moksha. Escape. We escape time
and space. We escape ego. But I
think all of the and the same
thing we have all of the
cosmologies of the religions of
the last 4000 years or so are
all up and out. Cosmologies. We
achieve salvation, we achieve
spiritual realization, and we
leave. We achieve nirvana. And
when we die, we move into parin
Nirvana, final Nirvana, or
Nirvana without the body. They
basically spiritual realization
culminates in some off planet
heavenly paradise, whether it's
the heaven or the garden or some
off planet paradise. And I think
basically that is a
fundamentally incomplete
cosmology. I think it represents
a certain stage of our human
development. But it's not the
end of the story. I think in
this experience, what I was
being shown is that eventually,
in this long, long process of
expanding and contracting, being
dying and being born, dying and
being born, learning more,
learning more, over time, over
time, sooner or later, sooner or
later, the soul, which usually
we experience. And by soul, I
don't I mean the totality of all
of our experiences in all of our
former lives. Sooner or later,
the soul wakes up inside the
body. The soul wakes up inside
time and space. That's what I'm
calling the birth of the diamond
soul. It is to be spiritual. It
is a spiritually waking up, a
spiritual maturing, a
psychological maturing where we
know that we are much, much more
than our body's physical
experience. We know we are more
than everything we have
experienced during the years
since our physical birth. We are
no longer tempted to identify
strictly with the limits of this
particular body. We have an
intuitive recognition of the
breadth of all of our
relationships with human beings
that we have been developing
relationships with for 1000s of
years. And there is a
transparency, not only to other
people or to other species, but
a transparency to the universe
itself, so that. Can we can
rest, we can absorb, we can
commune more deeply with the
divine, say, in while we are
inside time and space, that's
the birth of the diamond soul.
This is, this represents, I
think, the next stage of our
human evolution, which is a
spiritual maturation. It's
heaven on earth. It truly is
heaven on earth.
Ryan Kemp: So, so what you mean
is the spiritual realm as we
know it. One might kind of
perceive that as the dream
world. For those without
experience with the tools, the
dream world doesn't exist in
matter. It's outside of matter,
and that is the source of
creativity. It's the source of
what some people term God, the
source of the Divine, and that
is manifesting in matter. But
you're talking about the divine,
the collective mind, manifesting
in matter within the universe.
Is that correct?
Chris Bache: Yes, basically, we
can think of it perhaps, like
the mother universe and the
daughter universe. The mother
universe is spiritual reality
which is continually infusing
and orchestrating and shaping
and receiving physical reality.
So there is at the very quantum
level, this dance that takes
place. At the subatomic level,
we're learning that there's a
continual infusion of energy
into time and space coming from
this quantum or sub quantum
realm, that 96% of the universe
is dark energy, dark matter.
That that physical existence is
just the surface of things. Yes,
with reincarnation, we learned
that our our egoic identity, is
not our final identity. It's
only a temporary identity. There
is a deeper identity that is
emerging over long stretches of
historical time. There's a soul
identity. So there is, I think
there's just a sort of a larger
sense of the of the architecture
of the universe. Is a larger
sense of the landscape that we
are how to we are standing
always astride two realities. We
have one foot in the daughter
universe, one foot in the mother
universe. And the more we can
make this a conscious, you know,
integration, the more we begin
to consciously live as the
expression of the inflowing of
this mother, spiritual energy
into the divine energy of
manifestation. So I tend to
image this very simplistically,
as one reality is light and the
other reality is green, the
manifest universe, the green
universe, the physical world,
is, is the manifest body of the
Divine, the world of pure light,
the world of pure spirit, is the
other side of the Divine, the
transcendent divine. We live
with the foot in both of those
realities most of the time. I
guess we tend to get caught in
just the physical side of
reality, and so we tend to long
for the spiritual dimension. But
I think as we awaken more
completely and more deeply, we
realize it's not simply a matter
of awakening and leaving time
and space as if something's
wrong with time and space, but
awakening more completely to the
fruition of the evolutionary
project inside time and space,
so that can we become more
conscious creators and
collaborators in creation inside
time and space. It doesn't deny
the joys of heaven, it doesn't
deny the joys of transcendent
reality, but it is, it leads to
a new cosmology. It needs, leads
to a deeper understanding of
what the purpose and project of
physical existence is.
Ryan Kemp: Within one of the
questions that came from one of
the Terence McKenna groups, from
one of the members there was,
it's nicely slotted in here. I
guess would be that during your
experiences, did you meet any
entities, any entities that
existed in a non atomic realm,
in the quantum realm, any, any
entities there that were not
human souls? And we, we can read
about that in Rick Strassman
work, the spirit molecule and
some, some of the work he's
done, was there anything there
for you that was foreign from
that was not the collective,
that was not not this one soul,
or was it all a oneness?
Chris Bache: Well, it's
interesting. I have had
experience. Is where I have met
discrete intelligences, discrete
entities in spiritual reality.
But on the whole, that has not
been the flavor or the
trajectory of my experience. And
again, this is partly to do with
the substances, and partly to do
with how we work with the
substances. The entities seem to
be particularly prominent in
experiences that involve DMT, or
some of the variations of DMT,
Ayahuasca, or five Meo DMT,
sometimes or straight DMT. My
experience again, use LSD
somewhat different. I kept being
dissolved into deeper levels of
spiritual reality, and it was as
if I was being dissolved, not
into a society of beings,
though, I did meet beings in
different forms, but at a
different at a deeper level, I
was being dissolved into deeper
levels of being itself. It
really was like being dissolved
from atomic reality, leaving
atomic reality to entering into
quantum reality, into fields of
awareness and larger patterns of
awareness. So at every level,
there are patterns which one
could call, one could categorize
as entities. But if you really
sit with each of those entities
in deep forms, they eventually
dissolve themselves into yet
still deeper patterns within
existence itself. So on the one
hand, I do I'm really
comfortable with the entities,
and I see the wonderful art
produced by the great Ayahuasca
artist Pablo ameringo, and just
the it's a universe filled with
entities and spiritual
presences, and I'm really
comfortable with that. That does
resonate with my experience, but
my deeper experience has been to
be dissolved into deeper and
deeper patterns of being, rather
than separate beings. Right?
Ryan Kemp: Brilliant, brilliant.
So just moving then on as as we
look to the future. I mean, we
just touched upon that a little
bit. But what, what inclinations
you've had according to the book
and what you've just mentioned
there is you've seen where you
think this process is going and
how this ties in with the human
journey, not only now and the
past, as we discussed, but where
it's going into the future. I
mean, could you talk about your
insights there, and how you
think this is unfolding at the
moment, particularly now under
under these circumstances of
covid lockdown and whatnot,
which also part of something
much larger, much larger. Yeah,
yeah.
Chris Bache: Well, this is one
of the largest surprises for me
in this work, and I'm really
cautious about entering into it,
and yet I in discussion, even
though I also believe it's
perhaps the most important body
of visionary experience that
emerged in my work because, and
I say it was surprising, because
in the early years of my work, I
saw doing this work in terms I
had a model of individual
transformation, either
individual healing or individual
enlightenment. I was doing this
work to improve myself in some
way or shape or form. But what
happened was, of course, in
entering the ocean of suffering,
it all became about collective
transformation. It all became
about healing the collective and
about releasing the pains that
have been accumulated in
history, in the collective
psyche. And then I was moved
into deeper levels. And about
that time in that transition, a
series of visions began. And
these visions were consistent
from the 23rd session all the
way to the 70th session. It
wasn't that they were there
every session, but they were
periodically, I was being
initiated into a particular
understanding of history, a
particular understanding of
human history. And repeatedly,
there was a sense that humanity
was coming into a period of
decisive significance, a period
of profound breakthrough, a
spiritual culmination, a
culmination of our entire
reincarnation history, that
we're this was going to be a
before and after a. Moment, this
was one of the ways it was
envisioned. Was I was climbing
up this mountain, and on the
other side of the mountain I was
in sort of shadows, but on the
other side of the mountain there
was this brilliant light, a
brilliant valley with just
brilliant light, and that
humanity was coming into the
fundamental turning point. And
this went on for years, this
vision of it. And I eventually
wrote these down. I collected
them, and I call them the
visions of awakening. But I did
not see, I had not seen how life
was ever going to carry humanity
across the threshold, because
when I looked at the world
around me, I saw as much
evidence for our being stupid
and making just terrible choices
as I did for us making
spiritually wise choices. I did
not see us letting go of our
collective greed. I did not see
us taking more and more
responsibility for the well
being of others. Some were, of
course, but many weren't. And
then in 1995 and 55 sessions
into the journey the universe
took me deeply into deep into
the future, deeper into deep
time than it had ever taken me
before, and it took me into an
experience which I experienced,
not as an individual, even a
spiritual individual, but I
experienced it. And I know this
sounds outrageous, but I
experienced it as the species I
was dissolved into the
collective psyche, so deeply
that for these hours, I was our
species mind. I was dissolved
into the collective psyche, and
in that context, I experienced a
building crisis, a mounting
crisis that just was taking
away, stripping us of reality as
we had known it. It was it was
the dark night of our collective
soul. It was a time in history
where a real confrontation with
the consequences of choices that
we've been making, historically,
a real confrontation with our
poor choices. We were losing
control. We were we were just
being shattered. It really it
reached a point where I thought
it was an extinction event. I
thought we were all going to
die. It was like being on a
small island when a hurricane
comes upon, comes upon, it that
it just was wiping out all life
on the island. And just when it
was at its peak, just when it
was it seemed that death was
inevitable. The storm passed,
and there were survivors. Many
had been killed, but there were
survivors. And when the
survivors started to pick
themselves up and started to
gather and find each other and
reconstitute life. There was
springing forward, springing
from within us. The most
extraordinary phenomenon there
was this, a birth of new
insights, a birth of new values,
new understanding, new
priorities,
new social initiatives there
were basically an unleashing of
something that we had learned,
something that had taken place
in the center of the human heart
in the midst of this crisis.
Basically just as a saint in
undergoing intense spiritual
practice, goes through the
purification which John of the
Cross, cross calls the dark
night of the soul, likewise, in
our collective evolution, the
dark night of our collective
soul a time of complete
surrender and intense
purification which breaks us
down at the center, yielded to a
time of great awakening, a great
spiritual manifestation, a great
redirection of the human heart
and of human culture. It was a
true great awakening of the
species. And in time, in
subsequent sessions, I was taken
into the deep time again, and I
began to be shown that this
represented not simply a
historical breakthrough and not
simply a technical or economic
restructuring of our culture,
but it was a truly seismic shift
in the depths of the collective
psyche. A pivot took place in
this global crisis, a global
systems crisis, which appeared
to be driven by a global
ecological crisis. It was a
shift in the core psyche, the
collective psyche, which all
other. Human beings draw from on
their individual life. So when
the collective psyche shifted,
it meant that every generation
that was born on the planet
after this shift took place,
they were being informed by and
were infused by this new
blueprint, this new
psychological blueprint, this
new capacity. And I think what I
was experiencing was a true
spiritual awakening out of just
individuals, but of our entire
species. And this was deepening,
deepened in the years that
followed. So ever since this
time, I have come to understand
that my personal belief in the
visionary experiences that were
given to me in the sessions were
showing that humanity is coming
to a decisive moment in its
evolutionary journey. We were
coming into a time of critical
challenge and a time requiring
maximum effort and maximum
clarity. We are literally this
is a time of labor. Gestation is
long. The period of gestation is
a long time, but the time of
labor is short and intense and
convulsive, we have been
preparing for this time in
history for 1000s and 1000s of
years through reincarnation,
reincarnation, reincarnation.
But now we have entered into a
time, I think, in which we are
giving birth to the future
human. We are giving birth to a
different kind of human being.
And I think we are giving birth
to the diamond soul. I think the
soul is going is entering into
history in a collectively
unmanifest, an unprecedented
fashion. I think the world as we
know it was designed by ego. And
the ego is a magnificently
beautiful psychological
structure. I mean, I really, I
respect it enormously. But
ultimately, the ego is a
fragmented psychological
structure, and it leaves us cut
off from each other and from
existence itself. The world
designed by the ego creates
categories of problems of
division which we know and
recognize well in history now
dividing between races, dividing
between religions, dividing
between classes, just division,
division, division, division.
But the birth of the diamond
soul represents a new starting
point for humanity, a deeper and
I think the core of it is this,
a deep experience of oneness,
not just as a concept or as a
category, but a profound
awakening of oneness within the
human heart and the world that
is A species which is grounded
in this experience of oneness
builds a different world than
the ego builds. And I think the
diamond soul is we are giving
birth to the diamond soul in
history. And I see the covid 19
not as this crisis, but perhaps
as an early stage of this
fermenting crisis. It is a
crisis which is very painful and
very difficult, but it's
teaching us something. If we
learn the lessons that covid 19
is has the opportunity to teach
us, if we learn about well here,
everybody would put their own
fill in the blanks at this point
what it is trying to teach us.
But if we learn the lessons of
compassion, if we learn how bad
things go when we give ourselves
over to egoic leadership and
divisive patterns of leadership
and self centeredness within the
species, then things go very
badly. But if we open into other
caring, if we open into
selflessness, if we open into
reigning in some of the patterns
of blind repetition and greed,
then we are learning things
which will be very valuable to
us when the deeper crises that
are coming manifest, and all you
have to do is just read the
works of the deeply informed
ecologist and environmental
students of history to
appreciate the scale of what we
are coming into as we
increasingly heat the planet and
weather the tragedies that are
going to be generated, that are
being generated by our changing
climate. This, I think, is
really the crisis, the deeper
crisis that covid 19 is giving
us an opportunity to prepare
for.
Ryan Kemp: Yeah, beautiful. It's
it's in the collective mind as
well. I think that. All on an
individual level, aware that
something is brewing or
something is coming. And I don't
know if that's how it's been
throughout history of humanity
that we've always felt there's
some kind of cataclysmic event
on the horizon, but now, now
more than ever, it's certainly
in the collective mind and our
habits, our nature, our way of
being at this moment is is both
destructive, but we're also
seeing this kind of psychedelic
Renaissance, and we're also
seeing a lot of people looking
to the past for answers about
the future more than ever, I
think, in the past two years,
than say, in the past 20 but,
yeah, it's, it's a big part of
of of your vision. But you say
that the covid, what you think
is the covid is only a small
part of that. But as you look to
the future, do you see a very
like throughout evolution,
previous species have had to die
off in order for new versions of
ourselves to evolve. Yeah, do
you see like a catastrophe, a
world ending catastrophe? Is
that what you're you're pointing
to?
Chris Bache: Well, I want to be
careful. I'm not a visionary
outside of my psychedelic work.
Yes, I don't. I don't have a
psychic ability to see into the
future. And when I I only have
what I saw and what I was shown
in my visionary experiences
inside my psychedelic sessions,
these have been consistent, in
uniform. I trust the
consciousness that gave me these
visions. They seem to be
deliberate and well crafted, so
I trust them, but I recognize
that one person's visions are
only one person's visions, and
they don't necessarily hold the
same value to other people. So
what I saw was a world coming
into acute crisis, a depth of
crisis that was literally
breaking us down at very deep
and fundamental levels. And it
was only when we when we had
reached intolerable amounts of
suffering, that we were willing
to start making choices that we
were not willing to contemplate
previously, and in making these
new choices, choices for the
greater good, choices for our
children's children's children,
choices that were necessary in
order to pull ourselves back
From this destructive binge that
we had been on for the last
several 100 years. Then a new
future began to emerge. But I
was not given specifics about
how, when or why. I wasn't told
when I wasn't told why. It was
just very, very broad strokes,
but what I was given was the the
inner experience of this death
and rebirth as a species, and I
was given some understanding of
the collective mechanisms. See
we have, we have to travel a
great distance in a very short
period of time. How can we
really mature to the drives, to
the level, to the challenges
that we are facing as fast as we
need to in order to survive what
we are letting loose on the
globe. And I was given some
insights into mechanisms that
are operating at the collective
level. I won't go into these in
detail because they laid out in
the book, but it has to do with
how systems operate when they
move into non linear into non
linear ranges non equilibrium
systems. Some of the physics of
non equilibrium systems as they
apply to psychic fields and the
psychic field of the human
family as a totality, you know,
so to me, I I guess the some of
the greatest gifts I were given.
I was given at the end of my
journey was to be taken deep
into the future, and was given
the privilege of experiencing
this, what I'm calling the
future human, the child that we
are giving birth to, what the
future human feels like, looks
like, and if I try to describe
it to you, I'll probably end up
weeping, because it was So
beautiful. This being was so
beautiful, so magnificent. We're
talking about a healed humanity,
truly healed, right down to our
bones, a humanity with an
absolutely radically expanded
heart, what Christians look at
Jesus and call the sacred heart,
the heart, the one heart. A mind
open to the intelligence of the
universe in new and profound
ways, a truly enlightened
humanity, one in all, just a
magnificent shift in the common
ground of human experience. And
I believe that just as a mother,
when she has her baby in her
arms after a hard labor, forgets
the labor at one level, because
the child is is with her. Now,
likewise, humanity will is going
through this very, very intense
birth process, but when this
birth sees its goal, when the
child is born, when the future
human is born on the earth. And
I don't have any particular
vision of again, how when I
don't know whether it's this
long, gradual or it's a sudden,
cathartic thing, but when this
child is born in history, we
will look back on the terrible
pains that we went through to
give birth to it, and will say
it was worth it. Maybe if we had
been smarter, we could have done
it easier and faster. Maybe we
brought some of this on our own
heads unnecessarily, but when
the child is born, it will be
worth it. Beautiful.
Ryan Kemp: Yeah, yeah. Yeah. You
posed a question in your book.
You said, what is the value of
true but temporary knowledge,
moving into these planes and
coming back and being able to
sustain them? You mentioned you
have different answers at
different times, and so I
thought it'd be interesting to
to ask what? What is your answer
to it at the moment, at this
time?
Chris Bache: Well, the soft
underbelly, if, if we do this
work in order to facilitate, not
simply temporary Hies or
temporary, you know, insights,
but if we do it in order to
encourage or facilitate a
maturation of our psycho
spiritual life, which leads
ultimately to a shift in the on
the ground of our consciousness,
an abiding shift to shift not
Only into peak experiences, but
a shift into plateau
experiences. If we approach
psychedelic experience with this
long term maturational view,
then the soft underbelly of
psychedelics is their temporary
nature. You know, we enter into
these states. You can't stay
there. We're going to be in
there only for a few hours at a
time, and then we come out. We
have to kind of reconcile
ourselves with the limitations
of the of the practice that
we're engaging in. But if we use
those hours carefully, if we use
them conscientiously, I believe
they do accelerate our
evolution. And then they can, by
showing us where we are going,
they can, they begin to act as
kind of strange attractors,
drawing us into our individual,
individual and collective
evolution faster, more deeply.
And so it is frustrating to sort
of, you know, at two o'clock in
the afternoon to be so deeply
immersed in the wisdom of the
universe, and then by 10 o'clock
that night, you know your your
ordinary mind is congealed
around yourself again. And no
matter how hard you try, you're
not living in the same reality
that you were in before the
value, what is the value of true
but temporary knowledge? And I
think in my case, at least, I
pushed myself perhaps deeper
than was wise, into deep, deep,
temporary knowledge, and so
again, if I were doing it over
again, knowing what I know now,
I would be more patient with a
slower pace of my own personal
evolution. I would and and the
way this manifested for me is I
reached a point after 20 years
of this work where I knew it was
time for me to stop my sessions,
and, more importantly, the
consciousness that I was
engaging knew it was time for me
to stop and it ended our
sessions. I did not think they
were going to end. I did not
know we were ending, but after
this very, very deep what I call
the final vision, the last of my
great visions. In the 70th
session, there were three
sessions, which I call the
goodbye sessions. It basically
drew our work together to a
close. And I had been given so
many blessings and had been so
many joys on. The journey, I
thought that I could simply
withdraw and I would be able to
be nurtured for the rest of my
life by these blessings, and I
have been and and that is true,
but there's something else that
happened, and that is I began to
to experience a profound
existential loneliness, because
I was not able to go back into
this deep, deep intimacy with
the divine in even though I
continue to do spiritual
practice, the spiritual
practices that I was doing, if I
did them from multiple
lifetimes, perhaps I would be
able to move back there, but in
this lifetime, I knew I would
not reach that deep until I
died, and I found myself very
quietly, just waiting to die so
I could return to my beloved and
that that's not a good way to
live. And it took me a while.
Took me literally 10 years after
I stopped my sessions, to get
fully grounded, to recommit
myself into living within my
incomplete self, inside time and
space with some contentment for
the remainder of my years. And
that's why I think true but
temporary knowledge can be very
valuable. Transcendence can
teach us who we are. It can
teach us what we're doing here.
It can teach us maybe, what the
purpose of our life is. But if
you plunge too deeply into
Transcendence, as I did, I think
it can also undermine your sense
of belonging to the earth. And
that is an equally important
lesson that it took me a while
to, you know, kind of reground
myself in after I stopped my
sessions. But the other thing I
found it was so hard after I
stopped. It wasn't just the loss
of communion. It was the
sickness of silence. It was
having to stay silent about my
psychedelic experiences. I'm a
teacher. I love to get to learn
new things and to share that
learning with others, but in my
society, I was never allowed to
bring my experiences to my
colleagues, to bring my
experiences to my students, I
always had to keep silent about
my psychedelic experiences
because they were illegal and
but now that I've retired, I
retired from my university a
little early in order to write
diamonds from heaven or LSD in
the mind of the universe. And
now, you know, I've given myself
permission. I'm past the statute
of limitations for these
psychedelic crimes, and now I
can say whatever I damn well
please, yeah, and
Ryan Kemp: that's quite
liberating. It
Chris Bache: is liberating. It's
because it's like coming out of
a psychedelic closet is just as
liberating as coming out of any
closet where we are forced to
deny the truth of our being, and
so writing this book has really
been very healing and has
facilitated a deeper level of my
own experiences, because now
that I can talk about them, now
that I can just talk about them
freely and receive other
people's experiences freely in
the expanded psychedelic
conversation, now I can be in my
physical existence who I have
been also in my shamanic,
psychedelic existence. So the
two halves of my life are coming
back together, and I'm beginning
to be experience levels of
wholeness as an incarnate being
that I could not experience as
long as I was being forcibly
held silent to my experiences.
Ryan Kemp: Would you say you
have found any happiness or
contentment from your
experiences? Obviously, I
completely empathize and
understand with that separation
and that, I don't know if it's a
feeling of rejection, but
certainly like bereavement or
not being able to return to
those, those very unique
landscapes and those unique
feelings. But now in life, post
sessions, have you found a
deeper happiness and
contentment? Are you still Ram
Dass often says he hasn't cured
one neurosis through his entire
spiritual journey, and he's
still he never used to be and so
he never really changed, nor
found much, much deeper, deeper
liberation, I guess. How is it
for you?
Chris Bache: Hmm, wonderful. Ram
Dass, what an interesting man.
Absolutely great respect. Hmm,
there is a deep relaxation when
you I have had. Had so many
existential questions answered.
I've had so many existential
pains soothed with the clarity
of truth of experience. I feel
I've been given a much deeper
understanding and appreciation
for how life works, and in that
knowing, in that philosophical
and spiritual knowing, there is
a great relaxation and a sense
of deeper cooperation with life.
More than that, there's been in
the intimacy with the creative
intelligence of the universe and
experiencing the depth of love
that the universe pours into me,
into each of us, into all of us
together. There's just been such
a there has been a profound
spiritual fruition, which
probably has not cured me of all
my foibles, but I certainly hope
it's tilted the balance and has
helped me become a kinder
person, a calmer person, a more
compassionate person. You know,
enlightenment, that's a tricky
thing, maybe one day, but if I
were really aiming for
enlightenment, as this is
classically conceived, living in
a condition of deep transparency
to our eternal abiding nature,
living perpetually conscious of
that aspect of our nature which
Never begins, never ends, is
never divided. It is the the
unchanging truth on which all
changing truth stands. If that
were the goal of this work, I
would have done the work
differently. I would have worked
with very, very small doses. The
purpose of my work, or the
project of my work, it began
kind of pursuing enlightenment,
but it became that just fell
away early on, the work became
to support the enlightenment of
my people, to support the
transformation of humanity as a
whole. And then beyond that, it
became a process of cosmic
exploration, to enter as deeply
as I could into the inside of
the universe, and was given the
opportunity to see things and
experience things that are went
far beyond my ability to
stabilize as an abiding
consciousness when I return. So
it's not from this perspective.
I don't consider my sessions as
failures of attempted
enlightenment. I see them as
successes of cosmic exploration,
and which, of course, is related
to the condition of awakening or
enlightenment at one level, but
at another level, it's
different. It's really quite
different. You don't have to go
back to the beginning of the Big
Bang to be enlightenment. You
don't have to experience
archetypal reality. You don't
have to experience the future
evolution of humanity to be
enlightened. This is just a
different project. I hope,
however, in the deepening
intimacy with the divine, I hope
there's been some progress
towards spiritually wakening up,
you know, healing the fragments
that we all carry from our
historical experiences, I feel a
deep peace and contentment. And
perhaps most notably, not only
am I not afraid of dying, I'm
looking forward to it. It's
absolutely no fear for me,
because I know, I know where I'm
going. Yeah, I know where we're
going. You know, we're going
deeper into that light. So if
you're if there were one thing I
wish I could give to other
people from my experiences, it
would be this loss of fear of
death. Because if you're afraid
of dying, your entire cosmology
is upside down. Yes, this is
where, this is the hard place.
This is the time. Space is where
the hard work is done. Spiritual
reality is, is it's it's reward,
it's home, it's light.
Ryan Kemp: Have you been tempted
in these later years to go back?
I you'll know Aldous Huxley on
his deathbed, his wife injected
him with a large amount, I think
is around 500 micrograms of LSD,
and read him the Tibetan Book of
the Dead. Have you been tempted
to go back into a high dose
session of. All these years
later, I think it's been 20
years, hasn't it?
Chris Bache: Yeah, actually, he
was injected with two low dose
sessions, very low doses, yeah,
just low. And Laura Huxley
discusses this in her biography
of autobiography. No, I mean,
I've done, I've done low dose
sessions with LSD in the years
since I stopped, but generally I
find it, it doesn't work well
with me now. I mean, I've had
wonderful experiences, but I've
pushed my system so hard with
the high doses that it is almost
as if I've developed an allergy
for it. And if I were to take a
massive dose of LSD today, I
would not be able to get back to
where I was regularly journeying
in the last years of my work.
And it has to do with energy
every step into a deeper level
of reality is it moves you into
a more intense level of energy.
And there is an accumulation of
energy that builds up in your
being in your over multiple
sessions. So I found that my
system was accumulating energy,
storing this energy from session
after session, even though those
sessions were months apart, it
was accumulating a massive
quantity of energy which would
then focus that energy and lead
to a breakthrough into a new
level of consciousness. So those
breakthroughs are being paid
for, not simply by hours of
intense psychedelic work. They
sometimes were being paid for by
years of psychedelic work. So if
I wanted to get back into some
of the territory I was
exploring, of the diamond
Luminosity, that territory, I
think it would take me years of
conscientious work to develop
the momentum, the energetic
momentum to tap that deeply into
the universe again. So at this
point my life, I'm content with
more conventional spiritual
practices, a daily meditation
practice. If I do use
psychedelic, sometimes I use
gentler psychedelic Psilocybin
or Ayahuasca, which basically
helps connect me to the fields
of knowledge that continue to
surround me, deriving from my my
LSD work. So I experienced them
not as breaking new ground, but
it's helping me integrate and
absorb what I've already done
into my present being, which is
how I experienced my meditation
practice. I'm not trying to go
back to where I was into my most
intense psychedelic experiences.
I'm not trying to break new
ground. I'm simply facilitating
a deeper absorption of the
reality that I touched on those
days into my physical being
Ryan Kemp: like Alan Watts,
famous adage, when you've got
the message, hang up the phone.
What are your thoughts on that?
Is that right now?
Chris Bache: Well, that's No, I
don't that. I would just say
that's not been my experience. I
mean, this is thought. Huston
Smith used that adage when he
had had about he says in his
book, cleansing the doors of
perception after he had had
about a half dozen psychedelic
experiences, the bummers
increased, and it just really
wasn't working for him. And my
experience is, it's when the
bummers increase is when the
deeper cleansing is taking
place, and that's when it begins
to get interesting. It's only
when death starts to really
pound on you hard that it really
begins to get interesting. When
you're having to lay your life
on the line, then it's getting
interesting. So to me, if we
say, once you get the message,
hang up the phone. Well, okay,
but what is the message? And
there's so many messages and so
many levels, Nobody judges for
another. But to me, there are
messages that come through in
the early work, and they're
magnificent, and they're
messages that come through in
the middle work, and they're
the later work. And if I had
stopped with the early messages,
it would have been perfectly
okay, absolutely, perfectly
okay, but I would have missed
some of the things that came
later. Yeah, so to you know, so
I think everybody has to make
the choices of how much is good
for them, how much serves them,
and then whether it becomes
counter productive. And I'll own
right up front, that I think I'd
bit off a little bit more, not
not more than I could chew,
because I chewed it all, but I
bit off more. Or maybe then was
wise for for me to bite off.
Yeah.
Ryan Kemp: Well, you know,
Chris, thank you very much for
your time here and this
conversation, it's really has
been brilliant, and you've been
massively inspiring in my life,
and I know the lives of many
others that are involved in
these kind of paths and pursuits
and these things that sometimes
can seem so foreign and so
abstract that when you've taken
the time, as you have done to
rigorously catalog everything
you went through over these
years and put it in the book for
some of us to read, that is very
reassuring, because it can, it
can let us know that what's
happening to us and what's
happening to others is not just
some random, random happening.
It's like, Well, it happened to
this guy, and he's got a PhD,
and he's a teacher, and he lived
a very normal life and and so
you're not completely insane, as
some of us confuse some time,
and that's what your book has
done for me and for many others.
So I thank you for that.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Ryan. It
truly is. It's an honor to have
this discussion with you. Thank
you for the privilege of being
able to share this time
together. It's a true joy for me
and a privilege in my old age,
just to be able to have these
kind of conversations, because
you are there's a whole new
generation, and a generation
behind this generation which is
going into this territory, and
we all have a lot to learn from
each other.
Ryan Kemp: Yes, perfect. So your
book is available on Amazon. And
I don't know if you have a
website, do you, Chris?
Chris Bache: You know, I'm
afraid it's not finished yet. It
will be out. I hope in a month
or two. I've just been slow and
busy. I've just moved to North
Carolina. It slowed up some of
these things, but the website
will be Chris bache.com and but
for the time being, people can
find my articles and essays on a
website called academia.edu and
and the book is on Amazon,
Ryan Kemp: yep. And it's also
very nicely enjoyed as an audio
book on Audible, which I can
recommend to people because it's
read by you also. So I think
Chris Bache: that, yeah, I
enjoyed that. I think the
written, the word, the spoken
word has a power even beyond the
written word. And I really what
valued the opportunity to be
able to read the book for for
listeners,
Ryan Kemp: absolutely okay,
Chris, well, thank you very
much. Yeah, and so yeah, thank
you, Chris.
Chris Bache: Thank you. Love and
blessings.
Unknown: You too. You applause.