Chris Bache: I just have an
understanding of the life
process from studying the cases
of small children who have
spontaneous memories of their
most immediate former life, and
we have hundreds and hundreds of
these cases documented by Dr Ian
Stevenson at the University of
Virginia, and by studying the
various child psychotherapists
who work with children and adult
psychotherapists who work with
adults in Taking people back to
the source of their pain and
recovering the early trauma and
the healing that this produces
in their present life.
Eventually, we have accumulated
enormous evidence for the fact
that we reincarnate. We
reincarnate many, many times. So
then my concern is to say, well,
so what, what does? What are the
implications for how we live our
life, and how we understand our
relationships from this
understanding that we
reincarnation is a fact of life,
and my understanding is when we
die, we return to spirit and to
soul into a larger intelligence,
and then we consciously choose
the circumstances of our next
incarnation, and we get small
and focus in experience, and
then we die, and we expand into
the larger arena, and we come
back and we learn. It's like in
college, when you choose your
courses, you then focus for the
semester, and at the end of the
semester, you step back and say,
Ah, that's over. How nice. And
then we choose another round of
courses. And by going back and
forth, lifetime by lifetime,
hundreds of years, 1000s of
years, 10s of 1000s of years, we
are growing. We are becoming
more than we were before. I
think it makes an enormous
difference. It places all the
questions we have about life,
and all the projects we may
undertake in our life, and all
the relationships we have in our
life on a larger perspective, it
basically lifts the constriction
of time from our understanding
of existence. If we have, in
fact, 10s of 1000s of years to
accomplish whatever the purpose
of life is, it gives us a much
larger landscape, a much larger
canvas on which to create, on
which to understand, first of
all, and then on which to
create. We understand that we
are not simply developing the
life process for years or a few
decades, but we're developing
the life process for 10s of
1000s, hundreds of 1000s of
years that naturally invites us
to undertake projects which we
will not be able to fully
accomplish or realize in this
lifetime, but we undertake
projects which we will will see
a fruition in lifetimes to come.
And it also expands our sense of
our connections to other people,
because the relationships that
we have in this lifetime did
not, probably did not begin in
this lifetime, but they have an
older history, and likewise, the
way we treat people in this
lifetime will have consequences
in a subsequent lifetime. So it
just enormously expands the
canvas in which we create. I
truly think that we don't really
understand yet how entering into
extreme Non-ordinary states of
consciousness is impacting our
incarnation in this lifetime, if
we are dealing with gentle
states of Non-ordinary states or
psychedelic states, if we're
dealing with simply staying
close to the shoreline of time
and space and just unearthing
some pain from this life or
earlier in our life, we have
medical models for how to
understand that if we go deeper
to experience the continuity of
life across time and the
inherent presence of the Divine
or cosmic intelligence in life,
then we still have spiritual
models for understanding how
these things might work. But
when we go very, very deep into
the universe, when we go beyond
the limits of space, beyond the
limits of time, when we immerse
ourselves profoundly into the
crystalline body of the Divine,
how these experiences are being
assimilated by us when we come
back that I think we're still
working out. We're still trying
to understand, at least I'm
trying to work that out. It has
changed my understanding of my
life. It's changed my
understanding of history. It's
changed my understanding of the
Divine. And I don't when I say
the divine, I don't mean the
divine within our conventional,
historical, culturally embedded
concepts of the Divine, because
those get shattered along the
way. It's made me very calm.
Look forward to dying, because I
have no fear of what's waiting
for me when I die, because I've
already been there multiple
times, and I'm look forward to
what happens when I die. I think
the the most challenging aspect
of going into these states and
coming back is working to stay
open so you can use these
temporary experiences as seeds
to catalyze a deepening of your
own life. Once you are here,
once you are back, you can't
stay in those states. You can't
even recreate those states here,
but by entering into those
states, they give us seeds of
understanding and seeds of
experience, and we can nourish
those seeds here using
traditional spiritual practices,
meditation practices, acts of
compassion and so on. So for me,
how these experiences have
impacted my life are still being
worked out. Also, I found that
as long as I had to keep silent
about these experiences, as long
as I could not teach from these
experiences, I could not share
these experiences, there is a
sense in which my integration of
those experiences was only
partial. Now that I've begun to
speak freely about the
experiences. Now that I've begun
to write and teach from these
experiences, I find that their
integration into my being has
deepened. But this is just
beginning after 20 years, after
I stopped these experiences,
only now have I begun to write
about them completely and speak
about them completely. We'll see
where that goes. But I have a
sense that it's going someplace.
I do not know where it's going
to go, yet, the messages I take
away are banish fear. The things
that we're afraid of are not
rooted in reality, that there is
a deeper reality in which that
dissolves all those fears. The
message is to cultivate love and
compassion for all beings,
because compassion is inherent
in the nature of oneness and the
world is ultimately one in its
deepest forms and its deepest
roots, all individualized
expression of life emerges out
of a fundamental oneness. The
more we recognize that and live
in oneness, the more comfortable
we are, the more we embody the
values of oneness, the more we
are synergistically coupled with
the processes of life. Fear
comes out of a sense of
isolation and an atrophied
individuality, a rich, robust
individuality relates to the
world in compassion and looks to
the good of the whole it said in
some spiritual traditions,
everything I do for myself is
the source of my pain.
Everything I do for others is
the source of my freedom and my
joy. I think that's true. What
we do for others is is our
liberation, because we are
enacting the truth of oneness.
And I think one of the other
teachings is to have a long term
time horizon that we are in a
process of maturation which will
not be concluded in a few
decades or a few centuries. Our
maturational development takes
place over 10s of 1000s,
millions, billions of years. So
our relationship with the
universe is a dance which will
continue for long after we this
body falls away. Let me narrow
the scope a little bit to to
where I think the human race is
going, because in the work that
I did, I was given many, many
deep, visionary experiences of
human evolution. What's
happening with the human race
right now, and this is a natural
outgrowth when you when your
consciousness, when your
individual consciousness,
shatters, when the shell of your
individual mind shatters, and
you open into the larger context
of mind, you don't simply shoot
straight into oneness and become
one with totality, but one of
the things that happens is that
you open into your species mind.
You open into the mind of the
species. And when you were in
that state, naturally, you get
some insights into the
developmental trajectory of that
species that you are in that
larger sense. And many of my
experiences kept returning to
this theme in a way that
completely surprised me, where
we are going, what's happening
and over and over and over
again, the teaching was humanity
is coming to a time of great
awakening. Humanity is coming,
in time, into an explosive,
exponential increase in its
capacity and.
But for this to take place, for
there to be this tremendous
remaking of the human spirit,
there must be take place a deep
purification process, a
literally kind of a dark night
of our collective soul, which is
a purification, a confrontation
with the shortcomings of
everything that we've been doing
in history, which has been
keeping us small and the
confrontation with our smallness
in order to open to this new and
emerging greatness of our being.
So I think we in this century,
we are entering into a time of
tremendous purification, of time
of destructuring, a time of
losing control, falling apart.
And one of my experiences, I was
taken forward in time in and was
allowed to experience the death
and rebirth of humanity at some
point in the future, I don't
know when, but an organic, long,
historically embedded process
where I experienced the entire
collapse of humanity and
entering into what you might
call a near death episode
collapse. It seemed like we were
going to the point of
extinction, a complete breakdown
of life in our structures at
fundamental levels. But then
from that, there took place a
tremendous resurgence, a birth
process. So I think the
historical, the historical
crisis that we are entering, the
global systems crisis which we
are entering, which is being
driven by a global ecological
crisis, this external crisis of
a world which is trying to
become one and overcome its
history of factions and its
history of individualism,
history of nationalism, its
history of classism, its history
of of gender conflict, this
crisis that's taking place In
the global system is actually
synchronistically coordinated
with a developmental crisis,
which is taking place
internally. As we are trying to
become one planet. I think we
are trying to become one soul,
so that we carry the history of
the planet in our being through
our former lives. And so as the
planet is trying to become one.
I think we are individually
trying to become one. And I
think the solution ultimately of
our planet becoming one,
integrated whole in a healthy,
productive way, is actually
dependent upon ultimately each
of us becoming whole
individually. So that I expect
that the solution in the end of
the global systems crisis will
be the birth of what I call the
diamond soul, which is the birth
of soul consciousness inside
time and space. We will wake up,
we will wake up and realize we
are not just this body. We have
a much larger history. And all
the experiences of all of those
lives come together and fuse.
And when they fuse, they just
don't become a longer story, but
they fuse in an explosion of
energy which lifts the entire
experience of being alive to a
higher register. So I basically
think that humanity is coming
into labor. We have been in
gestation for hundreds of 1000s
of years. Gestation is long,
labor is fast. Labor is very
intense and painful, but we are
in the process of giving birth,
not just to a new culture, to a
new economy, but we are in the
process of giving birth to a new
form of human being, an awakened
human being, a being with A much
expanded compassion and a much
open mind. You
Unknown: you.