Stephen Gray: So going to call
on our friend and colleague
Chris Bache to share some words
with us, I want to thank you
very much for taking the time to
do this, Chris. And I know it's
getting later in the evening for
you, excuse me, and I imagine a
lot of you, the rest of us know
Chris by now, to some degree,
through his work. But if you
don't, I just want to suggest
that if you have any interested
in the fate, any interest at
all, in the fate of humanity,
you get yourself a copy of LSD
in the mind of the universe, his
most recent book, and it's a
stunner. It really is in a
beautiful and positive way. So
thank you for joining us. Chris,
over to you. Thank you, Steven.
Am I coming through? Okay? Mark,
Sound okay, good, yeah. It's a
pleasure and an honor to be with
the community again. It's truly
especially on this winter
solstice, and especially on this
winter solstice,
Chris Bache: Saturn conjunct,
Jupiter entering into Aquarius.
Good sign, good time, hopefully,
a marker of changes that are
coming. It's been a hard year.
The pandemic has touched us all
in one way or another, and many
of us are looking forward to
220, 2021, that's a time of a
shift, a time of change, and I'm
sure it will be, I hope it will
be so a few words spoken softly
in the mode, in the manner of
our special ceremony tonight,
about our collective
transformation. I've picked this
picture of the earth to start
with, because the earth is going
into convulsions. It seems like
there's no way to stop it. Now
we can ameliorate it, but we're
going into the dark night of our
collective soul. We have set in
motion a sequence of events
that's taking us into a very,
very turbulent, convulsive
period of history. That's what
my reading of the ecological
sources tell me. It's also what
my visionary experiences tell me
in psychedelic work, we are
going into a time of ascending
energy, a time in which nature
is reaching down and bringing up
energy underneath our feet,
taking us, taking humanity into
an extraordinary new phase of
its evolutionary journey, a time
of great awakening, a time of
great spiritual fruition, a time
of a change in the fundamental
archetypal architecture of the
collective psyche that informs
all of our individual psyches as
we work together. But when this
happens, when nature turns up
the heat underneath us, it
triggers profound purification
processes. It triggers a process
in which we have no choice but
to confront our shadows, both
our individual shadow and our
collective shadow, because our
shadow is rising, and it's a
time in history when our shadow
is rising, and clearly the
ecological consequences that we
are inheriting in this century
are aspects of this large
collective shadow and the ego,
and a civilization of ego that
has made the decisions that
they've made with respect to the
Earth, and made the decisions
they've made with respect to
each other, those are all coming
out on us really hard now it's
all coming forward. So I want to
change perspective a little bit
and take us because if we really
want to go deep into this
collective transformation, if we
want to engage it fully, it's a
good time to step back. It's a
good night to step back into a
larger context. But I'm going to
encourage us to step even
farther back, to place ourselves
in the context and in the
presence of the creative
intelligence of the universe, of
the divine intelligence, or the
creative intelligence, the great
power. These star lights behind
me are not just stars. Some are
stars, but many are galaxies
with billions. And billions of
stars, an unimaginable
outpouring of power and genius,
just incredible genius
unfolding. And it's the same
genius which birthed this
universe, which is birthing his
time in history, and it's the
same genius which has placed us
here to participate consciously
in this milestone period, this
milestone century that we have
coming into we will come out of
this century profoundly
different than we came into it.
And so I'd like to encourage you
to think about, who is it that's
undergoing this transformation?
Who is it that's engaging these
powerful forces carrying us
forward? And it's not who we
think we are. We are not who we
think we are. We have, by habit,
a custom of thinking of
ourselves as basically 100 year
old beings, but the science of
consciousness tells us today
clearly we are not 100 year old
beings. Reincarnation is a
simple fact of life, and knowing
this, when we look at ourselves,
we see that we are 100,000 year
old beings. We have enormous
quantities of time folded into
the person that we now are,
every talent that we have, every
piece of genius that we have,
every habit that we have, even
our bad habits that we have,
they come from somewhere. They
come from a deeper history. And
one way to imagine a human being
as a reincarnated being is the
samurai sword, which is made
from folding level upon level
upon level of metal folded and
hammered over each other up to
10,000 layers of metal subjected
to fierce heat and fuse together
to create a blade of incredible
lightness and strength and
agility. And I think a soul is
that too we are the result. This
generation is the result of
hundreds and 1000s of lifetimes
of precious human experience of
precious learning, folded in
upon one another, folded upon
one another, and are being
fused. And just as the planet is
facing a huge crisis to become
one planet, one ecosystem, one
system that lives in a healthy
manner, with each other, with
the planet itself. If that's
taking place in the outer social
world, there is a similar
process taking place in our
inner world. I think it's a time
when all of our former lives are
coming into us really hard. We
were born with many of our
farmer lives active in our
psyches much more than in
previous generations, and as we
engage our shadows, as we engage
our individual and collective
shadows, and submit ourselves to
the transforming fire of deep
awareness and let the divine
awareness that we all are focus
on our past and purify our past
of all of those things which
hold us back and constrict us.
We then become initiated into
deeper and deeper levels of
intimacy with the universe, with
each other. This geniuses behind
all these stars and galaxies
behind me. This is our nature.
We open ourselves as we purify
ourselves, we open ourselves
into the cosmic arms, into the
embrace of our own history, into
the sacred communion, which is
taking us forward out of this
century, I think, is coming a
new humanity, the future human.
You know, I call it the birth of
the diamond soul, which is
simply all of our former lives
coming together and fusing into
a single intelligence, a single
consciousness, an individual
awareness, which is individual,
and yet a deeper form of
individuality than we've ever
seen on Earth before, not just a
few of us, all of us, the entire
human species coming forward in
this crescendo of power,
purification, destabilization,
reaching out, reaching out, and
achieving something that has
never been achieved in history
before. This is something I
share with you, which comes from
my own psychedelic work, but I
don't think it's not it has
anything to do with me prior.
Privately I talk with people, I
think many of us are seeing this
basic same truth in our own
psychedelic sessions. The
indigenous people have been
seeing it for generations in
their work. Some of the great
saints and mystics who never
touch psychedelics have seen
these things coming forward.
This is the time of the great
unraveling. The pandemic
unraveled us faster than we ever
thought possible. But it's just
the overture. There are harder
times coming if we embrace those
hard times with foreknowledge,
with absolute dedication, not
turning away from any of the
hardship that's coming, but
engage it fully, asking
ourselves the question, what is
the highest good that I can
bring to the challenges that I'm
facing? What can I give that's
being asked to be given now I
think we accelerate our own
individual evolution, and in
accelerating our individual
evolution, we accelerate
humanity's collective evolution.
I think we're all in this for
the collective right now, the
time of the individual saints
and saviors is gone. It's over.
They've done their job. They've
done their work.
The hour now is for the children
and the grandchildren and our
great grandchildren, the only,
the only calling that's worthy
of ourselves is our collective
salvation, our collective
transformation, our collective
good to bring us back in
alignment with the deep truths,
with our deep soul, with our
deep heart. As the future human
emerges in history, I anticipate
a tremendous opening of our
heart to each other as we open
our heart to the Divine heart,
which holds all of existence,
not just humans, but all beings,
all of existence. And as our
minds open up into the deep
communion, it opens us up into
the cosmic communion that opens
us into the in taking of
awareness and insights, truly
scientific insights that can
come pouring into us when we're
open and clean and clear.
We've passed the longest night
of the year. We're coming into
the beginning of the rising
daylight in our lives, just a
short cycle, just a six month
cycle, and then the cycle of
darkness will begin again, this
challenge that humanity is
facing, it's a huge challenge.
We'll make it but that itself is
not the end. It's just a phase.
It's just a phase. We've been
here for billions of years.
We're going to be here for
billions of years more, taking
us deeper, farther, unimaginable
ways. My last thought I share
with you tonight is this, this
journey is so long we're not
going to accomplish it in this
lifetime. It's going to take
more than one lifetime, many
lifetimes, to stay on this
journey. And therefore, as we
open deeply to the cosmic
communion, one thing that should
fall away quickly is our fear of
death. Absolutely nothing to
fear in death, because death is
in no way an ending. It's simply
a punctuation in the cycle. And
the same beautiful universe that
we open up in sacred medicine
space is the same universe we
open up to when we fall when our
bodies fall away, the journey
continues in the cascading
ecologies of light. Thank you
for letting me share these
thoughts with you on this
special night.
Stephen Gray: Thank you so much.
Chris.