Unknown: Foreign.
Stephen Gray: Welcome everybody.
The very first YouTube channel
and also audio podcast on Anchor
is where it will also show up.
YouTube channel interview in a
series. It's the series is
called, you may have noticed
Steven Gray, vision. Stephen
gray all one word, S, T, E, P,
H, E, N, and then capital, G, R,
A, y, vision. And the purpose of
these is to explore the
possibilities of an awakening
humanity. I guess that's the
simplest way of putting it. And
you will be able to subscribe to
these. I hope to be able to put
a subscribe button up here
somewhere at some point, and
some contact information both at
the beginning and the end. So as
I say, I'm very excited, because
this is the very first one of
these in a series that I hope to
continue for quite a while.
Chris Bache is our first my
first guest, and we both
acknowledge, just before putting
on the recording, that we're
both feeling honored about this.
And so that's really exciting in
itself. And so before I actually
ask Chris to say anything. I'm
going to read a short bio and
add a couple of little comments
of my own. So Christopher M
Bache officially is professor
emeritus in the Department of
Philosophy and Religion at
Youngstown State University
where he taught for 33 years. He
is also adjunct faculty at the
California Institute of integral
studies and a fellow at the
Institute of Noetic scientists
sciences, an award winning
teacher. Chris's work explores
the philosophical implications
of Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, especially
psychedelic states. Chris has
written three books, lifestyle
life cycles. I won't describe
them here. They're findable, of
course, dark night, early dawn,
which I read about 20 years ago.
Wonderful book the living
classroom, which I have not
read. And his more recent, or,
well, quite recent, about a year
ago, maybe. Or was it less, I
can't remember, six months.
Yeah, anyway, LSD and the mind
of the universe, subtitled
diamonds from heaven. And also,
I'm going to be asking Chris
about to give a summary of the
20 year journey that he went on
that's described in LSD, in the
mind of the universe. But I
don't want it to take the whole
interview, and in particular,
because, well, among other
reasons, because it's he talks.
He does do a thorough, kind of
linear job of going through all
that in two or three of these
YouTube videos. And so I would
suggest, if you really want to
get into the details, short of
reading the book, which is a
stunner. It's just amazing. I
would suggest going on YouTube
and looking up diamonds from
heaven. Time waiver, summer
world 2018 and there's like a 50
minute talk that they recorded
of Chris going through the whole
journey. And that book, by the
way, I have it right here, so
I'm going to show it to you
called LSD in the mind of the
universe, diamonds from heaven.
Chris, Don't let me forget at
the end to ask you for any kind
of contact information or links
that you would like people to
follow up on. Thank you so
Anyway, welcome Chris to my
inaugural Steven gray vision
YouTube Channel series.
Chris Bache: It's a pleasure to
be with you today, Steven, an
honor to be in your memorial
voyage.
Stephen Gray: All right, so, you
know, there's lots of things I
want to ask you about and
discuss with you, and the I
think a good place to start.
However, it would be if you
could give a relatively short
again, because people can go and
look at the video videos on
YouTube, if you could give,
maybe, I don't know, five minute
or something. I don't know
exactly sort of summary of, you
know, well, in the in the talks,
you talk a little bit about, you
know, what got you into it, you
know, maybe just a real brief
reference to, you know, why you
did this in the first place, and
then a little bit about the 20
year journey, and perhaps what
you know where, where it went
after that, something like that.
Chris Bache: So basically, what
you're asking for is, is a
highlight reel or trailer for
the book? Exactly. Yeah. Well,
I'm a philosopher of religion. I
was trained in philosophy of
religion. And I came to this
work with an interest in the
potential of psychedelics to
explore the deeper reaches of
consciousness, and by pushing
through our personal, personal
unconscious, entering into the
consciousness, what I eventually
came to understand is the mind
of the universe itself. So I did
20 years, 73 high dose LSD
sessions, and I'd emphasize the
significance of that particular
protocol, high dose sessions
working at 500 to 600
micrograms, because this opened
up territory and experiences
that were much deeper than when
you're working with the types of
psychedelics and the levels of
doses of psychedelics which are
being used in the therapeutic
community today, which is so
important and very important
development there. This was
different. This is a much more
aggressive shattering of
different levels of
consciousness and the boundaries
of consciousness. I worked for
four years, stopped for six
years, and then worked for 10
years. I did an average of about
five sessions a year. And where
I went is a long story, but the
highlight reel is I spent about
two years basically working at
what Stan Grof calls the
perinatal level of
consciousness, processing a lot
of material around very early
experiences, birth experiences
death, experiences fear of
death, experiences existential
crisis. Kind of work went
through a deep ego death that
just exploded my identity and
catapulted me into early level
spiritual experiences, spiritual
reality. Then I spent another
two years going through a much
more intense purification
process that I call the dark
night of the soul, where the
work clearly pivoted. It took me
a long time to recognize it, but
it clearly pivoted away from my
personal transformation or my
personal healing, and entered
into the collective psyche,
where the focus was the healing
or transformation of the species
mind itself, where I was
processing experiences coming
from 1000s and hundreds of 1000s
of persons and 1000s of years of
time. When that culminated, I
was spun into archetypal
reality. Experienced various
permutations of archetypal
reality and vast territories in
the collective unconscious. And
basically was learning how to
how our species lives as a
single integrated entity, as a
single being, all of us being
fractal embodiments of that
being. From that culminated, I
went through yet another round
of death and rebirth into causal
level reality, where basically,
instead of the world being
composed of parts, even the very
big parts, of archetypal
reality, here the universe
basically pulsed as a single
entity, as a single life form,
dissolving all boundaries, all
membranes, even the membrane
between matter and spirit. I
explored or was given many gifts
in that territory for about a
year, and a chapter that I call
the benediction of blessings,
and then for the last five years
of my work, I entered into a
domain of that I came to call
the diamond Luminosity, entering
into a state of consciousness
that was pure light, and the
most difficult thing to describe
is the hyper, hyper clarity,
just clarity beyond measure of
this form of light. I discovered
that there are many levels of
light, and the diamond
Luminosity was the purest,
highest level I reached in my
work, what Buddhism calls
Dharmakaya are the absolute
reality, the clear light of
absolute reality. For those five
years, I entered this reality
only four times in 26 sessions
with a lot of purification, lot
of lot of healing work done in
those intermediate sessions, and
then I was given one final
vision of the human trajectory,
where we are in history, which
had been a consistent theme in
the work, and then basically the
universe kicked me out. It gave
me two sessions, or wrapped up
our work without me really
understanding yet at the time
that it was wrapping it up, but
it wrapped me up, wrapped up our
work, and then ushered me on my
way, and I stopped my work. So I
stopped the work. I began it in
1979 and I finished it in 1999
and after I finished it, Spirit
said to me in my meditation, 20
years in, 20 years out, meaning
that it would take me 20. Years
in order to understand and
digest the 20 years of
experiences that I had had. And
then it just so happened, not by
any intent, but it just so
happened that LSD in the mind of
the universe was published 20
years after my last session.
Stephen Gray: Wonderful, yes.
And you know, for people
watching and listening to this,
I want to say that, you know, if
you didn't quite gather how
stunning this journey, or series
of journeys, really has been,
read the book because it's mind
blowing. It's truly paradigm
shattering material. I like to
occasionally joke with no
particular offense to Terence
McKenna, who did a lot of lovely
work that the descriptions that
he gives of where he went were
just kind of tapping into the
realms where you have explored,
where you've gone into the, you
know, in these in these
journeys. So a practical
question, though, or sort of,
yeah, user friendly question, so
to speak, you have spoken in
different ways about, Well,
several things related to this.
One is, you said you wouldn't do
it the same way again because it
was so intense, and then you
also understood that it wasn't
about getting anywhere
particularly. That's one aspect
of this question I'm about to
pose. The other one is, clearly,
this is not for everybody, and
so there's something in there,
and and then, just on a
practical level, for people who
do feel like they are those sort
of deep exploring Psychonauts
and want to do something like
this, feel that kind of a call
like you have. Could you just
briefly describe the protocol,
the safety protocol, that you
employed?
Chris Bache: Well, let's start
with the safety protocol. Yeah,
I basically use the protocol
established by Stanislav Grof in
the early years of his work and
published in his book LSD
psychotherapy in 1980 he
distinguishes clearly low dose
psychelytic sessions and high
dose psychedelic sessions in the
early years. Those psychedelic
sessions were limited to three.
I basically took that protocol,
which always and then and then,
multiplied the number of
sessions to 73 but I was always
working in isolation. I was
working in the privacy of my
home or my wife's clinical
office. I was always lying down,
protected from the outside
world, no interruptions. I had a
sitter. My sitter for all this
work was Carol, my first wife, a
clinical psychologist, listening
to a very carefully curated
playlist of music to support the
deepening and the unfolding of
the work. So basically, the
sessions were completely
internally focused, sheltered
from the outside world. There
was no interface with the
outside world except through the
music. And the focus was on
encountering as deeply as
possible what was arising from
within my own consciousness. Now
the reason I
Stephen Gray: Chris, before we
go any further, a quick question
regarding the sitter, for anyone
who's going to do this kind of
work on their own, what would
you say the job description
prerequisites are for the
sitter, like, does that person
need to have been to some of
these inner realms themselves to
be able to do that job? Or what
would you say, you know, who
could do that job properly?
Chris Bache: Ideally, a person
who's doing the sitting should
be experienced in these domains.
It partly depends upon how
interactive the work is, but the
more experienced the sitter is,
the more comfortable he or she
is likely to be when the subject
gets into this territory. In our
case, Carol was not really
interested in exploring these
domains herself. She read the
literature with me, and that's
not perhaps an ideal
circumstance, but it works
sufficiently well for us. The
responsibility of the sitter is
to take care of the subject so
that they don't hurt themselves,
because some of the spasms that
come up in this session are
pretty violent. There's a lot of
throwing up when working with
high doses, and that has to be
taken care of, basically making
sure the subject stays focused,
so that there's no acting out
any attempt to sort of step away
and step outside of the session,
needs to be discouraged and keep
the person focused material and
then managing the music, staying
in touch with the subject, so
that they know they can
anticipate where the subject is,
sometimes asking questions, but
usually not often. So. That they
can shift the music when the
person has gone into a shift in
their own inner experience.
Stephen Gray: Can you say a
little bit about the music, how
important it is? Is it to get
the right kind of music? I think
in your talk, the one that I
mentioned on YouTube, you said
something about you kind of a
developing quality to the music
as it changed over the course of
the of the session of the Yeah,
it was six, eight hours or so.
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, I
basically followed Helen
Bonnie's recommendations that
Stan had cited in his early
work. And she differentiates
five stages of an LSD session,
and there's basically an
ascending there's an early
latency, and then when the drug
begins to kick in, there's a
high activation. And again, this
is working with high levels of
LSD where the activation level
is particularly intense, and
there's a huge surge in the
quantity of energy that one is
processing, and that continues
to build. And you want music
that can encourage the
surrendering, encouraging the
giving in to whatever is
happening, and supports the
breakthrough of your own
defenses. And then the
experiences will build until you
reach a level where eventually,
if you manage them well,
courageously, you go through
some form of crisis, some crisis
in the experience, some death
and rebirth, experience where
then you're catapulted for the
remainder of the session into
the ecstatic portion of the
journey. My experiences were
always the early portion of the
session was a purification
experience, culminating and then
ending in an ecstatic portion of
the experience. Then there's a
long peak of the experience,
where, once you've made that
breakthrough, you want music
that supports the long
expansing, expansive worldview,
and then a very, very slow
decline, a re entry with gentle
music that gives you a spacious
background that allows you to
process your experiences, and as
you come back to your ordinary
consciousness, integrate your
experiences With your
conventional your identity, your
ordinary identity. I found that
after a number of sessions, that
when I began to use indigenous
music chanting with my sessions,
I found that to be much more
powerful, much more evocative,
than classical music, even
powerful classical music. So I
had a preference for that, and
so I collected a lot of
indigenous music over the years
from different cultures. And you
don't want music with any words
that you can understand. So you
want music that doesn't keep you
on familiar ground, which is
another advantage of indigenous
music, or, you know, vocal or
non vocal types, because it
throws you into foreign
territory, and the foreign
territory is what you really
want to be exploring right now,
not staying on the familiar
ground
Stephen Gray: Absolutely. Yeah,
so before we get into the sort
of farther reaches of some of
the experiences you had and the
implications of that I just
listened or watched parts of
that video that I had mentioned
earlier, and you referenced
William James, the great early
20th century psychologist, who
said something like that, there
are three stages of this kind of
work that you've been doing, and
one is the first one is kind of,
you know, pushing the
boundaries, going out into
exploratory territory, but then
following that up with
meticulous recording, and then a
third stage of analysis and
sharing. Is that more or less
Chris Bache: accurate? Yeah,
that's my that's not so much
William James, but it's my
articulation of the principles
of psychedelic philosophy based
on the pioneering work that
James did in that he used
nitrous oxide and drew very
striking conclusions in the
context of the varieties of
religious experience book. And
basically I just articulated
this method from that that you
go into temporary Non-ordinary
states, you record those states
afterwards as clearly and
precisely as you can. And that's
important, because that's really
important, I think, to complete
the circle of learning. Because
if you want to do this in a
systematic fashion, integrating
and attending to and trying to
understand your experiences lays
the foundation a strong
foundation for your next set of
experiences. Just like our
dreams are very revelatory, but
if you keep a dream journal,
people find that their dreams
often become more powerful. More
articulate. It is as if your
mind knows that you're paying
attention. The unconscious knows
you're paying attention to it,
and therefore it ups its game.
Likewise, in a session, the more
attention you pay to integration
and consolidating your
experiences. It is as if the
cosmic mind knows you're paying
attention, and and therefore it
engages you more systematically
at the end. So retaining the
experiences is really important,
and particularly if you're
pushing the far boundaries, like
I was doing, and entering into
territory that was radically new
to me and uncertain and I didn't
have many cues, even in in the
psychedelic literature, for
trying to understand much of it,
writing at the very edges of my
of my ability, and trying to
consolidate what I experienced,
was an important part of the
process. And if I can loop back
to your earlier question, why I
wouldn't do it the same way
again, I wouldn't do it the same
way because of some of the
things I learned on the journey.
First of all, I found that over
the long haul, working at doses
this high, even doing it very
responsibly and conscientiously,
and supplementing it with a lot
of other spiritual practice, a
lot of attention to my body, a
lot of yoga, a lot of
meditation, it's a very, very
demanding protocol. It exerts,
it's it's a very taxing
protocol. If I were doing it
over again, I would be gentler
with myself. I would balance
high dose sessions with low dose
sessions. I would balance LSD,
which tends to be a high level,
cosmic level psychedelic with
Psilocybin Ayahuasca, other
psychedelics which are more body
grounded in order to facilitate
an ongoing integration of the
peak experiences, doing it the
way I did, just hammering the
high levels, Just pushing and
pushing, it did open great
cosmic vistas. But I think it I
think I was harder on myself
than I really needed to be, and
maybe then was wise, and it took
me a long time to internalize
and in some ways, to recuperate
from that entire journey. The
other reason I would do it a
little differently is because I
learned along the way that this
is not a journey that comes ever
comes to a distinct end. When I
began this work, I thought there
was an end point. I was trying
to get to the end point. Some
people describe the end point as
oneness with God, or entering
into the primal void, and I had
entered into oneness with the
Divine many times, and I had
learned that there are many
levels to that experience, and
even levels to immersion in the
primal void and deep. About two
thirds of the way through the
journey, I had an experience
where the universe showed me
that it's an absolute, infinite
universe, I would never be able
to get to the end of it. It's an
open ended journey you take in
as much of the universe as you
can, as as healthy and as wise
for you. But the idea of getting
to the end was just it was a
misconception, and because of
that, that's another reason why
I would just be a little gentler
and a little patient with the
pace of a slower pace of
evolution.
Stephen Gray: Yeah, the, my old
Buddhist teacher, chugging
Trungpa, has one of his books is
called journey without goal. And
then there's the Are you
familiar with the 10 ox herding
pictures? Yes, yeah. The way
I've encountered them was like,
the last one is something like
and Thus ends the journey that
never need to have been made in
the first place, or something
like that.
Chris Bache: Yes, yeah. And now
it's a little different that,
you know, I started this work
kind of with a focus on
enlightenment, and that really
is what the 10 Oxford and
pictures are about, that journey
of awakening to the ever present
condition, so that in the end,
you come back to where you were,
but you come back with your
filters clear and the present.
The always present, ever present
condition is luminously there.
That's where I that's the agenda
I started with. But it was over
come over. It was superseded by
two other aspects. First, it was
superseded by the challenges of
our collective enlightenment, of
our collective evolution.
Eventually, my personal healing,
or my personal enlightenment,
was just completely superseded
by responding to the call to
support our collective
transformation, the
transformation taking place in
history. And the second thing
that superseded then even that
was the opportunity. Need to
explore the deep structure of
the universe itself to what I'd
call a cosmological exploration.
You do not need to explore the
deep structure of the universe
in order to become awakened, to
become to your spiritual senses.
You do not need to go back to
the beginning of the universe
and the Big Bang to transcend
all limits of time, to enter
archetype of reality, to abide
in the true and natural
condition that Buddhism calls
our essential nature. These are
different projects. So my work
kind of combined the
Enlightenment project, but
really it kind of yielded to a
different project, what you
might call the philosopher's
project, the invitation to
explore, as far as I could, the
nature of cosmic reality.
Stephen Gray: Yeah, wonderful.
Thank you for clarifying that.
So I don't know how to ask this
question exactly, or even if it
is a good question, but
something like this, you know,
that kind of deep work is
clearly not, you know,
prescribed for a great majority
of people. It's for particular
individuals who feel that they
that calling, and, you know,
feel that they're up for it. And
you you've indicated in your
talks, that you felt that
calling, you know, earlier, at
the beginning of your career,
you know, that you'd always been
interested in that state, and
you felt like, are those kinds
that, you know, effing the
ineffable, as Alan Watts put it,
unscrewing the inscrutable. So I
guess where I'm trying to go
with this question is, people
that are, hmm, a lot of people
are not ever going to use
psychedelics. But then there's
another whole subset of people
in the communities that are the,
you know, in the populace, that
are working with these. And I'm,
I guess, I don't know if
they're, you know, like I say,
what you could say about this.
But you know, the people that
are not in that small group of
people that are going to do that
extremely deep work, do you have
any, have you had any kind of
thoughts, intuitions, feelings
about, you know, how a lot of
people can approach the work
that needs to be done with the
help of psychedelics? Hmm?
Unknown: Well,
Chris Bache: first, you're right
that I wrote LSD in the mind of
the universe with the hope that
it would be read, not only by
other psychedelic voyagers. I
hope psychedelic voyagers would
would read it, and there would
be a kind of conversation that
would emerge from Voyager to
Voyager, back and forth. But I
hope that this book would also
be read by people who are not
interested in taking
psychedelics and or who haven't
had the opportunity. Because
what's important, I think, in so
many ways, in the book is the
cosmology that emerges, is the
visions of reality that emerge
in the psychedelic state. And
these can be very valuable to
people, whether or not they ever
touch these experiences
themselves, just to see what the
understanding of reality that
comes forward. And I've had many
people write me since the book
has come out, and say, I've
never taken psychedelics in my
life, but I've been a lifelong
meditator, and I really relate
to what you're saying. I've had
many, many similar experiences
of collective suffering, for
example, or different death and
rebirth experiences, but I've
never used psychedelics, and
that's, of course, what we
expect, because psychedelics are
simply an amplifier of
consciousness. It's
consciousness that does the
work. So if you work with
consciousness in a focused way,
then naturally, you're going to
have similar experiences in
different ways to what emerges
in a psychedelic session. Now
for people who want to work with
psychedelics, sorry, several
basic rules of thumb stand out
for me. One of them is very,
very meticulous attention to set
and setting, which, of course, I
think is widely understood now,
but I would emphasize clarity of
intention in creating the
conditions of long term
engagement. Sometimes our
engagement is short by a few
months. Sometimes our
undertaking is several years of
work. But the longer our focused
engagement, the more important
it is to really set up the shop
carefully, to really have your
Kiva prepared, both inwardly and
outwardly, so that your contact
what you want is clean contact
and good recall. And clean
contact means not obscuring the
field with a lot of other things
going on or tending to a lot of
outside things. Tripping is fine
if people want to trip, and a
lot of people have life changing
experiences trip. Being no
criticism there. But if you want
to use this for deep inner work,
you have to clarify your field,
clear it out. And then the
second thing that stands out is
the importance of retention, the
importance of holding on to your
experiences, clarifying
recording them, either with
works of art. Sometimes people
do it with music. For me, it's
always been the written word,
methodologically. This, a lot of
the work which is being done,
important work being done with
psychedelics, is therapeutically
focused, aimed at healing the
wounds of the personal psyche.
And that's really important
work, and we're learning a lot
about that, particularly now in
this renaissance of
psychedelics. But that which
heals at the therapeutic level,
at the personal unconscious
level, is also that which opens
work experiences deeper into the
cosmos itself. It's in renewing
our relationship with the
universe that heals so much of
our wounds of incarnation. And
if you are called, or feel
called to push the boundaries, I
mean, it really is. There are
some people who love to climb
mountains and lum some people
who love to, you know, go deep
into the oceans. They just have
an adventurous spirit. And I
think that also is true for
those who want to explore states
of consciousness. But it takes a
certain personality type, if you
will, to you have a certain
rigor, a certain capacity to
maintain ambiguity, to deal with
ambiguity, a certain kind of
stability of your social
circumstance, because it's not
just you who go into these
states, but into a degree.
Everyone that you are intimately
associated with is touched by
your work. So you have to make
sure your life is grounded and
solid that supports the work.
And the last thing I would
mention is the deeper you want
to go into these Non-ordinary
states, the more important it is
to have a daily spiritual
practice. I just have become so
convinced of this over the time,
because you need a daily
spiritual practice to ground
first just the energy that's
unleashed in these states, and
then to ground the experiences
the more you learn about
mysticism and the more you study
the autobiographies of our great
saints and sages, the easier it
is. I think to have it gives you
a touchstone for grounding your
more radical experiences.
Stephen Gray: You know, it's
funny, you mentioned the great
saints and all that. And I don't
think there's an answer to this,
but it's just been on my mind a
little bit later, lately that,
you know, there are these, you
know, kind of pinpoint people
over the last couple of 1000
years that you know we hear
about. I don't remember all the
names, but you know, St John of
the Cross, St Francis, Meister
Eckhart and a few of these great
mystics that we know about. You
know, of course, you know, there
are probably many from
indigenous traditions that
weren't writing anything down.
But you know, where are these
people now? I mean, are there
just too many of us for them to
stand out on the planet? Now,
like, Where are the people like
Ramana Maharshi and these people
that seem to have completely
gotten it, so to speak.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I don't know
the answer that question. That's
kind of a sociological and
historical question. I don't
really know the answer. I think
that we are that they're more
hidden saints than we might
appreciate, but I also think, in
a fundamental way, I agree with
those who have observed that the
age of private enlightenment is
coming to an end. It's already
come to an end, and it's not
like individual you know,
enlightenment work is not
important. It is important, but
we have entered into a time of
history where we need to draw
the whole human species needs to
enter into the Enlightened
condition. The whole human
species needs to really get at
the roots of what's holding us
in this tight configuration of
ego. Because the world, the
civilization that we are in now,
is a civilization built by the
ego, and the ego is ultimately a
cut off psychological entity. We
don't experience our common
ground with other beings, and we
ground with the universe itself.
It's a fragmented condition, and
it builds a fragmented universe.
And right now, the fragmentation
of our universe is threatening
the very vitality of the lives
of the all life on our planet.
So I think we are moving into a
time where the real impetus is
collective transformation. And
that's a that I think is kind of
taking us into a different level
of the game than we were in for
the. Last 2000 years.
Stephen Gray: Yeah, well, put
beautifully, but yeah, my old
Buddhist teacher that I
mentioned earlier, chugyam,
Trungpa. I don't you probably
know more about this than I,
than I do as a concept, but I
think there are different uses
of the word term arhat. But
wait, Trungpa talked about it
was he, he was critical of what
he called the arhat mentality,
which was the enlightenment for
self kind of mentality, was the
way he described it. Yeah. So,
you know, I completely agree
with you. So perhaps that leads
in, for me, anyway, into this
discussion of the sort of great
death and great awakening that
you talk about in your work and
that you explored in those
journeys, and yeah, the probably
the primary motivation for me
doing this YouTube channel
series altogether, is because of
the kind of things you were just
talking about, that we've
reached a karma, a kind of
karmic comeuppance point where
the that fragmented ego
mentality has brought the planet
to place where it's not
sustainable to continue in this
direction anymore. So I'm
wondering if you could explore
and talk a little bit about I
know one thing that you've
mentioned in your talks is that
you weren't given a timeline on
this. There was no 2012
involved. But it sounds to me
like I don't know. An image I've
been using occasionally is a
boat coming down a river toward
a whirlpool, or you might use
the term vortex. And you know at
first, when the when, when the
boat first gets pulled into the
into the orbit, as it were, of
the of the vortex. It's going
around the outer edge kind of
slowly, but then it's gradually
getting pulled. The strength
becomes of the pull becomes
increasingly strong and rapid,
and it seems to me where we're
well into that vortex. Now, I
don't know, do you? Can you
comment on that?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, this
was a great surprise for me in
my work, because when I began
this work, I was thinking that
this was thinking in terms of a
model of individual
transformation. I was doing this
work to transform and improve my
my private self in some way, and
that was shattered after two
years. The game changed. It was
it was not about that. And about
four years into the work, I
began to be given a series of
visions that continue to unfold
over over 50 sessions. And the
the theme of these visions was
always humanity's collective
transformation. They were
consistent in in over over time.
And the message was, humanity
was coming to a point of a
before and after point in
history, of a decisive
transformation, of an
evolutionary jump in the quality
of of consciousness that we
would be living out of and
through just just an exponential
a time of great blessing, a time
of great grace, of great
illumination, of great healing.
And these visions came for
years, but I was never shown in
these early years how nature was
going to pull this off, because
when I looked around me, it
didn't look like that was what
was happening. And it looked
like for every indicator that we
were getting better, there were
other indicators that we were
getting worse, more insanity,
more greed, more corporate
control and and then in 1995 I
was given a very, very deep
session, a series of visions,
and I was taken into the future.
Time became very horrible,
permeable. In my sessions, I I
entered into multiple modalities
of trans temporal experiences.
And in this I entered into the
deep future, and I experienced
what I came to understand was
the death and rebirth of our
entire species in some
collective historical crescendo,
and I experienced it not as
crisp Bache, individual self
looking on, and not even as a
spiritual aspect of crisp based
looking on. By this time, I had
dissolved so many times and so
deeply into the collective mind
that I experienced this crisis
as a ask the species. I
experienced it literally as a
rippling of crisis arising
within the collective psyche,
and I experience a time of
tremendous suffering, a time of
things falling apart, of loss of
control, of of human beings
losing more and more of the
constants of their world. It the
image that comes to mind is of a
hurricane that's coming over.
Over a small island which is
just threatening all life on the
island. And for a time, in my
experience, I thought we were
going to go extinct. I thought
we were heading into an
extinction event. But then at
the peak time, the storm passed,
and humanity began to recover,
to pick themselves up, and when
we began to pick ourselves up,
something extraordinary
happened. In the process of
going through this crisis, we
were changed. I think it's our
heart was broken open, in a way,
there was some kind of deep
transformation. When the pain
became so terrible, we we began
to make choices that we weren't
willing to consider making. At
an earlier time of stability, in
such extreme instability, we
began to make different choices.
And when we were past the worst
of this crisis, there was a
tremendous kind of up surging of
new values, new insights, new
ways of being, new ways of
organizing. And if there were
one fundamental theme that
emerges, it is the theme of
oneness. We had an experience
deep in our psyche of oneness
that permeates all existence,
and that's a tremendous
spiritual revitalization. And
then subsequently, in other
sessions, I was taken deep into
deep time and given an
experience of what I came to
call the future human that that
is this is a change which is not
going to simply precipitate a
political restructuring or an
economic restructuring or a
social restructuring. It's a
change which is going to reach
so deeply into the collective
psyche that it actually causes
an evolutionary flip of the
archetype of the blueprint, or
the archetypal blueprint of the
human psyche, so that there is
literally a an emerging, an
emergence of A restructured core
around which our individual
lives crystallize in time. I
came and just to touch this
future human, to go into deep
time and just to touch it was
such a clarifying experience. It
was so gratifying, because this
magnificent humanity, with its
heart healed of all the pain
that we've caused each other
through time, and that has been
caused in us by nature, a
tremendous illumination of the
human mind. It was truly an
enlightened species that was
emerging out of this process.
And this has been this, I think,
gave the larger context for my
entire life and my understanding
of history that we are in right
now. It gave a context which
helped me understand why my
individual enlightenment fell
away as insignificant, and that
my sessions went for years
aiming at collective
transformation and trying to
support this collective
transformation wherever
possible. It did not give me any
timeline, as you said, it did
not give me any specifics. It
did not tell me when, where or
how, but the certainty and the
magnitude of this convulsion
seemed to be driven by some kind
of global ecological crisis that
triggered a global systemic
crisis, crisis of global
systems, which then I began
after I began to have these
experiences, I began to do my
ecological homework. I began to
read more widely in the
ecological literature, to pay
attention to the people who've
been tracking these things, and
I think it's clear, and I give
the references in the book, that
we are coming to a critical time
in human evolution. We are on
the verge of losing the planet
if we don't change our ways, and
we don't seem to be changing our
ways nearly fast enough to avoid
a crisis of unprecedented
proportions. So I had these
experiences, oh, 1985 to 1999
you know, 20 years ago, and it
seems that these are unfolding
now that we are entering
increasingly a time of
ecological plague, in a way, a
time of great, great ecological
uncertainty coming at us,
devastation coming at us in
global climate change. In this
context, I watch covid 19, and I
don't see it as the true crisis
of this. Era. It seems to be too
small a crisis, but it's a
serious crisis, and it's a
crisis that, if we respond to it
well, it could teach us many
things that we will need when
the deeper crises emerge, which
are coming in the decades ahead.
And I think, I think it is
teaching us, I mean it. There
are those who are learning from
it, and then those who are just
trying to quickly get back to
normal as quickly as possible.
But I think, I think normal
we're going to find is farther
and farther irretrievable. We
now have no choice but to go
into a new future and to find
our way into this new future.
And I think the divine, or
whatever you want to call the
intelligence of the universe,
the creative capacity of the
universe, is pulling us that
way. It supports us as we
cooperate with this crisis. It's
taking us somewhere that it
wants us to go,
Stephen Gray: beautiful, yeah,
yeah, yeah. I've the, I've, I've
kind of had the same intuition
about the covid situation. It's
kind of a fantasy. I suppose you
could say in my mind that that
you know the gods as it were,
whatever that is, as you say,
the divine there. I don't know
how this functions, of course,
and how hands on they would be
with our journey. But it I could
almost imagine that there that
the covid situation is kind of
like letting us down step by
step, like, here's what can
happen when there's a great
disruption. And as you say, You
know what? What kinds of changes
in our individual mentalities
and the way that we do things
collectively might come out of
this? And you know, of course,
that remains to be seen. But you
know, I have a feeling that at
the very least, you know the
whole world has been quieter and
cleaner for a while. And, you
know, even if people, I mean, I
could be completely wrong about
this, but I wonder if you know
that, even if people don't
really consciously, kind of pay
attention to, you know, the
implications of that, it's, it's
gotten in under their skin on
some level. You know, birds are
more audible. There may be more
of them around, you know, the
air is cleaner. The pace of life
has been slower. I'm seeing so
many people riding bicycles
around my neighborhood, you
know, I'm hoping that more of
them will, you know, many of
them will continue to ride those
bicycles. And people are jogging
like nothing, like nobody's
business around my neighborhood
lately. You know, they're going
to come, you know, when people
get back to their quote,
unquote, normal life, I think a
lot of people are going to find
that they've come back rested,
healthier. They've probably been
eating more at home, cooking
more at home. It's hard to find
yeast in the stores around
making east, you know, but at
the same time, you know, the way
you describe this great death,
you know, trajectory sounds
pretty frightening in a sense,
you know. And I guess to what
comes out to my mind, comes into
my mind about that is that it's
increasingly becoming more and
more important for anyone who
possibly can to be a rock, as it
were, for others. You know,
Chris Bache: yeah, it is
frightening. It really is
frightening. And I think It's
therefore important to really
understand what's happening. I
mean, there are a lot of people
who will be calling on the
apocalyptic End of Days and all
sorts of interpretations.
There'll be people be talking
about extinction and so on so
forth. But I think what's really
happening is that we are in
labor. This is a birth.
Gestation is a long process.
It's a nine month process, but
labor takes place with 24 hours.
It's a very short, very intense
process in which we give birth
to something new. I think
humanity has been gestating the
future human for 1000s and 1000s
of years, but the process of
giving birth to it is really
convulsive. And if you walked
into a room when there was a
woman giving labor right in the
middle of it, and she's yelling
and screaming and everyone's
running around, you would think,
Oh, this is terrible. She's
going to die. But if you know
what's happening, you know that
this is labor. This is what
labor is like. Well, we are
going into a collective labor, I
believe, and therefore it's
important for us to cultivate an
appreciation of what this
actually consists of. We are
giving birth to a new form of
human being, not simply better
in a few little ways, dressing
up the edges, but a deep
reconstruction of the human
psyche. Me, and the way I've
come to understand this is in
terms of the concept of the
diamond soul, which is a
different image, but basically
it refers to other sessions that
I went through where I
experienced what seemed to be I
was given a series of teachings,
experiential teachings, about
where reincarnation is taking
us, you know, and it led me to
have an understanding of
reincarnation which went
considerably beyond the way it's
been talked about in the
traditional Eastern sources.
Because I think basically the
idea in traditional thinking of
reincarnation, we reincarnate,
we reincarnate, we reincarnate.
Karma follows us. We make
improvements. We get a little
bit better and better. We go
from third grade to fourth grade
to fifth grade, hopefully more
compassion, more intelligent,
more resourceful, incremental,
incremental change. But I think
what happens eventually in the
reincarnation process, we die
and we go into spirit, where we
reconnect with soul, the
consciousness that holds all of
our experience. We're born, we
get small, we learn, we die, we
get large. We're born, we get
small. And we keep this up for
1000s and 1000s of years, only
touching our soul, our total
consciousness, usually in the
afterlife state, in the Bardo
state. But if this keeps up, all
of us has been going through
this for 1000s, 1000s of years,
sooner or later, there comes a
point where I think all what
happened in my sessions, all my
former lives, started coming in,
and they hit critical mass, they
and when they hit critical mass,
there was a massive explosion of
energy, and they fused. And when
they fuse, an extraordinary
diamond light broke out of my
chest, and it catapulted me into
a state of consciousness beyond
anything I had been in up to
that point. And it was a state
of consciousness in which I was
an individual, but I was an
individual beyond any frame of
reference that I had known it
previously. And I think what
that's what's happening with
reincarnation, that there comes
a time in history when all of
our former lives become
integrated. In the early stages,
when we integrate our former
lives, we often have to deal
with leftover pain and problems
that have been that are still
reside in these former lives. So
the emphasis is on healing and
clarifying, but eventually, when
they when all of that work is
done and they fuse into a new
singularity, and that
singularity, I think, is the
birth of the soul in time, so
that we permanently shift our
identity from the ego of this
small, short term body which
lives maybe 100 years to the
soul which lives and thinks and
feels on a much, much larger
time horizon. I think this birth
of soul consciousness inside
time is taking place
simultaneously Well, as the
planet is trying to come to
terms with its divisive history
and is trying to deal with
problems which it cannot solve
at the national level, but can
only solve at the global level,
As we're trying to come together
as one planet. Internally, the
players there are trying to come
together as one soul, so that
there is a reciprocity between
the the outer, political,
ecological dynamic in the inner,
psycho spiritual dynamic, so
that, I think the ego is the
psychological structure that
built this world, and the ego
will never be able to solve the
problems that we have generated.
It takes the expansion of the
soul to really have the depth of
courage and the depth of
compassion and the depth of
insight to really carry us into
the creation of the next stage
of our planetary evolution.
Stephen Gray: Yeah, beautifully
put again, yeah, yeah. My, my
sense of of this passage, I
guess you could say, is that it,
you know, it is scary, as we
were saying that it looks like a
lot of things that, you know,
people have been able to, you
know, hold as status quo and
stability are going to be ripped
away from us and so on and so
on. It's going to be a really
challenging time. I guess the
hopeful, or more optimistic part
of my my mind, adheres to this
old saying, necessity is the
mother of invention, and it
feels like, as we move out of
it's like we've been, you know,
as, you know, living in, you
know, in an illusion, in a
sense, you know, in a kind of a
collective and individual dream
that's virtual, that's based in
our thoughts and our you know,
it's in our heads and all that.
And you know, as Terence McKenna
has, and others have. It
whistling past the graveyard you
know, trying to ignore the you
know, the reality of ego death
and the spirit that you know,
encompasses all. But as we, as
these conditions destabilize, I
think perhaps one of the amazing
thing that's things that's going
to come out of this is, you
know, because there is such a
deep well of creativity and
capability in the human species,
I think we're going to see a lot
of that coming forth. You know
that, oh, that's another one of
my favorite sayings from Victor
Hugo, something to the effect
of, there's nothing as powerful
as an idea whose time has come,
right? Yeah, so I think we're
going to see, you know, as as
the old ways become less viable,
people can put less faith in
them, a greater openness to new
ideas.
Chris Bache: Yes, I think we're
experiencing this profound
polarization taking place now.
There will be forces pulling us
very strongly toward the past,
towards the divisions of the
past, towards the certainties of
the past, towards the patterns
of the past. And then there will
be forces taking us into the
future, taking us into something
less certain, more unexplored,
but, but I think the the juice
is going to be with the future,
because with the past, if we, if
we keep allow ourselves to be
pulled into the past and the
patterns of consumption and
corporate control and so on
violence and, you know, placing
one race over another, one
religion over another, one
continent over another that way
ends in death. It just ends in
death. But a different a future,
a collaborative future, working
for a world that works for all,
working, working where a certain
portion of the population has
less, so that everybody has more
is going to produce a much, much
happier, better existence for
all of us in the end. And I
think we have the courage to
make it. I think you know,
things like the coronavirus are
basically giving us an
opportunity to flex our courage,
to flex our wisdom and to say no
when we're being told lies by
people who represent the past,
people who represent, you know,
the faded wisdom of patriarchy,
the faded the you know The
unspeakable shame of ego, and we
see it dramatized on the body
politic today, you know, and
that just leaves a sour taste in
our mouth. Where, when we see
courage, when we see compassion,
when we see wisdom, insight,
working for our collective good,
that we recognize and say, Yes,
I want to be like that. I want
to support those forces.
Stephen Gray: Yeah, so again,
hopefully that, you know, as
Leonard Cohen put it, there's a
crack in everything. That's how
the light gets in, that the
light will be coming in. And,
you know, I read some of the
channeled books that were
popular back in the late 80s and
early 90s. And one guy that I
kind of liked more than others
was a guy named Ken Carey. He
had a book, a couple of books
called star seed, Millennium and
things like that. And one of the
things that, assuming this was
actually channeled, that his,
you know, ch, his source, his
entity, was saying, was, these
technologies that you have, you
know, these communication
technologies, they're actually
pretty interesting, because you
know when, when the information
gets to the point where you can,
you know, be sending out that,
you know, the idea whose time
has come. We now have this
capability of sharing
information instantly around the
planet, pretty much, right? It's
like a we have these stepping
stones, in a sense, now, right?
Chris Bache: Yeah, and, and I
think what I'm saying and what
I'm describing if, if it were
just me having these
experiences, and then it would
be maybe not that significant.
But a lot of people have been
having these experiences and
sharing these ideas. They've
been seeing the same thing. A
lot of psychedelic voyagers have
been seeing this basic vision of
a time of fundamental historical
crisis and choice. Indigenous
cultures have been seeing this
vision emerging for decades in
their work, mystics like and
contemplatives, meditators who
would never go near
psychedelics, have been having
this deepening insight that this
is a time of crisis, this is a
time of where we must grow up.
And I think that's one way of
looking. At it. This is a time
of maturation. We have to grow
up and to take responsibilities
as adults. And there's a certain
way in which we've been living
like adolescents, with the
qualities of adolescents, but
now we need to grow up, and I
think we have that capacity, and
I really think we will. I think
we're going to make this
transition, even though it's
going to get difficult, I just
have confidence in I think, when
I'm really feeling deeply
uncertain and fearful, I remind
myself that the universe has
brought us this far, and I know
that there are end roads, there
are extinction events that are
taking place all around us, but
I trust that if, if we are
entering into a time of such
momentous choice and
consequences, that we the
universe must think that we're
ready. And I think I will. So I
place my trust in the universe's
wisdom, and at least in my
sessions, the universe seems to
clearly think that we're ready,
in that it knows what it's
doing, and we will be able to
participate in that, knowing
Stephen Gray: well this is the
reason why I'm so happy that you
are my initial or inaugurative
guest On this hopefully
developing series, because that,
you know this one, it's, it's,
it's central to why I have such
respect for you and your work,
Chris, is that that it's
hopeful. It points out that
there, you know who we possibly
can be, and that there was a,
there is a way to get there,
right? You know, there is a
little bit like the Four Noble
Truths, you know that, that
there is a way to get there. You
know, there are pathways and
and, you know, and as we've been
talking about here, you know,
people need that kind of, you
know, encouragement, that kind
of, you know, vision to be
shared. You know, as things get,
you know, less stable for people
that they have less to less
ground to hang on to, so I think
this is probably a good time to
bring it to a close. We've been
talking for close to an hour,
and I'm clear that you could
have a lot more to say on these
topics, so we might have to do
it again. Actually, it just
occurred to me at this very
moment, because you're, you're,
I'll have to say you're an easy
interview, Chris, because I just
need to ask one question and
articulate it so so clearly and
so beautifully. I really
appreciate that I'm really moved
in my heart to, you know, to
hear these kinds of things that
you have experienced and that
you're sharing with people. So
this being my very first one, I
don't haven't figured out how to
end these yet. I know sometimes
people would, you know, say
goodbye to the guest and then
talk to the talk to the the
viewers a little bit, but I
think I'll just do that while
you're still here, if you don't
mind.
Chris Bache: So so before you do
that, and that's fine to do, but
first I want to thank you for
your initiative, because you've
been drawing people together in
the conferences that you've been
organizing for years now, and
your commitment to our
collective transformation has
been profound, and this
continues in this series, your
your your vision is for
collective awakening. And I just
honor that, and just want to
thank you for it.
Stephen Gray: Well, thanks so
much for saying that. And yeah,
that is the reason, you know, I
just feel really connected to
that vision. And you know, I
another one of my favorite
sayings is from Bishop Desmond
Tutu, the legendary South
African Bishop. And I don't,
don't remember the full
sentence, but it was something
to the effect that a lot of
people don't believe in the
possibility of possibility, and
that that's what we need, is you
have to believe in the
possibility of possibility. And
to my mind, you know the the ego
and whatever it is, can cook up
all kinds of stories about
what's going on, but there's
only one attitude that's
functional, and that is to
believe in the possibility of
possibility and do what you need
to do your own healing work and
participating whatever You can
do.
Unknown: Yeah. Yeah, yeah. I
think so, yeah.
Stephen Gray: So it's a
wonderful vision. It's a
wonderful prayer. And excuse me,
do you want to say anything? Is
there can people contact you? Or
is there anything to say about
that?
Chris Bache: Well, actually, I'm
embarrassed that I haven't
gotten my website finished yet.
I hopefully it will be up in a
month or so. It will be Chris
bache.com will be where people
will be able to find me online
right now. They can find me if
they go to my articles and
publications, if they go to
academia.edu and sign in. There,
they'll be able to find me under
Chris M Bache and everything
I've written, and many of the
podcasts are there, but Chris
bache.com soon will be where
people can reach me, and they
can also reach me at my
university website. My address,
C, M Bache, at y, s, u.edu
Stephen Gray: I should be able
to put little tabs up on the
screen at some point. Yeah, show
those for people, and in the
meantime, just so they know.
Well, I think maybe it's showing
on the screen. It does on mine
when I'm speaking and when
you're speaking. But it's
spelled B, A, ch, E, yes. It's
not necessarily an intuitive
spelling and pronunciation
match. Yeah, yeah. So again, the
book that we're talking about
more than any you know, he's got
other works, as I mentioned at
the beginning, is this one. It's
it's incredible. It's really
remarkable. And there's so much
more in this book that we didn't
cover today. So I hope people
will go and find this book. It's
going to be, it already is and
will continue to be part of this
kind of transformation that
we're talking about. So yeah, I
guess Thank
Chris Bache: you, Steven,
really. Thank you very much.
Thank you for the conversation.
Thank you for the opportunity to
bring these ideas forward to
your listeners,
Stephen Gray: and you do it so
well, Chris, really, you know, I
know you're humble about it, but
you know, I could listen to you
all day. You really have the you
know you're in you're doing the
right job. You know you've you
found your job, I think because
you explain it so, so clearly.
So again. Thank you very much.
And I'll just say, while you're
still here, because I haven't
like I say, I haven't figured
out quite you know, how I want
to end these things, I'll just
say that I'm hoping to be able
to put a little subscribe button
up on here, and I hope people
will subscribe to this YouTube
channel and share it and so on.
And it'll also be on Anchor,
which is an audio podcast, I
hope. Well, once I figure it
out, we'll strip the audio off
of the video and put it on
Anchor as well. So again, much,
much. Thanks. From the Heart,
Chris, take care.
Chris Bache: Bye, bye, my
friend. You. You.