Unknown: Foreign
Richard Rudd: welcome everyone
to a series of talks that I'm
doing here with my friend Chris
Bache, and we're going to be
discussing a subject that we're
both really interested in and
fascinated by, which is rebirth
and all the things that go along
with rebirth. Might also call it
reincarnation, because that's
part of the story. And this
began really because I read
Chris, a book by Chris, a
wonderful book called LSD and
the mind of the universe and and
what it did is it kind of just
triggered a real recognition in
me. And since I'm a teacher of
spiritual matters and I'm the
founder of a system called the
gene keys, that resonance that
went off in me, it caused me to
reach out via email to this
amazing man, and you never know
whether you're going to hear
back from in those instances.
And Chris, very kindly, got back
to me, and we started a series
of dialogs and discussions, and
we realized that we we really
enjoyed having dialogs together,
so that's why we're here, and
we're going to explore this
subject in several sessions. So
today we're going to just begin
with some introductory concepts
and basics and and then see
where it leaves us. So I hope
you enjoy it, and I'm very much
looking forward to it.
Chris Bache: So we're
anticipating three discussions
Richard Rudd: Absolutely. So
Chris, if you want to say a few
things about yourself, just so
that, yeah, people know who you
are.
Chris Bache: It's a pleasure to
be here, and I've enjoyed our
conversations that we've had
prior to this and this, our this
present dialog grew out of those
earlier conversations. I am a
Professor of Philosophy and
Religious Studies. I'm on the
religious studies side of the
shop. I'm retired from
Youngstown State University. In
the course of my teaching, I've
taught courses on world
religions and Eastern religions
and Transpersonal psychology of
religion and comparative
mysticism, Buddhism. So I've
been teaching in areas touching
on reincarnation for many years.
I've written several books. My
first one was on reincarnation,
starting with the scientific
evidence for reincarnation,
which we'll be touching on
today, and it's been seminal in
my thinking. And I just believe
that reincarnation is one of
those concepts that is like
plate tectonics. If you at first
it's hard to see because it's
not obvious, but once you see
it, it changes everything. It
changes so much, it opens up the
horizon of existence. So we
thought this would be a good
topic to have a shared
conversation about. And I'm just
a real pleased to be here.
Great.
Richard Rudd: Thanks, Chris. And
I mean, we'll put the link in
afterwards, but there's some
great things talks that you've
done, and particularly one which
I watched fairly recently about
is there evidence for
reincarnation, and it's so
illuminating and extraordinary
and kind of overlooked by so
many people. Tell us some of the
you know your story, in
assembling and amassing that
some of that evidence or meeting
the other people that have,
Chris Bache: well, you know, I
came from a traditional
religious background, but over
the course of many years of
graduate education, I finished
My doctoral work in philosophy
of religion as an atheistically
inclined agnostic. And basically
I had studied my way out of
religion altogether. So I
started my academic career as a
young man a long time ago, in
1978 and I met there the work of
two people in my first year, and
both of them changed the course
of my life. The first was Ian
Stevenson, the Carlson professor
at the University of Virginia,
whose lifelong work has been to
provide carefully documented
cases that clearly of young
children, small children, who
have spontaneous memories of
their previous life, and then
researching these children from
all over the world, collecting
1000s of cases, publishing
hundreds of cases, and he
convinced me that reincarnation
was a simple fact of life.
Richard Rudd: Well, that's quite
a book, isn't it? That's a big
book he's written.
Chris Bache: The book he's
written about, oh, I think close
to a dozen now, but this first
one was called 20 cases
suggestive of reincarnation.
Reincarnation, and to me, it was
a life pivot, because
reincarnation was never
discussed in my graduate
education. It was never
discussed in the Western
religions or in the scientific
tradition that had kind of wiped
the slate clean for of the
religious traditions. So I just
erased my Blackboard and began
to rethink again, the larger
questions of life, incorporating
reincarnation. The second person
I met at that time was Stanislav
Grof, who is the foremost
authority on integrating
psychedelics into psychotherapy,
and he was providing a
methodology that actually allows
one to explore the deeper
dimensions of one's own
consciousness. So that began a
whole nother journey, a second
journey, which culminated
eventually in the publication of
this book. Richard mentioned LSD
in the mind of the universe. But
today, the focus here is on Ian
Stevenson's what he started in
the revolution of really
providing carefully documented
evidence that reincarnation is
just simply a fact of life. It's
not a religious thing. It's not
it's simply a natural phenomenon
that's happening in the world.
Richard Rudd: And in your talk
you gave again, which will the
link will be? Here it was, is
you know, you as a wonderful you
know, years spent as an
academic, you kind of argue both
sides, so you show how you know
different people have come in
and and even written books to
refute those things, but how
they've fallen short. And so
there's this, there's this whole
story around it. And there's
this, this growing body of
evidence that maybe in the last
50 years has been documented as
I mean, it's fairly recent,
isn't it?
Chris Bache: It is recent. 50
years ago, we didn't have this
evidence. It was still
reincarnation. Was a speculative
topic that the theologians
argued back and forth on. But
now it's moved from the
theologians table to the
psychologist table. And now, as
we explore more deeply the
deeper levels of consciousness
in the depth psychology
tradition, we just find we're
bumping into this evidence over
and over again. Now the Western
philosophical tradition, of
course, is kind of still
saturated with the metaphysical
position of naturalism, which
says, The only thing which is
real is that which is physical.
So therefore the brain produces
your mind. So obviously, in that
system, once your brain dies,
your mind, this ceases to exist.
So it's impossible for there to
be something like reincarnation,
because it implies a dimension
of reality that's behind the
physical world, if you exist
there for any if consciousness
can exist there for any interval
of time between the death of one
personality and the birth of a
second personality. So
naturally, there's been a real
pushback from philosophical
traditions in the West, mostly,
they've just ignored the
evidence. They don't look at it,
and even those who look at it
and engage it, the foremost
critic that I mentioned in my
talk was a man named Paul
Edwards, a substantial American
philosopher, even in his work,
the evidence really a careful,
dispassionate analysis of the
debate between Ian Stevenson on
the one hand and Paul Edwards on
the other hand is that he just
refuses to look seriously at the
evidence because he's convinced
beforehand that the evidence
must be somehow faulty, because
We know that reincarnation can't
happen,
Richard Rudd: of course, and
that's often the way with
academics sometimes, isn't it?
Yeah, and what you know, a great
you know? So that's like, that's
really interesting in itself,
just the evidence. And I don't
think we need to kind of go any
more into that now, but it's
like, what are, I guess, you
know that. What are the
implications? You know, if we
do, because I this year, I've
done a series of videos myself,
short ones, just exploring the
implications of, what if I say
yes to this concept and I
explore it in, you know, if I
open my mind and my heart to it,
and I begin to really deeply
explore it? You know that the
the the implications, to our
worldview and the way we move
through life is huge, isn't it?
Chris Bache: Yeah, it all hinges
on time, how much time we have,
because, if you have a sense of,
Well, let me back up. I'm a
professor, right? So if I give a
quiz in class, I can expect a
certain quality of an answer
back. If I give an exam that
takes an hour, I expect a higher
quality of response. And if it's
a take home research paper, I
have higher expectations still,
because they have more time. So
for. Philosophically, if we
believe we only live on earth
one time, and we only have, in
some cases, a few minutes to as
many as 100 years, and we
extrapolate from that if there
is a purpose to existence, that
purpose must be proportionate to
the amount of time we have to
fulfill that purpose. But if we
have 100 lifetimes, 1000
lifetimes in which to actualize
the purpose of the universe,
then I think it expands
exponentially our potential
assessment of what the purpose
of existence might be. So that's
why it's such an important
philosophical discussion,
because once you understand the
dynamics of reincarnation, once
you grasp the fundamental
principle, then it lifts the
constriction of time, and it
allows us to begin to think in
terms of and appreciate and
understand the larger patterns
of the pulse of cause and
effect, over arching over
centuries of time, and it just
elevates the whole discussion
Richard Rudd: Absolutely. And I
think, like, you know, if I can
be blunt, like if you if you
have an inherent sense of a
divinity behind creation, then
it seems logical to extend that
into, if you know that this
concept of generosity, because,
if you had a divinity and you
only have one life, it's very
stingy. It seems like it doesn't
seem to have any kind of pattern
or reason to it. You know, it's
like I, for me, life is is just,
you know, spirit is just filled
with generosity and in terms of
time and and if we, and if we
kind of open to the eternal
nature of life, then of then, of
course, that would make sense,
you know, for there to be a
continuity of consciousness. And
I think that, you know, the more
people open to this, the more
they kind of realize it has some
deep root inside them, you know.
And I've, I've, you know, I
discovered that a lot because
I've begun to talk about it more
and more. And one of the things
I realized is no one else is
really much other than people
who doing past life regression.
Therapeutically, a lot of the
teachers and spiritual teachers
in the world today avoid this
subject. They, I mean, I don't
know if they consciously avoid
it, but they don't talk about
it. I mean, they get asked
questions, but then their
answers are kind of generally
quite short, and it doesn't get
picked up. And so, yeah, I'm,
I'm really interested in
something that is passed over,
that is so in, so obvious, and
it's, it should be in plain view
for all of us. Yeah, yeah. So,
yeah,
Chris Bache: isn't that curious?
I mean, I understand why my
colleagues at the University,
who tend to be, you know,
materialist and reductionist,
why I understand, but why
spiritual teachers wouldn't talk
about about it, or wouldn't use
it to sort of frame a larger and
expanded horizon. You know,
sometimes I've heard people say,
well, it can dilute your
intensity of commitments for
realization in the present. But
you know, if you think you have
many lifetimes and you're not
going to take this lifetime as
seriously, but I think that that
argument kind of evaporates
quickly once you look at it
carefully, yeah, I think it
deepens the textures of the
situations which we find
ourselves in. Let me just give
you one example, some of the
research of Michael Newton's
research, for example, in his
book journeys of the soul and
destiny of Souls, He and other
past life therapists have found
evidence that we choose our
incarnation. Now, I think in
some ways, many people don't.
They may kind of go very
haphazardly and take what's
available. But as you get
mature, you choose your
incarnation carefully. Now, if
we choose our care information,
our incarnation carefully, when
there was a time when we knew
more than we know now and we
could see more than we could see
now, if we chose the life that
we're living now, with all of
its ups and downs and challenges
and opportunities, then doesn't
that change how we might relate
to those very circumstances in
which we find ourselves, you
know, not to go chasing all
sorts of hidden mission, You
know, hidden meanings, but to
basically temper the quality of
how of the self responsibility
that we use in how we engage the
people that we're with, the
circumstances that we find
ourselves in.
Richard Rudd: Yeah, and doesn't
it make you also I mean, for me,
it makes me feel more. Like a
kind of eternal, cosmic
adventurer. So I, you know, it
enriches this time I'm in now,
it actually in where, in many
ways, it focuses me a lot more
into the present, because I'm
not worrying about dying, if you
know what I mean, it changes
that. And it's not just a
concept, you know, you have to
go, you know, this is my
understanding through my
teachings, is you have to
contemplate something very
deeply like this for it to start
to kind of take root in you, and
then as it takes root in you, it
brings out of your literally, I
feel it's the truth of it is in
our DNA. It's like it's, it's in
us. So once that gets triggered,
that kind of awakening of the
memory, it there's a sort of
certainty and a stability that
grows inside us that enables us
to handle whatever challenges
come to us in a really, much
more powerful way, because we're
rooted in this kind of eternal
acceptance of this, you know,
this is because you hear, I you
hear it all the time on people
on the radio, is I heard last
week, like someone just saying,
Well, yeah, you've only got one
life, so you've got to, you
know, really make the most of
it, which is a great thing to
say, but it's also you only got
one life. It's just, I keep
coming back to the it's that's
really a tight kind of reality
from which ever belief system
you're operating out of, yeah,
cuts the
Chris Bache: legs right out from
under you. Yeah? Because it just
because of correlating with that
is the usually, the ideas of
your exist in the universe is
being driven by blind chance.
It's just random mutation.
There's no existential
significance to the
circumstances in which you find
yourself in. So you only get one
shot make the best of it. But
then when you die, it's gone.
You're gone anyway, so who
cares? And that's just such a
demeaning and counter intuitive
philosophy of life. Because I
think when we look at the
beauties of nature, when we look
at the night sky, when we see
the pictures from the Hubble
telescope of the magnificent
patterns in the deep cosmos.
When we look around us at Earth
and look at the depth of the
emergence of life and the
emergence of self awareness on
the planet over time, all these
projects take place over
enormous sweeps of time, and we,
we are the first generation to
really appreciate how much time
the universe has had to be
evolving into the form that it
is now. If the universe and
everything it's doing takes
enormous amounts of time and we
only have one life, then
existentially, we're cut off.
We're not we don't participate
in that, in that massive
project. But if we do purchase,
if we live multiple lifetimes,
there's a good news bad news
situation. You know, the bad
news is, you know, well, it's
hard work in this lifetime, and
we'd like to have it over with
when we die, but if we keep
coming back, you know, there's a
larger project afoot. You know,
it's not a simple grade like we
thought it was before. It's a
whole university education. The
good news is, you're right, it
drops away. The fear of death
drops away. I mean, it just
drops away. The good news is, it
allows us to envision a deeper,
to feel, into the deeper
currents of life and the deeper
projects, and it allows us begin
to think in terms of longer term
projects. And I think this is
one of the things you see when
people take to heart this idea,
even without specific knowledge
of their former lives. I mean,
that's interesting, and that can
be helpful. But even without
that, when you really let that
in, and you look around you and
you realize that every person
you're seeing has been here
before and will be here again.
It just allows you to engage
life with so much more meaning
and intensity of the process
that you know, what we are good
at are things we have practice
in the past, things that we are
just getting started on, are
things we'll get better at in
the future. And we can think we
have that much time, we can
think in terms of that larger
landscape.
Richard Rudd: Yeah, and of
course, you know, we're not, you
know, there are many there.
There are many great thinkers
and philosophers and sages who
have come to the same conclusion
about rebirth, and, you know,
notably among them in the
western because of, you know, we
can talk a little bit about the
Eastern views in the east, yeah.
But Jung is someone who
obviously. Springs like straight
up into this, into the center
frame, because he's a bit more
contemporary. And, you know,
he's been this pillar of modern
psychology in the way in which
we now understand the
unconscious and and, yeah, and
the collective unconscious, and
mythology and all these other
transformational kind of
consciousness tended to
Chris Bache: hide his belief in
reincarnation, you know, he came
to it kind of late in life, and
he began to hide it because he
had pushed the boundaries so
much he was concerned about the
backlash. But there in his work,
and I
Richard Rudd: think that's what
happens with a lot of people, I
think they go, Well, I'm not
sure I want to go into that area
because it's, it's got a stigma
attached to it, yeah, and it
really has, isn't it? Because
the moment you say the word
reincarnation, you've got, like,
there's a whole kind of battery
of of skeptics coming at you,
whether they're coming from
Christianity or whether they're
coming from, you know,
materialist science. You know,
it's like you're really put your
head above the parapet,
Chris Bache: yeah, you know, for
years, for decades, I was taking
students into the literature on
reincarnation, and it's like you
just once, you put all that
aside, and you just look at the
cases. You just look at the
evidence. I mean, I found 95% of
my students were able to
overcome all kinds of
resistances, both secular and
religious resistances, because
they're trained in our culture
to follow the evidence once they
saw the evidence and how
consistent it was and how it
appeared in so many contexts,
spontaneous memories evoked
memories. They just they
accepted it. Once they accepted
it, it was a it was a life
changing event. And many of
their
Richard Rudd: lives, every
favorite stories that you
remember, of those, those
recurrences, because it's
Chris Bache: not I have so many.
And the one I opened the store,
the book with life cycles, the
one I started in the opening
pages, is a case of a young girl
named Romy Creese. And Romi was
born to Catholic parents in
Iowa. So it's like, it's okay if
they want to reincarnate in
India. That's their business.
But everybody knows Ian
Catholics do not reincarnate.
But she had spontaneous memories
of having been a man, Joe
Williams in a previous life. She
remembers being married. She
remembers three children, having
three children and their names.
She remembered dying in a
motorcycle accident, and she had
a phobia of motorcycles and long
story short, the researchers got
to her eventually, and brought
her to the town where she had
remembered living as Joe
Williams, and she was able to
remember identify the mother of
Joe Williams, she insisted that
they Pick up blue flowers on the
way to the house, because she
said those are the flowers that
she likes. And that turned out
to be true. She was able to
identify from pictures who the
people were in Joe Williams
life, the players of their life.
And she developed this deep
emotional bond to Joe Williams,
mother, who was alive, and his
wife named Sheila. He had been
married. She had been married to
Joe. Had been married to Sheila.
They were did have three
children. Sheila and Joe were
killed in a motorcycle accident.
So this is goes on and on and
on.
Richard Rudd: Hundreds of these
days, there's so many of them.
Yeah, so
Chris Bache: many these children
remember very intimate details
of family history. They remember
the they know the architecture
inside homes that they've never
been in. They can walk around a
town that they've never been in,
and they know their way around.
They remember the personalities
from the previous person,
person's life, and they remember
arguments that they had had with
neighbors, incidents that came
up in like the time a child and
they're when they were having a
birthday party for their child
that a neighbor's dog bit one of
the children in the party. I
mean, very, very things that are
just don't make the public news
and just
Richard Rudd: no little details.
It's the little details, isn't
it? There's one I've read I
loved. I can't remember exactly,
but I remember a reincarnated
memory of in a Muslim family and
and they took the little girl,
or think it was a little girl
into the family, and the women
were there, veiled, completely
veiled. And she identified from
from looking at them, from
seeing their body language,
without seeing their faces, at
anything she could name them and
and that was like, wow. That's
how deep this kind of detail
goes. Yeah, yeah, it's, it's fun
to explore those things. And I,
you know, I recommend to people
that you just take a look at
some of the evidence, because
it's very, I find it very
affirming, you know, sort of
like it's difficult to refute
that level of detail. And I
don't know you can come up with,
I'm sure good cynic can come up
with all kinds of Well,
Chris Bache: here's one for the
cynics. This. This is one of Ian
Stevenson's cases. They brought
this boy back into the life
circumstances of the previous
personality, and the wife of the
previous personality said, Okay,
if you're my husband, where did
you put the will? We after you
died, we looked all over for the
will. We couldn't find it. Yeah,
the little boy walks over to a
floorboard in the kitchen, picks
up a board, reaches down and
underneath the floor and pulls
up the will. Wow, isn't that
something? Yeah, it's how many
of those cases do you read
before you begin to understand
this is just happening. It's
just part of the rhythm of life.
Richard Rudd: Totally, it is
extraordinary. And also it has,
you know, there's, there's a
whole load of documentation
about marks on the body, isn't
there? You know, marks on the
body that relate to previous
events or, you know, I don't
think we need to go down that
route, but it's, it's, it's
another whole area of
documentation that
Chris Bache: was Steve Ian
Stevenson, his last work. And if
you do want to go down that
area, you can read his two
volume, 1000 page book on
reincarnation and biology, which
he studies, 187 cases with
medical documentation, really
rigorous, rigorous, very, very
rigorous. And what we find is
that the death wounds, wounds
associated with death in the
previous personality show up as
birthmarks are scars in the
subsequent personality. So this
is suggesting, not only do our
does our mind influence
subsequent mind, but even our
body, our mind's experience in
the body can influence the
formation of tissue in our
subsequent body. And that, of
course, just deepens the story
Richard Rudd: Absolutely. And
that's why I wanted to bring it
up, because that's what leads
into the therapeutic work,
doesn't it? Because if you open
to this idea, then, I mean, I'm
just thinking of all the people
out there who have difficulties,
maybe in their health or maybe
in their relationships, or maybe
addictions, or, you know,
whatever we're facing in life,
or just things that you know
that they they've complexes that
they find really hard to
overcome, yeah, and if we
understand that those things may
have a root in a previous
lifetime, and that that was
something unfinished or
incomplete, then It can open up
a whole therapeutic journey for
us. And that's what this this
whole therapeutic community has
has evolved out of this
Chris Bache: past life therapy
community. Basically, there are
any number of therapists who've
said something to the effect of
this, if you put someone into a
relaxed, inward, focused state,
a hypnotic state, but people
have a lot of misunderstandings
of what hypnosis, but it just
relax inward focused state, and
you invite them to go to the
source of the problem that
you're they've come to therapy
to address about 35 40% of them
will go back to something in
their present life. It'll come
back to something that happened
in their childhood or something
in their in their infancy, but a
significant 50, 60% of people
will go back to something that's
rooted in a previous lifetime,
and when they consciously
remember that previous lifetime,
and they consciously
reappropriate the trauma that
they weren't able to fully
internalize and address in that
lifetime, particularly death,
circumstances surrounding their
death, when they are able to
consciously remember and
assimilate it into their present
consciousness, then consistently
over and over again, underlying
psychological problems and even
physical problems begin to
loosen their grip on us and
untie the knots. So because
Richard Rudd: a greater depth,
because they have these roots
deep in the collective
unconscious, you know, and we're
going into the collective
unconscious to find them and
pull them out. Or, you know,
that's
Chris Bache: well, let's be a
little careful here, because
collective unconscious, in a
Jungian kind of usage, refers to
the unconscious of the entire
species. But so let's maybe call
a soul consciousness, which is
the collective unconscious of
the individual. You all through
time,
Richard Rudd: I got a good, a
good question for you, which is,
I have a really dear friend, and
he is a a kind of startling
intellect. He's in his late 70s
now, and really, really
intelligent, very spiritual man,
and yet he has a difficulty with
reincarnation, and we have
wonderful discussions around it
in the past. And his kind of his
very sophisticated spiritual
intellect, you know, where it
goes is in and I think others
may come from this direction as
well. That's why I'm saying it
is that you know you really
want, you know you want to
believe it. Everyone wants to
believe in the continuity of our
existence. And yet you know the,
you know, the the great Advaita
teachers, or whatever, that you
know that they would talk about
the surrender of the individual
ego, into the higher, you know,
into the back, into the ocean of
being, and that that's something
that you have to undergo in
order to attain liberation. And
so there is this, there is this
very strong spiritual kind of, I
think we, you know, we've
referred to it as up and out
kind of cosmology where you know
that we are here to escape this,
this cycle, the samsaric cycle,
and that, you know, so that we
can attain this liberation. And
we may attain it within this
lifetime, in a body, or we may
attain it, you know, afterwards.
So that's another whole kind of
interesting area, isn't it?
Chris Bache: Yeah, simply
because there are cultures who
have believed in reincarnation
for 1000s of years and have
developed a certain
understanding of it in their
culture doesn't mean that
they've got it right. And I
think that reincarnation is one
of those ideas that simply, once
we begin to see the evidence,
then it begins to deepen a line
of inquiry, which, for me,
personally, I think, is I've
revised dramatically the
understanding I had of
reincarnation borrowed from
Eastern traditions, Eastern
cultures. And one of the
traditions has to do with this
larger question, Where does
reincarnation go? Where is it
taking us? What is the what's
the end game of reincarnation?
And you're right, all the
cultures, all the religions of
the Axial Age, it came into
existence three to 5000 years
ago, all of them teach a
cosmological journey, that's an
up and out cosmology. So there
is a sense that we're trapped
here. This is not as good as
spiritual reality. We want to
develop, either in one lifetime,
if it's a Christian salvation,
salvation by grace, you know, or
multiple lifetimes to achieve
Samsara, excuse me, achieve
moksha, which is escape from
Samsara, escape from the
physical world. We achieve some
type of enlightenment condition,
which is the passport that
allows us to leave and not come
back. And all of these
traditions are up are basically
about escape. And that leaves
unanswered the fundamental
question, what is the purpose of
physical existence in the first
place? And now that we have a
deeper understanding of how many
billions of years of genius have
gone into the manifestation of
the physical world, it's not a
very satisfactory conclusion to
think that just within we only
became conscious of this deeper
dimensions about 5000 years ago,
as soon as we become self
conscious of the level of
consciousness, which we share
with all other beings and all
existence, as soon as we become
aware of That and can live our
life from that center, then the
purpose of existence is to
escape the entire physical
world. And I don't think that's
really
Richard Rudd: true, and it's
rooted in that kind of slightly
self denial philosophy, isn't
it? That you know that also is
many 1000s of years
Chris Bache: old. Yeah, I think
they're basically all the axial
religions got two things
fundamentally wrong. They got
many things right, but they got
two things wrong. They got
nature wrong. They don't really
have an adequate theology or
understanding of nature, and
they got women wrong. And the
two are connected, because women
are so closely connected to
nature, and they're
patriarchally oriented, and
they're escapist oriented. And I
think it makes as an historian,
I understand it. I think about
four or 5000 years ago, through
various psycho. Technologies,
either yoga or meditation or
psychedelic substances, we began
to have a deeper experience of
the mother universe, of this
universe that surrounds the
physical universe. Once you have
experiential contact with that
universe, it is so blissful, it
is so ecstatic, soaked that you
cannot help, and you recognize
that that's where we're from,
you cannot help believe that
that's where we belong. This is
not where we belong, that's
where we belong. Yeah, and they
develop a theology of return. So
they're the Savior comes to take
us home, the enlightened being
comes to liberate us back into
our home. But that still leaves
the question, what is the
purpose of creation? And I think
what we're beginning to
understand now, as our
experience of this mother
universe is deepened over time,
and our understanding of the
physical universe has deepened
over time, is that we're not
here to achieve escape velocity
and leave we're here to
incarnate more and more and more
of spiritual reality and
capacity inside our physical
being, so that we can truly live
and create heaven on earth, to
wake up and stay Yeah. I mean,
not just to wake up as an
individual, but to wake up as an
entire species and stay,
Richard Rudd: yeah, now that you
can't leave that. I mean, we're
going to discuss that more,
aren't we? We're going to come
back to that. But that's a huge
that's a huge window to open up.
It's this, you know, and you've
touched on a lot of themes
there, particularly, you know,
the thing about the feminine
that you know, the the the
physical, the physical body, you
know, like, that's what I think
I interpret, partly what you're
saying as well, is that those
religions didn't really
understand the physical body, as
you said, nature didn't value
because there's, you know,
there's vast beauty in this
physicality, and it's, you know,
perhaps what we're exploring is,
perhaps it's here to be
spiritualized. Perhaps it's here
to it's you know. Perhaps that's
why we're here to bring that
ecstatic realization deeper and
deeper and deeper into the form,
because then we're, you know, if
we see that that's our highest
purpose, we no longer want to
leave you know, because that's
then our role is, through
subsequent incarnations, to
bring more and more of that
light down into the earth, into
you know, to you know. And then
we're also taking full
responsibility for the body and
the earth, you know, which is
something we also haven't done
very well. Yeah, yeah,
absolutely.
Chris Bache: And if that sounds
at first disappointing, where we
would say, Oh no, I want heaven,
please. Thank you very much. I
don't want a transformed body
here, because here is still too
difficult. I think we may be
underestimating how what we may
be underestimating what is
possible and just what it would
really feel like to live a
truly, fully spiritualized,
enlightened existence. And here,
I think we can look at some of
the god soaked masters of
history who are truly living in
the god soaked condition, or
the, you know, a primordial
condition that is radically open
to the vast mind of the
universe, inside their body,
inside time and space. And what
we're seeing from these
mahasiddhas, these great beings,
is that they can do what we
would call miracles, because
there is so much spiritual power
concentrated in their presence
that it is as if the laws of
nature operate differently
around them, and they're showing
us a prototype of what each of
us is in the process of
becoming, yeah, no. And
therefore, if we imagine what it
would be like to have an entire
species kind of living in that
kind of presence, and what
Richard Rudd: and our physics is
is also pushing us in that
direction, isn't it, to the
understandings that we're
entangled with nature, with the
universe, and that you know
that, and my whole teaching is
based on this notion that in our
in our DNA, are contained these,
these sleeping, dormant codes,
these cities, these, as I call
them, 64 cities. And like you're
talking about that they are
they're an activation inside us
that's that is waiting for its
moment so that we can enter more
fully into the next phase of our
evolution, the magical universe,
the quantum universe, you know,
where our thoughts and our
feelings and our sensations are.
Are actually traveling kind of
outside our physical body. You
know, they're entangled with
nature. So nature then responds
with us to us, which perhaps it
already does, at a level that
we're not aware of. So it's just
about opening up those pathways.
You know, there's literal
pathways in our being, into
that, into that next phase of
our evolution.
Chris Bache: We are already
plugged into nature at very,
very deep levels, down to the
quantum level, in the unified
field, we're plugged into our
ecosystems and these subtle,
intimate feedbacks, and we're
plugged into each other. Our
minds wash back and forth, we're
already there. But when we can
become conscious of those
connections, when we can sort of
lift off the obstructive shadows
that are carry overs from other
sadder times, then that
connection becomes, begins to
rise, and it empowers a
conscious participation, and it
makes what was unconscious
conscious, and then existence
becomes more enlivened, I think,
and enlightened with the
synchronicities that sort of
indicate the broader
intelligence that's, You know,
that's alive in life around us?
Richard Rudd: Yeah, yeah, I and
I'm sure that, you know, I'd
love it if we could bring our
conversation also into, sort of
into people's lives, a little
bit, so that they can consider
their relationships and, you
know, from this perspective, and
how that might change one's
attitudes or views towards
difficult relationships or
towards, you know, what? You
know, what's the afflictions
that come up in us and that we
have to handle in our everyday
life? It really changes all of
that, doesn't it? Because, you
know, then you look at life, and
it's actually a process of the
opening of the heart, you know,
which the teachers have always
said it's like every
relationship, its purpose is to
show us some grace. And I call
this this law of unseen grace.
You know, where every
relationship that shows up is
offering us some, you know,
particularly the difficult ones,
is offering us some incredible
teaching, some, some virtue that
we haven't yet polished. You
know, whether it's forgiveness
or whether it's you know, some
you know, clarity, or whether
it's you know, whatever it is,
it's just, it's, it's some form
of love that we are here to
learn from those relationships,
because they have. They come as
part of our teaching karma, you
know. So I always see like that,
you know, the ancients called it
this life a Leela. And I always
see these a game, a drama
theater. And it's almost like,
before you come in, you're given
this little envelope, and in
there you open up the envelope,
and in there is like, Okay,
here's your script here, and
here are the, you know, and
there's going to be some things
that show up. And these are the
things you're going to learn
this, you know, you've chosen it
at some level. And so that
changes the way that we kind of
see behave, doesn't it? Yeah, I
think statics, I'm sure, like,
if you had personal experience
of that in your in your life, in
your emotional life, I mean,
that's
Chris Bache: Yeah, and it one
little one more step. It's not
simply the envelope that was
given you, but you were given
three envelopes, and you chose
the one that you felt was most
suited for your evolution at
this particular point in
history. And so it's your choice
to engage these challenges. And
yeah, and when we engage our
life in that way, as taking full
responsibility for the
circumstances in which we find
ourselves. In it. It allows us
to engage the challenges with
more patience and with more
dedication and with more of the
long term, because we know we're
not if this is something that,
if we don't deal with it now,
it's not going to go away, it's
just going to come back in
another form. So let's get it
done now. Let's let's deal with
it now. And it also allows you
to build on things. Because I
think our understanding of
reincarnation is being very
informed by the therapist
working heroically in past life
therapy. But if you only pay
attention to those cases, it can
tend to create an understanding
of reincarnation that is tilted
towards failures, coming
forward, that we traumas,
traumas, yeah, but it, but just
like the school system around us
has many faults, but most of the
kids learn and most of the kids
pass. Every year. And I think
most people rise to the karma,
the challenge of their of their
life. And that means every
lifetime, we're not simply
dealing with leftover issues
from the past. We're building on
assets. We're spending assets
and investing in greater
fruition in the future. And so
it's it helps us handle the
challenging circumstances, but
it also helps us embrace the
positive circumstances of our
life, the hidden talent which
comes forward unannounced, the
partnership which emerges that
we can we feel such a deep
kinship with this person that we
can go forward and do something
new with Yeah,
Richard Rudd: and I, you kind of
triggered a memory of mine about
from Sri Aurobindo, you know,
who spoke incredibly Clearly,
you know, with his penetrating
mind about the complexity of
karma and how we, you know,
because we need to sort of
probably discuss karma a little
bit and how it, you know, we
misunderstand it so easily by by
trying to oversimplify it. And
actually, you know, when you
look at the universe with all
its multiple dimensions, and,
you know, the quantum field. And
there's this, there's this,
these force fields operating at
different levels, but there's
this karmic force that's that's
equalizing and balancing, you
know, or that has a tendency
towards balance, we could say,
and is in allowing us to go
through this educational
process. But everything at
different levels is is
influenced by these, these
strands of the karmic force. And
that karmic force seems to have,
it's like this, the idea I said
about unseen grace. If you are
able to fully embrace it in your
life. Then you get the grace
through going through through
unwrapping it and but you've got
to kind of have the courage to
face it fully and really take it
in and let it in. You know,
whatever the suffering is,
transform it, transmute it so it
doesn't. Transmutation of karma
play a huge part in this
reincarnative theology.
Chris Bache: If we just look
around us, it's the web of cause
and effect. Everything is cause
and effect. We live in a
continuous web of cause and
effect, the air we breathe, the
weather patterns, our biology,
what we ate, the purity of what
we ate everything is this flow
of cause and effect the
universe, the movement of the
planets, the solar system. We
live in a continuous web of
cause and effect, and here we're
simply focusing on that portion
of the web of cause and effect
which influences the human the
development of the soul
influences our human
psychophysical development,
which is a subset with the of
this much larger cause and
effect. And in that context, I
think we've had a tendency, I
think, to narrow our discussion
of karma. Usually, many of the
teachers will talk about karma,
and they're only talking about
that portion of the karma which
immediately impinges upon our
spiritual maturity, whether
we're making progress becoming a
more spiritually mature person.
But a lot of karma, probably the
bulk of karma, is just a moral
cause and effect. You have a
habit. You practice something,
it becomes a skill. That skill
carries over into another life.
You have an automobile accident,
you develop a trauma of a
particular circumstance that
carries over into another life.
It's not necessarily about your
spiritual development, it's just
cause and effect,
circumstantial. Yeah, and so
when, as you open up to the
conditioning that's kind of
etching itself in your life, and
you lift it out, you engage it.
Lift it out, then that the
wellspring of your life becomes
freer. It becomes clear. And
you're, you're not ex you're not
stepping out of the web of cause
and effect, but you're you're
stepping into a greater freedom
within the web work of cause and
effect that surrounds you. You
have greater capacity to make
increasingly free choices,
greater capacity to choose. Ask
yourself, well, what do I want?
What would I like have, instead
of a compulsion of, you know,
grabbing, you
Richard Rudd: know, you know,
it's tempting, isn't it, for
some people to kind of say,
well, karma and reincarnation,
you know. And then there's this
story of like, well, that person
over there was born disabled.
Does that mean they've done
something terrible in their last
life? And and there's that
whole. Be a sort of
oversimplification over very
complex kind of arena where you
know we don't, unless you can
plug right into the soul quality
inside that person, inside that
being you don't really know, you
know what you know they could be
that hidden saint that has
deliberately taken on that
incredibly challenging role to
polish one particular virtue you
know or skill you know, like
over, over the period of one
lifetime, and equally, I guess,
like very short incarnations
that I don't think you and I
talked about those, But I'd love
to hear what you, you know, like
a child that comes in for a very
short time and then leaves, that
also has implications for the
healing of the whole doesn't it?
Because Why does a child come in
for a short time, or a baby is
born very, you know, for a very
short period of time, and then
there's leaves, this grief
behind it, but then there's this
feeling that it's also still
part of your life, yeah, yes,
explore that. I mean, we
haven't. We can go and talk
about that, yeah, yeah.
Chris Bache: You know, it's you.
We can recognize the principle
of cause and effect. We can
recognize the principle of
karma, vipaka, cause and effect.
But then we can get so many
teachers, I think sometimes get
or all of us. We think we can
determine cause and effect. We
think we can understand it when
really, we're just touching the
wrapping, on the park, on the
package, we're just really
touching the surface. And the
safest position, I think,
really, is recognize that we're
looking at a deep, deep mystery
here, and you're it would be
foolish to try to judge
anybody's karma that's just
that's a wasted exercise. Better
to stick with the karma that you
can penetrate within your own
life. And you're right, because
we don't know, we really don't
know what's happening when we
see cause and effect operating
around us. When you I would tell
my students, when you see great
suffering, you're see they're
seeing a sinner or a saint, and
you can never know which it is
so best not to make any
judgments at all. And I think
there are many hidden saints,
many more hidden saints, who are
taking on a lot of cause and
effect, either from their own
larger soul stream or from even
a collective soul stream. So
they're actually focusing in
their body, in their in their
psyche, what we might call
negative karma, negative cause
and effect for the uplift of the
whole and that type of
generosity and compassion we see
it around us all the time. And
good parents and good mothers
and good fathers, they would be
do anything for their children.
And I think souls at that deeper
level do that too. So, yeah, we
can't judge. We really just
couldn't judge. It's a waste of
effort.
Richard Rudd: No, I read this
book. I think I told you about
this book. It was and anyone,
it's a recommendation called
sand talk, and it's by an
Aboriginal from Australia or
part Aboriginal and really
intelligent man. And he tells a
story of when he went to to talk
to one of the elders about, you
know, the problems of the, you
know, the indigenous people,
particularly the men who had
kind of just got gone down the
role of alcoholic, the way of
alcoholism, and we're eating
really terrible food, and, like,
we're overweight and obese, and
these terrible problems that
he's and he was, like, really
concerned about. And the the old
elder just said, yeah, they're
the Warriors, you know, they are
taking on the karmic you know,
they are warrior spirits in our
tribe, in our lineage, and
they're holding this kind of
negativity in their bodies. And
you know, one day they will
become, they will move from
warrior to healer, and that's
the path, that's the kind of
evolutionary pathway, yeah. But
it was a beautiful it really,
like, it really stuck with this
young man as he was exploring,
like, wow, that's a really, kind
of powerful, empowering way to
see someone dealing with, like,
a cultural problem, you know,
or, you know, a societal, you
know, difficulty that's more
collective, you Know, that we
see a lot. Yeah, you know,
collective Karma is a, you know,
we're touching on here as well.
Chris Bache: Yeah, it's a very,
very deep, those deep currents
that run underneath that
requires us to open to a much
deeper, expanded spiritual
story. And because we often
think of Rhee. Incarnation and
karma in a very individualistic,
atomistic fashion, where we're,
you know, the individual soul is
involving themselves over the
skillful use of choice in in the
context of karma. And if we
start to sink into a larger
understanding, a deeper
understanding, then we recognize
that each individual is a
fractal point within a unified
field, and that there's a these
deep currents that are running
within the the unconscious of
humanity or the soul field of
humanity, and that we are all
players on a larger evolutionary
dynamic, then it just opens up a
deeper understanding of what's
taking place here. And I know
that we've sort of tagged this
for one of our topics for our
second discussion, but it's,
yeah,
Richard Rudd: well, we plant the
seed now it perfect. You know,
when you go into that kind of
worldview, the perfection of the
choreography of what you're
explaining is just mind blowing,
isn't it? It's mind blowing in
terms of the interconnectivity
of soul groups and these
fractals and these patternings
of humans and, you know, and
this is why, one of the great
insights that I got from your
your unit mind of the universe
book, because you described this
really well. It's a paradox, I
think, and maybe it's one of the
last things we can just discuss
to hear today, because it's so
important, I find, and it's the
paradox of being an individual
soul and yet being everything at
the same time. Yeah, you know,
so how does that paradox? How do
we? How does that hold up? You
described it beautifully in your
book, as I think you said the
soul or the or the you know that
the soul was open, open on all
sides. I think that was the
expression used, which I really
liked, open on all sides, yeah,
and it's so like part of the the
ocean, and yet still a focal,
focalized drop, yeah, I'm under
awareness. Also, you have named
it,
Chris Bache: yeah, it seems, it
seems common sensical that you
can't be both a part and the
whole at the same time. Those
are mutual exclusive categories.
And even, you know, great
spiritual teachers, the Vedanta
tradition in Hinduism and other
spiritual systems, have said the
goal of life is to abandon your
individuality, dissolve that,
and allow yourself to be
absorbed into the totality and
to know the bliss of absorption.
So that means all the individual
capacity which we are developing
over all these incarnations, in
this view, ends in extinction.
And it's kind of wasted. Yeah, I
think it's wasted, and I think
that's it's an inadequate
worldview. And what has emerged
in in my spiritual path and in
my psychedelic path is a very
different kind of worldview that
I think we share, and that is
that that we are moving into
higher and higher, more
sophisticated forms of
individuality, that
individuality is one of the
great gifts of creation. It's
something the divine wants to
encourage in its creation and
but at early stages of
individuality, we experience our
individuality cut off from the
larger texture of surrounds. So
it's us against them or us in
the whole but when individuality
matures into a richer
expression, into what I would
call the birth of the diamond
soul, then there is both a sense
of being a specific, defined
individuality emerging out of
the specific Historical lineage,
and yet at the same time,
profoundly open to the larger
patterns of existence, open to
each other and compassionate
heart, open to other human
beings with whom we have such
deep histories with, and open
to, in a sense, the the
intelligence of the universe,
Open to the the perceptions and
the influence of ideas that flow
into us and this communion with
the universe, which and I
actually believe that you have
to have developed a very, very
strong individuality to
withstand the intensity of the
communion that's available to us
when we enter into communion
with the one, with the whole it
is, is if, if we didn't, if we
weren't really, really diamond,
hard and focused and clear when
we encountered the love of the
universe for us, it would just
shatter us. You know, we. Have
to be strong in order to
actually participate in the
deeper levels of communion.
Yeah.
Richard Rudd: And I think, you
know, that that's such an
empowering vision. It's so
empowering that's and it's also,
you know, I think it opens this,
this question of, like, our
notion of enlightenment, our
notion of divinity, we have to
kind of go on expanding that,
because it's just a notion that
we've inherited, you know, and
they and it's and even though,
you know, it's been useful to
get us to where we are, we have
to just go on expanding. And for
me, what is kind of missing more
in the current, you know
modalities is creativity, you
know, like that. You know, that
whole idea of it coming to an
end and then going out into the
you know, into the into the
wonderful absorption of the
whole you know, by maintaining
the individuality at the same
time, what you are maintaining
is creativity, creativity
itself, because then you're like
a shard of the Divine creative
essence. And it's like you say
in your book, go out and create
my children, you know. And if
there, if there were a divinity,
let's say like, and it, you
know, and it wanted to have
children, then the thing it
would want for its children is
to be free, right? And to go out
and create and to become Gods
within God. That's, that's,
that's the vision I hold that,
you know, we, we become creator
gods within the wider, Yes, God,
you know, lovely in a big G
Chris Bache: God within god,
yes, yeah, the creative spark
within the fire of creation,
yes, yes. I agree with that. I
share that. And it changes
everything. It changes how we
greet the children who were born
into our families, because we
know that they're not coming
from us, they're coming to us.
It changes how we see old people
and how we see little people,
because young people are not
necessarily young in terms of
their soul age. Old people are
not necessarily old in terms of
their soul age. It just opens up
a much larger tapestry, and it
gives us permission to recognize
the deep aspirations that we
have, towards greatness, towards
great creativity, towards the
great love, towards great
spiritual fulfillment, things
that we may or may not finish
and get through in this
lifetime, but we can, we can
move toward them.
Richard Rudd: It's a much more
in some respect, sophisticated
spirituality, isn't it? It's
more nuanced. It requires a
subtler kind of understanding,
intellectual, I wouldn't say
intellectually, but through a
subtler intelligence to
understand it. It's not this
sort of, you know, here's the
law of karma. It governs
everything. You know. Bang, it's
not that simple. It's like
Aurobindo says, There are layers
and layers of understanding and
subtlety and nuance. It's like,
I'm a lover of tea, you know,
fine tea. And you know, when you
when you find something like
that, and you can be anything,
you know. You can be a chess
player, and you and you find the
subtlest nuances in the in the
in the thing you're really
understanding the layers and
layers and layers as you become
more attuned to it. And I think
that's what we are. We are
becoming more and more attuned.
The the more evolved that
individual soul essence becomes,
then the more the more subtle we
can, the more we can understand,
you know, these nuances, and
then we're kind of, I don't know
that we're really, we're really
inspired by the empowered as
well by the creative current. I
mean, maybe we can leave this to
the next one, but people always
talk about past lives, and I'm
my part of my teaching is like,
I'm interested in future lives
as well. And because when you
expand your sense of time
broadly enough, you know really,
like, really, don't hold back
anything. You don't need to just
look backwards, you can also
remember forwards. And because
there's this feeling that memory
has to go back, but memory,
also, for me, is like it travels
forwards, and that's what we
call revelation, you know? So,
so revelations can come
backwards and forwards through
time, into this into this
essence, and this essence can be
hugely expanded by those
revelations and and and more
focused than ever in the
present, you know, in the beauty
of the present moment. So, yeah,
I think that's the thought I'd
like to end on. But does any
like? Do you want to like close
us off?
Chris Bache: That's a that's a
really good thought and a good
spot to end on to me. It's. Yes,
the principle of accumulation is
one of the fundamental
principles I bring to
understanding what's happening
in creation. That the universe
is accumulating. It's learning.
It's a self learning system, and
so we are constantly learning.
We can't help but learn. Even if
we do a mediocre job in our
lifetime, we're still learning
in that lifetime. And if we do a
better job, we're learning. And
as we learn, we activate, in one
sense, I think we are learning
to be geniuses in every area of
life, a genius at chess, a
genius at relationships, a
genius in all the different
areas of life. And as if each
lifetime is a petal in a flower,
the soul is the flower and
there, if you just, I meditate
sometimes on a flower, and
imagine each 100 year lifetime,
it's a pistol and a stamen and a
petal in this magnificent
flower. And that's, you know, to
be a genius at life, to really
to be completely unfolded and
taking advantage of the
opportunity that we've been
given to grow and become more
than we've been. And again, so
many, even though many cultures
have understood reincarnation, I
don't think they've grasped it
fully. They haven't really seen
the the full potential of the
concept. They've really seen it
within an early limited,
limitation of it. And on the
future. We're going to talk
about time more I know as we go
on. But let me just leave with a
thought that Robert Monroe, the
great out of body researcher and
the founder of the Monroe
Institute of Applied Sciences.
His book far journeys, ultimate
journey, he said he reached a
point in his explorations out of
body where he discovered, he
realized that you don't
necessarily have to incarnate in
the next century. That
incarnation isn't necessarily
historically linear. You could
have former lives that were
actually lived in future time.
So that isn't that that just
like, oh man. I mean, I really
unpick that one a little bit.
Yeah, that really challenges
things. So in addition to
intuiting the future, which is
not yet, and bringing the not
yet into the now. I wonder
sometimes whether some of us
have sampled that future time
and are inculcating the
awareness in the now.
Richard Rudd: So that's what I
would call a current, the
current of involution, as
opposed to evolution. You know,
it's like there is a spiritual
force coming down, and there is
a there is an evolution,
evolving force going up, if you
want to do it up and down, but,
you know, yeah, it's like a
funnel.
Chris Bache: Yeah, Sri
Aurobindo, I love you quoting
Sri Aurobindo, because he's one
of my heroes too. Yeah, he's all
that clearly and I agree.
Richard Rudd: Yeah, great. Well,
what a wonderful beginning.
Chris, yeah, thank you. Where we
go next, yeah, me too, yeah,
take care. All right. Take care.
Richard, you.
Unknown: You.