Nick Mather: Nick, welcome to
rebel spirit radio, exploring
the frontiers of spirituality,
consciousness, the esoteric and
humanity's sacred relationship
with the living Earth. I'm your
host, Nick Mather, and in this
episode, I speak with Dr Chris
Bache, author of LSD in the mind
of the universe, which details
his experience of 73 high dose
LSD sessions taken over the span
of two decades. In our
conversation, Chris discusses
reincarnation, its role in human
evolution, the creative
intelligence of the universe,
our current ecological moment
and more. So much so please join
me in a fascinating conversation
with Dr Chris Bache on rebel
spirit reading. Dr Christopher
Bache is professor emeritus in
the Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University in Ohio, where
he taught for 33 years. He's
also an adjunct faculty member
at the California Institute of
integral studies, Emeritus
fellow at the Institute of
Noetic Sciences, and serves on
the Advisory Council of Grof
legacy training. The heart of
Chris's work has been the study
of the philosophical
implications of Non-ordinary
states of consciousness,
particularly psychedelic states.
Chris has written four books,
life cycles, a study of
reincarnation in light of
contemporary consciousness,
research dark night, early dawn,
an investigation of psychedelic
philosophy and collective
consciousness the living
classroom, an exploration of
collective fields of
consciousness and teaching. And
his latest work, LSD and the
mind of the universe, the story
of his 20 year journey with LSD
by way of 73 high dose LSD
sessions, greeting Chris and
welcome to rebel spirit. Radio,
I am so very grateful for your
time today, and I can't even
begin to tell you how much I'm
looking forward to this
conversation. I'm glad to be
here. Good, wonderful. So first
I wanted to say that I
thoroughly enjoyed your book.
LSD, in the mind of the
universe, I found it to be
deeply personal. It's
beautifully written. It's very
engaging, and I believe
necessary. You know, I've read
all of your books, and in a way,
even though this is your latest,
it seems to me to be the first,
as the experiences you describe,
I think, undergird all of your
other work. That's correct,
yeah, yeah. It seems to me it's
the source material.
Chris Bache: It really is, yeah.
So
Nick Mather: I wanted to ask,
you know, I'm sure that my
listeners who are unfamiliar
with you and your work, they
want to know, you know what led
you on this journey? You know
what led you to this journey and
why?
Chris Bache: LSD, yeah, quite
unexpectedly. I mean, I was
raised in the Deep South, in
Mississippi. You know, I got a
degree in theology from Notre
Dame. I mean, I'm the last
person you would expect to have
written a book on LSD research,
and especially a psychedelic
autobiography. So I really
understand here the background
is I had, I was, had just
finished my graduate work at
Brown University. I was, I
finished my work as a
philosopher of religion. I came
out of graduate school as an
atheistically inclined agnostic,
and I had just begun teaching at
young sound state in Northeast
Ohio, and I was looking around
for where to take my research
after, I mean, I was publishing
articles out of my dissertation,
and I came across the work of
two people who's changed my
life. One of them is Ian
Stevenson at the University of
Virginia, and his work on
reincarnation, which convinced
me, in one reading, that
reincarnation was a fact of
life, and this was totally new
to me in my thinking. And even
more influential was the work of
Stanislav Grof. He had just
published realms of the human
unconscious. This was in 1978
when I was a young academic, 30
years old. So I read Stan's work
in one reading, he convinced me
that of the importance of
psychedelics for philosophical
inquiry, not just psychological
inquiry. And I became convinced
that the people who would be
making the most important
contributions in my field would
be people writing out of an
experiential basis, not simply
an intellectual basis. So I had
a choice to make, because
psychedelics were ill. Legal at
this time, and I made the choice
to begin a private, hidden
psychedelic inquiry just with
myself, which led to eventually
73 high dose LSD sessions
following Stan Grof protocols,
as he outlines in LSD
psychotherapy his book LSD
psychotherapy, and I during the
daytime. I was a conventional
philosopher and philosopher of
religion, teaching my students,
year in, year out, and in my
private life, I began this
systematic exploration of the
deep structure of my
consciousness, and by studying
my consciousness, studying how
the universe manifested itself
in these deep states of
consciousness. So that's how I
got into it wonderful.
Nick Mather: And you know, I
really appreciate that because,
you know, also coming from the
background in religious studies
and philosophy myself, it drives
me a little bit crazy that it's
all theoretical, that, you know,
there's so little of the
practical aspect the practice,
not practical, but the practice
part of it. And, you know, I
think that sometimes students
have a feel for this. You know,
they can tell someone, not
necessarily, if they have had
psychedelic experiences, but
whether or not they've had
profound religious experience,
Chris Bache: yeah, yeah, yeah.
And I want to mention right up
front that I do not recommend
that people do what I did. I
don't recommend that they
setting aside the issue of the
legality or the illegality of
psychedelics. Okay, that's a
changing landscape, right? But I
don't recommend that people
follow the protocol that I
adopted because I know more now
than I did in the beginning. And
I really would recommend, as I
do in the book, I explain, I
would recommend a different
protocol if I were doing it over
again
Nick Mather: today. Yeah, it, it
doesn't, it doesn't read like it
was fun. You describe a lot of
pain and suffering, which is
something I want to get to but,
you know, I think that a lot of
folks who aren't familiar with
psychedelics probably have a
false view of them in many ways.
You know, this isn't a wild
weekend in Las Vegas or, you
know, I think there's also a lot
of fear involved centered around
psychedelics. I wanted to, since
we're kind of talking about, you
know, you had to keep this
secret, and you describe in the
book how this it was that was
also painful for you, that you
couldn't be open about this for
a variety of reasons. You know,
the illegality, of course, is
important. It also, I think
probably there was a question of
credibility with some of the
academic community, who I think
still have a tendency to look
down on these experiences. And
you know, you mentioned that the
landscape seems to be changing
somewhat. Yeah, I know that. I
think Oregon legalized
Psilocybin mushrooms, there is
legislation currently moving
through California to
decriminalize all psychedelics.
And I'm kind of curious, given
this new landscape where
psychedelics are more accepted.
Have you ever wondered or
thought about what it would have
been like to teach in this sort
of new environment, or a new
environment where these things
are more accepted?
Chris Bache: Wouldn't that have
been interesting there. I mean,
at first I did have an
opportunity to do some teaching
at the California Institute of
integral studies in the
philosophy cosmology and
consciousness program, but this
came rather late in my series. I
mean, basically, I did my work
between 1979 and 1999 when I was
between 30 years old and 50
years old, you know. And now I'm
in my early 70s. So, so I did
have an opportunity to teach
graduate students this material
after dark net early dawn came
out, but it would be.
Fascinating to be able to be
doing this work in the classroom
today, instead of in online, you
know, settings and whatnot. But
there's another there's an
upside for having waited as long
as I did. I waited 20 years
until after I'd finished this
work to write LSD in the mind of
the universe. And I did so, not
only for the legal
ramifications, but I did so
because these experiences were
extremely difficult to
understand. When you work with
high doses of LSD, it pushes you
into dimensions of reality that
go considerably, considerably
beyond what even appears in much
of the mystical literature. And
it just and the methodology that
you're using to engage these
deep states of consciousness is
very different than the
methodology that's found in
contemplative, you know,
meditative mystical traditions,
and so there were a lot of
riddles to figure out, a lot of
puzzles. And if I had been
teaching while I was doing this
work, I I might not been able to
produce as mature final product.
So by holding on to it for a
long time, really pondering it
and working out a lot of the
details. I think the end result
is a more polished, clear
presentation of the stages of
the journey, because my
experience was, but Well, two
things My experience was, I went
through a series of death and
rebirth experiences going
through layer after layer after
layer in in the universe. But
let me say something about the
methodology itself, because, as
you say, this is an unfamiliar
protocol. And if people are
familiar with psychedelics at
all, they tend to think of
psychedelics either as the
recreational in a recreational
way of tripping, and, you know,
social taking psychedelics and
socializing, or, you know, going
into the woods or something. Or
if they're informed by today's,
you know, experiences, they
would think of psychedelics in
terms of a therapeutic protocol
aimed at, he at personal
healing. The work I did
methodologically was similar to
the current protocols under
adoption. That is, I was working
completely isolated from the
outside world. Every day that I
did a session, I had no contact
with the outside world. I was by
myself in my home, are in my
then wife's office, and my
former wife was my sitter for
all my sessions. So I was
working under the care and
supervision of a clinical
psychologist, isolated lying
down on the floor, eyeshades
earphones, listening to very
carefully selected music that
was specifically designed to
pace the various stages of
opening and closing in a
session, and then my I would
write up my session within 24
hours of the session. So it's a
very different environment than
if you're, you know, taking LSD
and going to a concert or
something like that, yeah, yeah,
for sure.
Nick Mather: Um, I'm curious, in
a sense, because you were doing
this at a you know, the high
dose level, would the same
methodology apply for lower
dosages,
Chris Bache: same methodology
would apply. But the the nature,
the nature of the journey, is
different when you work with
lower doses or with gentler
psychedelics like Psilocybin,
perhaps, or Ayahuasca, you
basically, you're these, but
psychedelics do is they amplify
the unconscious. They amplify
consciousness, and they catalyze
consciousness. So things that
are usually far beyond your
capacity, out of your conscious
ability to experience, begin to
come forward into your
experience. So there is a
churning and a rising of
unconscious content in your
conscious awareness. If you're
working with lower doses of a
psychedelic, you tend to peel
consciousness in layers, so you
may spend lots and lots of time
working through various
psychodynamic levels of
consciousness, then moving stage
by stage, slowly into deeper
levels of consciousness. When
you work with high doses of
psychedelic there's a much more
powerful, cathartic sense of it,
and you you tend to move very
quickly through various
psychodynamic levels and engage
starting with what Stan calls
the pair. Natal level of
consciousness are at the
boundary between physical
reality and and spiritual
reality, and then you keep
pushing deeper and deeper into
various levels of Transpersonal,
our spiritual consciousness.
Nick Mather: Okay, one more
question, kind of about
methodology, a understand that
it's helpful to begin a session
by stating an intention. And you
had an intention, I believe that
you wrote it was something like,
you know, may I made this help
me serve the common good, or
something like that. But then
later you write that with the
high doses you were taking, that
the intention didn't seem to
matter that you were taken
where, I guess, by this cosmic
intelligence, which we can talk
about a little bit later. I
wanted to take you. I'm curious,
is the intention still important
in the low dose sessions, or is
there a similarity where you can
set the intention but you're
going to go wherever, whatever
is driving this experience wants
to take you?
Chris Bache: I think it's a
combination of both. If you are
the essence of this type of
practice is surrender. You just
completely once you create safe
conditions, once you are really
contained, you surrender
completely to the experience and
let it take you wherever it
wants to go, whether or not you
understand it at the time, but
when you are working with lower
doses, it disrupts your
psychological structure less,
and so your your reasons for
doing the work can influence
more where you go when you work
with high doses. My experience
was, at least my personal
experience was that it it just
whatever intention I had going
into the work was very quickly
completely shattered, and it
didn't really make much
difference the intention I
brought in. I was on a journey,
and a deeper consciousness, a
larger consciousness, was
guiding my journey. And there
were many, many things that
happened and I didn't really
understand, in certain respects,
I did not understand the deep
structure of what was happening
until years and years of
experiences later. I mean, there
was a journey that I was on, and
you can't understand what's
happening simply from where
you've been in the past without
knowing where you're going in
the future. So it's from the
hindsight perspective that I can
understand some of the structure
of what happened. But what I
found was that I was always
engaging or being guided by an
intelligence, which I think of
as the mind of the universe, a
cosmic intelligence.
Nick Mather: Okay, yeah, I
wanted to talk a little bit more
about this cosmic intelligence.
And, you know, is, is this what
other people might identify as
God? Is it something beyond God?
What else can you say about
this? You know, I'm assuming
that this is the mind of the
universe from the title of the
book.
Chris Bache: Yes, what shall we
call it? You know, shall we call
it God? But then, all of a
sudden, we have to start dealing
with all the historical
conditions and interpretations
of that concept in the different
religions of the world. And I'm
not really comfortable with
that. I'd use. Sometimes refer
to it as the divine, but that's
really just a step sideways a
little bit. I don't know what we
should call it. You might call
it the Dao. I think of it as the
intelligence, the generative
intelligence of the universe,
the intelligence which is
responsible for the Big Bang and
the unfolding of all time and
space since the Big Bang. I
mean, I have this virtual
background behind me, because,
just because it tokens the
dimensions of the Universe,
which we have now understand in
this century better than we've
ever understood before, how
incredibly large it is, how
incredibly old it is, and
psychedelic research adds to
this. It's also conscious. So
the size of the universe and the
age of the universe are a
reflection, in a way, of the
intelligence and the
consciousness of the universe.
And it is so large we can't see
the edges of it, and it's so old
we can't see to the beginning of
it. So what shall we call this?
In classical cultures, one would
call it God, but. The but the
interpretations of God over the
last 6000 years have always been
constricted by the cultural
context in which these concepts
have been formed. And I don't
want to buy into that. And yet,
there are certain, clearly
certain qualities about this
consciousness which echo the
qualities of the infinite
divinity which have been talked
about, particularly in the
mystical traditions of the
world. Spiritual traditions,
more than in the neighborhood
church theology, specifically in
the contemplative mystical
traditions.
Nick Mather: When you speak, it
kind of reminds me of the
merkabah mysticism of Ezekiel,
where you can't actually
describe or explain this full
vision of God, but you can talk
about the throne, you can talk
about the hem of, you know, the
robe that God is wearing, but
it's just a very small portion
of this grander vision.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think so. I
think in the end, I mean, I've,
I've spent more ink than most
people trying to describe these
things, and even so, I still
feel like I'm really just
talking about the hem of the
garment.
Nick Mather: Yeah, yeah,
absolutely. So I want to dig a
little bit deeper into this
cosmology that is that was
revealed to you, but also you
reveal to your readers and one
of the key elements is
reincarnation. And like you said
earlier, you were deeply
informed by the work of Ian
Stevenson at the University of
Virginia. And I agree with you,
I think that he provides
absolute evidence, even though
he was very cautious, trying to
be good scientists there, but I
think that the evidence is
unequivocal, but yet you have a
bit of a different Take on
reincarnation, it seems, than
the traditional understanding.
And so I would like you to if
you could speak to that a little
bit more and say something also
about how reincarnation fits
into this cosmology.
Chris Bache: Well, Ian Stevenson
and and a host of researchers
who have followed in his stead,
and a host of therapists who
have been working in pet and
past life therapy in the
hundreds and hundreds of cases
that they've generated. Convince
us, if you are really on
unbiased and you really look at
the data, I think it's
overwhelmingly clear that
reincarnation occurs, that there
is continuity of memory across
multiple lifetimes, that our
consciousness is older than our
body. So the mind that I'm using
to speak to you now has a
history that's older than my
physical body, but how it works.
You know, we we still are
beginners in this. We don't
really know the physics of
reincarnation. We don't really
know what the soul is. We don't
know how consciousness encodes
its learning into a new brain
physiology. We don't know how
consciousness leaves when a
person dies, how our experience
leaves intact and stays coherent
after the body falls apart.
There's so much that we don't
know. I'm sure we'll be learning
more as we go on, but there's
much that we don't know, and I
think many of our early
understandings of reincarnation
are just inadequate. I mean, for
example, the idea that you
incarnate as a human being and
then you come back as an animal,
you know, and most sophisticated
thinkers of reincarnation reject
that idea that it's like once
you once you can function at a
certain level, there's nothing
to be gained from coming back
and functioning at a lesser or
lower capacity level. So once a
human, human and up, in a way,
other ideas that that
reincarnation is somehow
something simple, like going
from one life to another life to
another life, much more
complicated, because when you
get into the past life
literature, you find that
actually my present life is
informed not simply by my most
immediate previous life, but my
multiple lives that I have
already lived. So it's like
playing cards, the deck may
have. 52 cards, but you're only
dealt a certain number of cards
for a particular hand, so the a
certain number of my former
lives may be active in
structuring some of the issues
that I'm dealing with in this
life, and for the most part, the
other lives are quiescent and in
the background, so to speak. So
lots and lots of changes and
modifications to the idea. But
the basic vision is that when we
die, we expand into a larger
state of consciousness, which I
think of as the soul. And I
define the soul as the
consciousness that holds all of
our experience, all of our
incarnation experience. When we
incarnate, we contract down into
a very limited physical body,
historical circumstance, social
circumstance, so on so forth. We
it's like going to college. When
you start the college, when you
start the semester, you're in a
specific set of courses,
learning a specific set of
things. Then at the end of the
semester, spring break, you
know, you expand into a larger
state. When you die, you go into
a larger state, reconnect with
the universe and you contract.
So reincarnation, the pulse of
reincarnation is this rhythm of
expansion at death and
contracting at birth, over and
over and over and over again,
whatever the details and in this
process, we learn, we challenge
ourselves, we become more than
we were before, and naturally,
The lessons that we're
investigating exploring in every
lifetime. Mature is just like
students go back and forth to
college semester after semester,
but they're studying different
things as they the longer they
stay in school. They're
maturing. They're developing new
capacities. The primary
difference that I see from
traditional that I hold, from
traditional thinking about
reincarnation is that
classically, in the Eastern
traditions which affirm
reincarnation, the idea is that
we grow, we grow, we grow, and
then we come to a spiritual
plateau where we truly wake up
to what's been going on, and we
Wake up to what we are. We wake
up to that essence of us which
has never died, the essence
which allows us to die and be
reborn, that essence which in
Hinduism, it's called Atman, and
that Atman is Brahman, the
essence of the individual is the
essence of the Divine. In
classical reincarnation thinking
when you are sufficiently mature
that you wake up to this deeper
spiritual identity and
experience some of the deep
spiritual truths of oneness, of
the essence of divine being, the
essence of everything which
exists at that point, when you
die, you leave the system, you
leave time space, and there is a
culmination which takes place
off planet, whether it's heaven
or the Islamic garden or the
Buddha pure Land, that existence
culminates off planet in leaving
I understand that theory. I
understand its historical
context, and I think it makes
sense, given what we are capable
of understanding when these
ideas began to percolate about
three to 4000 years ago, but as
we now understand more about the
universe, more about the
evolutionary development of the
universe, more about the time
frame of the universe. I think
we are beginning to see a
different outcome. I think the
goal of reincarnation, at least
the I don't think we can see the
ultimate goal any more than we
can see the ultimate goal of the
universe, but the intermediate
goal is to wake up and not to
leave, but to wake up and to
fully embody your soul
consciousness in physical
reality. So the soul wakes up
and you're you no longer are
tempted to identify with your
physical body as yourself, the
soul wakes up, and I call this
in the book The birth of the
diamond soul, that we wake up
and we have, First of all, we
remember our former lives, more
importantly, we live consciously
the deep life which has been
gestating inside all these
incremental courses that we've
been taking all these centuries.
Nick Mather: That's absolutely
beautiful. And I love that you.
To, you know, it's this not
escaping into a heaven or
Transcendence or nothingness and
Nirvana, but you know, you say
it's this deepening of a sacred
presence on the earth. Yes, and
I'm kind of one of the questions
that came up for me while
listening to you was, you know,
we don't remember necessarily
our past lives, but you know,
some children have, you know
some aspects of it, and you
know, I've always suspected that
there are some things with me
that come from past life
experiences that I just can't
explain. And I've just had this
ongoing suspicion that something
that happened previously, that
explains everything. But what
I'm curious about is having
this, this, this knowledge that
we are souls on this journey.
Unknown: Does that
Nick Mather: how I'm trying to
figure out how I want to state
this question, but I don't want
to say obligation, but can we
start working being cognizant of
this Can we start doing things
now in our lives to affect the
long picture of this cycle and
where we are In this cycle? Can
I do things now that will
consciously affect my rebirth? I
guess maybe is the way I'm
Chris Bache: I think so. And I
think, to their credit, the
spiritual traditions, the
classic spiritual traditions,
have always said, even once you
begin to understand what's
happening, once you begin to
understand the truth of
reincarnation and the truth of
karma, and karma simply is the
cycle of cause and effect, which
conditions consciousness and
conditions destiny, once you
begin to understand that then
whether or not you have active
recall of your former lives, you
can still begin to make. You can
improve the quality of your
choices. So, for example, once,
once you understand karma, you
naturally begin to make non
choices of non injury. You make,
begin to make more choices of
generosity. You begin to make
choices which are not simply
tuned to the short term
circumstance, but choices of the
long term. We see this in the
Native American tradition, where
you're looking for seven
generations. Every important
choice is over seven
generations. That basic mindset
that you begin to think long
term, and you think not just how
your choices are affecting you,
but understanding how they
affect other people,
understanding that spiritually,
you and other people are like
two leaves on the same branch of
a tree. You're separate at one
level, but you're not separate
at another. And once you kind of
even understand that
intellectually, you make choices
that serve the good of the tree,
and in making choices that are
larger and more deep and deeper,
you accelerate your evolutionary
development. You accelerate it,
and you improve the outcome of
this lifetime, and this is this
does not require knowing who you
were in the 17th Century or
anything like that. It simply
requires that you begin to
understand the structure of
reality. This is what the Hindus
call Dharma, the teachings of
about the way things are, and
it's simply learning what's real
and then adjusting yourself to
live in harmony with what's
Nick Mather: real wonderful. I
was actually thinking this
morning, in thinking about this
conversation, the analogy that
you used of the Native American
belief, you know, the seven
generations out. It kind of
occurred to me that in this
picture that you're presenting,
you know, I think that when we
hear this seven generations out,
we often consider them as that
they're not us, yeah. But in
reincarnation, they are us,
yeah. And I was wondering if
more people had that idea, how
would it change? Because, how
would it change how we act in
the world right now? Yeah, you
know.
Chris Bache: Um, well, let's
take just the ecological
situation in this in a
fundamental way, reincarnation
tells us that the world we come
back to is the world we leave,
not only in terms of its
psychological structure, but
literally in terms of the earth.
Now we've never faced a
situation like we are facing now
in terms of the impact of our
industrial culture on the entire
planet. But if we truly believe
that in 100 years from now,
we're going to be back on this
earth, don't you think we'd be
make taking better care of the
earth? Don't you think we'd be
looking to more care of our
ecological systems if we believe
that we would be coming back
into society and we did not know
and could not control
necessarily, what part of
society we're coming back into,
don't you think we would be
trying to create a society that
worked for all that was just for
all that was fair in its
distribution of resources. So,
yeah, I think those choices,
those ideas, do have impact on
how we think about organizing
our culture.
Nick Mather: Yeah, and it seems
to me that it's you know,
because I've thought about this
before, where, you know, I try
to be as environmentally aware
and cognizant as I can be, and
not harm, although I know that I
do, and part of that is just by
the virtue of this system that
we are embedded in. But I, but
I've often thought about this in
terms of karma, and that my
actions now are definitely going
to affect, you know, these
future generations. And it seems
kind of fundamentally wrong to
me to think that I would escape,
or any of us would escape the
consequences of that. Yeah, and,
and I wonder we'll move on from
reincarnation here in a little
bit. But I'm deeply fascinated
by the question
if more people accepted this
idea of reincarnation or were
aware of this, do you think and
this larger vision that you're
providing? Because one of the
questions I wanted to ask you
about this is, it seems to me,
and I'm probably jumping way
forward more than I should be.
But it seems to me that we are
undergoing this transformation
of spirituality, especially in
the United States, and I think
that more and more people are
hearing sort of the call to
spirituality. I've personally
been going through this for the
past couple of years, and I'm at
this place where I just want
absolutely everything I do to be
grounded in spiritual practices.
And I know I have other friends
that are doing similar things,
and so my question is, do you
think this is part of the
evolution of our collective
consciousness? Do you think that
we are moving towards this
larger vision that you
experienced.
Chris Bache: I think so. I think
that while there is a growing
appreciation and awareness and
thirst for spiritual truth
spiritual encounter, it's not
necessarily expressing itself as
a an increase of religiosity or
an increase of religious
participation. And personally, I
think what's happening is that
the religions that exist today
have largely done the bulk of
the work that they were kind of
charged with doing. I mean, once
you understand the breadth, the
length of human evolution, how
many hundreds of 1000s of years
we are involved in Evol growing
and growing and growing and
growing. Then when you look at
religions, and religions don't
last more than a few 1000 years,
you know, for a few 1000 years,
and a religion can't we have a
history of sort of thinking that
a religion, if it's true, it's
eternally true, it'll be true
forever and ever. But that
doesn't really seem to be
realistic. And I think it's more
likely that a religion helps an
evolve. Humanity helps a
reincarnating humanity go from A
to B, and then we come to B, and
there's so much more to go. It
requires a new set of insights,
a new inspiration, a new vision
to take us from B to C, and when
we get to C, it'll require a new
vision to take us from C to D.
And I think we're at that a
phase where the vision, which
has taken us to here is is not
sufficient to take us where we
need to go next. And I would
mention that all the religions
of the world, and I know you're
a professor of religion, so
you'll appreciate that there are
fundamentally two core mistakes
that all the religions of the
Axial Age make. Many others,
perhaps, but at least two. One
of them is it gets women wrong.
Systems, you know. And
relatedly, it gets nature wrong.
So are, when you have an up and
out theology where the goal is
to become spiritually awakened,
or to spiritually saved, and
then leave time and space, you
have this gap so that the
physical world is not valued as
deeply as the spiritual world.
And you know, you're so on, so
forth. So what happens is we
don't really have an answer to
the question, what is the
purpose of time space? What is
the purpose of the physical
world? It becomes a veil of
tears, or it becomes something
that we basically are trying to
get away from, to get back home
or to get to someplace better
that these religions are wrong
about women and they're wrong
about the Earth, and what we
need going forward is a vision
of reality that is larger, that
includes the best of the
insights of the religions of the
past, but then expands them into
a new set of visions which is
truly gender balanced and also
species balanced, because now
you know, the religions have
been, for the most part, and
anthropocentric in that they
value men and human beings more
than other species. And a vision
which values physicality, values
the experience of being physical
as more than simply a training
ground for going to heaven.
Yeah, very good. Yeah. I think
we're basically we're at a
transition time the collapse of
the old is getting clear and
clear, but it's not yet clear
what the new is going to be yet,
because we're at the cusp. It's
like we're in the middle of a
night, and we are seeing the
early, early layers of dawn, but
we really have not seen what's
gone what's coming forward
fully. It's a very uncomfortable
time to be in because there's so
much uncertainty, things are
falling apart. We haven't really
congealed around a new vision
yet. There's a lot of anxiety, a
lot of back and forth, a lot of
push pull, lot of conflict. We
can see this, this polarization
in the political arena, but now
we don't have any time the earth
is forcing us into a new
formation of our values.
Nick Mather: Yeah, absolutely.
And you know, I was thinking
that there's so much I want to
say, but I was thinking about
our current moment, and in
particular with this pandemic.
And initially I thought that the
pandemic was a almost like a
final warning shot and a last
opportunity to make a lot of
meaningful changes. You know, I
remember when the lockdowns
first happened, I was out
walking one evening, and, you
know, I'm in Pasadena, which is
in LA County, and the air was
clean, you know, I could
breathe. And I think for a
while, la had some of the
cleanest air in the nation. You
know, there were stories about
dolphins returning to the canals
in Venice and wildlife coming
into the cities. And for me, one
of the great things about this,
even though I was riddled with
anxieties, was it was quiet
again. I could hear nature. And
you would hear stories about
that, like in New York, you
could hear bird song again. And
I thought, well, this is
amazing. This is even though
this is horrible, it's also
potential. And then a couple of
weeks ago, we had thunderstorm
here, and wasn't too bad, but
there was this tremendous crack
of thunder. Here, and you might
appreciate this, but since you
know, I grew up in Ohio, so I
hear this crack of thunder, I
immediately have to go out to my
front porch. And it wasn't
really raining, and it wasn't
horribly overcast. I could
actually see pollution, again,
hovering over a nearby freeway,
and I could hear the sounds from
the freeway. I could hear cars
and horns and a siren, and I
thought, then, it's like it it's
too late, you know? You know, we
lost our chance. We have to go
through these experiences. And
it seems to me that in your
book, you actually make it seems
like you're suggesting something
similar. We have to go through
this. We are going to have to
experience this pain that we
spend so much time avoiding the
pain, but it's a necessary part
of this initiation into a new
form of humanity. Am I getting
that right?
Chris Bache: I think we are
being initiated. I mean, we're
kind of jumping, this is a
chapter that I deal with towards
the very end of the book. So
we're kind of jumping over a lot
of intermediate places. But
basically, I think humanity is
being initiated into a new level
of consciousness and a new level
of maturity, we're basically
inheriting the consequences of
our egoic history, where, in the
ego is a beautiful thing. I
think ego often gets a bad rap
in the religious traditions, but
individual consciousness is a
beautiful thing. I mean, it's
just an extraordinarily
beautiful mechanism, but it's
fundamentally fragmented. It
really cuts us off from each
other. We don't experience
necessarily, the common ground
that we share with each other
and with other life forms and
with the physical world itself.
And I think we can no longer
afford that kind of
fragmentation, because a world
built by the ego, the
civilization built by the ego,
is an inherently divided and
fragmented world. It's in
divides into have and have nots.
Just the definition of who is
haves and who the have nots are
and changes, but it's a
fragmented world, and it's a
world we are basically
inheriting centuries and
centuries of the consequences of
a world built by the ego, and we
need to grow up to become less
of an adolescent and more of an
adult, taking adult size
responsibility, adult size
vision and an adult size
commitment. Yeah, and I think
there's, there's going to be
pain, because these the choices
of the past have accumulated,
not only in our social systems,
in our legal systems, economic
systems, but they've also
accumulated within our bodies.
And we have all this history.
And so there's a tremendous
detoxification that's taking
place and is about to take place
in a purification process. And I
think that basically we're
coming into, I mean, this is, I
think of this as a birth
process. And birth is really,
really hard work, as every woman
will tell you. I mean, gestation
is a long, gradual process, but
birth when the waters break and
it's time to get that baby out.
That's a very short and
cathartic and powerful process.
And I think basically what's
happening is this new human, or
this future human, has been
gestating inside of us for 1000s
and 1000s of incarnations. The
diamond soul has been gestating
and developing and developing,
century by Century, century by
Century, and now it's time for
this higher being, this larger
being, this deeper being, to be
born. Labor is hard work, and I
think we're going into global
labor. Yeah, yeah.
Nick Mather: And it seems, you
know, along those lines, that we
also have, you know, you say
that we've embodied a lot of
this trauma, and also the trauma
from our past lives, and that we
are going through a necessary
healing process, and the pain is
part of that healing, it seems.
Yeah, I'm also kind of curious
about, not just in terms of the
past lives, but also in terms
of, I guess, like ancestors, you
know, I think about. About this.
Personally, my family has a lot
to account for, but I also
thought of it in terms of just
the culturally, you know, like
we have the founding fathers,
and those are kind of collective
ancestors, and there's a lot of
pain and trauma from them that
we still have to account
Chris Bache: for. Well, just as
we are those future seven
generations, we are our
ancestors. So our ancestors are
not separate and other than us,
but in a reincarnating universe,
where generation after
generation, we are constantly
coming being born. That that
means that the ancestors in us
are in the how it's easy to over
generalize and to over simplify
what is an incredibly subtle and
complex process. So I forgive me
if I do that, but the strains of
our ancestors, the themes and
the learning of our ancestors,
qualities of our ancestors, are
woven into our current
incarnation, and not only the
pains left over from our former
lives, but also the strengths
and incredible qualities, I
think that many of us have
learned about reincarnation by
reading the literature on past
life therapy. So our approach to
our understanding of
reincarnation tends to be
inflected by a therapeutic
model, and people go into
therapy not because of the
things that makes them feel
good. They go into therapy
because of their pain, but I
think that's really a relatively
small percentage of the
carryover from our previous
lives. Our school system has
many, many problems, but most
kids pass every year. Most kids
learn all right. And I think the
most people learn and come out
of every incarnation with more
positive than negative. And we
carry the positive forward as
well as carrying the negative
forward, so that there's a
tremendous accumulation of
capacity of intelligence built
into our into our bodies,
musical intelligence and
mathematical intelligence and
social intelligence that are, in
a sense, the voices of our
ancestors alive in us as we
Continue to this process of
becoming the ancestors of our
future selves,
Nick Mather: wonderful. And that
gets to, I think, one of the
final points I wanted to get at
in terms of reincarnation, which
is you talk a bit about, and you
have been speaking about the
evolution here, and you know the
evolution of the species and
reincarnation. I think at one
point you say that evolution
grows species, where
reincarnation grows individuals,
but there seems to be this
connection between human
evolution and as a species and
the individual reincarnation.
Yes, I was wondering if you
could maybe say a little bit
more about that.
Chris Bache: I think of
reincarnation as the higher
octave of evolution. And of
course, well, evolution, our
scientists tell us that
evolution is an evolving of
whole species. It's a learning
and development of whole
species. Somewhere along the
way, nature has figured out, or
the intelligence behind nature
has figured out, how to evolve
individuals within certain
highly developed species. So
somewhere along the way, as we
move from group evolution,
individual evolution is added on
top of that, where it becomes a
matter of the evolution of our
consciousness. So it has to do
with the birth of individuality.
When individuality begins to
emerge within species. Where
does that begin? No one knows
quite for sure, but somewhere
along the way species begin to
birth individuals, then those
individuals make choices, and
those choices begin to influence
their learning. And once you
have that cycle established, you
have the cause and effect that's
influencing not just the
physiology of species, but the
psychophysiology of individuals.
So I think of reincarnation as
the higher octave of evolution.
It is when evolution has reached
a point where it is involving
individuals and it is evolving
the consciousness. Of
individuals.
Nick Mather: Okay, wonderful.
And when you were speaking, the
thought occurred to me that this
model avoids, in a sense, and
maybe I'm wrong, but it seems to
avoid this issue of, like
intelligent design that it's
coming from outside, because it
seems like in this model, we are
the ones that are actively
driving human evolution through
this cycle. Would that be
correct?
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think, I
think the idea of design in this
way, is a reaction to the sort
of inadequacy of conventional
evolutionary theory and its
failure to explain certain
aspects of evolution. So
Intelligent Design is an attempt
to bridge some of those gaps.
But the problem is that it's all
external. You always have an
external deity who's tinkering
from the outside. And I would
think that evolution and
reincarnation is an emergent
principle. It's the intelligence
is already there in matter. The
intelligence is manifesting
itself in ever greater
complexity, partly through the
mechanisms recognized by
science, but partly through
other mechanisms, subtler
mechanisms. But it's an emergent
quality, which means it's
arising from within So evolution
arises from within organisms,
and evolution arises within
reincarnation. It's, it's so
it's a, it's a self expressive,
self transformative process,
Nick Mather: okay, yeah, that
makes a lot of sense. I want to
turn to
some of your experiences again,
and this idea of, and we've
already talked about this a
little bit, but the pain and the
experiences, and, you know, you
describe, again, this ocean of
suffering that's both personal
and collective. And you know, it
seems to me that most religions,
I think all religions have
something to say about
suffering, and many of them are
centered around ending the
suffering, but you write that we
need to be open to our
suffering.
Chris Bache: Yeah, so let me
back. Let's back up a little
bit. Okay, this back into a
context here, when you are
working in a therapeutic
modality with psychedelics, your
system becomes hyper conscious.
You are temporarily more
conscious than you were before.
And what happens when, when you
do that, is that the system
begins to spontaneously cleanse
itself to clean itself. So it
brings forward, not simply, it
brings forward the parts of your
past which you've had difficulty
dealing with. It brings forward
your pain. It brings forward
your fears. It brings forward so
on and so forth. And by
confronting those fears and
confronting those pains
heroically, one can bring to
better resolution things that
had gotten started somewhere in
the past but didn't really work
out completely. So deaths that
were ugly, relationships that
were ugly, are problematic in
different ways. So you basically
by embracing the suffering which
presents itself to you in your
sessions, you engage that you
see it, you let it into your
awareness. And by letting it
into your awareness, you bring
it. It brings itself to better
outcome. And when you face the
trauma, say, in a particular
aspect of life, either from this
life or from another life,
something like this, then there
is a tremendous relaxation that
takes place in the system. And
the system is then free to move
into deeper and deeper levels of
reality. Now, in the early
stages of one's work, one
reaches a point where, when
consciousness begins to expand
beyond time, space reality, you
begin to be threatened with what
is called ego, death. And ego
here means simply the identity
that you have formed in your
time space experience. But when
consciousness begins to go
beyond that time space identity,
that time space identity of.
Eventually is shattered. It dies
simply because your mind is
bigger than your body, your
body's history. And you go
through an ego death experience,
which is very painful. It's it's
kind of like an inversion of
everything that you've ever
known yourself to be. But you go
through that process, and in
that surrender, one's
consciousness is liberated into
deeper textures of mind, deeper
textures of consciousness. If
you continue this process, if
you keep exploring these deeper
textures, you will go through
more cycles of purification,
more cycles which eventually
lead to deeper layers of dying,
deeper layers of surrendering,
and you will go through another
catharsis of death, and then
you'll be exploded into yet
deeper dimensions of reality,
which you will then be able to
explore in future sessions.
Again, this is always working
within a very highly focused
regimen of exploration. It's not
like this way, this time, this
way, that time. You're really
always working particular edge
now as you go through different
layers of consciousness, of
consciousness which transcends
your individual awareness. There
are different patterns that you
engage. And so there some of the
early patterns will be these
unfinished businesses from your
personal life and from your
soul's life. But sometimes you
engage unfinished trauma that
species wide, that has to do
with your entire human family.
And this is what I write about
in a chapter called the ocean of
suffering, where, after I'd gone
through ego death, and after I
continued to go deeper, I began
to get drawn into vast fields of
human suffering, just terrible,
terrible anger, terrible
torture, terrible pain and
suffering. And it went on for
two years, just huge tracks of
human suffering. And eventually,
at first, I saw this essay, a
refining of ego death as sort of
another layer of the death of my
own ego. But eventually I came
to the conclusion that this was
wrong, that this was not
something aimed at my personal
transformation at all. It was
aimed at the transformation of
nothing less than my entire
human family, that somehow, in
these experiences, in these
sessions, if you're if you're
willing to go, go there by
bringing into your consciousness
the suffering of humanity in
some way, shape or form, if
you're willing to let the
suffering of humanity come into
your full consciousness and
remember that by saying your
consciousness, I'm not talking
about Chris Bache, his narrow
personality consciousness,
because at this point, your
consciousness has expanded to
much, much, much larger
dimensions. So it is as if you
are the species, remembering the
species pain and reliving the
species pain. And if you do
that, you there is a
transformation that takes place,
which registers within your
individual awareness. But it
also, I think, registers, and
this is the hypothesis, but it
registers within this, the
awareness of the human species
as a whole, that I think we are
actually working to heal
humanity of some of the trauma
that it's carrying. Just as an
individual carries the scars of
his or her trauma, the species
carries the scars, all the wars,
of all the terrible things we've
done to each other, all the all
the terrible things we've done
to each other, is still carried
in the collective psyche. So for
two years, I was processing this
pain, and let me back up in
every session, there's a
purification part and there's an
ecstatic part, right? So it's
not like there was nothing but
pain and suffering from all
these sessions. There were
several hours of pain and
suffering, and then they would
come to a culmination, and I
would go through some type of
dying process, and then I would
be spun out into ecstatic
Transpersonal spaces where I
would be given more instruction,
more opportunities to learn and
grow. So it was always a rhythm
of purification, personal or
collective, followed by ecstatic
instruction, personal or
collective, right? And then
eventually. And after two years
of working in the ocean of
suffering, I went through a
profound culmination of that
process, hard to describe, but I
do the best I can in the book.
And then it stopped. It never
reoccurred. And I was operating
from that point on, I was
operating beyond the collective
psyche level, beyond the level
of the of the collective
unconscious. I was catapulted
first into archetypal reality,
and had spent a year and a half
exploring different dimensions
of archetypal reality. And then
there was another death and
rebirth process which catapulted
me into what some thinkers would
call causal reality, the reality
of oneness, where you begin to
explore what life is like. In a
sense, you might say what life
is like from the perspective of
the Divine or from the
perspective of the creative
intelligence itself, because the
creative intelligence has
manifested itself in the body of
the universe, and there is
divisions and diversity in the
universe, but within itself,
there is a oneness which has
never been shattered, which is
not divided, and you can
dissolve into that oneness. And
when you dissolve into the
oneness, you experience all of
reality functioning as an
undivided whole, different you
know, different colors,
different textures, different
qualities, different beings, in
a way, but underneath those
differences a fundamental
wholeness. And then there was
yet another series of deaths and
rebirths. And then I was
catapulted into yet another
level of reality beyond call. So
level reality. So the last, the
last thing I treat in the first
chapter of the book, where I'm
introducing the method, is my
primary concern I have for
readers of this book, and that
is the quantity of suffering
that it tells and
and it's not because I'm a
sadomasochist. It's not because
I enjoy suffering. I'm like any
ordinary person, I'd like to
avoid my suffering. Thank you
very much. But the suffering is
part of a cycle of purification,
and once you learn that the
deepest breakthroughs and the
deepest insights come after the
deepest purifications, and you
learn that rhythm, that there is
purification and then
breakthrough. Then you surrender
to the suffering willingly, in
order to be of use to the
system, to be of use to the
universe, but then also to
receive the blessings that are
waiting for you when you go
through that process that are on
the other side of that
suffering.
Nick Mather: Okay, yeah, and
yeah, that answers a lot of
questions, because it answers
why. You know, you write that
you know, creation is a choice,
and we all voluntarily
participate. We choose to take
this on. But there's always a
blessing. There's always a
blessing. After all of this,
which I think is phenomenal, let
me ask you, the subtitle of the
book, which you refer to as the
inner title, is the diamonds
from heaven? Yeah, are these
diamonds from heaven? Are Is
this the blessing? Is this the
gift that we get from going
through this process?
Chris Bache: Well, there are
many blessings that come in this
work, the many blessings of
insight, of transformation, of
opening and deepening. But the
phrase diamonds from heaven, I
use in a more specific way after
I had been doing this work for
15 years, and I was had worked
through all the layers of ego
death and then collective
species, ego death and archetype
of reality and causal level
realities. I was catapulted. I
went through yet another
Death-Rebirth process, and I was
catapulted into a dimension of
consciousness, or a dimension of
reality which was pure light,
clear, clear, clear, clear,
crystalline light. I had
experienced light as many
psychedelic voyagers do at
different levels of one's
journey, but this was when I
call it diamond consciousness,
or. I'm in Luminosity. I'm not
simply using a metaphor to
describe the light. I'm trying
to describe a particular quality
of light, ultra, ultra, ultra,
clear, clear, beyond
imagination. And over the last
over the next five years, the
last five years of my work in 26
sessions, so about a third of
the entire sessions of the of my
journey, I was taken into this
diamond Luminosity four times.
And in between those four times,
there's lots and lots of
purification, many lessons and
many teachings, but lots of
purification. And it's those
four sessions and the immersion
in the diamond Luminosity on
those four days, which I
consider the greatest diamonds
from heaven. They are the true
diamonds from heaven. They are
the, for me, the most important
takeaway the domain I entered
when I looked at the religious
literature to try to find the
closest thing that would
correspond to this. Of course,
the Divine is always imaged as
light, which is relevant. But in
Buddhism, they talk about
Dharmakaya, this dimension of
reality, Dharmakaya, and they
call it the clear light of
absolute reality. It is the
light out of which the Big Bang
emerges, and that, I think, is
what I was experiencing in what
I call the diamond Luminosity.
Nick Mather: There were a lot of
the cosmology that you present
seems to be very Buddhist, in
many ways, there's, there are
clearly some differences, you
know, especially with the
reincarnation to that. You know,
the goal is not to enter party
in Nirvana, but to continue
evolving. I wonder, are there
any other differences? I mean,
do you feel that this, in many
ways, confirmed much of
Buddhism? Or, you know, what are
the what would be the
differences?
Chris Bache: Well, I've really
been deeply influenced by all
the religions of the world. I
mean, I taught world religions
for decades, you know. So every
semester I was going around the
world, exploring so I've been
deeply influenced by
Christianity, and I I began life
as a Christian and as a
Catholic. I actually was in the
seminary for four years studying
to be a Catholic priest, and the
two and I've learned so much
from Hinduism and Buddhism and
Taoism and some of the Native
American traditions, the two
which have been the most, the
deepest and long, lasting
influences on me, and Judaism, I
should add. I mean, I learned
Hebrew because I was doing
Biblical Studies in the early
years. I learned Greek, and
Hebrew have been Christianity
and Buddhism. And so I think my
my journey, affirms the deepest
truths of Christianity and all
the world's religions. I think
that affirms the deep truths of
of the Kabbalah and Judaism and
of Hinduism and Buddhism, and at
the same time, not just in in
reincarnation, the theory of
reincarnation that emerged in my
work, but in many ways, it
affirms, but it also eclipses,
the religions of the last
several 1000 years because I
think the the universe that I
was initiated into, the
opportunities that I was given
to explore the deep structure of
reality took me into, let's say
It demanded that I develop
levels of understanding that
went beyond anything that I had
learned or been exposed to in
these in the religions of the
world. And I began to, I was
forced to, sort of learn how to
become operational within an
even deeper metaphysics that
said, I think these experiences
do affirm the core truths of the
different religions. It doesn't
affirm the kind of the cultural
privilege that each religion
places on its own teacher, its
own lineage, its own revelation,
its own scripture. Those are
because every religion says its
scriptures are unique in the
Word of God, that tells us that
none of them are really unique.
All of them are part of a larger
dynamic process, but it affirms
the core insights of the
fundamental part the way we are.
Participating in each other's
reality that way, that we're all
hardwired together, and that our
deepest well being lies in
serving not just our small good
but the good of all, the good of
the whole, the value of self
sacrifice that you know he who
that it's worthwhile to
sacrifice for the good of others
when the opportunity calls for
us to do that, taking the long
vision, looking to the deep
future, orienting ourselves to
the deep future, opening our
consciousness to the inspiration
that comes from deep, deep
within not only our own being,
but that inspiration that arises
out of nature itself, at the
very, very deepest levels of
nature, as the Taoist would say,
to become one with the Tao you
know, that type of deep
inspiration. So on the one hand,
I feel very comfortable with the
religions of the world, and at
the same time, I feel where I've
ended up is in a place which is
larger than the than the
religions of the world.
Nick Mather: Yeah, I can see
that. And it's, you know, I've
been kind of asking this
question, and I touched upon
this a little bit ago, in terms
of feeling this call to ground
everything in spirituality. And
it's I feel like, and I know
others feel like this as well.
You know, where do you turn?
Because so many of the
traditions that we have don't
seem to answer or fulfill that
deep desire right now, yeah, and
you know, we can recognize, yes,
they have value, and led us to
this point. And, you know, I see
a kind of, and I hate the
clunkiness of the term, but a
kind of eco spirituality. But
I've also been thinking a lot
about in terms of like, and I
see others doing this, wanting
to reclaim a paganism, and I see
benefits to that. But something
that you wrote, and some things
that you were talking about that
I think that a lot of folks who
are considering this sort of Neo
paganism, they're looking at the
ancient gods not as actual gods,
but of archetypes. Yeah, and
yet, you mentioned at one point,
I think that this whole
experience, this journey that
we're on, there's going to be
new archetypes. And so I'm
wondering, and this is a huge
question, I don't know, and I
don't again, I don't know if I
can frame it as well as I would
like, but do you think that
these do you think that this new
spiritual vision is something
that is unfolding now it's I
don't know. I guess I'm looking
for advice to give people, and
maybe even for myself, in terms
of how to go about grounding
ourselves in in this new
spiritual experience and reality
as it kind of unfolds, and I
guess We're all probably
participants in the creation of
it.
Chris Bache: Well, you know the
movements that you mentioned, a
NEO paganism and ego
spirituality. I see both of
these movements as attempting to
put back into spiritual
discourse nature, which is what
was one of the two things lost
in the classic patriarchal
religions. You know, they're
trying to to bring us back to
the innate wisdom of nature,
which is a wisdom which runs
throughout our consciousness and
throughout our bodies, and
connects our body consciousness
to the body consciousness of
Earth and eco. Spirituality is a
way of being spiritual, way of
experiencing a form of
spirituality which connects us
to the planet and connects us to
the stars. And I think we can
see this also in the resurgence
of interest in astrology, not
kind of that a naive,
mechanistic understanding of an
astrology, but the vision that
the universe has a pulse to it.
The galaxies have a pulse, and
our solar system has a pulse to
it. And if you really know how
to read that pulse, you can kind
of feel how your body and your
destiny. Reality unfolds in
rhythm with the pulse of the
solar system. And that's a form
of eco spirituality, of solar
spirituality, of galactic
spirituality. So I think there,
there is a lot of
dissatisfaction with traditional
forms of religious spirituality.
I think psychedelics are very
interesting in that respect. I
mean, psychedelics have come
along at precisely this time.
Hold on. Suddenly, got a word
that my computer is about to go.
There we go. Psychedelics have
come along at a particular time
in history. Of course, they're
very old. They've been in South
America and in the Mesoamerican
and the Native American
traditions and the shamanic
traditions have been working
with psychedelics for 1000s of
years. But in our culture, in
our industrialized culture,
they're they're relatively
young, and so just that we're at
this point in history where we
are the most educated, we have
the most sophisticated science,
with the deepest understanding
of nature, but we've also bought
into the vision that the entire
physical world is devoid of
consciousness. It has no
consciousness. It's a giant
machine, and it's growing
randomly with just random
mutation. There's no
intelligence to it. There's no
intelligence. There's no purpose
to our lives. There's no purpose
to existence. It's just, it's
just blind matter spewing out
more complex blind matter. At
precisely that point in time,
these mind openers have been
dropped into our laps, and
they're giving highly educated
people, highly scientifically
informed people, the experience
of the the lie that that is a
lie. They're they're being given
the experience of the truth that
our consciousness and our very
existence is the result of an
intelligent action. That the
universe is intelligent. In
fact, it's so intelligent that
all the previous visions of its
intelligence are inadequate, all
the visions of prophetic
revelation and how we have
envisioned that intelligence are
totally child's play compared to
the reality itself. So
psychedelics, if we use them
carefully and constructively, it
can give us direct experience of
layers and layers and layers of
this intelligence and that that
that ruptures this vision that
it's all pointless, it's all
purposeless, and that when we
die, our consciousness
disappears. As soon as our
brains go, it opens up the eye,
the experience that the universe
is a living intelligence. And if
the universe is alive, that's an
aliveness that we might want to
merge with, to enter into
conscious communion with. So it
reanimates this interest in
vision, quest of you know,
immersing ourselves in solitude,
in nature, immersing ourselves
in meditation, where we go
deeper. We sink deeper and
deeper into our consciousness,
until we drop out from
underneath the floor of our
individual consciousness and
enter into communion with the
deeper consciousness, which all
spiritual traditions have told
us it's there, but now we can
actually accelerate our
immersion into it. So I think
there are many, many things
going on all at the same time.
All of us are kind of helping us
break out of the husks of where
we have been growing in the
past, and exposing us to all
sorts of new ideas, which are
giving us tokens of where we are
going in the future.
Nick Mather: Yeah, wonderful.
And I think that that is
actually, I'm mindful of the
time that's, I think, a
beautiful place to end.
So let me ask, I know that you
have a website, Chris bache.com
is that the best place for
people to find out more about
you and your work.
Chris Bache: It is and as of
this moment, that website is not
finished, but it's almost
finished, and that is generally
the best place for people to
find me or to connect with me.
You can also go to a website
called academia.edu it's where
academics post articles have
published. And if you search for
my name there, Chris M Bache,
you'll come to my page. And so
my most important publications,
articles and things like that,
will show up there. But soon. My
website will be done. It'll be
finished, and that'll it'll have
all my publications, and it'll
be an easy place to keep track
of me and for us to dialog.
Nick Mather: Okay, wonderful.
And I know that your books are
all widely available on Amazon
and bookshop.org if you don't
want to make Jeff Bezos any
richer than he is. And is there
anything that you have coming up
that you would like the
listeners to know about?
Chris Bache: You know, after
holding my silence about
psychedelics for so many
decades, the conversation that
I'm having now is about
psychedelics now I don't think
my experiences are more
important than other people's
psychedelic experiences, but
they are my experiences, and so
they're the best thing that I
have to offer the psychedelic
conversation at this time. And
so what I am doing is hosting
conversations around LSD in the
mind of the universe, six week
conversations which are just
beginning, and those will be
announced on my website for
there for people who have read
the book and want to have
conversations around the themes
of the book, not necessarily
Around my experiences, but
around the themes that were
touched in those experiences.
And I want these conversations
to be useful and available to
not only to psychedelic
initiated people, but also to
people who are not
psychedelically initiated. I get
lots and lots of emails from
people who have said, I
understand what you're saying. I
completely agree with you. I've
had many of the same
experiences, and I've never done
psychedelics at all, and that's
the way, that's what you would
expect, because psychedelics
don't give you an experience.
They amplify consciousness, and
it's got consciousness that does
the work. So of course, there
are other ways of working with
consciousness to access these
very, very deep states. So
conversations of with LSD in the
mind of the universe. And, you
know, I'm just, I go where I'm
called. You know, if people want
to work together or invite me to
go to different places, then
I'll show up. But otherwise I'm
I'm comfortable just being
relaxed and growing old.
Nick Mather: Very good. Well.
Thank you so much for your time.
I thoroughly enjoyed this
conversation, and I look forward
to everything you're doing in
the future, and your work has
been very profound for me. So
thank
Chris Bache: you, Nick. I really
appreciate it. I've really
enjoyed our conversation today.
Thank you for the opportunity to
talk with all your viewers.
Nick Mather: Okay, well, thank
you, and that's a wrap on
episode two of rebel spirit
Radio. Thank you so much for
listening. If you enjoyed this
podcast, please make sure to
give it a positive review on
Apple podcasts Spotify, or
whatever service you use to
listen to podcasts, your reviews
really do help, and please
consider subscribing. For those
viewing on YouTube, please give
this video a thumbs up and
subscribe to the channel. Make
sure you hit that notification
bell so you will be kept in the
know regarding upcoming
episodes. For the time being,
I'll be releasing episodes every
other week, with the goal of
releasing them every week in the
near future. Also, please
consider making a donation via
Patreon. You can make a one time
donation or join as a sustaining
donor with three levels of
membership. Available details
can be found@patreon.com forward
slash rebel spirit. Your support
makes this podcast possible. I'm
Nick Mather, and you've been
listening to rebel spirit radio
until next time, may you be in
peace and flourish in all
possible ways.