Donna Loeffler: Hi everyone.
Welcome to LSD and the mind of
you of the universe, with author
Chris Bache. The format of this
meeting is going to go as
follows, I'm going to introduce
everyone, then the we're going
to have a Q and A and as John
said, just put your question in
the chat. Let us know who it's
directed to, and we'll try to
answer as many questions as we
can. Our panel, Teresa and David
are have some questions that are
going to be asked first, and
that will be, basically be the
format. So I have the honor to
introduce Chris Bache. We are so
happy he is here with us today.
He's here from North Carolina.
He is a professor emeritus in
the Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he
taught for 33 years. He is also
adjunct faculty at the
California Institute of integral
studies, Emeritus fellow at the
Institute of Noetic Sciences,
and on the advisory board of the
Grof legacy training. Chris's
passion has been the study of
philosophical implications of
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, especially
psychedelic states, an award
winning teacher and
international speaker. He has
written four books, life cycles,
a study of reincarnation in
light of contemporary
consciousness, research dark
night, early dawn, a pioneering
work in psychedelic philosophy
and collective consciousness,
the living classroom, an
explanation of collective fields
of consciousness and teaching
and LSD in the mind of the
universe, the story of his 20
year journey with LSD. Chris is
a father of three, a vaccineer
and lives in Weaverville, North
Carolina, welcome Chris, and
thank you so much for being here
today.
Chris Bache: Thank you Donna, my
pleasure, and thank you everyone
for spending part of your Sunday
with me. It's a pleasure to be
here, a pleasure to talk about
these things, and I'm really
looking forward to our
discussion that follows my
comments here. So let me first
shift us into share screen so I
can throw this PowerPoint up and
people can let me know if this
is coming through correctly.
John, we're looking good.
John Hock: We are looking good.
Good.
Chris Bache: All right, what I'd
like to do today is simply take
you into some of the highlights.
It's kind of a highlight reel of
my book, LSD, in the mind of the
universe, As Donna mentioned,
I've written four books, but all
of them come out of my
psychedelic work, and all of
them, and this book summarizes
the entire trajectory of my 20
year journey working with LSD. I
consider it probably the most
important book I will write in
my life, and it's an honor to
share it with you here today. So
let me give you some background
when I came out of graduate
school in 1978 I was a
philosopher of religion and kind
of an atheistically inclined
agnostic, and I was looking for
where to take my research next.
And it was at that juncture that
I met the work of Stanislav
Grof. Let me get my picture out
of here, a little bit of Stan
Grof and this book changed the
course of my life. All right,
come on. Get to me. Here we go.
Here we go. These two books,
realms of the human unconscious,
which Dan had just published two
years before, and LSD
psychotherapy, his manual on
conducting psychedelic sessions.
I immediately saw not only the
psychological significance of
Stan's work, but the
philosophical significance to
actually be able to explore
experientially the deep states
of consciousness that allow us
to experience the deep structure
of the universe itself that
immediately I recognize had
profound philosophical
significance. So what I did was
to split my life in half. During
my day job, I continued to teach
at the university. I was
teaching in a Department of
Philosophy and Religious
Studies, doing the things that
professors do. And in my
nighttime job. I began a 20 year
journey working in Stan Grof
protocols with high doses of
LSD, recording all my
experiences systematically.
Yeah, that's that's the back
story to the book. Now, as you
know, instead. Dan's work, he
differentiates clearly between
low dose psyche therapy and high
dose psychedelic therapy. Low
dose, maybe up to 100 sessions
unfolding the mind gradually,
layer by layer, psychedelic
therapy limited to three
sessions designed to trigger
something approximating a near
death episode experience for
people who were facing death. So
after three introductory
sessions, medium dose sessions,
what I eventually chose was to
work in the high dose
psychedelic therapy protocol. I
eventually did a total of 73
high dose sessions, and I tried
to be as systematically,
systematic and rigorous as I
could. I followed the same
protocol in all these sessions,
the same sentence, setting, same
sitter, same substance, same
dose level, same recording
process and even the same
location working in Northeast
Ohio, I mentioned that because,
as you know, sometimes the
setting in which we do our work
can influence the nature of the
experiences itself. So this was
a long, sustained inquiry into
the deep structure of
Consciousness in the Universe.
Now, I saw myself, at the time,
simply doing an extended course
of psychedelic therapy, but when
I got to the end of my journey
and I was looking back, I
realized that this was more than
simply psychedelic therapy, that
I was encountering phenomena and
dealing with challenges that
were not being addressed or had
not been addressed in the
psychedelic therapy literature.
And so eventually I named this
particular protocol, psychedelic
exploration. The protocol the
methodology, is that of
psychedelic therapy working in
isolation, protected with the
sitter, eye shades, headphones,
the whole nine yards. The usual
thing, the difference is the
number of sessions. The high
number of sessions allow, turns
this into something more than
therapy, into an exploration of
the deep structure of the
universe. So of course, there
are many uses for psychedelics.
We use psychedelics for many
different purposes, for
recreational purposes or to
augment creativity. Let me
mention just three purposes that
stand out in my world. One of
them is, of course, therapeutic
healing, as this picture from
map shows which is generating so
much attention in the literature
and so much important attention
in this new renaissance. The
second use is for spiritual
awakening, as we see reflected
in this dialog between the
Buddhist community and the
psychedelic community. Zigzag
Zen the use of psychedelics to
facilitate a spiritual awakening
into one's deeper essential
nature. And this is actually why
I got started in psychedelics
myself, was to accelerate my own
spiritual transformation
process. The third is
cosmological exploration, and
this is what my journey turned
into, cosmological exploration.
And by this I mean not simply
collecting insights that arise
whenever we open in a
psychedelic state, as always
happens, but the systematic
pushing the boundaries of
consciousness again and again
and entering into deeper and
deeper communion with the
consciousness that lies within
and behind the universe itself.
I kept detailed, careful notes
of all my sessions, writing up
every session within 24 hours,
track the dates of my sessions.
Of course, even looked at the
astrological variables of my
sessions, exploring correlations
that Stan and Richard Tarnas
have proposed. Now, few more
introductory comments before we
jump into the book itself. The
story that I'm telling in LSD in
the mind of the universe is not
primarily a personal story. It's
primarily a cosmological story.
I found that this series of sine
waves represents a series of
psychedelic sessions, which I've
drawn overlapping in order to
emphasize the continuity that
runs between our sessions. I
found that insights into my
personal life tended to arise in
the beginning and endings of my
sessions, when I was leaving and
and coming back to times. Based
reality working in this
modality, and I worked at 500 to
600 macrograms, which, as I
explained in the book, is a
protocol that I don't recommend
working at such high dose
levels. When I was in my peak
hours of my sessions, I was
usually operating far beyond my
personal reality, at least after
the first 10 sessions or so. So
sometimes an entire session was
given over personal healing, and
sometimes I would be shown
certain correlations between
what I was being seeing and what
I in my own personal life. But
for the most part, when I was in
my sessions, I was operating at
a state of consciousness that
far outside my personal
consciousness, and When I've
tried, when I've written down my
experiences, I
uh, unmute.
Donna Loeffler: Hold on, Chris,
you're muted. Hold on, hold on
one moment. Okay, there you go.
Chris Bache: Okay. I actually
filtered out a lot of my
personal experiences or
experiences of personal healing,
because I did not consider them
primarily important to the story
I wanted to tell. If you're
writing about therapeutic
psychedelic use, then your
personal experiences are, of
course, absolutely essential.
But I was really functioning as
a philosopher of consciousness.
I wanted to explore the deep
structure of consciousness. All
of us have a story. All of us
have a personal story, but this
personal story tends to fall
away the deeper one enters into
the cosmological journey. Now I
found that let me get some
reason I'm losing contact. Yeah,
let me back up just a second. I
found that there was a
continuity between my sessions,
that one session tended to start
to end and the next one would
start exactly where the previous
one had ended, more or less,
with some varying degrees of
overlap. And in that process, I
found that one I went through,
not one, but a series of
Death-Rebirth experiences. In
this graph, everything below the
line is time, space reality and
our consciousness functioning in
time. Space reality above the
line is Transpersonal
consciousness when we enter
spiritual reality. And of
course, when one makes this
transition from time space
consciousness to spiritual
consciousness, one goes through
an ego death experience, which
Alex Gray has illustrated so
powerfully in this picture,
which I like very much, a
complete loss, a complete
destruction of one's individual,
ordinary, conscious identity.
What I found on my journey was
that as I continued to press the
limits of my consciousness, I
went through not just one type
of Death-Rebirth experience at
the egoic level, but a series of
Death-Rebirth experiences, and I
began to understand that death
and rebirth is a cycle that
repeats itself as you enter
deeper and deeper levels of
consciousness. And if we use the
vocabulary that Stan uses as we
enter psychic, subtle and causal
levels of consciousness. Now, I
don't have any vested interest
in any particular metaphysical
ladder or description of these
deeper states of consciousness.
The in my experience, the
universe is infinitely deep. One
can enter hundreds of levels of
consciousness. This is simply of
the articulation of a principle
that, as we stabilize
consciousness at one level, when
we go deeper, we have to go
through yet another cycle of
complete surrender in order to
enter into the initiation that's
possible at this deeper level of
consciousness. In some ways,
working particularly with high
doses of LSD, has been compared
to a nuclear bomb. The nuclear
bomb was created in the same
decade that LSD was created, but
a long sustained series of
psychedelic experiences focused
in a therapeutic modality,
triggers, as it were, a
sustained nuclear explosion, not
only destructuring reality as
you have known it, but
introducing you. You into deeper
and deeper levels of reality,
the way this nuclear explosion
exposes deeper levels of the
atmosphere that were always
there but had been invisible
until this nuclear explosion
brought them into our awareness.
Now we're not talking about
nuclear bombs, of course. We're
talking about this beautiful
universe that we are part of,
100 billion galaxies, billions
of stars in our own Milky Way
galaxy. So I'd like to use this
picture now as the backdrop to
talk about some of the turning
points on my journey and some of
the levels of reality I entered
when I was looking back over the
whole of my journey and trying
to create the structure for the
telling of the story. I
identified five core levels of
consciousness, are core cycles
of death and rebirth that I went
through, one having to do at the
level of personal mind, personal
consciousness, the second
collective mind, or the species
mind, the third archetypal mind,
the fourth operating at the
level of call, so oneness, or
the one and the fifth diamond
Luminosity. So this is the
organization I used in actually
creating the travelog that's in
the book. So let me back up and
simply pull out the chapters or
take you through the book,
identifying the sequence of
experiences. Can't talk about
them very much in the brief time
we have, but just give you some
sign posts. The chapter dealing
with personal mind is the
chapter two, crossing the
boundary of birth and death.
This is, in my experience, this
was like classic perinatal
Death-Rebirth process. I felt
like a poster boy for Stan Grof,
description of the perinatal
process, very intense
convulsions, very intense
confrontations with the
meaninglessness of life, with
the limits of existence,
eventually, after, in the course
of two years and 10 sessions,
coming to a point where the
universe just snapped me like a
twig. It just basically broke me
in half, and it did that by
forcing me to become the exact
opposite of everything that I
had known myself to be. I
entered this work as a male,
white, male academic,
passionately interested in the
meaning of life. I became the
exact opposite of that. I became
hundreds of women, women of
color, women who have no
interest in philosophical
inquiry at all. It was just it
was a terrifying ordeal, and
when I let go and I surrendered
to that ordeal, I was then
flipped into the positive side
of women's experiences and taken
on the most extraordinary
journey of women's experiences
under the arm of the great
mother. Now I believe in
reincarnation. I believe we all
have had lives as men and women
and but this wasn't simply an
encounter with my previous lives
as women. The message here was
not embrace your former lives.
The message was where you are
going. Gender does not exist.
Let go. And when I let go of my
identity as Chris Bache, as I
had known myself, I entered into
the beginnings of a deep
conversation with the universe,
a deep communion with the
universe. And I thought, after
having gone through this very
deep ego death, that my
suffering was over then, now
that I would just be introduced
to a banquet of cosmological
insights. But that's not what
happened at the level of
collective mind. There are
several chapters here. Now I
divide my sessions, or my
sessions divided themselves into
two halves, a purification, a
purifying stage, our cleansing
stage and an ecstatic stage in
the sessions. In the two years
following the crossing the
boundary of birth and death in
the in the purifying stage, I
began to enter levels of of
reality that involved hundreds
of 1000s of people, 1000s and
1000s of. Years a vast domain of
terrible anguish and suffering
and violence. I was brought back
into this domain consistently
and taken deeper and deeper into
it. At first I thought this
represented a deepening of my
ego death. But this went on for
so long and it involved so many
people in such excruciating
detail, that eventually I came
to a different conclusion. And
the conclusion was that somehow
in my sessions, my personal
reality, sort of, my personal
transformation, had been
exchanged or had been had been
surrendered, and became a
process of collective
transformation that the healing
that was taking place and the
uncovering of trauma that was
taking place was not about my
personal healing and not about
my personal trauma, but was
about collective healing, the
healing that our species has
collected over its 1000s and
1000s of years of history.
When I went into the ecstatic
portion of the same sessions, I
entered in what I called deep
time in the chapter, deep time
in the soul. I had a for one
year. I had a repeated
experience, seven sessions of
experiencing my life, from start
to finish, beginning to end as a
simultaneous present. I
experienced the beginning of my
life, the end of my life, all
the middle of my life as a
completed whole, as something
yet to be and something that was
already complete when I first
entered deep time. It was an
extraordinarily powerful and
moving experience to me, and
yet, when I came out of the
session, I lost it. I couldn't
remember it. But what I found
was that by going back into the
same state of consciousness
again and again, my experiences
in those states got clear, my
recall got more complete. I was
learning how to stay awake, stay
conscious inside deep time. And
this is an important
epistemological point when you
systematically enter states of
consciousness that are so far
removed from anything we know
inside time and space, it's very
hard to bring back all our
experiences intact. But if you
go back to the same state of
consciousness with rigor and
discipline, eventually your
consciousness adapts to the
unusual conditions, and you
learn how to stay awake in
states of awareness that
previously had simply swallowed
you. And this repeats itself, or
in my experience, it repeated
myself over and over and over
again when I would break into a
new state of consciousness, it
was very hard to retain
everything that I had
encountered, but with with
repetition, my recall got
stronger. Now, quick, just a
side comment. In my 20 year
journey, I worked for four years
I stopped for six years for
reasons given in the book, and
then I resumed for a very
intense 10 years. This is where
my journey stopped after four
years, and then I took a six
year hiatus, and when I began,
this is reported in the chapter
initiation into the universe
when I began the ocean of
suffering began exactly where it
had stopped six years before
without missing a beat, and it
continued to deepen and deepen
and deepen in intensity.
Meanwhile, in the ecstatic
portion of the session, I was
taken into an extraordinary
journey into the universe,
completely transcending anything
to do with my personal life that
was over now. It was as if the
consciousness guiding my
sessions was giving me a crash
course in cosmology. 101, now i
i give names to all my sessions.
I give names, I take notes, I
break them down into bullet
points. When I see the name, it
brings the entire session to
mind. My goal as a philosopher
is to hold my entire journey in
my mind at the same time. So the
names of the sessions that I
address in this chapter are as
follows.
All of these were operating at
the subtle level of
consciousness beyond the psychic
level of consciousness. They
were. All taking me deep into
this learning about how the
universe is put together. The
master plan was an initiation
into some of the core themes of
humanity's evolution. And I'm
going to come back to this
later. Eventually, the ocean of
suffering culminated in session
24 healing the collected womb.
The suffering that I was
absorbed into reached
unprecedented levels, and then
it culminated in this orgy of
healing, healing, this
collective pain, and then it
disappeared. And the collective
pain, the ocean of suffering,
never reappeared in any
subsequent session, we then went
on to the next level of work.
And the next level of work for
me involved an encounter that
took place at the archetypal
level of consciousness in the
chapter the greater real of
archetypal reality, so much that
I could say here trying to keep
it short so we can go into the
questions and answers soon, I
found that basically, I could
break down My experiences here
between two levels, one level
taking place at the highest,
subtle level, at the what you
might call platonic level of
consciousness, in which I
experience archetypes that lay
far, far beyond time and space.
But they were not archetypes as
Plato described them. Plato
describes archetypes as
unchanging, eternal ideas in the
mind of an of an eternal Deity,
I experienced archetypes as
vast, living processes so
radically beyond anything we
know of inside time and space,
anything I had known of that I
literally could not wrap my mind
around them, the closest I could
come to seeing them in any
coherent way was I saw them as
galaxies, which was simply the
best my mind could do to
approximate them. They were
operating in a different order
of time, a different order of
intentionality, and these were
the constitutive forces that
were responsible for creating
time and space and creating the
reality that was unfolding
inside time and space. At a
lower, subtle level, also at the
archetypal level, I entered what
you might think of as a union
level of consciousness where I
had repeated experiences of the
universe of this mind of our
species operating as a single
whole, one mind of the entire
species. And I was given
repeated lessons in how the how
this works. How is it that each
of our individual minds are
fractal aspects of the mind of
the species? How our individual
karma is part of our collective
karma? I began to have
experiences at this level of
collective reincarnation. That
is, I began to have experiences
of the entire species
incarnating, generation by
generation as a single unified
whole. Previously, I thought of
reincarnation in terms of the
individual, the story of the
individual soul, the story of
all of our individual souls,
choosing individual lives for
our individual development. But
here all this dissolved into an
experience of the entire species
as a single organism evolving
itself through a deep, profound
collective process, and all of
our individual lives were
fractal aspects of this deep
collective process. The
magnitude of what I was seeing
completely reframed my
understanding of the
intelligence operating inside
the universe and in our own
evolution these are the sessions
which I address in this chapter.
And I'd like to point out how
much cleansing is involved, even
at this high archetypal level.
Session 28 The fever is broken.
Was a very high my first
encounter with call so reality,
very pure, celestial state of
awareness, after which I was
plunged into three grueling
sessions of just excruciatingly,
excruciating purification. It
took me a long time to
understand what was happening
here, but eventually I began to
realize, to begin to understand
the following, that every step,
every deeper level of reality
functions at a higher level of
energy. And when you break
through to a higher, a deeper
level of reality, your entire
psycho physical system has to go
through a purification process
that will allow you to handle
the enormous flows of energy
that are operating at that
higher level of reality. This
repeated itself again and again
after I would have a major
breakthrough into a new level of
reality. The following session
was always kind of a carrying
out the garbage session. It was
always a session of deep
cleansing. So much so that I
began to dread the session
following a major breakthrough
session. Again. This is, this is
an insight that's important if
you, if you touch a deep state
of consciousness very briefly,
this may not manifest itself,
but if your goal is to have
sustained awareness at a
particular level of reality,
then you must go through this
cleansing ordeal, otherwise your
experiences at that deeper level
will be fragmented and you won't
be able to bring back a coherent
story. After moving into
archetypal reality, I then went
into what I came to understand,
this causal reality. Causal
oneness was an extraordinary
year of blessings, one blessing
after another. The four sessions
that I address in this chapter
are these. The forest was an
experience of Shunyata, what the
Buddhist call Shunyata,
emptiness of self, profound
transparency, no self in me, no
self anywhere in the world.
Experience the world as a
manifestation of diversity, but
complete interpenetration and no
separate self anywhere in
existence, singing the universe
away was an experience that
culminated in an experience of
the void, the fertile void out
of which all existence springs.
Jesus's blood was an experience
of profound, cosmic love, love
unlike anything I had ever
experienced up to this point in
time, the birth of the diamond
soul. Let me just linger there
for just a second, the
traditional teaching of
reincarnation. This was about
reincarnation. The traditional
teaching here is that when we
achieve a certain state of
spiritual maturity, we awaken to
our spiritual essence, and at
that point, then we leave time
and space. The Hindus call
awakening spiritual awakening
moksha, to escape Samsara to
escape cyclic existence. When
one reaches spiritual maturity,
one then Transcendence, time and
space. You can leave Samsara.
You can enter the Pure Land. You
can enter the Garden or enter
Heaven. In this experience, in
session 38 I was given a very
different model of
reincarnation. I began to
experience all my former lives
coming into me very quickly, and
it was like wrapping a filament
of white light around a kite
spool. And at some point,
all these lives fused, and there
was a huge energy generated, and
it catapulted me into a state of
consciousness beyond any that I
had experienced up to that time.
I was both an individual, but I
was an individual beyond any
frame of reference that I had
imagined previously. And I came
to understand there was when I
this happened. There was an
explosion of diamond light from
my chest, and I was given a
series of teachings that this is
where reincarnation is taking
humanity. We're not simply
growing incrementally, lifetime
by lifetime, year by year,
century by Century, making
incremental improvements in our
developmental sequence, becoming
more bit by bit, actualizing our
innate potential. Eventually we
come to a point where all of our
former lives merge, we
experience our soul. Now I think
this happens when we die and we
return to spirituality, but the
birth of the diamond soul is the
birth of soul conscious.
Consciousness inside our
physical incarnation. I think
that humanity is evolving in a
direction where eventually every
human being born will be born,
not into a contracted, egoic
consciousness, contracted into
our time space person, but every
human being will be born as a
soul more conscious, fully
conscious of their past, and in
a much deeper communion with
surrounding spiritual reality.
From here, my sessions took me
next into the diamond Luminosity
material in the chapter called
Diamond Luminosity. Now this
chapter covers 26 sessions and
four years of work. And in those
four years, I entered this
state, which I call diamond
Luminosity, four times and only
four times, I entered a state of
reality that was beyond anything
I had previously touched. It was
exceptionally, exceptionally
clear, luminous reality I had
touched light many times before
I had been taken into light many
times before, but this was a
higher order of light than any I
had previously known. And when I
call this light the diamond
Luminosity, I'm not simply using
a metaphor to describe the
light. I'm trying to describe a
particular register of light, a
particular quality of light.
I've learned that light has
many, many levels to it. There
are many gradations of light,
and this was an exceptionally
pure state of luminous
awareness. I think that this is
what the Buddhists would call
Dharmakaya, the clear light of
absolute reality. In between
these four immersions, there
were, as you might guess,
repeated episodes of deep
cleansing, profound
purification, many personal
healings, and then coming back
into these states of hyper,
clarity. So much more that I'd
like to say here, but I'll let
it stop here and and move on the
ninth chapter. And I wish I had
written the book and put it in
this order, because this is the
order it really belongs. One of
the recurring themes that kept
coming up in all of my work,
going all the way back to the
chapter on the initiation End of
the Universe, was this master
story of humanity. I kept being
taken into the deep future and
being taken into the deep
structural evolutionary process
underpinning history, and I kept
being given a series of visions
about where humanity was in its
evolution and where we were
going. And what I've done in the
book is I've pulled all these
bits and pieces, rather than
address them bit by bit, I
pulled them together and
presented it into this one
chapter, the birth of the future
human. And let me say that when
I began this work, I never
imagined that I would be talking
about the birth of the future
human. I thought of this work as
personal transformation,
personal awakening. And yet I
think that this chapter may be
the most important chapter of
the book, because if the visions
shared here are true, they
concerned my children, my
grandchildren, your
grandchildren, all of the
children of our grandchildren.
The vision that emerged this
here is that humanity is coming
to a turning point in its long
evolutionary journey, a turning
point that will forever change
the conditions of life on this
planet. Here's the material I
address in this chapter, the
visions of awakening. I gather
all the snippets of bits and
pieces from these sessions that
covered over four years into a
series of six visions, which
basically are powerful visions
that are indicating that the
creative intelligence of the
universe is trying to awaken the
entire species, not simply
individuals, but the entire
species. Now for there to be a
profound collective awakening,
there must be a profound
purification. And in session 55
which took place in 1995 I was
taken deep into the future, and
I. Apologize for the seemingly
absurd nature of this
description, but if you've been
with me so far, you'll go with
me here. I hope I was taken deep
into the future and experienced
not as an individual, but as the
human species as a whole. I
experienced the death and
rebirth of our entire species. I
experienced the entire world
coming into a profound global
systems crisis that seemed to
have been generated by a series
of global ecological crises. Now
I was not informed on ecology at
this time, I was not at all
aware of the series of
ecological challenges that we
are facing, which we are all
quite aware of. Now. This was in
1995 so this is over 25 years
ago, and yet I was taken into a
future where I experienced
humanity being brought to their
knees, a radical loss of all the
certainties that we live with in
life, a complete loss of
control, just an absolute life
threatening, species
threatening, crisis that went on
for years, and yet, just when it
was at its worst, Just when it
seemed as if all was lost, the
storm passed, and when the
survivors picked themselves up
and began to reassemble, they
were different. They had been
changed profoundly at the core
of their being by the intensity
of the crisis that we had all
gone through, they were
different. Their hearts were
different. Their minds were
different. They began to
generate powerful patterns of
new patterns of civilization
based upon the new values, the
new understanding, the new
insights that had been awakened
in them during this crisis. So
much more to say there, but I'll
have to stop at that point. The
11th Chapter, final vision, is
the last year of my work, which
included one particularly
intense session, the most
radical strip down that I had
gone through in any of my
sessions, taking me far, far
into the future and giving me a
series of experiences of our
universe that seemed to be the
capstone of everything that had
taken place on my journey up to
this point in time. I won't try
to summarize it here, because
time is the clock is
relentlessly moving. And the
last chapter, which I don't
think you can see here, is
coming off the mountain in which
I describe what happened when I
stopped my journey?
Long story, I will say that this
was the hardest chapter for me
to write. It took me over a year
to write this chapter, because
when I stopped my journey, I had
been given so many gifts on this
journey, I thought that I could
simply withdraw and would
receive the blessings of all
these visions that I had been
given. I would you know, I had
been given the gift of a
lifetime as a philosopher, but
what I found over time was that
I was entering into a state of
deep existential sadness as I
sat with this and lived with it.
Over time, I realized that I was
suffering from a withdrawal of
intimate communion with the
divine fabric. I eventually
reached a point where I realized
I was simply waiting to die so
that I could return to intimacy
with the divine could dissolve
into the divine light again,
because once you've dissolved
into the diamond Luminosity,
time space can lose it can lose
its appeal. It took me years. It
took me about 10 years to
finally consolidate myself back
into time space in a way that
allowed me to live contentedly
within time and space and the
conditions of time space. And I
did so by grabbing my life and
focusing myself on living in the
physical world, in the continued
assimilation of the impact or
the implications of the visions
that I had been given. All my
books come out of my psychedelic
work. The work on reincarnation
comes out of my early work in
deep time, in the soul, dark
night, early dawn, though it was
published after. My Sessions had
ended. I did all this work
between 1979 and 1999 I talk
about my journey in dark night
early dawn, but I only talk
about the first half of the
journey. I really don't talk
about the second half. The core
theme of dark night early dawn
is the collective structure of
consciousness and the collective
import of our transformative
practices. And then I wrote a
book called The living classroom
in 2008 and very quickly, the
back story of that book is that
even though my students never
knew anything about my
psychedelic experiences, and I
did not talk about my
psychedelic work on campus for
obvious legal reasons, I found
that my students were being
impacted by my psychedelic work.
That they were there was a
ripple effect that the deeper I
went into the Unified Fabric of
Reality, it was as if the it was
center sending ripples of
transformation out around me,
and my students were being
impacted by those ripples.
Eventually, I had to study them.
I had to really understand more
deeply what was taking place,
what was happening. And I wrote
the living classroom, which is
about collective consciousness,
and I don't mention psychedelics
there at all, because
psychedelics are not the issue.
The issue is the nature of
consciousness itself, and it
doesn't make any difference
which transformational method
you're using. If you go deeply
enough into the structure of
consciousness, you will have
ramifications that will spread
out around you in 360 degrees.
All of these come out of my
psychedelic work, and it is
where we go here. Yeah. LSD, in
the mind of the universe,
diamonds from Heaven really
tells the core story of this
journey. Thank you very much for
letting me describe it to you
today.
Donna Loeffler: Thank you so
much, Chris. It does tell the
story in detail. It's an amazing
book. I highly recommend it,
especially after hearing this
talk, before we move on to the Q
and A, I'd like to introduce our
two co hosts and our CO one of
our CO hosts, Teresa is going to
ask a few questions, but I'm
going to give introductions
right now. Teresa Marie is a
certified coach and speaker on
neuroscience and consciousness.
She has a master's degree in
organizational development from
John F Kennedy University.
Teresa has spoken
internationally and has a TEDx
talk on what the dying can teach
the living. Teresa and Dr David
Jackson, an anesthesiologist co
facilitate psychedelic
psychotherapy sessions using
ketamine and other psychoactive
medicines. David uses his
medical, scientific and problem
solving nature to work with
clients to find the right
medicine, and Teresa supports
clients through the integration
work of the medicine. The goal
is to make clients conscious of
unconscious patterns that keep
them in the cycle of depression,
anxiety and addictions so that
they can experience personal
transformation. Their integrated
approach helps clients achieve a
more meaningful experience
existence rather Teresa. You
want to
Teresa Marie: say, hello, hello.
How are you? Okay?
Donna Loeffler: And Dr David
Jackson. Dr Jackson is an
anesthesiologist and functional
medicine doctor with his BSEE
from Rice University and MD from
Southwestern Medical School,
David developed his interest in
transform a transformative
mental wellness and entheogenic
treatment of addiction in a
family member after 30 plus
years of failed conventional
therapy, using his experience
with the practice of
anesthesiology, Dr Jackson has
developed specific means for
mitigation of undesirable
effects pharmacological
treatment, while developing
compounded therapies tailored
for optimal effect, timing and
safety. David emphasizes the
importance of interaction with
concurrent medications, age,
coexisting medical conditions,
medical and therapeutic history,
precision dosing, chemical
purity and safety through the
education of therapists and
clients. David partners with
Teresa for an integrative
approach to transformative
therapy for enduring results,
and offers telemedicine
consultation to determine the
best advantageous approach to
your wellness. Welcome David.
Unknown: Thank you, Donna, thank
you. Chris. Was awesome. Thank
you.
Donna Loeffler: Okay, at this
point, we're gonna go to the Q
and A and we're gonna start with
Teresa. Chris.
Teresa Marie: That was an
amazing talk, and I love it. And
I have to tell everybody his
book is really wonderful, really
wonderful. Can everybody hear
me? Okay, okay, great. So I
would love for you. You know you
worked with Stan Grof early on,
and you know you worked with an
awful lot of protocols and
things like that. And I know a
lot of people will indicate in a
lot of ways, that, okay, well,
can you get to these states of
consciousness other than through
psychedelics? So what? How would
you compare like Holotropic
Breathwork to your high LSD
sessions? Because you've trained
with him a little bit.
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, I've
not done any of Stan's training
in the Holotropic Breathwork. I
mean, train Stan as a colleague
that we've we've been in dialog,
and we've been on podiums
together. And I consider Stan to
be the primary intellectual
figure that I've been in dialog
with as I've unfolded my own
account. Yes, absolutely, one
can enter into these states
without using psychedelics.
Psychedelics are an amplifier of
consciousness. So in the end,
it's consciousness that does the
work. I've had many people write
me after this book has come out,
and say, I understand what
you're saying. I've had many
similar experiences myself, and
I've never used psychedelics.
I'm a lifelong meditator, so on
and so forth. As an academic,
I've taught courses in
comparative mysticism, and I've
studied, you know, the lives of
the great masters, the great
spiritual masters, who certainly
moved into these states and into
even deeper states of
consciousness. And clearly, all
the great masters, all honor to
the great masters. They've
always been my guides in this
process. So, yes, one can move
into these states without
psychedelics, but we're talking
about not just a few years of
work, or even a few decades of
work. We're talking about
lifetimes and lifetimes of
consistently working to push
these boundaries. The great
spiritual masters have been at
this for many lifetimes. My
sense is that Holotropic
Breathwork is a very powerful
evocative, you know, amplifier
of consciousness. I think it
basically, it can evoke states
of consciousness equally strong
to psychedelic states. I don't
know think that it would be I do
not have enough experience to
truly say this, but my
impression is, in talking with
many practitioners, that I would
think that Holotropic Breathwork
would be able to generate states
that are comparable to low or
medium dose LSD sessions, but
not high dose LSD sessions, not
the type of states of
consciousness that open in a
sustained series of such
sessions. But we're talking
these are points on the
continuum. I've had some very,
very deep experiences in
Holotropic Breathwork sessions
that were certainly in many
respects comparable to my
psychedelic experiences. Great.
Teresa Marie: Thank you so much.
Now you also talk a lot about
the future human, and you talk
about kind of that we're going
to go through a lot of
suffering. Okay, well, most
transformation tends to happen
in suffering, and it's kind of a
shame that it's that way. I
always say that, but it propels
us on. Can you talk a little bit
more about kind of what some of
your visions were? Because how
about have some of them come to
pass, since what you saw in the
90s, have some of them come to
pass? Or are you still waiting
for some of them to come to
pass? Because I think that, I
think a lot of people are really
interested in that. Yeah.
Chris Bache: You know, the
consistent theme in my sessions
was positive, that humanity was
coming to a turning point in
history, that humanity, after a
very, very long evolutionary
journey, was coming to a
decisive turning point that was
changing the course of history,
that there was we're coming to a
collective spiritual explosion,
and that this was being driven
from underneath this. It was, it
was a decision made at a
cosmological level, driving up
underneath us and surfacing in
our individual lives that we
were cooperating with, but was
much larger than the simply the
act of all of our individual
lives. It's really. Only, only
one particular session where I
was taken into the specific
conditions of our death and
rebirth, our collective death
and rebirth. And in that vision,
in that session, session 55 I
wasn't given any details. I
wasn't given any time. I wasn't
given any specific experiences
of like covid 19 or anything
like that, what I experienced
was the entire species of the
planet being brought to its
collective knees, being entering
a period of profound
compression, profound loss of
control, deep, deep existential
anxiety. Angst and just an
absolute almost hopelessness,
just being overwhelmed by the
conditions we were facing. And
then in the depth of that, in
some ways, a collective
Death-Rebirth process, like a
collective near extinction
event. And in that process, we
meta morphized, we changed. We
became more than we had been
before. Now, in many sessions
leading up to that, I was taken
into what I think are the nuts
and bolts of this, and that nuts
and bolts of this are
reincarnation. I think that we
have been evolving and
developing ourselves and
becoming more for 1000s and
1000s of years. And just as
gestation is a long, gradual
process of development, but
birth is a very short, cathartic
process, likewise, human
evolution is a long, gradual
developmental process, but the
birth of the next level of human
experience, the next form of
humanity, the birth of the
future human, which I think will
be the birth of the diamond soul
in history. That birth process
is, relatively speaking, short
and cathartic. I don't know how
long it will take. I would I
would anticipate that it would
take multiple generations. This
is an evolutionary pivot that
we're making. I have had
experiences where I was taken
into the future and allowed to
experience the future human,
experience the archetype of the
future human and those
experiences drove me into deep
ecstasy. It was some of the most
profoundly moving experiences of
my journey. Because we're we're
talking about a human, a
humanity healed of all the scars
of history, of all the terrible
things that we've done to each
other, a humanity with its
consciousness open, capable of
profound communion with the
creative intelligence of the
universe. I think we are going
through a developmental process.
We're coming into the hard part.
We're coming into the birth
process. And I think it's really
important for us to have a
vision of what this is all
about. Because when it starts to
get really bad, and I think
covid May be the overture of the
symphony of our transformation,
it is not itself sufficiently
powerful to bring about the
events that I that I experienced
in my sessions. But I think it's
an overture. It shows us. It's
teaching us a lot. It has taught
us a lot, if we're paying
attention a lot, that can be
very helpful when the deeper
crises come. And I think the
deeper crises are going to be
any number of forms of
ecological punctuated crises
that are going to hit us wave
after wave in the decades ahead.
Now we're getting a better sense
of what's coming at us. We can
see it with you know, we've got
good maps. Dwayne Elgin's book
choosing Earth gives a the next
five decades, breaks it down
decade by decade of the
challenges we're facing, there
any number of books that are
pointing this out to us, so I
think we can see what's coming.
The challenge is understanding
the evolutionary implications of
what's coming. Yeah, yeah,
Teresa Marie: I would agree.
Thank you. So there was a
question in the chat that asked
you about when you said the same
set and setting each and every
time, can you describe your set
and setting? For those who have
not read your book, I know what
the set and setting is, but you
know it would be really helpful
for you to explain how that
worked in your process.
Chris Bache: I do a lot of
preparation for every session. I
take good care of my body. I
make sure that my body is
relaxed and clear. I watch my
diet, particularly in the day
session day, personally, I would
always start in the morning. I
start in the early morning with
yoga and meditation. I was
always working either at home
or. In my wife's office. My
wife, then Carol, was a clinical
psychologist. She was my sitter
for all of my sessions. All my
sessions were focused on
spiritual intention. I found
that I tried experimenting with
setting an intention for my
sessions, but I found that
working with doses is high. That
basically was irrelevant. My
personal intention became
irrelevant, so that my intention
became one of absolute, complete
surrender. My prayer was
whatever you need. I give you
whatever the universe needed
from me on that day is what I
would give after the session. I
mean, I always wrote my sessions
up within 24 hours the next day,
I developed, the more frequently
you go into these states in a
sustained manner, the greater
the impact is on your subtle
energy system. I found that it
was really important to do very
active spiritual practice,
particularly after a session. So
later, when I was entering the
diamond Luminosity work, it was
during that time that my
spiritual practice became more
focused on Vajrayana Buddhism.
So I do specific practices
before a session and different
practices after a session. I
found that when I began to do
these Vajrayana practices, these
ancient practices that have very
old morphogenetic fields
associated with them, it had a
distinct impact on my journey.
It had it really helped
facilitate, not only the entry
into these deep states of
consciousness, but it helped me
absorb the insights and the
energy of the impact with these
deep states of consciousness. So
a lot of intentionality and
these experiences take a lot out
of your body. I mean, these are,
you know, huge you're subjecting
yourself to huge tidal waves of
energy. So careful preparation,
careful focus, and then very
careful debrief. It's absolutely
essential.
Unknown: Chris, you mentioned,
didn't you mention that music
was a pretty big part of your
journeys, at least in the
beginning, and the replaying of
the music afterwards to help you
with your recollections. Did you
feel like that's important, or
that is important even at that
level, your higher levels later
in your sessions?
Chris Bache: Yeah, I worked. I
used music in all of my
sessions, all the way through
very carefully selected music.
You know, there's we have
literature on the theoretical
approach to the stages of a
session, matching the stages of
the session with the music that
has qualities that match the
stages of sessions. I like never
working with music that has
English, if there are words at
all, it would have words that
you couldn't understand. You
don't want to trigger familiar
associations. I very quickly,
after a year or so, I let go of
classical music for the most
part, and used almost
exclusively indigenous music. I
found that to be much more
powerful evocative for me. When
I would write up my sessions, I
developed a strategy for
improving recall. I would listen
to the music that was played in
the session in exactly the same
order in which it had been
played, and I would keep playing
the same music over and over
again while I was writing up the
session, until I felt I had
captured what had happened
during that piece of music. Then
I would go to the next piece of
music and I would continue the
process. I found that playing
the music of the session while I
was writing up the session
allowed me to get a more
complete portrait down in print
of the session itself, and
really helped improve recall.
Thank you. Now I've also done
subsequent, I mean, after I
stopped my high dass LSD work,
of course, I've done other
sessions since then, sometimes
I've used music, sometimes I
haven't used music at all. I
understand. I understand just
opening up without music as well
as opening up with music, but
for me, working with high doses
of LSD, the experiences are so
intense, so extreme, I found
working with music to be a very
helpful adjunct to the opening
process.
Teresa Marie: Great. Thank you.
Also you, you mentioned in your
book too, that, of course, your
LSD doses were primarily between
five and 600 micrograms,
correct.
Unknown: Yes, yes.
Teresa Marie: And then you've
mentioned after you, of course
you had that down regulate where
you connect. With the divine.
And you you felt oneness of
everything and that amazing
consciousness state, and then to
kind of come back down here to
this state and this everyday
being can be a little
disappointing. And you'd
mentioned that you had tried
other, other psychedelic
medicines, and someone had
asked, you know, in the chat,
you know, I know you said you
tried Ayahuasca and Psilocybin,
but you didn't feel like they
were as powerful as LSD in your
journey. Can you express a
little bit as to you know why
you feel like that was the case?
Chris Bache: Well, there are
many, many psychedelics, of
course, 1000s of sympathetic
psychedelics, hundreds of
organic psychedelics. My sense
is that each psychedelic, while
having the common feature of
opening consciousness,
amplifying consciousness, each
psychedelic has a particular set
of qualities and activates, has
a potential to activate a
certain range of consciousness.
Serial usage over multiple
sessions can deepen that range,
but there's basically a certain
range and a certain quality. I
experience LSD as being kind of
what I would call a high ceiling
psychedelic. It tends to push
the cosmological ceiling,
whereas Psilocybin tends to be
much more body grounded,
emotionally saturated, tuning to
our physical body, tuning to our
emotional body, it has ceiling,
but it's my experience of it is
it tends to be a much more of
kind of an embodied, open to
state, rather than a potentially
disembodied open state, or far
from bodied, open state,
Ayahuasca, I've had limited
experience with, but it seems to
me similar, in that way, very
closely integrated with the
body, with the emotional body.
It has more headroom in my
experience than Psilocybin does,
though I have only initial
preliminary experience with
that. I have had some experience
with five Meo, DMT, very
different psychedelic, very
potentially profound,
catapulting psychedelic. The
challenge with that
particularly, of course, it's so
short acting, and that opens up
a whole nother area of
discussion, short acting
psychedelics versus long acting
psychedelics. And I discuss this
in the book. I think there is,
there are certain advantages.
There are clearly disadvantages
to the hassle of a long acting
psychedelic but there are some
advantages. It does allow the
kind of sustained contact with
these deep, Non-ordinary states
that leads to a purification of
the mind doing the exploration.
Short acting. Psychedelics don't
give you as large a window to be
changed and transformed by the
dimensions of consciousness that
you're contacting. This was
Richard trust Strassman
observations from his work with
DMT. He found, much to his
surprise, that while many of his
subjects had profound
experiences on DMT, it did not
result in very lasting change to
their personality structure, and
he thought it was because it's
very short acting. It's the
window which is important, which
is significant here. Thank you.
So I don't I think what I did in
my work was to drill an
unusually deep borehole into the
universe. But there's so much
that I didn't see, so much which
these other substances revealed
to us which I did not
experience. I mean Psilocybin
and Ayahuasca connect us to the
elemental world. They connect us
to the world of spirit. They
connect us to the the all the
levels of intelligence that kind
of live close to and saturate
time, space, reality, so many,
many levels that I did not
particularly engage or touch.
Teresa Marie: Okay, thank you.
So I know we have some questions
in the chat. So, David, do you
want to address some of the
questions in the chat? Thank
you.
Donna Loeffler: That was a
beautiful answer. Chris, I just
want to say that that was just
so well said. And I've got a
question, or John hawks got a
question, actually, David, while
you look, why don't we let John
ask his question? Go ahead,
John,
John Hock: couple quick ones,
actually. Well, this first one
may not be quick. I asked Stan
Grof at one point directly if
there was anything that he could
correlate a difficult trip with
and he said his work with Tarnas
and his own work turned up that
a hard transit to Mars to nail
Mars was the only thing he could
point to. That would predict a
difficult trip, and at the time,
he was still working with Rick
to go further. Now, I find it
fascinating that you charted
correlations while you were
doing your journeys, and I'm
wondering specifically, if
you've come what sort of
correlate, what things have
correlated astrologically and
specifically, has there been
something that would correlate
to a breakthrough, to moving to
a higher level?
Chris Bache: Yeah, good
question, and a complicated
question I'm aware of, and Rick
Tarnas is a good friend as a
Stan, and I'm aware of Stan's
writing in his analysis of
certain cases and and the
astrological correlations of
certain people going through
breakthroughs. I'm aware of the
proposal that the outer planets
correlating with the perinatal
matrices seem to be somewhat
predictive of the patterns of
oppression, contraction,
breakthrough and liberation in
people's experiences. I've
looked at these correlations in
my own work and on the one and
first of all, I completely
accept the proposal that they've
made. I understand it. I think
that makes sense the
intelligence of the universe
that I experience. It makes
intuitive sense that the rhythm
of the universe would be part of
the rhythm of this intelligence,
and that as we open up beyond
personal psyche, that there
would be this kind of this solar
system pulse to the nature of
our experiences that said, I
have not found correlations to
be as striking as I had
expected, and I have found that
as my work deepened over the
years that I could not correlate
breakthroughs and impasses with
astrological variables as much
as I had expected to do, and so
that led me to formulate a
hypothesis, and I call it the
roll off hypothesis, and that is
in the early stages of our work,
or when we're working at lower
doses, or In earlier stages,
when our time space identity is
being unfolded and impacted, I
think there'd be stronger
correlations between our natal
transits, the transit to our
natal chart, or even our global
transits. But as when works once
work deepens, when you begin to
go into and beyond archetypal
reality. When you're going
beyond time and space and deep
into the universe, I think that
there is a roll off effect of
the planetary correlates to
experience. At least, I found
that the dynamic relationship
with the universe, the way the
universe crushed me and kissed
me and drew me out and melted me
into herself. Did not seem to
correlate tightly with specific
planetary correlation. Sometimes
it did, sometimes it didn't. So
I think there is a roll off
effect. My proposal is that
there's a roll off effect of
astrological import. Now this is
an open question. I'm not an
astrologer, and this is
something I'm interested in.
It's an active dialog between
Richard Tarnas and myself about
this, about this issue. Yeah.
Thank you for that. This is why,
in my book, I actually put the
dates of all of my sessions, and
I give my birth information,
because I would like to
encourage this discussion of the
correlations between astrology
and our own psychedelic
experiences.
John Hock: Thank you very much.
So excellent, excellent answer,
and your hypothesis makes an
awful lot of sense. I'm going to
stop my questions now and let
other people open it up for
other people, there's a number
of very good questions in the
chat.
Donna Loeffler: So David, did
you? Did you have
Teresa Marie: one or Teresa?
Well, Rachel had a really good
question. I don't know if she
wants to ask it herself, but she
wanted to speak a little bit
more about how your
consciousness work has changed
and affected your life over the
time in your physical essence
right now. In other words, how
has that been transformative in
your life?
Chris Bache: Good question, hard
question to answer, and I'll
tell you one of the things that
really complicated things in my
particular instance, and the
thing that complicated it was
that I wasn't allowed to talk
about my work. I wasn't I mean,
I'm a teacher. I love to teach.
I love to learn and share what
I've learned. I'm a.
Philosopher, and yet our
psychedelic, phobic culture did
not allow me or give me any
platform to bring the deepest
philosophical experiences of my
life forward and mind them with
my students or with my
colleagues, to extract their
philosophical potential, so that
when I stopped my sessions, the
kind of the deep sadness I
entered was not simply a sadness
that came from withdrawing from
the cosmological communion, but
it was a sickness which was
generated by silence. I have not
been allowed to talk about this
work publicly, and as I wrote
the book, I began to experience
a number of changes taking
place, and as I began to speak
about the book, these changes
have deepened. I found my
sessions beginning to as it
were, come together and into a
larger aggregates, into a larger
whole, as I began to own my
sessions, to own my psychedelic
history and come out of the
psychedelic closet, the sessions
began, as it were, to saturate
me and soak into me at deeper
and deeper levels. And this
process is still continuing. I
don't know where it will go. I
live, I wish I could say, wow,
I've touched the oneness of the
universe, and I live in
perpetual oneness all the time.
You know, I live in this state
of ecstatic joy all the time.
But it's not like that. I think
that going into these temporary
states, and it's really
important to these are temporary
states. These are not the same.
They don't have the same impact
as touching these realities
after 30 years of contemplative
practice on the top of a
mountain. It's not the same
thing. These are temporary
immersions which are genuine and
you can't, you can't abide in
these states simply when you
come back when you're done, even
if you've done all your homework
carefully and even if you attend
to integration very
conscientiously. But they change
the trajectory of your
evolution. They change the
trajectory of your soul's
development. I live with an
understanding of reality that
allows me to open into a
prayerful engagement of reality,
which is certainly different
than I had in the beginning of
this journey. And I think that
late in my sessions are at the
end of my journey. Spirit said
to me two things. It said 20
years in, 20 years out, meaning
it would take at least 20 years
to assimilate 20 years of the
journey. And I think now I
thought at the time that sounds
about right now I'm thinking
that might have been optimistic.
I literally think it will. The
things that I've touched will be
unfolding over many lifetimes,
not simply one lifetime, but
it's changed the trajectory of
the evolution of my soul. The
other thing it said to me is,
there's the dying of seeing and
the dying of keeping. The dying
of seeing is the death and
rebirth process you go to when
you're being initiated into the
deep structure of the universe.
The dying of keeping is what you
do when you were in your
ordinary state of consciousness
back inside time and space, in
order to let those experiences
enter into and saturate you
deeper, more and more deeply
into your daily life. My
practice these days is primarily
contemplative practice, Buddhist
Vajrayana practice. I'm
basically kind of sitting still
and letting the universe come to
me. Come to me here, rather than
going out to meet it there.
Teresa Marie: Thank you. So I
know Donna, you said there were
a couple more questions in the
chat you thought were
Donna Loeffler: good. I do,
yeah. Andrew has a question for
Chris. And you know, Chris, none
of these are going to be easy
just because of the nature of
your work. How has your
understanding of the future
human changed or been reinforced
since first experiencing it in
the late 90s to the writing of
this book to the present day?
Yeah.
Chris Bache: It hasn't changed
one bit. I say in the book that
when I had the experience in of
session 55 the death and rebirth
of humanity in 1995 for weeks I
walked around one. Like I was
walking around Hiroshima a week
before the bomb went off. I have
carried in my being in my body,
a knowing of where we are in
history and what's coming. And
when I look around everyone
around me, whether I agree with
them, politically or socially or
not, I look at them and I see I
see heroes. I see every human
being who is here on this planet
has incarnated voluntarily, has
chosen to be part of this
evolutionary pivot. Every person
here, even though they may not
remember it at all, has chosen
to be here, and this is going to
be a very, very difficult period
to incarnate, and the beings who
are part of the Incarnation
process are just extraordinarily
Powerful, valuable beings.
Nothing has changed. I still
it's been interesting to watch
covid It's begin. It's been
interesting to watch ecological
awareness begin to grow and
ferment. And frankly, things are
coming to a head or happening
faster than I had expected. I
expect this decade, if
everything the scientists are
telling us this decade is the
last window we have to change
the trajectory of what's coming
at us, but if the past is an
indication, we're not going to
change as radically as we need
to change to avert this trauma,
and so I expect the patterns of
trauma to intensify in the
decades and decades coming, this
century is going to be an
extraordinary ordeal. It is
going to be the dark night of
our collective soul. But the
dark night of the soul is, of
course, a process of profound
purification, and we as a
species are purifying ourselves
extraordinarily rapidly. We're
purifying ourselves of all the
decisions we've made in history,
of all the choices we've made in
the past, our choices on how to
treat each other, our choices on
how to treat animals, our
choices on how to treat the
planet itself, all of these
choices are kind of coming at us
very, very fast and very, very
deeply. This is what I saw in my
sessions. This is what I've
carried. This is what I'm
carrying now. This is what I I
bring to my children and to your
children. And that is the vision
that what we are doing is
profoundly significant, and it's
important for every individual
to reach as deeply as possible
and as high as possible, and to
manifest their the noblest
intent possible. If the future
were moving in the same way at
the past, if we were using
linear understanding of history,
we might say it's the forces
arraigned against us are
overwhelming. It's just too
much. The individual can't do
anything. We're just going to be
swallowed whatever, by these
environmental processes. But
that's not what I saw in my
sessions. What I saw in my
sessions is that as the
suffering increases, the entire
psychic field of humanity, the
collective unconscious. That
collective psyche is going to be
increasingly pressurized. It's
going to be shoved into what
physicists call nonlinear
conditions. Are far from
equilibrium conditions, and in
far from equilibrium conditions,
individual perturbations produce
large changes, large outcomes,
which means that as we enter
deeper into our crisis of
history, individuals can have a
larger and larger share an
impact on the outcome, on how
this crisis will manifest. So I
think it's a time of individual
empowerment to facilitate deep,
cultural, profound social
transformation.
Donna Loeffler: Thank you,
Chris. Another amazing answer.
Again, I highly, highly
recommend this book. It's so
detailed, just an amazing work,
and we're almost at the end of
our time with you, Chris and
again, many thanks for being
with us today and presenting on
our platform. And just as a note
to everyone, everyone here is
not being paid. We're all
volunteers. Chris is here for
the love of the work. So is
David and Teresa. All of us are
if you find any of our content
valuable and you're able to
donate, we would much appreciate
it. And.