Vanese McNeill: Hello everybody.
This is vannice McNeil from
MAGICAL EGYPT, live. And today I
have a very special guest with
me. Chris is one of my favorite
people in the entire world. I
think that he has some of the
most important knowledge to
share with us, as well as
wisdom, and I'm also now
declaring that he's a prophet as
well. So welcome, Chris,
Chris Bache: happiness. I don't
know about the Prophet part, but
okay,
Vanese McNeill: well, sweetie, I
have to say things have got
interesting since we've talked
last, right?
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah, the
turbulence of this century is
certainly increasing, isn't it?
Vanese McNeill: It is indeed, my
dear. It is indeed, but it is
necessary, if I understand you
correctly.
Unknown: Well, you know, as I've
written about in my book LSD, in
the mind of the universe,
there's a chapter on the birth
of the future human, where I
summarize all the visions that I
was given through many years of
doing the deep psychedelic work
that I did. And I don't know
whether it is necessary, but the
vision simply showed me that
humanity was coming into this
period of profound spiritual
awakening, a major spiritual
turning point, a tipping point,
a bifurcation point that would
really change human history. But
then it also showed me that
going into this period, we were
going to be going through a
period of tremendous suffering,
a falling apart, an unraveling
of civilization as we've known
it, and that. But coming through
this, we would be changed
profoundly. We would tap into
levels of our core and actualize
potentials. That were really
have been realized only by
relatively few in history, but
now must be realized by the
entire population, a shift in
the collective psyche, not
simply our personal psyche. Now,
whether this is the suffering is
inevitable or meant to be or
something, I don't know. I only
report the visions that it's
going to be there, but it's not
going to be terminal. It's not
going to be extinction. It's
actually labor, and labor
results in a birth, and a new
birth is coming for the human
family. I
Vanese McNeill: mmm and labor,
why it's not fun is necessary
for this birth. And I also
believe that holding our hands
through this process, and that's
why I'm talking to you today, I
can see I'm breaking up. Am I
breaking up? My dear, can you
hear
Chris Bache: my end? Am I into I
hear you now?
Vanese McNeill: Okay, great. So
to the end of holding our hands
through this process, I would
love for you to share with us
all today a little bit about the
course that you have coming up.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to share the screen. All
right, okay, okay, so tell us a
little bit about this wonderful
Chris Bache: well, you're
breaking up a little bit, but
I'm going to assume that I can
just go ahead and talk now. You
know, I spent, after doing this
deep LSD journey for 20 years, I
spent another 20 years thinking
about my experiences, digesting
them, processing them, and
eventually writing down the
story of this journey in my
book, LSD in the mind of the
universe, or as I prefer to call
it, diamonds from heaven. And
now that this book has been out
about a year and a half, I'm now
beginning have been invited to
roll out this course with the
shift network, where we spend
seven weeks on the material
covered in the book. Everybody
who signs up for the course will
receive a free e copy of the
book so that they can read the
chapters as we go through them,
week by week through the course.
It's basically simply, I'm
inviting people to join me in
this journey to through our
conversations, through my talks,
through the Q, amp a, through
some visualization exercises,
inviting people to come with me
on this long journey spiraling
deeper and deeper into the
universe. Now I don't think my
experience. Experiences are
special or unique in this way,
many of us have deep psychedelic
experiences. I've tried to put a
lot of energy into clarifying
the concepts involved, and now
these experiences that the
course is built around are not
primarily personal. When I wrote
the book, I dropped out, a lot
of my personal experiences.
Tried to focus on the
experiences that were universal,
that were really addressing the
human family as a whole, are the
deep structure of the universe
as a whole, not my own personal
little garden of it. So in this
discussion, we go in layer by
layer, stage by stage, following
the rhythm of the journey
itself, the cycles of death and
rebirth, a death at one level of
reality followed by a birth in
another level of reality,
acclimating to this new level of
reality, learning the rules
they're receiving teachings.
There another round of death and
rebirth a couple of years later,
entering a new level of reality,
the same thing, repeating
itself, learning what's
happening there, learning what's
going on. And my hope is that by
taking this journey with me,
will generate a lot of value in
our conversation, in our
discussion, in the clarification
we can bring to really thorny
issues about why life is the way
it is, what is the purpose and
goal of our existence? And I
know it sounds grandiose to sort
of bring those categories in,
but I think if we my basic
understanding of psychedelics is
that it allows us to enter into
deeper communion with the
intelligence of the universe,
and that when we do that, the
universe will speak to us, it
will teach us, it will take us
in. It'll it will give us a
sense of the larger landscape.
And so I don't think that
anything I'm sharing is in any
way unique. I think it shows up
in the work of other psychedelic
assists Psychonauts. It shows up
in Stan grofs work. It's just
laid out in the very carefully,
man careful manner, and it allow
us to discuss some deep topics
that are you don't find
discussed very much. So that's
that's my hope for the course,
that's the agenda.
Vanese McNeill: I think it
sounds amazing, and I am very
blessed to have kind of a cheat
sheet here. But before we
actually go into that, I think
your point is is very important.
I think that for those who have
not read Chris's books or or at
least or possibly even not seen
a video, Chris's journey took
him through a personal journey,
a kind of expanded into
masculinity, or the male
journey, expanded into a human
journey, and the expansion just
kept going on. And so for most
of us, we
Chris Bache: you're breaking up,
back up and start again. For
most of us,
Vanese McNeill: oh, for most of
us, we barely get out of our
personal journey. I am so sorry
that this is so unstable,
sweetie. Why don't you give us a
taste, because you're not
breaking up. Give us a little
sneak peek.
Chris Bache: Well, we're going
to start with the first module.
There's seven modules. The first
module is going to be on
methodology. We really I'm going
to lay out the method, answer
people's questions, address
their misgivings about
psychedelics, explain what
psychedelics do and don't do,
and in specifically address the
particular protocol, which I use
because it was an extreme
protocol, a protocol that I
don't recommend, that others
adopt today. I would be gentler
if I were doing it again, but
it's an extreme protocol, and we
need to really address the
method as we move into then we
move into what happened when you
follow this method. The second
module is going to be on the
crossing the boundary of birth
and death, a letting go of our
egoic identity, time, space
identity, a process of
purification which culminates in
ego, death or the destruction of
the now, the destruction of the
consciousness that holds our
experience inside time and
space. And when I say
destruction, I don't mean that
we're going to permanently
damage the ego, but basically,
we have to allow the ego to fall
aside if our consciousness is
going to enter into dimensions
of the cosmos which are larger
than time and space and are
larger than our historical
experience of time and space. So
we talk about ego death in this
context, and then in that same
module, I'll be talking about.
The ocean of suffering work,
because I found that in my
experiences, at least working
with very high doses of LSD,
after I went through ego death,
I began to get in, drawn into
another round of purification of
dying. And it was not personal.
It was collective. It opened up
into 1000s and 10s of 1000s,
hundreds of 1000s of human
beings and 1000s of years of
time, it became a fundamental
riddle for me. It took me years
to figure out what was
happening, and the conclusion I
eventually came to is that this
purification process was not
aimed at my personal
transformation, but rather the
universe was using my sessions
to bring about a healing of some
aspect of the collective psyche,
some way of letting the wounds
of history, all the wars and all
the terrible things we've done
to each other and we've
experienced together droughts
and famines, that these wounds
still live within the collective
psyche, and somehow, by opening
up to these living memories in
my sessions, these these painful
memories, were being lifted from
the collective psyche. So we're
be talking about that, looking
at the material, looking at the
concepts that are involved. So
that takes us up to module two.
In module three, we then follow
the process into a deeper level
of reality, into archetypal
reality, into what I've
differentiate my experiences
there in two levels, which you
might call the Jung Ian level
and the Platonic level. The
lower subtle level is the kind
of quasi Jung Ian level where I
had experiences of the human
family as a unified single
being, similar to Jung's concept
of the collective unconscious,
that all of our minds were part
were fractal components in a
single mind of the human
species. Even our bodies were
cells within the body of the
human species. How I handled my
diseases had an impact on how
the human family was learning
and handling its diseases, how I
handled my pain, psychological
pain, was related to how the
human species was being able to
hand handle its pain. So this at
the and I say quasi Jung Ian,
because I didn't engage any of
the archetypes that Jung talks
about, wise old man, wise old
woman. But it was this
experience of over and over
again, focusing on the one human
family, then at a higher level,
moving into what I would call
the quasi platonic level,
engaging archetypes that were so
far removed from time and space,
so far beyond any our any
conventional categories, that I
literally could not wrap my mind
around them. I could not see
them as they were in and of
themselves, but I knew I was
engaging vast cosmic forces that
were responsible for creating
the conditions inside time and
space, even time and space
itself. I call this a quasi
platonic level, because Plato
envision the archetypes as
eternal ideas in the mind of an
unchanging God. That's not how I
experience these beings. I
experience them as vast, huge,
living, dynamic beings that
lived in a different order of
time and a different order of
space than we do inside time and
space. So after spending then
two years or so exploring this
reality, I went through yet
another death and rebirth, and
we go into the fourth module,
where I think I've got the
modules listed right here,
oneness, fundamental, the
blessings of oneness, of moving
into causal reality, beyond
archetype of reality, and in
this level of reality, the world
lives and breathes This one. As
Plotinus says, The World
breathes this one. All the
components of the world are
there, but the fundamental
experiences, experiencing the
world as a unified reality, all
of its life forms, cells within
this unified reality, all the
galaxies, cells within this
unified reality, experiencing
emptiness of self, what the
Buddhists call Shunyata, to
experience being alive in a
world, but absolutely no self in
me, no separate self, no
separate self in any part of
reality, experiencing the primal
void ex. Experiencing an ocean
of cosmic love pouring into me
just multiple manifestations of
of oneness, permutations of
oneness, going still deeper,
another round of death and
rebirth entering into the
diamond Luminosity material, the
diamond Luminosity is what I use
as a term. I use to refer to a
state of consciousness that I
entered into in the last five
years of my work, extremely
clear. The most striking
characteristic is, first, it's
just pure light, all light,
realm of pure light and clear,
clear, beyond imagination, just
clear, clear, phenomenally
clear. Where the joy came, not
from anything that happened in
this state or from anything I
experienced in this state, but
the very state itself, the
clarity and of this state, the
absolute freedom, the sheer
bliss of the freedom in this
condition, I think this is what,
as a professor of religious
studies, the closest thing I've
been able to find to this
condition is What Buddhism calls
Dharmakaya. In Buddhism, there
are three kayas, Dharmakaya,
sambhogakaya, Nirvana, Kaya,
three different dimensions of
reality. Dharmakaya is the
deepest. It's called the clear
light of absolute reality. It is
the light out of which the Big
Bang emerges. So in the last
five years of my journey, 26
sessions, I entered this reality
four times when I touched it.
The first time, it was so
powerful and it was so it filled
me with so much joy and ecstasy
that I completely lost interest
in any of the earlier levels of
reality that I had explored. I
lost interest in personal and
collective and archetypal, even
the bliss of causal level
reality. This was different.
This was a higher order. It took
me about a year of very intense
work, lots of purification
before I was able to go back
into this deeper state of
reality, and I went back into it
over four years, only four
times. The next module has to do
with the birth of the future
human, which we mentioned before
that it is a chapter where I
gather together years of
visionary experiences that I was
given about where humanity is in
its evolution, about the turning
point we have come to my sense
is that we can no longer afford
to live on this planet As a
species of egos that emphasize
our separate, private existence,
where some can lose and some can
win. We need to grow up. We need
to grow up into our next
evolutionary expression.
Over and over again, I was shown
these visions that this is
what's happening. Nature is
taking us through this. We are
going through a tremendous
pressure cooker. We're going
through a transformation that
will result in the birth, not
simply of a higher civilization
or a more ecologically in tune
economy, but literally this. We
are going through a series of
crises that we're going to shift
the architecture of the
collective psyche, so that all
human beings born after we go
through this process will be
born in the context and be
operating in the context of a
new collective psyche, of a
different collective psyche, a
more evolved collective psyche
for our species, the birth of
the future human, which I also
conceptualize as the birth of
the diamond soul. I think
reincarnation has been taking us
toward this point for 1000s and
1000s of years. Gestation is
long. Birth labor is quick. The
gestation which has been
developing within us, has been
developing through death and
rebirth, reincarnation, dying
and being reborn, dying and
being reborn, incremental gains,
incremental gains as we grow.
But there comes a time when the
soul, which holds all of our
experiences from all of our
lives, which is our natural
state of consciousness when we
die, and the ego, which is the
small consciousness we're born
into when we incarnate, back and
forth between ego and soul, ego
and soul, there comes a point
where sooner or later, the soul.
So the consciousness, which
holds all our of our memories,
fuses and integrates into one
and becomes conscious inside
time and space, not outside time
and space in the pure,
beautiful, pure paradise or in
the garden or in the heavenly
realms, but awakens inside time
and space. And this is what I
call the birth of the diamond
soul. When this happened to me
in my sessions, all my former
lives came together, they fused,
and they were catapulted. I was
catapulted far beyond my
ordinary capacities, and I think
this is simply what's happening
to the entire human species. I
was given the gift of getting a
taste of what's in the
evolutionary works for all of
us. We are coming into a hard
labor. We're coming into a time
of unraveling. We're coming into
a very, very difficult time. But
my experiences in my sessions is
that we come through this human
beings do not go extinct, but we
give birth to a divine child. We
give birth to the future human,
to the birth of the diamond soul
in history. The last module in
the course is on coming off the
mountain. It's about
integration. It's about how do
you integrate such extreme
experiences? Now, as long as
we're working about in a
therapeutic model, then we have
therapeutic models for how to
integrate the various content
that emerges in our on from our
unconscious when we're working
at the level of the personal
psyche. If we go deeper and
begin to experience life after
death and begin to experience
the connective tissue, the
intelligence of the connective
tissue of life, we have
spiritual models for integrating
and absorbing these experiences,
but when we go very, very deep
into the fabric of existence,
when we go repeatedly outside of
space and time, when we go deep
into the archetypal fabric, deep
into the light which is the
light that underpins all of
reality. How are those
experiences being integrated by
us? Then, what does integration
even mean in this context? How
can a finite being integrate
infinite experiences or
experiences of infinity? How
does a time bound being
integrated experiences of
eternity or deep time? So that's
what we're going to be looking
at at the last module we'll be
looking at the challenges of
integrating, not just
integrating individual sessions,
but integrating an entire
journey that explores deep,
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness year after year
after year. Personally, I don't
think we have begun to map what
these deep experiences are doing
to us. I don't think we've
really begun to understand fully
the opportunities that they're
giving us and also the
challenges, the hardships they
bring to us in order to, you
know, come back into time and
space after such glorious
adventures outside of time and
space. So that's the kind of
that's the trajectory of the
course, in a nutshell.
Vanese McNeill: So, Chris, I'm
going to leave my microphone
off, I mean my camera off, as it
might help my interactivity,
right? So, sweetie, do you have
a sense of once we integrate the
soul?
Chris Bache: Say again, you're
breaking up once we integrate
the soul function,
Vanese McNeill: how do we act?
What do we look like? Do you
have a sense of that?
Chris Bache: Well, I think we
act like old ones. I think what
we're doing is growing up. We've
we see the prototypes in Jesus
and Muhammad and the Buddha in
some of the great saints of
history, whose natural horizons
are so large, whose compassion
is so deep, whose ability to
download information from cosmic
mind is so augmented. And I
think it will look something
like that. It will look like an
older human being, a being who
is steeped in time, who carries
the knowledge of 1000s of
incarnations, just as our ego
carries the knowledge of one
incarnation. I don't think it'll
be a science fiction. Action,
exotic looking human being
growing another set of fingers
or getting a bigger skull. I
think we are it will bring about
deep metabolic changes in our in
our body, but we'll register it
will register first as a
profound series of psychological
changes, changes in our heart.
We will enter into what I
sometimes call the one heart,
the one heart of the human
family, the one heart of the
planet. We will enter into
deeper communion with the mind
of creation, the mind that's
been generating this extra
ordinary Galaxy this planet, all
the life on this planet will be
able to enter into communion and
download information from this
intelligence more easily than we
can do it today. I think this,
this new human being will
actually live in the body
differently and experience their
senses differently. One of the
last gifts I was given on my
journey, actually was the very
last gift given on my last
psychedelic journey, was what I
call diamond vision. My vision
suddenly I was in a condition
five hours into the session,
late in the wind down stage of
the session where my vision was
100 times more acute than it
normally is, where I could see
levels, ingredients of color,
edges of detail, much, much more
fine than I was ever able to see
before. And after about 10
minutes, it disappeared. It
stopped. And it was at that
point that I began to realize I
was had been given the gift of
seeing through the eyes of the
future human. We have a tendency
to think of our perceptual our
senses as kind of mechanical,
neurologically generated, but I
don't think that's really the
case. Our system certainly uses
our physiology, but as our
consciousness gets stronger and
bigger and older, it brings out
deeper and more refined senses,
a deeper form of vision, a
deeper form of hearing, a deeper
form of testing and sensing our
physical body. So I think that
the future human is not simply a
human with a healed heart and an
open heart, and not simply a
human being with an open and
deeper mental capacity, but as
somebody who lives in a deeper
sensory experience, a more
satisfying sensory experience in
their body with all the hills,
or a long, dark history healed
in the body, emotionally,
psychologically and physically.
Yeah, so that's, that's what I
think the future human will be
like. It'll be like a grown up
version of ourselves, the soul
Vanese McNeill: that's
beautiful, Chris, that actually
makes a lot of sense to me. You,
as you pointed out these sci fi
vision of humans, and when you
say also the collective soul, my
mind jumps to the Borg or
something like that on Star
Trek, which does not appear
appealing to me at all. This,
yeah, this vision is, is very,
very beautiful. I was reading a
book last night that was talking
about the relationship between
sleeping and death. And what
occurred to me is that there is
a Mandelbrot type set of
magnification between the state
of dreaming and dying and then
the series of dyings that you
went through on this journey.
And just like dreaming is a
state very much akin to death,
and being alive in the or being
awake in the daytime is very
much akin to being alive in a
life you just progressed up into
the bigger Mandelbrot sections
of that process, right dying
every time, on a different layer
and a higher register, if you
will. And as a result of that,
being able to kind of access
these larger perspectives. And I
think that one of the fact that
you did that for us is
invaluable, because in a normal
waking state with everything
that is going on in the world,
it's very, very hard to. Be in
touch with your intuition at
all, let alone having a broader
state of consciousness. And
that's why I think it's very
important for people. And yes,
look, it is your journey and
filtered through your senses and
your experiences. But
fundamentally, there is very,
very precious information that
you have died for and brought
back for us. And if you are
going to share one of those for
the people today who are kind
of, you know, living like out of
all the different levels that
you went through, what a piece
of information would be most
helpful for us today with what
seems to be the bifurcation of
people into red people and blue
people and Vax people and unvax
people and all of these kinds of
things, yeah, what can help us
most today?
Chris Bache: Yeah, good
question. I don't know whether
there's I can think of one thing
that would help us most today,
but so let me just ramble a
little bit and see if we can
move towards something like
that. First, let me mention that
I think this is a personal
journey, and I own it. I accept
the personal nature of the
journey. It's very but I think
it's what happens in one one
serious psychedelic work is
something like the following, my
experiences that consciousness
is an infinite ocean, that
there's an infinite ocean of
consciousness, and my mind acts
as a seed catalyst that
catalyzes a certain set of
experiences out of the infinite
potential of this larger
consciousness. Now, so in a
sense, my experiences in the
psychedelic state are always
participatory. They're always
interactive. My being evoked
certain sets of experiences. It
doesn't mean that I'm simply
reading my own mind in these
experiences, but my being
catalyzes a certain set of
experiences from the infinite
mind. But as I internalize those
experiences, as I let them
change me, as I let them purify
me, as I let them kill me allow
myself to die as I allow myself
to be purified at deeper and
deeper levels. What happens is
the seed catalyst of my mind is
changed, so that when I go into
psychedelic space, the next
time, my mind is a little
different than it was before,
and it catalyzes a still deeper
response from the cosmic, the
infinite mind of the universe.
And if you keep this up many,
many years, this very much
matches the experience that the
more you allow yourself to be
purified, the more you allow
yourself to let go of your old
ways of thinking and old ways of
feeling and just go with it.
Just allow yourself to be
solved, to be dissolved into the
winds of the world that the
universe can show you more
because you you are capable of
receiving more because you've
emptied out your being and have
been made yourself into a
receptacle. I don't think, I
think the infinite consciousness
is truly that an infinite
consciousness. So even though
there were many homecomings, and
even though there were many,
many deeply soul satisfying
experiences, I couldn't imagine
being more satisfied. I also had
experiences which showed me that
it is truly an infinite world
that I was entering and I would
never be able to get to the end
of it. I could not get to the
end of this reality. It was just
too vast, and I was too small,
even using this very accelerated
process. So from this journey, I
bring back experiences that were
given to me by this larger
intelligence, which over the
years, it became clear I was
being given these visions and
trust these experiences and
trust they weren't being given
to me privately, but they were
being given to me so that there
would come a time when I could
do my job as a teacher, just as
I'm an academic, you know, I'm a
philosopher of religion, to
share them with other people, so
that these visions, to the
extent that they truly reflect
universal truths, people would
recognize those universal truths
and they they would find ways of
integrating them into their own
life. So excuse me again. Didn't
turn off my ping
Vanese McNeill: on my phone.
That's okay. Neither did I.
Darling.
Chris Bache: So in terms of what
would be useful to people, a
number of things. That come
forward. One of them is to trust
the intelligence of the
universe, to trust the wisdom
that is alive and operating in
the universe. We are taught that
the universe came about by
chance, that that it evolves by
random mutation, screened by
brutal survival of the fittest.
That's not an accurate
reflection of my psychedelic
experience at all. My
experiences is that we are
everywhere, surrounded by orders
and orders and magnitudes of
intelligence, that when you go
deeper into the universe, you're
entering into more and more and
more awareness, more
consciousness, more intelligence
than we generally experience
inside time and space, but to
trust the universe, to trust the
universe that has created the
conditions of reincarnation,
where we choose our lives, we
choose the conditions In which
we enter into, even the
difficult ones we we choose
these things to understand
reincarnation, not simply as a
personal soul story, but a
collective soul story, a human
family soul story that
incarnates intelligently
generation after generation as
we grow as a human family, to
feel that intelligence, to
recognize the intelligence how
it works, to recognize the
intelligence of how the human
family is now being catalyzed
all of us together to bring
forward a deeper form of
functioning, a deeper way of
being human on this planet, if
there were maybe only one thing,
if I were to point to one thing
that I wish I could give people,
it would be to lose their fear
of death. I wish I could reach
into my heart and give you this
absolute freedom of any fear of
death. Because if you fear
death, you've got your cosmology
all upside down. If you're
afraid of dying, then you don't
understand that the hard work is
done inside time and space. The
really hard work is done here.
When we die, it's graduation.
When we die, it's it's
homecoming. When we die, it's
recess. We get this tremendous
joy. We have so many Hollywood
narratives about the spooky
things that happen to us when we
die, and they're they're just
nonsense. They're just
ridiculous. When you, when you
experience death yourself, when
you are near a person who
studies near death episode
research, and you talk to people
who have truly died and have
come back to life, or who have
been nearly dead and come back
to tell about it. Or when you go
to the shamanic traditions where
death and rebirth is an
understanding, is a deep
understanding what happens in
one's psychedelic sessions when
you've gone through death, many
times, you lose all fear of
dying, because you know from
your own personal experience
that death is simply a
transition, and it's a
transition to a happier place, a
finer place, a place what you
will eventually choose to return
into time space again, because
of the Great value of time and
space, but death is absolutely
nothing to fear. So a
combination of the the wisdom of
the universe, the genius of the
universe, the way that the cycle
of life takes us in and out of
death, many, many times, and in
and out of rebirth, many, many
times, and that there is purpose
in this, there is design in
this. The universe is creating a
species, the likes of which we
haven't even begun to imagine.
It has been billions of years in
the making, and it will continue
to be made for billions of years
more every time we think we can
do it better. If we were God, we
would have designed the world a
little better. We would have
eliminated this or eliminated
that. I think, well, that means
that you know where we're going,
and we don't. I think we're just
get glimpses. Even in our deep
visionary states, we get
glimpses of what is being built.
And I think we're going to see
in this century some early signs
of what is being built in
history, in the future, human,
Vanese McNeill: sweet, I can't
agree with you more. And I
remember when I was a student
and came up against the great
saints or the great sages that
would choose death rather than
compromising their idea or their
belief, they would literally go
and be burned at the stake
because the importance of that
idea. Idea was so strong, and
they have remained through
history as being people whose
messages still resound right in
our in our day to day lives. And
what's been very evident to me
is that with this virus that has
occurred that the populace on
mass remains very much in a
state of fear of death. And I
wonder how an individual that
hasn't been on your journey is
able to arrive at that state
without undergoing what you've
taken or what you've gone
through. How do I get where you
are without having 72 doses of
LSD?
Unknown: A number of ways, I
think, first of all, read books,
there are wonderful, wonderful,
very well researched studies of
people who have died or who have
nearly died. And when people
begin to read the near death
episode literature, it changes.
I've taught this for decades to
my students at the university.
And when you read the near death
episode literature, it changes
completely how you experience
the or how you anticipate death.
Another body of literature is
the reincarnation literature.
The evidence, which I find is
absolutely, empirically,
overwhelmingly good evidence for
reincarnation. And once again,
it is if there, if we
reincarnate, if there is a mind
which moves through one
incarnation after another in
some way, then it basically
takes away the fear of dying.
You understand that death is not
the end. It's simply the end of
one half of a cycle. The cycle
goes from birth to birth, or
death to death, let's say birth
to birth. Halfway through that
cycle, there is death, but there
is activity on the other side
after death, which brings us
back into birth again. We can
study that. Literature, the past
life therapy. Literature, when
people actively encounter their
former lives in order to heal
those former lives, the near
death episode. Literature, the
reincarnation literature, it
just when you put together all
these bodies of information
intellectually that should
assuage our fear of dying. And
then I think, to spend time,
either in books or tapes or in
person with people who have gone
through whatever spiritual
practice they've used that has
truly dissolved their fear of
dying, to be to spend time with
them, because this is something.
It's not magical, you know, it's
not super duper supernatural.
It's simply a kind of opening to
a larger horizon where certain
things don't frighten you
anymore, and it's something
which can be learned, it can be
transmitted from one person to
another, so that it becomes kind
of a shared community value. So
I certainly don't think you need
to do what I've done in order to
awaken this sense of
fearlessness confronting life,
Vanese McNeill: that actually
makes a lot of sense, sweetie.
Yes, I agree with you. I mean, I
am rather au fait with the
literature, and it does. I mean,
there is overwhelming evidence
out there. You have a book
Dolores, Cannon's done so much
work on it. There's a lot of
really, really good researchers
that have reported on this. And
then the drew the, I think it's
the Druze, which is a culture in
the Middle East where the
children that have been,
unfortunately, they've passed
away as a result of some
traumatic experience, come back
very quickly, and can literally
go and identify their ex wives
or their children. I mean,
that's uncanny, yeah.
Unknown: Ian Stevenson's work, I
think, is a game changer. He
really is the Charles Darwin of
reincarnation. He's given us
sufficient hunt cases. Children
have not only continuity of
memory, they can recognize
people from the circumstances of
the previous life. They know
intimate details of the previous
personalities life and the
people they lived with. And.
Were associated with. They
sometimes, and this is a really
fascinating thing, they
sometimes carry in their body
scars that are related to the
death wounds of the previous
personality in their previous
life, so that it not only mind
transfers from life to life, but
in some cases, even sort of a
cellular memory, some transfers
from life to life.
Vanese McNeill: I, as a very
young girl, had a friend, my
father's friend, who had a
constant pain in his right
shoulder, and he went to a past
life regressionist Who told him
that he had had a sword stabbed
directly down his body, and
through the process of
acknowledging that he felt a
sharp pain, the things start
filling up from the bottom and
was healed completely as a
result of processing that wound,
which is very much like the work
that you're doing, or the work
that you have done for us, it is
akin to the personal work that
we do on ourselves. If we
identify a trauma that's
happened in our life, we look at
it, we heal it. And so you did
that for us on many, many levels
of human and cosmic
consciousness, right? So again,
there's kind of a Mandelbrot of
healing that proceeds up and
down this chain. And
Chris Bache: you know, it may
sound exotic describing it after
the fact, but when you're in it,
it feels like the most natural
thing of the world. And again, I
don't think you have to be a
saint to do this things. Any
mother or father worth this salt
when they see not only their
child, but other children
suffering, if there's anything
they can do to alleviate that
suffering, they would naturally
do it, because the path of
parents compassion is deepened
by their children to all the
children of the world. So if
you're given an opportunity in
the physical world or in
psychedelic space, if you're
given an opportunity to somehow
engage suffering and to bring by
bringing it into awareness, to
heal that suffering. It's the
most natural thing in the world
to do that. I don't know whether
I think that I did this work not
because I had to. I did this
work because it was chosen by my
soul before I was born. I think
all of us who chose to enter
time and space during this very,
very intense period, in a way, I
think, took on more karma than
was maybe common in centuries
past, that just to be here, to
live in these very, very
challenging times is to take on
heavy responsibilities for the
entire human family. We are
doing this in the physical
world, just as we do it in our
psychedelic sessions. And I
think that we chose it. We knew
what we were getting into, and
we are now here living it out,
bringing it into fruition inside
physical world.
Vanese McNeill: I have always
been a compassionate person.
Chris, I've been accused of
being pathologically forgiving,
but I find that in this moment,
my compassion is increasing at
an exponential rate like I feel
I can I can see in myself I am
being forced to grow. I'm being
pulled to grow. And I see that
happening to a lot of people
around us. So I I concur that we
can all do this work on many
different levels, and it's just
important to heal your child as
it is, you know, to do the large
scale work that you did. I don't
know. I mean, it's just again, I
keep coming back to the point
that I really would encourage
everybody to either read your
book or to come to this seven
week course, I feel that it is
God's work that you're sharing
with us, my dear, and that the
people that come to this class
are going to have a an expanded
understanding of the workings of
The universe and how to be kind
of a soldier in the
transformation towards this
diamond human being that we all
want to get to. And the sooner
the better, right? The less
chaos the better. And so that's
why I wanted to take this time
and to kind of share this with
with the people. At fans of
MAGICAL EGYPT, because I think
you know, you're greasing the
wheels, my dear, you're making
it just that little bit easier.
Chris Bache: It is, in some
ways, like being a soldier, but
it is a very different kind of
soldier, isn't it, because here,
one conquers by surrendering
you. You you you confront evil
or pain, and you don't fight it.
You let it in. You surrender to
it. It becomes part of your
world, and then it moves through
you, and it's resolves itself.
So it's a very peculiar way.
It's it's like a woman in labor
doesn't fight her pain. She
cooperates with it. She works
with it. She surrenders to it.
She lets the pain carry her
through the birth process. It's
like that in a psychedelic
session. And you know, this was
a hard book for me to write. It
was hard for me. It took me
years to get my head around
sharing these sessions, because,
you know, they're the deepest
experiences I've ever had in my
life. They're the the my
experiences of God. And at first
I wanted to publish this book
posthumously, just wait till I
die and leave it behind, but the
mother told me, No, you can't
read that, there's not enough
time, we're going into choppy
water. All hands on deck,
please. Thank you very much. All
of us need to show up and put
our gifts forward so that
together we can support each
other, we can nourish each other
and bring this critical period
of history to good outcome.
Bring us through it faster.
We'll go through it faster. If
we go through it smart, if we go
through it with compassion, we
can admit we can reduce the
suffering. It's like, you know,
the global climate crisis, the
conferences which have just
taken place, the g20 if we are
smart and take more aggressive
steps, we can minimize we can
reduce the pain and suffering.
If we don't act with
intelligence and courage, we're
going to increase the suffering
later. So we all have options as
we come into this period of
history. We all have options. We
all have choices. We're all part
of the human family dealing with
this. And the more we know, the
more we understand, the more we
trust, the better our choices
can be, the speedier outcome,
the better world we can leave
for our grandchildren.
Vanese McNeill: Well, we're
blessed to have you, Chris, and
I'm so glad you didn't wait,
because then I wouldn't have had
the opportunity to talk to you
and and I think hearing this,
you know, from your own voice,
is so powerful. So I want to
apologize, first of all that my
connection has been so bad.
Next, I want to point people in
the chat, there is a link to
Chris's course that's coming up
again, I highly suggest that you
go. If you can't go, please
share it, just so that we can
have as many hands on deck as
Chris said. And I want to thank
you, my dear so much for your
time today and holding my
breath, you know, surrendering,
Chris Bache: doing what I can.
Thank you. Thank you so much for
this conversation and for all
the conversations that you host,
which is part of the
facilitation of this larger
awakening process for humanity.
If you, if anyone on your cast
wants to go to the pay the
website of the course, they can
find it at explore cosmic
mind.com explore cosmic mind.com
you'll see the course, you'll
see the descriptions. You'll see
all and that there are all sorts
of free bonuses you get if you
sign up for the course, you got
lots of nice free bonuses.
Everybody gets a free ebook.
Some of Stan grofs courses are
going to be given to you. Some
unpublished articles that I've
written will be given to you, a
chapter of the audio book. So
there's lots of freebies that
will come with the course, and I
hope it attracts a wonderful
group of people. I'm sure it
will people who, like yourself,
are curious, wondering, and who
are workers who really want to
bring about a better world.
Vanese McNeill: I'm sure it will
be the best group of people.
Darlin, I'm sure we'll come away
with wonderful new friends. So
thank you. Just again, it was
explore.com explore cosmic
mind.com. All right, my loves.
I'll pop that in the chat, and
I'm going to email this to all
the MAGICAL EGYPT people, so
I'll make sure. Put that in as
well. So thank you, Chris. You
have a wonderful evening, and it
starts on the 17th. Is that
correct? So coming up? Well,
actually, the
Unknown: course itself starts on
November 30. Oh, fantastic.
Yeah, there was, there's a an
invitational event, a one hour
Invitational event in which
Steve Dean and I talk about the
course and what it's going to be
that's going to be rebroadcast
on the 16th here. I don't know
whether that's 17th where you
are, but basically the course
will not start until November
30. Okay, every Tuesday for
three weeks, we take two weeks
off for Christmas holidays, and
then four weeks through January.
Vanese McNeill: Fabulous
sweetie. All right. Well, we
will see you there. Hopefully
we'll see lots of MAGICAL EGYPT
people. Thank you for listening
as well. MAGICAL EGYPT people
and Chris, you have a wonderful
evening. Thank you again. Bless
you, my dear.
Chris Bache: Thank you. Thank
you very much. Vaness, bye, bye.