Richard Rudd: Hi, Chris, Hello,
Richard. Here we are. Here we
are
Chris Bache: made possible only
with new technology. Exactly me
in North Carolina and the USA.
Our guests from all over the
world. I see,
Richard Rudd: yeah, absolutely
and, and also the magic of, you
know, even though we're doing
this now, any other people will
be watching this in another now.
And I want to welcome all the,
all those people in all of those
now, yeah, yeah, all those
different timelines.
Chris Bache: Yes. It sure has
been fun having this dialog with
you, sharing ideas and
perspectives on reincarnation.
I've really been enjoying it
Richard Rudd: Me too. Me too.
It's I've learned a lot from you
and and you know, since I read
your book, it really, you know,
book that really blew, blew my
mind, and had so many resonances
for me, diamonds and, you know,
LSD in the mind of the universe,
those who Haven't heard about
that yet, it's quite something.
Chris's book, so I recommend
that heartily, right at the
beginning here, and the
exploration that it's afforded
us and the overlaps with my work
with the gene keys. So,
Chris Bache: real pleasure, real
Richard Rudd: pleasure, and
we're also, you know, it's an
ongoing journey for us, isn't
it? So we, we, we haven't
finished this is just us sort of
getting going, I think. So, I
think we're probably going to
explore this subject in the
coming months and perhaps years,
and keep diving deeper into it,
and, yeah, mining the insights
that we that we can and also
involving a community of people
to to engage with us like this
today, yes,
Chris Bache: yeah, that's going
to be fun. I look forward to
that if we can get into as much
trouble as we got into it three
hours. Just imagine what we
could do with more time.
Richard Rudd: Exactly, help it?
Yeah, yeah. So, I mean, we might
as well just jump straight in.
We've, we've got a load of
questions that have already been
sent in. So the plan here is,
we're going to Chris has, and
I've sort of sorted the
questions that you've sent in
into categories, and we're going
to kind of rip through them
first, because they cover broad,
a broad kind of area of subjects
connected to reincarnation. And
thank you. By the way, all those
who send in your questions,
they've really helped us to kind
of sharpen and some of those
questions lead to more
questions. And you should know
that we don't know the answers
to some of those questions as
well, and but we're going to
explore them together. So so
we'll do that first, and then
we'll come round to the live Q
and A questions that you can put
in to the little Q and A button
down here. If you get any point
you have a question, you can
drop it in there. And hopefully
we'll be able to get to as many
of those. So we have 90 minutes.
So a lot to you know, a lot of
time to explore.
Chris Bache: Well, you know, we
broke up the questions. There
were so many good questions, and
we could spend hours and hours
just in the questions that have
already been sent in. There were
so many good questions, we broke
them up into clusters. And so we
thought that let's go through
some of the ones in the first
cluster just to read some of the
questions so that the
participants can get a sense of
the types of questions that
people were asked to move to ask
after they listened to our
dialog, and then we can just
touch on a few of those and then
move into the second cluster of
questions, the first cluster we
identified as, how can we
acquire personal knowledge of
our farmer lives? Because it's
one thing, as many of you noted,
to have someone tell you about
these things. It's another thing
to do your own research and to
investigate these things, and
then it's another thing still to
have personal experience of your
own former life history. So let
me just hit a couple of these
questions. And then one was, how
can we get closer to completely
trusting the universe and that
reincarnation is true? If all we
have is book knowledge on the
topic or stories from others and
another person wrote, is it
possible to have a connection
with your previous lifetimes in
your present life, in another
Can you give us a practical
method that allows us to
remember our past lives and see
the lessons that are working we
are working on in our present
life and what needs healing in
our present life. Just to touch
lightly on these, just to start
on these three questions, maybe.
And then one last one was, have
each of you personally
experienced an awareness of your
past lives leading to the
present, and was it beneficial
for you to do so? It strikes me
that this whole question of, can
we trust this material? How can
I get closer to this material?
How can I begin to experience
these things for myself? It's a
really important question. I
personally started to accept
reincarnation on the basis of
research, on the basis of
people's research, and I think
this research is abundant.
There's a lot of wonderful books
that it's just deserving of our
close attention. But it's
another thing when you start to
have personal experience of your
own lives, when you do the work,
when you go inside, either
through contemplation or
hypnosis or some form of past
life therapy, and you begin to
follow your own memories back
into your earlier memories, And
to begin to have this vivid
experience that your
consciousness is bigger than
your body, it's older than your
body, it has a longer history
than your body, and that does
tend to cause this, this idea,
to live in your heart
differently than before. Don't
you think?
Richard Rudd: Richard,
absolutely. You know, one of my
favorite questions in there was
once I know about the soul that
gathers all my lives into one.
What are some practices to help
me embody it in my present human
life? You know? Because we're
talking about contacting the
energy of the soul, you know,
contacting the energy of the
part of us that's eternal, you
know? And that's like, that's a
journey, you know? It's a
journey we're all on, and most
people listening to this are
very certainly on. Otherwise you
wouldn't be here, I'm sure. So,
yeah, it's, that's the first
thing that could to contact
these realms and to discover or
come across wisdom that's that's
buried somewhere inside you, and
I firmly feel that this, these
memories, are actually held in
the physical body, in the
physicality of our body. So
right now, begin with that.
Begin with the knowing that, or
even the premise that inside
your physical body, somewhere
are memories held and and so
this is going to involve some
work with the physical body in
some form, some relationship
with the physical with
breathing, with awareness, with
mindfulness, with, as you said,
Chris, with contemplation. And
you know, there are, there are
lots of ways, and there are lots
of techniques and tricks and
things that can help you. And
but rather than kind of give
lots right now, I'd rather just
give a very broad guidance,
which is for me, is if you're
keen to know more about your own
story beyond this lifetime, and
that can be forwards or
backwards, then Start really
listening. And to really listen,
you need to clear space in your
life. So you need to have a
practice, I would say, of
listening or of contemplation or
of meditation, or perhaps of
prayer, or perhaps, you know,
anything that begins to enhance
and increase that awareness of
those other frequencies beyond
the body and and so finding the
ones that really work well for
you, the techniques that really
feel good to you and resonate
with you, is going to be a good
indication that that's a good
technique to begin to open up
the inner world and then begin
to create the space so that the
and you can put out the
question, I'd like to know more.
That's it. It's already in you.
If you're if you're here, it's
probably already in you. I'd
like to know more. I'd like to
remember more. And what you're
doing is you're really reaching
out into the ethers of the
cosmos, and you're inviting a
revelation. Revelation, or a
series of revelations, and
that's going to be a journey, as
it has been for Chris and
myself, and we've gone very
different ways, you know, Chris
is. Chris's route towards this
has been very different from
mine, you know, and and so you
have to follow begin with, begin
with what feels right, what you
resonate with, and then the rest
will begin to open up inside
you. You, I mean, you've had
more experience, I think, Chris,
with the past life therapy
community, than I have, so maybe
that you could give a few
pointers in that
Chris Bache: well, you know,
when one of the questioners
asked, Do we have any practical
suggestions for techniques that
can help people and discover
their former lives? And I don't
want to go in that direction.
This is there are no shortcuts
here. There is a matter of
living with this information.
And then also there is the
systematic exploration of your
deep consciousness, which is
just a matter of following your
your memories to earlier and
earlier stages. And this is can
be done with contemplation, as
Richard said, in various
meditation exercises. But then I
think it's also can be greatly
aided by working with
professionals who can, who can
help you stay conscious at
deeper levels of your memory
than you might ordinarily be
conscious of, because often when
we go beneath our personal
unconscious. We tend to get
fuzzy and maybe fall asleep, but
someone can help you keep
focused as you go deeper and
deeper. And it's often good to
focus on a particular issue or
problem or joy and follow that
to its root as you go deeper
within. But there are many ways
inside, some people's memories
are activated on a massage
table. Some people's memories
are meditated and activated in
meditation. But once you begin
to appreciate that your being is
older than your body, and live
with that idea every day, it
just becomes increasingly
natural to live in a world
that's saturated with time, to
live in relationships that are
saturated with time and with
life projects. It makes less and
less sense to try to compress
everything that's going on
inside us into one lifetime, and
more and more sense to let it
unfold into a larger agenda.
Richard Rudd: Yeah. So another
good tip is don't be in a rush.
No, take your time. Take your
time. You have all the time you
need to explore this amazing
mystery and the subject that
we're opening up here is not
just about reincarnation and
rebirth. It's, it's, it opens up
into into all, all other
questions, all the deep
questions, like, what are we why
are we here? How does it work?
You know, all those deep
questions that we have inside us
that we carry. How can we be
eternal? How can we know? How
can that work? And then we hear
all those, those things, and in
the work I do with Gene keys, as
many you will know has this
infuriating habit of pointing
people back into them their own
wisdom. Because if you can
begin, when you can begin to
access the wisdom that lies
inside you and it's and as I
said, start with your body, with
the physical, and begin to you
know, begin to kind of explore
what's inside you and who you
are, and begin to work through
some of the issues and the
shadows and the trauma that you
hold and begin to forgive and
begin to let go and surrender
and go through this process of
transformation, of inner
transformation, which is a whole
journey in itself, as as
everyone here will know, then
you start to open up space
inside for your wisdom to
appear, and your memories to
appear, and they will tell you
exactly what you need when you
need it, not before, not after,
just exactly when you need it.
The wisdom will come. The memory
will come if it's meant to come,
and it'll come in the way it's
meant to come. So for some
people are very visual. Some
people are kinesthetic, like you
go to a place, you're like, I
know I've been here before. Or
you meet a person and you look
in their eye and you know you've
met them before, those kind of
things. Or it could be it's just
a it's visual inside your
cortex, you know that you see
it. Or there's so many different
ways. Or it could be a smell, or
it could. Be through any of the
senses, or just an attunement to
synchronicities that are going
on around you, you know. And as
we get more heightened and more
aware of these other realms, we
begin to pick up on this
interconnectivity that lies
beyond this world, this, this
world that we are used to
inhabit, inhabiting, you know,
and we realize there are other
dimensions, and we begin to kind
of resonate with those
dimensions. And that's what we
call wisdom, you know, when the
when our when our world begins
to open up, and that clarity
starts to come through from
those other dimensions. And it
informs this dimension we're
living in, in some expansive
way, in some therapeutic,
virtuous way inside us, in some,
you know, in some process of
opening. And that's so, that's
really, you know, if you have
these questions, whatever they
are, know that you know the
journey is always, you know, one
of going deeper and deeper
inside the question itself and
sinking right down into the
heart of it. And because it's a
very valid question, if you hold
it and it probably has another
question hidden inside that, and
then another one inside that,
and then begin to open up and
open up and open up. So I want
to kind of say that as a as a
way of empowering everyone to to
trust in their own, in your own
intuition, and follow the
threads you know through the
labyrinth,
Chris Bache: yeah, yeah, yes.
Shall we pull a couple of
questions from the nuts and
bolts section, yes, Section
category, nuts and bolts
basically. How does
reincarnation work? You know,
some of them are long answers.
Some of them are short answers.
Here's a few that could be
answered quickly. Do we stay in
one ancestry? Do we hop across
to others? We hop, you know, do
we think our next reincarnation
could be as our children or as
our grandchildren? And there's
research that says, Yeah, could
be, you know, people reincarnate
in families. And another person
asked, are animals part of the
reincarnation cycle? And the
answer to that, I think in all
reincarnation cultures, they
say, Yeah, animals are part of
the cycle, but they tend to be
at the earlier stages of one's
reincarnational lives, because
once you have gone through a
certain level of cognitive
development that you can
function at a human level.
There's not too much to be
learned from going back and
living lives as an animal. So
they're part of our heritage,
but not necessarily. We don't
incarnate from a human to an
animal, even though that's a
very popular folk belief, it's
not really, it's not really a
belief held by more informed
thinkers of reincarnation. Do
you want to pull a couple of
questions from that
Richard Rudd: list? Yeah, and
actually, I'd like to go back to
the one about ancestry, because
I was recently talking to this
wonderful man, Tyson Jung ka
Porter, who's an Aboriginal
indigenous man, and he was
talking to me about in a kind of
interview we did together, kind
of informal one. We were talking
about transmigration of souls.
And in many indigenous cultures,
there are kind of they track
their incarnations, and they
have us that there's a strong
intuition held that within a
tribal grouping or a family
grouping or a clan that's close,
that's close knit, that's
operating like in those
cultures, then there's a there's
a real link between one's own
person and the great
grandchildren, or the great
grandparents. So it skips a
couple of generations, but they
see their great grandchildren as
the as the next wave coming
through, and there's all kinds
of cross patterning within that,
and there's no kind of fixed way
of understanding it, but it does
seem to be a strong, firm
tradition. So and recently for
myself, my father died recently,
and I've been going through all
of his ancestral things, and I
found photographs of my great
grandparents as it happens, and
and I, and I haven't, and was
before I knew I'd spoken to
Tyson and heard this, I have an
uncanny resonance to them that I
can't explain. And it just came
to me, and I've and I
intuitively just put their
photographs on my. Desk, and out
of all the photographs that I
looked at of ancestors and
people like that, those are the
two that I really wanted to look
at. And so I put them on top of
my desk, and they've been
sitting there looking at me for
the last few months, or month or
so. And so there's something in
that I believe, and I think it's
interesting that, yes, it
follows. It does tend to follow
through family lineages, but it
also hops about. And there may,
there may be a deeper storyline
to that that we could go into
another time. But yeah, I'll
hook another question out.
Sorry, I kind of wanted to touch
that one. There was also one
about wounding, which was from
the past, one, which I thought
was important not to miss, about
healing trauma in the body. And
I think it connects to some of
the further later questions,
which are about the nature of
incarnation and how we, you
know, what it really, what it
means to be in one of these. And
the way I understand it through
the work I do is that, you know,
as as you so well put Chris, you
know, we're, we're kind of
moving on now from this up and
out philosophy of like we have
to get, you know, we have to
attain this enlightened state,
and then we're out, and we're
beyond Samsara, and we're moving
on to another plane. And I speak
more about being down and in.
You know that the more work we
do internally, inside ourselves,
to clear patterns, to transmute
shadows, to forgive and let go
of trauma, through the physical,
emotional, mental body of our
being, then the more space there
is for us to incarnate more
deeply. So it's like our soul is
is a vast thing. It's vast. It
exists in another dimension.
Most of it's not here. Most of
us haven't incarnated, actually.
And so the more that work we do
inside us, inside our being, and
particularly I bring a deep
focus to the belly, to the
navel, which is where everything
seems to cluster, so that as you
clear your being, then more
light can, can actually come in
and live here and and more, you
know, you begin to radiate.
More. You begin you, you begin
to unlock more of that joy and
more of that healing energy
that's inside you, more of that
trapped energy, because more of
your soul can, can come here.
It's a bit like that's how
heaven comes to earth, through
us doing this shadow work, and
then more of us incarnate. So I
wanted to say that because it
felt like really important
connection between trauma and
incarnation. So I'm gonna let
you take it from there.
Chris Bache: Well, let me toss a
couple of these questions here.
One of them, I thought two of
them stand out to me. One is,
why do we forget our past lives
in the first place? And a
variation on that question is,
if we are all eternal, immortal
and infinite, what is the point
of reincarnation in a different
physical body? Could we not all
live eternity, different
experiences, places and people
in one body? And when I've been
talking about this to my
students, I ask them to imagine,
imagine that you are the
creative intelligence of the
universe, and you wanted to
design a system to maximize
accelerated learning,
accelerated development. And you
had two scenarios. You could
create a body that would live
100,000 years, and then set them
loose in the world to gather
100,000 years worth of
experiences. And you could plan
B would be to create a body that
lived 100 years. And every 100
years, you pull it out, and then
you plug it into the system in a
different body, a different
gender, different sex, and
different, you know, role in
society. At the end of 100,000
years, which of those two
systems do you think would
produce the most evolved being?
And I think we'd recognize
quickly that it's the one that
has discontinuity, because
discontinuity leads to greater
variety. Greater variety leads
to more accelerated learning.
And so the reason we forget our
former lives is precisely, I
think, so that we can completely
immerse ourselves in a new set
of circumstances that are
different, and it's the
differences that make them
challenging to us, and those
differences basically accelerate
our learning process. That said,
there comes a time, I think,
when the soul begins a process
of not simply differentiating
and gathering, differentiating
and gathering. But a process of
bringing in, bringing those
lives together, and when we
begin to assimilate the lives
that we have led, what often
occur, what manifest in our
lives first are the pain or the
problems left over from these
other incarnations, the tensions
and stresses. But as we continue
to work with those we begin to
tap into, I think, also the
assets of those lives, the
virtues and the capacities that
those lives have. And see, I
think much of our discussion of
reincarnation is influenced by
the past life literature. And
the past life literature is a
therapeutic literature where
people come to therapy because
they're they're carrying a pain.
But I think most of our past
lives don't manifest as pain in
our present life. Most of our
past lives manifest as
capacities, as skills, as
knowledge, as a capacity to do
things and know things, so we
have to be careful not to get
our understanding tilted just
towards the pain that that's a
figural part, but it's also all
the other things that are latent
in most lives. So there comes a
time when we begin to integrate
those lives and begin to bring
them together, and that's a sort
of a different stage than
earlier, when we were going out
and seeking new and different
experiences. And I think we are
coming at a time in history
where the emphasis is on
integrating our past, not simply
pushing the boundaries of our
past into new territory.
Richard Rudd: Yeah, yeah, that's
a great point, Chris. And I
think you know what we were
talking about earlier. You know
that what's being processed on
an internal level then is
manifesting externally as well.
By the way, be careful of your
mic, because sometimes it's
griping and so what we're seeing
in the world is we're seeing the
after effect of an inner
transfer, transmutation that's
taking place through the through
the group soul of humanity, the
group consciousness. And, yeah,
that was, I was looking at that
question about, you know, are
there parallel universes to
incarnate into? And it made me
think of, you know when you
know, when a soul evolves to
that level of beginning to kind
of, you know, beginning to
transmute more of the karma of
the of the world, or of the, you
know, of the suffering of the
world. There also is a more
there's a seems to be a greater
elasticity available to that
being, to that, to that aspect
of consciousness. So there's a
little bit more play, and that
means that there's more ability
to travel, to kind of
transmigrate between dimensions,
and to be able to kind of break
some of the rules of the
linearity of incarnating
sequences, you know, because
there's this like idea that
there's time, and we're moving
with like we're stitching this
beautiful cloth, this fabric
through coming in and out of
lives like that. And I think
that that, I think probably
there are many lives where we do
do that. But I think as we gain
in wisdom and soul evolution,
sorry excuse me, then we begin
to kind of reach a higher
velocity or higher frequency
where time is more is more
flexible for us, you know. So
some of you asked like
questions, like about, do we
have specific, do I have
specific memories of past lives
and and I kind of, I do in a
way. And I also don't, because
there's a part of my mind stream
that doesn't wish to cling to
locations in the space time
continuum, because there's a
playfulness I find in the way
that my mind operates. It reads
the whole stream, or it reads a
whole fractal, or a whole
pathway and a passage down a
lineage, and then it feels a
resonance somewhere, and then it
follows another one, and it
feels a resonance there. And
they're forward and backward in
time, you know? So they're not
just historical, they're more
mythic, and so there's more of a
there's more of an inter
dimensional play, the more
experience, let's say, a soul,
and a soul essence has gained.
And I think that's kind of
that's where we. Cross over into
other dimensions, and perhaps
even travel with beings from
other dimensions for periods of
time, so and have connection and
connectivity and memory of
beings in other dimensions, or
awareness of sometimes twins
even kind of like a twin energy
in another dimension, and that
can appear to us in many
different ways. And I've heard a
lot of stories down the years of
people who have that kind of
feeling, you know that they
carry, that they carry, that
they're not alone. There's
something traveling with them
and and whether they give that a
name or not, it's something
that's sort of that they're
participating in another kind of
level of experiment. So I think
there are so many layers and
intricacies within this woven
tapestry of time, space, you
know. And what's clear is that
in our talk, Chris, we decided
we started to explore this
notion of deep time, where you
begin to kind of step outside
the space. Time can dimension,
and then, you know, 10,000 years
on the earth can pass, you know,
as a single stitch in time, out
of the form. That's an almost
instantaneous so we have that
idea that, Oh, I may not, you
know, like one of my last
incarnations, I feel is quite a
long time ago and, and so that
might seem like, oh, I I've been
waiting around in some other
plane for a long time. But
actually that was that could at
that time was instantaneous, you
know. So it was just a bigger
loop in the stitching, rather
than lots of little ones. It was
like a bigger loop within the
time continuum. And then also
there's this idea that you can
then go the other way as well.
You can go forwards and take
leaps and loops forwards in the
stitch, in the weaving of this
journey that we're on. And you
can begin to the wider that your
your evolutionary lens becomes,
the more collective it becomes,
the more of the tapestry and the
fabric of reality or of space
time you can see. So it's like
you're no longer just doing a
little stitchy, you know,
pattern in the fabric that
you've been making for you. You
then suddenly see a whole
section of the weave that's been
created. And you suddenly see
your place in that, Oh, I did
that little stitch there, or I
was part of that. And then, and
then it's like, you pan out, and
you're like, it's, it's fast
beyond comprehension, because
there are so many beings, and
they're all one being, and
they're all weaving this
incredible tapestry together.
And it's within this, this
vibrating, rippling fabric of
space time. So there's a lot of
play in here as well, and, and I
think it's important to kind of
open one's heart to that, you
know,
Chris Bache: yeah, beautifully
said, Richard beautifully. You
know, reincarnation answers
certain questions, but in many
ways, it really is kind of
changes the direction of the
questions that we're asking. It
just opens us to a much more
complex universe, where we don't
necessarily know the rules of
where everything is going, where
it's heading, but we can begin
to explore it with a different
set of hypotheses, a different
set of assumptions. You know,
there is one question that we
put into this category I'd like
to make sure that we that we get
to and that is the question
about suicide, because it
obviously comes from a very deep
place. One person asked, what
happens with the soul of a
person who commits suicide, and
I'll just throw something in and
then hand it to you, but in a
reincarnating universe where
nothing is eternal, everything
is constantly changing, and
we're learning in incremental
bits. Suicide is just one more
episode of learning. It's not a
mortal sin. It's not doesn't
lead to eternal damnation. There
are many, many reasons why
people may take their lives, and
we may call them all suicide,
but they're not all the same
kind of suicides, they have
very, very different
motivational structures. But
even if we're dealing with a
suicide that comes as an act of
desperation or an act of almost
cowardice, we might say, if it
were, that even that kind of act
is greeted by. Universe with
understanding and with
compassion. When we die and we
begin to go through the life
review and we debrief our life
with the other levels of
intelligence and beings of
intelligence that surround us. I
mean, let's face it, life inside
time and space is hard. It's
challenging, and people get
themselves in all sorts of boxes
and dead ends where they they
get desperate. But even acts
made in desperation do not have
eternal consequences, and we are
not punished for such acts. We
are we are met, and we have to
learn from them. It's important.
I mean, all of our actions can
become habitual. So anger can
become a habit, a character
trait, suicide can also become a
habit that shows up in multiple
incarnations. So it's important
to confront the limits that led
us to such a desperate act and
find out how to bring that those
limits to different outcome, to
bring our life into a different
outcome, but certainly,
certainly, I don't think suicide
leads to anything like perpetual
estrangement from the
intelligence of the universe or
the love of the universe. Your
thoughts? Richard, yeah,
Richard Rudd: well, I was
thinking how suicide is almost,
it's always almost loneliness
taken to its far, far extreme,
isn't it? You know where it's
become so unbearable that you've
you know that that's the only
option you feel there is. And so
that's a very human condition.
You know? It's as you said, it's
like, it's absolutely
understandable that we feel, at
times, deeply lonely, and
sometimes the conditions that
surround us are so difficult and
challenging that, you know, one
can empathize, empathize with
that and and I think you're
right. I think, you know, in one
of the recordings I did recently
that I shared with you was, and
it's, I think we're going to put
a link to it. It's the I called
the rebirth sequence and the and
it's sort of the stages of
moving from dying and going
through these Bardo stages and
but very simply laid out. And
the final stage is called, I
call the arms of the mother. And
it has various levels to it. But
the arms of the mother is that
that's what you land in when
you've gone through those
sequences, those that life
review, and you're coming into
that place of self forgiveness,
you know, because you are
forgiven, but you have to
forgive yourself. And that
includes, also not just, you
know, that includes acts of
aggression and violence towards
others, or it could be things
like murder, you know. And you
know terrible things that take
place on this earth plane. So
the view from without, you know,
outside the human this human
plane in from the arms of the
mother is not, as you said, it's
not about revenge or
retribution. It's simply about
reconciliation and
transmutation, and a lot of the
times about forgiveness, self
forgiveness. You know, we we
have to, at some level, the soul
has to learn from whatever it's
done, and then absorb and
integrate that and forgive and
move on and become stronger
through it. And that's what this
whole reincarnating pathway
journey is offering us. So if
you really tune in deeply, like
you have Chris and your journeys
into the, you know, into the
into the field of wounding. And
in your book, as you describe,
you realize that you have done,
we've all done atrocious things.
You know, in our history, we
carry the memory of of terrible
deeds that we were party to or
part of, or on the victim side
of, and carry, and all kinds of
levels all inside us. I mean, I
have a hunch that a lot of that
memory is CO is in the non
coding DNA in our body. You
know, the so called junk DNA
that forms almost 90% of of our
DNA, that's that's not we can't
understand, we can't see that it
what it codes for. And so
somewhere in inside here are all
those, those memories of of
places we've been, people we've
been things, we've done. And.
Isn't the most beautiful insight
that arises from that, from an
incarnating worldview that we
are always forgiven, you know,
we love, we you know. And
knowing that you know that it,
it opens up the the journey of
the higher soul. You know,
because then the soul begins to
experience itself as light, as
as a Christ impulse, or a Buddha
impulse, and it begins to kind
of really become a beacon and
wishes to help others and be of
service and enter into that
higher evolution. And that seems
to me to be the natural
progression of the deep. And you
know that deep kind of encounter
with the nature of what we call
evil, or you know, or sin, you
know, and and that is like the
or suffering you know. That is
the edge that that helps us
become better people, better
beings, you know, more beautiful
beings, ultimately, through self
forgiveness and forgiveness of
others and and it, but it takes
a wide it's a big it's a big
stretch. For some people that I
understand that it's a big
stretch.
Chris Bache: So, yeah, yeah,
forgiveness of ourselves and
forgiveness of others, but also
restitution. There's nothing
that we've done that we can't
repair, that we can't make
better, because we have
opportunity, we have time. We
can change our past by changing
our present and by moving
forward, we can make
restitution, we can help, we can
bring healing, where we brought
entry before, yeah, maybe I'm
very much aware that we have
many questions that are stacking
up in the Q and A, but I know
that we wanted to touch briefly
On the coming shift. Because for
a couple of questions about the
coming shift, let me just
mention a couple. One person
wrote, I feel very worried about
the changes ahead that you spoke
about, and wonder if you could
offer a sense of hope to those
of us who are struggling. And
another person said, I think
this shift that you are
discussing can happen in as soon
as 20 years. So very different
kind of takes on this. And I
think there is, I think there is
great grounds for hope. And it's
not not the hope that we can
avoid the suffering that's
coming at us so that we can
change it, but the hope based on
trust and trust on the
intelligence of the universe,
and that the intelligence that
had brought us through the
oxygen crisis billions of years
ago, and the intelligence that
gave us the 50% increase in the
size of our brain 200,000 years
ago, and the intelligence that
we see bubbling up underneath us
all over layer after layer in
the natural world, that
intelligence has brought the
human race to this point in its
story where it is basically
forcing us to shed the
limitations of living at a level
of awareness of just our
private, egoic body, mind
awareness and the summons is to
live out of a deeper soul
awareness with a deeper set of
our felt connection to other
beings and to other species, and
to the planet as a whole, and to
life as a whole, I think there's
tremendous grounds for hope, but
the kind of hope that is not the
hope and the avoidance of pain
and suffering, but the type of
hope that's born in the middle
of pain and suffering Out of a
deep, deep conviction that there
is a deeper intelligence It's
expressing itself. We may not be
able to see the full parameters
of this intelligence, but we
can. We can have the confidence
that this television
intelligence is functioning here
as it does function in other
areas of life,
Richard Rudd: exactly, and, and
that, that intelligence is
essentially benevolent, you
know, it is, it has, it has that
it, you know, it's highest, as I
described just now. It's like it
through suffering, it comes to
know, its higher nature, you
know? And so as we experience
that as individual souls, so as
more and more of us begin to
come to that point, inside our
inside our own souls, evolution,
then the whole of humanity
begins to come towards that
realization that we are actually
one being here doing this. You
know, and so we see this
externally, through the through
the way we our world now
operates through the internet
and through, you know, this,
this global connectivity that we
now have. And yet, we also see
all the shadows through that
more clearly than we ever have
and but we're also, we have the
capacity, potentially, to kind
of heal the situation more than
we ever have, because we have
this connectivity. And humanity
seems to kind of need to drive
itself to the edge of a
precipice. Sometimes it seems to
be a pattern. Again, talking to
the indigenous people I've been
talking to recently, they say,
you know, in their memory banks,
their racial memory banks are,
oh, this has happened, you know,
many, many times. You know that
we've come to crisis and and
they're talking millions of
years, even, you know, the
memory banks go a long, long
way. And so, you know, sometimes
we have to come to these Crux
points in order for there to be
enough of a kind of energy shift
for us to push us, you know, to
push us over and through. And
that's not a, not a pleasant
situation, and it and as that
energy builds more and more
towards that we will
collectively feel more and more
uneasy in our in our sort of
body biome, however, in the soul
awareness that you know as we,
as we expand into that more and
more deeply and into that trust,
that field of trust That's
underpinning the whole process,
and that's underlying creation
that then begin, that can then
begin to inform our biology. And
it really does you know that I
know that Chris and myself, we
both feel deeply safe in this
world, even as the world begins
to move closer and closer
towards what looks like a kind
of, you know, Armageddon type
scenario, but there's this
underlying benevolence, and as
you say, Chris, intelligence,
that is, that is preparing us
for this quantum leap, and we
have to kind of really sink into
that trust field in the that is
embedded in the eternal nature
of our soul. So this journey
into kind of expanding our
awareness of the incarnating
universe and humanity is really,
really important, because it
opens up, first of all, opens up
the mind to begin to, like, play
again, like, you know, this is
like when we were teenagers. The
teenage mind loves this realm,
you know. And for many of us,
when we went into our kind of
20s and 30s, then, because of
the way we condition mentally,
intellectually by the
materialistic viewpoint, many of
us, then these kind of
conditioning paradigms fall over
us, like, like a kind of heavy
cloak, and so it's, it's
actually can be a great fun and
a huge relief to kind of shed
some of that stuff. And it
doesn't mean we're shedding
science and all its wonderful
revelations. It just means we're
opening up to a deeper kind of
set of possibilities and and the
mind then kind of can go, wow,
anything really is possible. You
know, we do live in a, in a, you
know, in a magical universe
where, yeah, we can't understand
everything yet, you know. And,
but, you know, science is very
slow in its kind of methodical
processing. It moves at its own
pace, but the mind can really
expand and open up to great
vistas, and that that's the
first stage, I think, in
beginning to kind of feel safe
inside oneself again. So I want,
I really hope, that that's a
part of the journey that we can
help build Chris here together
by continuing to map these other
Chris Bache: realms. Yeah, yes,
very much. So we're committed.
We're committed. We're here. And
you know, one of the things I
talk about in terms of this
coming era, is the birth of the
diamond soul in history. And I
think actually the conversation
that you and I are having here,
with all the people who are
gathered with us is a small part
of that process to become
because, to become aware of
reincarnation, to become
intellectually and in your
heart, aware of this larger
story that's playing itself out
inside your life. When you
become aware of something, you
give permission for that thing
to manifest more deeply into
your life, so to become aware of
reincarnation, to become aware
of the soul, and that the
dynamics actually i. Think it
facilitates the emergence of the
diamond soul in your own
awareness, in your own being.
And I suspect this awareness can
come in slowly for some people
and in some circumstances, and
it could come in dramatically
and with sort of stunning
effects in other circumstances.
But it's all coming in and to be
conscious of something conscious
even of the possibility actually
facilitates this deeper
integration taking place. Shall
we shift to some of the
questions coming in from our
live audience? Yeah, before the
money that we haven't touched
on,
Richard Rudd: before we do that,
I want to just nail a couple of
the gene keys questions. Oh yes,
yes. More specific to me. You
know, someone asked, and I have
been asked this before, like
this, this, this notion that of
walk ins, of like a being that
comes into a body and kind of
supersedes it in some way. And,
you know, some people say, Look,
I've had an experience like
that, and I was completely
changed after that experience. I
was a new person. And, you know,
should I study a different gene
keys profile, you know, and from
that date, and what I'd say is
that it's important to have
both, because, you know, it's,
it's, it's like, you need the
old root stock. You know, it's
really important to have the
root stock. And then if there's
a new kind of hybrid that's come
in, those two have to harmonize
together. So you can use both,
and you can explore both, and
that's an added complexity for
you, but it's also a rich
journey to explore. So play with
that, as you wish I would say.
And there's also a question
about gene keys once gene keys,
which are these algorithms that
kind of determine our our kind
of awakening journey and our
incarnation and its themes? You
know they do. They? Is there a
continuity between them?
Absolutely, I would say that
there is a continuity between
sequences. But you don't have
the same sequences. And, well,
you might Through, through, you
know, some kind of sleight of
hand of the Creator or whatever.
But it's not this. You know,
that there's a there are, there
are patterns woven within the
matrix and the numbers that if
you were able to really look at
different, lots of different,
like lifetimes, you would begin
to see these patterns and
sequences. But they're not
always like obvious and clear. I
can, I can feel them, and as
when I used to do human design.
I mean, not human design, but
when I used to do gene keys
readings for people and human
design readings, I would see all
these patterns between people
and their families and their
partners and their loved ones.
And you get to see recurring
numbers and sequences, so, you
know, and it's really, really a
lot. So you get to see, wow,
this stuff that is so densely
woven, these patterns in the
fabric of these numbers, that
it's showing me something that
is not just kind of kept to one
lifetime. It actually continues
on. It's the thick in there are
these threads that, like I said
earlier that we're weaving So,
yes, there are continuities.
More on that at a later date, I
think. But yeah, let's, let's
move to some of the live
questions.
Chris Bache: So many good
questions here. I'm just
scanning through the list so
many wonderful questions. We're
going to need more time.
Richard, one touches me here it
says, Why do you suppose that
souls reincarnate for short
periods of time, like the infant
that dies just after birth or a
young child that dies very
young? These are great
heartaches, of course, for any
parent or anyone who experiences
the death of a child, and I just
suggest that things which look
very large from inside the time
space perspective, and from
inside the egoic time space
perspective, from the soul
perspective, don't look
necessarily the same that it it
it feels, it feels tragic for us
to have a short lived life. But
for the soul, they're all short
lived lives, a 10 Minute life
and 100 year life are all
relatively small bits of time
against the vast spectrum of the
souls lifetime and sometimes,
you know, some of the past life
therapists have engaged souls
who have had this experience,
and they all generally tend to
agree that the most part they
are chosen incarnations. They
chose the Incarnation knowing
they were getting into.
Sometimes the out the lesson was
for. Someone else. It was to see
the be the grain of sand and the
oyster that leads to a
development of other people.
Sometimes it's but they are
chosen. They are they are all
part of an ongoing and unfolding
process. And it doesn't mean, of
course, with reincarnation, we
really have true intellectual
permission to really understand
that our life does not begin at
birth and it does not end at
death, so we can let go of the
heartache. I mean, there is
separation in death and there is
separating, and there is pain
when a life that we wanted to
spend a lot of time with, we
don't get to spend that time
with but life does not end at
death. Relationships do not end
at death, and purpose is not
extinguished in death.
Richard Rudd: Yeah, beautifully
answered. That's such a tender
question as well. So malabika
has asked a question about the
soul outgrowing guy and moving
on to other systems and and can
the soul determine where it will
go, when and as what? And, you
know, so there's this notion of
how much free will, does the
soul have? And are there other
kind of forces at work? This is
a big, deep, deep question. I
kind of, I think we touched on
it a little bit in our sessions,
but for me, it's that, it's that
kind of notion of these two
forces of evolution and
evolution. And there's evolution
where the soul, let's took,
talking about it as a soul
evolution. So the soul is
evolving through through its
experiences coming in and out of
the form, and it's getting
broader and wider and more aware
of its universal nature, right?
And then there's also another
force involution, which is the
arms of the mother. You know,
the whole the mother itself, the
whole mother ship, the whole
collective consciousness. You
know, the God conscious, the
divine consciousness that's
doing all this through all
these, these monads, these, you
know, these fractals, these
holographic children, you know,
that are different sort of
crystalline aspects of itself.
But they are it then. So the
whole is also doing it. So there
is, there's both a kind of
choreography from the whole
taking place, and yet within
that, there's also this kind of
serpentine freedom and flow as
the as the crystals, the
individual crystal souls,
diamond souls, let's call them.
Become more and more aware that
they are of what they really
are, that they are the whole,
and yet they also exist in the
paradox of being a part of the
whole. How can that both the
ocean and the drop? How can both
of those take place? How can
that occur that's beyond the
mind's capacity to understand in
you know, that's a paradox, and
a paradox of startling truth
that can only be known as a kind
of as a through a bolt of
Revelation, I would say so. Both
are true. You know that we
determine where we're going. The
soul determines, but also the
mother determines. The
mothership has its own
choreography and dance that
we're a part of. And it's, it's
an incredible dance playing with
that paradox. That's all I can
say, is just to lay out the
paradox before us so that we can
consider it. Yeah, thanks.
Malabika,
oh, I think you're muted. Chris,
Chris Bache: thank you. A
question from Catherine says
Buddhists say that reincarnation
is like transferring the light
from one candle to another. What
do you think of this
interpretation? This way, it can
be transferred. This way, it can
transfer both personal and
collective, karmic stuff. I
think when the Buddha was asked
a question about, what is the
self and the self that
incarnate. So we have many ways
of thinking about reincarnation
which are not very subtle and
not very adequate. And many
people think of the
reincarnation as a self
migrating from life to life. And
when the Buddha was asked this
question, he lie, had a series
of candles lined up, and he had
one. Lit and then he lit the
second one, blew out the first
one, lit the third one blew out
the second one, and passed the
candle flame all the way down
the line. And so then the
question is at the end, is it
the same candle flame, or is it
a different candle flame? And
the answer is, well, it's both,
but Buddhist wants to emphasize
it's a different candle flame.
And it's actually, if you get
right down to it, it's a
different candle flame from
second to second. So the
important point here for the
Buddhism is the teaching of no
self, that and no self is the
teaching, not that we aren't
individuals. That's an often
that's a misguided
interpretation of it. It doesn't
mean that there isn't an
individuality here. What it
means is there is no permanent
individuality and there is no
separate individuality. So there
is no permanent self which never
changes, and there is no
separate self, which is cut off
from the rest of existence, so
that the individuality, which
is, I think, the essential,
well, the center of our
individual experience, is open.
It's porous. It takes in
information and experiences and
energy from beings. It gives out
its own energy. And it's not
static. It's constantly changing
over time. So I think if we were
to take the Buddhist example of
the candle, it would lead to a
more subtle description of the
categories of reincarnation. And
that, I think, is the great
value of the exercise. It's the
subtlety of that description.
Likewise, I think that feel
theory is very is a very good
set of categories and metaphors
to talk about the soul, that
that the soul isn't an entity or
a thing or a machine or a
separate, you know, nut, if we
think in souls of souls in terms
of feels. Feels are, by
definition, open. They're open
at the boundaries. There's an
easier give and take between
fields and so, yeah, good
question.
Richard Rudd: Catherine,
beautiful answer. Chris, really
that was really beautifully put
and really great to have your
your vast knowledge of you know
different theologies here as
well, brought to the fore. Some
Nishad has asked about the Bardo
realms, which maybe both of us
could say something on. And
she's suggesting, is it possible
this life is in Bardo? So those
of you don't know the Tibetan
Buddhist, only Tibetans. I
think, is it only the Tibetans
that that name the Bardo
Chris Bache: Chris, their
vocabulary? I think, yeah,
Richard Rudd: so there's this
notion of the Bardo is the is
the transitory threshold state
between lives or it. That's one
way of understanding it. It's
the stages as we move from one
state to another state. And
there's a whole description of
different, you know, stages and
states that they will describe
as we move from birth to death
and death to birth. And so
there's a transformational
process that goes on in that,
and there's also attachments to
those different layers and
layering. So the way I kind of
would understand it on a very
broad level, is that, because
the another way you could the
word Bardo has started to be
used by Western people, more
perhaps, is as a to refer to a
kind of an impermanent realm, a
changing realm, a transitionary
realm, or transitionary world or
sphere. And so in that, from
that perspective, yes, it is
possible that the earth is one
of those Bardos, and it is one
of those experiences that the
whole is exploring. And it
explores these theaters, let's
call them theaters, you know. So
it explores this theater, and
there's all these characters and
storylines that come together in
this theater and all these plays
that take place and, and the and
the whole is the audience, you
know, that's that's just
watching the whole, you know,
expansion of this process and,
and the whole, or the audience,
is out side of space and time.
And yet all the Bardo is exist
within space and time. So they
are the they are these journeys
and theaters and productions you
know, from hell to heaven and
all these you know, because
there's the heaven realms of the
deities and all the bliss
realms, and then there's the and
then there's the hell realms
with all the stuff. Offering.
And then there's all the places
in between. And all of those
are, in one sense, you could say
that they are, they are Bardos
experiences between states and
and so, yeah, it's all a
theater, as Shakespeare said. So
anyway, that's my, my, my
starting there, but you might
want to add some more of your
wisdom,
Chris Bache: yeah, well, no, you
say it, well, it's, it is
sobering. I mean the teaching.
There are different aspects of
the Bardo teaching, and the word
Bardo is used in different ways,
but you know it, one of the ways
it's used is in terms of the
levels of existence, as you say,
from the lowest hell realm to
the Hungry Ghost Realm, animal
realm, human, lower deities and
higher deity realms that there
are, these are exist in the
cosmos. They exist in the
spiritual world that lies
outside of physical reality. And
we enter into those various
Bardos, various levels of
reality, depending upon the
quality of our consciousness
that we have accumulated over a
course of many lifetimes. So,
but then it gets much more
intimate when the teacher says,
all those Bardos are taking
place right now in the physical
world, right here, right now. So
there are deity realms. There
are people who are born with a
silver spoon in their mouth, and
they just seem to everything
always goes well with them.
They're the captain of the
football team, or everything
just kind of breaks their way.
And there are other people who
are living in Hill realms, and
everything is changing.
Everything is turning over. And
then we can get even more
intense. It reminds me of a
story. I don't know whether I
can remember it completely, but
there was a samurai who came to
a Zen master, and he wanted to
understand the difference
between heaven and hell, and the
Zen master basically stood
there, and he began to insult
the samurai and tell him that
his clothes were dirty and his
sword was dull and he really
wasn't, wasn't wasn't worthy of
the name of samurai. And the
Samurai, of course, had
permission to kill anyone that
they deemed deserving of death.
And so he pulled out his sir
Lord, and he held it over the
Zen master about to cut off his
head. And the Zen master said,
That's hell. And then the
samurai recognized the great
compassion of the teacher who
had put his life at risk in
order to give him this lesson,
and he immediately felt
compassion and put away a sword.
And the teacher said, That's
heaven. So it's not just states
that last for an entire
lifetime. They're states that
last minute by minute, we're
constantly going in and out of
different levels of reality
minute by minute, then the
invitation is, what is it that
doesn't change? What is it that
is inside us that witnesses
everything and doesn't change as
our emotions change, as our
bodies change, as all these
things change. What is it that
doesn't change when we discover
that and then we hold that in
our awareness while we are
living these changes. It changes
the quality of the life that
we're living. It just kind of
deepens. It grounds us deeper
into the into the living quality
of the deep texture of existence
is to live in, in God awareness,
or in the divine awareness, or
in the in the awareness of the
Living Universe. Beautiful.
Richard Rudd: And thank you for
that great story you know
occurred to me that one of the
great modern, clear metaphors
for the whole reincarnative
story is, is Groundhog Day, you
know, because that film is
wonderful, funny film. It's so
wise. It's it hits something
very deep inside us, you know.
And many people have had that
same feeling like this is like
this repeat of like, trying
things out in different ways,
and then trying to take
advantage of it, and then try
and then becoming hopeless with
it, and then all the different
dramas that get played out in
one day, you know, and that you
could, that's the metaphor for
here, this planet, one light,
one world, all those different
dramas to play out until you
come to create the perfect day,
you know, like the absolute,
just your perfect day. What's
your perfect life? You know.
And, and then you're kind of
like, ah, that's, that's what it
is, I you know. And, and you've
brought it to the you've brought
it to the zenith, to the
crescendo. You've perfected your
soul within it, you know, even
though you had to go through
some terrible things, you know.
And. And, yeah, so I like that
idea, and I because I was, you
know, I know there's lots of
other questions, but it just
came to me as you were talking.
And, yeah, what do you think
about that? It's a good one,
isn't it?
Chris Bache: You're muted.
Chris, yeah. Oh, this is, Am I
on now? Yeah, it is. Here's the
Here's another good one. Maybe
mention this one here. Sherry
writes, I have had many traumas
in this lifetime. I'm tired of
all the spiritual practices and
processing. There are so many
different ones. I have done so
much spiritual work. This is why
I love Jean Keyes and Richard's
way of teaching. I'm at a point
of just desiring to be the love
I know myself to be. And her
question is, do you think it is
necessary to do past life
regression? I do not have the
money to go to those who do this
type of work. Or will we ever
just be the love and know that
that to be enough? And I this
has been the flavor of a few of
the other questions we received.
And no, I don't think you have
to go to past life therapy in
order to engage one's karma
conscientiously and to heal what
needs healing and to deepen what
we have an opportunity to
deepen. What's important is to
live one's life well. And if you
live your life well, all the
karma from your past that will
will come up in your life at
some time and circumstance. And
if you're living your life well,
you're taking care of business
as you go. Remember that
reincarnation has been going on
for hundreds of 1000s of years,
and it goes on and it works very
well, whether or not we know
that reincarnation is happening,
whether we know or believe or
understand reincarnation and
karma, it's still happening.
It's still been going on. It was
going on in the 15th century. It
was going on 1000 years ago, or
2000 years ago. What awareness
of reincarnation adds? It adds
an awareness. And with
awareness, we accelerate the
process. We can speed up the
process. We can we can stop
avoiding things and start
embracing more things. And as we
embrace more things, we solve
more issues. And as we solve
more issues, we live a more
relaxed life, a more open and
challenging life. So no, I my
two cents is I don't think
anyone needs to do past life
therapy in order to live a very
well and satisfying life. Live
your life deeply. It's all. All
your karma is right here around
you at the time. Live it well.
Live it deeply. If you want some
help getting around a particular
issue or getting a particular
boulder out of your life, well,
that can be it can be helpful if
you can do it. But it's kind of
a, it's an extra
Richard Rudd: great, great and a
lovely question as well, you
know, really beautifully phrased
like that, the being just is,
it's enough to just be. It is,
of course, it's enough to be.
That's a, that's the most,
that's, that's the most we can
do, really, you know. So I'm
very much resonate with that
question. There's a question
here about old and new souls,
and number of souls and, you
know, and and kind of
populations expanding and
contracting. And it's
interesting question. And, you
know, if you think about it,
like most of the answers lie in
nature, you know, and and if
you're observant and you're
listening and you're looking and
you really contemplating nature,
most of the answers are there,
you know, I like you're walking
through a forest or a word, and
you look in there and you see
all These plants and trees. And
there are old trees, and there
are kind of middle aged trees,
and then there are young, kind
of ones shooting up everywhere.
And then there are parasite
trees. And there are all kinds
of, you know, there are weeds,
and there's, you know, they're
all in there, and they're all
part of this ecosphere. And the
same here on this earth, you
know, on Gaia, we have, you
know, enlightened beings. You
know, we have beautiful beings.
We have villains and ruffians
and vagabonds, and we have all
the different souls, exploring
and experimenting. We have young
ones, young little saplings that
are still learning that kind of,
you know, maybe get involved in
all kinds of difficult things
and suffering, deep in
suffering, and deep into
corruption and and and learning.
Are learning through that, you
know. And then there are older
ones. Ian's perhaps, who've done
all that. And they're like here,
and they're like, trying to kind
of work more deeply into the
collective, or into some, you
know, area where they've taken
on a lot of suffering, you know,
to heal either inside
themselves, on behalf of the
whole or they're working in
service, in the service
professions or whatever, where,
you know, in service in some
way. So there's all these
different, you know, story lines
and threads within the picture,
and, and, and sometimes, you
know, the forest dies back in
places and it and it's, it's
less populous. And then there's
sometimes when it suddenly
expands and it's more and
there's and it does. It's
thriving, but they're all phases
then none of it's healthy or
unhealthy. It's just what it is.
It's just part of the of the the
whole theater, the tapestry. So
you know, one of the things that
the whole reincarnating view,
the rebirth view really brings
to me is this sense of, you
know, amorality, you know, and
that doesn't, doesn't take away,
you know, true morals and
ethics, and you know that are
naturally inherent in human
beings, I believe. But there's
this kind of, it's just going
on, and there's a journey taking
place, and we're at some point
in that journey right now. The
Collective is in some point
right now. Our individuality is
at some point participating in
that right now. And as I I, I
was really sharing deeply
recently, in the process, I'm
taking a big retreat, 1000s of
people in the Venus sequence,
which it's a process of healing
trauma, emotional trauma,
especially. And I was saying,
you know, when you heal some
pattern inside your own being,
then you reach out and you heal
it in the whole in the
collective, because it is all
just one rippling web, one
interconnected, woven web. I
mean, I seem to be saying the
same thing over and over, but I
really want people to
understand, you know, that, yes,
it's kind of, this is, this is
the theater, old souls, new
souls, you know, and then
there's old souls. And maybe,
yes, when you get to a certain
stage, you have more choice
available to you. You can leave,
you can go somewhere else, you
know, it's like you've earned
it. You've you've earned enough
money to be able to buy a ticket
somewhere else, further. And,
and it's, you know, that's the
kind of metaphor, so, but yeah,
then you might also come back,
you know, and bring your wisdom
here. So I think there's a lot
of the sinkers, a lot of a lot
of, you know, imagination that
is needed when we're entering
into this, into this kind of
territory.
Chris Bache: Yes, very much. So
you know reincarnation, you have
to live with it for a long time
and then bring that, bring the
questions that people are asking
to into that reincarnation
paradigm and sit with it for a
long time to get intimations of
the depth the way it
recontextualizes and gives a new
context for the way we usually
think about these things. And
here's a question that really
stretches us, a question by
Jacqueline she and this is a
challenging question, how can
collective suffering be a
creative process rooted in
cosmic love? How can Creative
Collective suffering be a
creative process rooted in
cosmic love? That's a hard
question, just because the sheer
scale first it works. It's it's
a question that's hard for an
individual life. How does
suffering, you know, is, how is
suffering in our individual life
compatible with the idea that
the universe is compassionate
and loving, but at a collective
level, how does collective
suffering of the type that we
were talking about in our third
dialog, in our coming, you know,
our coming, challenging period
of history. How can that mag
magnitude, of that suffering, of
that magnitude be a creative
process rooted in cosmic love?
And I'm reminded that
Ramakrishna, the great Hindu
saint said, if you want to
understand God, you must be
willing to look evil in the
face, because evil is not
outside the divine, but it's
actually part of the Divine
process, and suffering is part
of the Divine process. So in. We
want to understand how any
compassionate person wants to
reduce suffering and end
suffering. That's the natural
impetus. That's what we want.
And we see suffering as the
enemy, and it's something we
want to stop. But when we start
to second guess creation, when
we start to think there has to
have been a better way to do it,
God, you know, damn it, you
know. Couldn't you have given us
everything that you want us to
become without dragging us
through so many centuries and
millennia of pain and suffering
are taking us more in the
future? That's a wonderful
impulse, but that assumes that
we we know what the project is,
that we know what the agenda is,
and that we know what is the
best way to get to that
particular outcome. So we would
have to ask, what is the
project? What is the project of
cosmic love. What are we doing
here? What is creation growing
on this planet Earth? And could
it grow a species of diamond
beings? Could it grow a species
of fully awakened beings and
fully empowered beings, and a
species that can create out of
the sheer power of the divine
consciousness that lives that is
flowing in their awareness
without having to have gone
through some of the ordeals that
we have gone through In our long
evolutionary agenda. This is
challenging. And I on the one
hand, I want to affirm the
compassion behind the question,
and I want to invite a deep
sitting with the scale of
creation. We have to look at the
galaxies and look at the stars
to appreciate the scale that the
universe thinks on, and the
scale of the creative
intelligence thinks on. And look
at all the stages of evolution
that humanity and all life on
this planet has gone through.
Suffering seems to be part of
it. Is just part of the grit of
life that brings us forward.
Now, I think we may be coming
into a time when we won't have
to grow through suffering so
much as we have in the past that
we I think suffering has been
part of the paradigm of how we
have grown in the past, and it
may be that we'll be able to
grow out of grace more in the
future, that we be challenged By
creativity, not simply by our
pain, but certainly suffering
has been part of the stuff which
has brought us where we are, and
I think where we're going. It
suffering takes things away from
us. It breaks us down. It
doesn't allow us to continue the
way we are. It forces us to
reassess and do and to look at
things anew. And I think we're
coming into a time where in
order for something radically
new to come into the human
story, we have to let go of what
we have been. And letting go of
what we have been is hard work
and does involve a certain
amount of suffering, but the
sooner we cooperate with this
process, the sooner we surrender
to it, the sooner we let it go,
and the sooner we start taking
care of each other with that
deep compassion which is rooted
in that cosmic Love, the sooner
the suffering ends and the
creativity begins. I know that's
not a completely adequate answer
to the depth of this question,
but it's, it's just a piece.
Richard Rudd: Thank you so much
for that. I mean, I'll add a
layer, which is in, in the in
the book I wrote the gene keys
book, I laid out the kind of, as
I see it, the codes of
consciousness available to
humanity, you know, and and so
you see this through these
shadows and these different
these low frequency shadow
patterns that we, all you know,
play out with playing in the
suffering, and then hidden
inside those are these potential
gifts. And then even inside
those gifts, those gifts are the
creative flowering, the healing,
if you like, of the growing
through that suffering. And then
out of that comes this, this
fruit, which is, I call the
cities, the 64 cities. And this
is like, probably where we want
to bring our talk to a close
with this, with this notion of,
there's something hidden deep in
the in the core of that
suffering, and it is something
so. Are beyond what we can
understand now, and it's
something so beautiful, and it's
another realm, it's another
dimension, it's another way,
another field of learning, you
know, and we might call it
grace, or might call it bliss,
and it's another whole. And
well, you could even say we may
be entering the epoch in which
incarnation itself starts to
fall apart and starts to open up
and so that we no longer need to
move in and out of these forms
in the way we did. We may one
day look back and go, Oh, yeah,
we used to have to differentiate
in that way because of the
shadow and the impetus of the
shadow inside us. But now we've
explored that fully. We can sit
in these cities. These cities
are the these, these higher
states of consciousness, these
avataric fields of oneness, and
we can still retain our souls,
wisdom and individuality and its
journeys and its continuation
and its continued adventures,
but from within a much greater
field and of understanding and
compassion, you know, and these
Cities are the kind of these
Buddhic fields that are opening
up for us in the future. And I
think it's, you know, Chris and
I, we set this talk for Good
Friday, for good reason. In a
way, it just fell there very
beautifully, because it's, it's
this notion of the constant
rebirthing of the universe, of
itself, from within itself, and
it's just it, you know, I was
saying recently that it's like,
if you take the image of the
butterfly, you know, of what a
butterfly is, the myth of the
butterfly, that the allegory,
that the metaphor of the
butterfly, it's, it's, do you
need any more proof for
incarnation, for reincarnation,
than that? You know that that
right there is, is the emblem of
what is hidden inside our
suffering, of what's hidden
inside this, this thing here and
and in this whole journey. So,
so, yes, I think we're moving
into this next phase, and it's
good to be realistic, and it's
also good to really expand and
open up into that and let your
heart really ring out with
what's, what the what the
boundless potentials are inside
you, of your soul, and what
happens if you really have
worked those shadows through,
and then the full soul can come
in, the full soul can come in,
and that the body would hardly
be able to hold it, contain it,
because The incredible frequency
of the quantum field that's
generated from that, what we
call those cities, those and
then then we start to be co
creators with the Creator.
Because then we're like, you
know, our thoughts become all
empowering, and we become these
children of of God, or these
children of Christ, where we get
to play in a much vaster field,
that field that Chris was
talking about, the galactic the
galactic level, the the
universal level, would become a
universal consciousness. And we,
we can kind of interact with
dimensions and paradigms that
right now we can't even begin to
fathom. So I think there's cause
for great hope, more than hope
certainty, really, but we have a
few boulders to clear. First, I
invite you to have the last
word.
Chris Bache: Well, I'm glad you
brought in Easter, because it is
Good Friday, and this is a
special weekend in the Christian
calendar, and I know that you
and I have both been touched by
Christianity, by its teaching,
and by people who have been
steeped in Christian Teaching.
And we have been Christians and
we have been Hindus at different
lifetimes, and we have been
Muslims and we have been
aborigines. We have been all the
religions of the world and the
non religions and atheists we
have we have sampled and drunk
from those wells. We have been
male and female, and in that
constant collecting of
experience, and gathering
experience and bringing that
experience it to higher, higher
levels of fruition, when we
encounter figures like Jesus or
like Siddhartha, Gautama, the
Buddha, or like Muhammad the
Prophet, when those. Beings are
pictured in art. They're always
pictured filled with light. They
have halos around them, and
light just emanates from their
body. And they have so much
energy in them that they can
heal beings with a touch. And
Easter, of course, is, is death
and rebirth, the the
indestructibility of life, death
and rebirth, continually going
and also, of course, the symbol
of compassion, because this is a
being who did not have to
suffer, but who chose to suffer
out of his great love for the
world and every mother worth
their salt, every father worth
their salt, understands that and
would suffer for their children
for this. Those qualities, those
precious qualities, those are
the qualities that we're
developing. Those are the
qualities that we're bringing in
and empowering, and empowering,
as Richard said, the power of
the soul, the energy of the
soul, is huge, and to be able to
internalize the soul, we must
make our body capable of
functioning at that level, the
way Christ was able to function
at that level, the way The
Buddha and the Prophet were able
to function at that level. So I
think that's I think that's what
we're coming to in history, at a
time when we, who have been
struggling in the shadows for so
many generations, are now
beginning to come into a time of
light, a time of great
culmination, a time of greater
freedom, greater compassion,
greater wisdom, and where that
will take us will be a great
adventure, an adventure for us
all. I really appreciate this
conversation we've been having.
Richard, I really appreciate
everyone who's gathered around
us and made this possible and
made this adventure possible.
Thank you very much, everybody.
Deep.
Richard Rudd: Thank you to me or
from, from me also, and to me,
to my soul, to all of you who've
who've joined us and who are
joining us in other timelines
and in other dimensions. And
thank you so much, Chris and we
will. We are going to continue
our journey, Chris and I
together, and we'll have more
for you in the future, I think
so. Yeah, see what that turns
into good you.