Luisa: Passion harvest. Hello,
passionate listeners and
watchers, welcome to passion
harvest. I am Luis, your host,
international passion
ambassador. I am really, really,
really excited about my guest
today, his I've just read his
amazing book, and if you don't
know who he is, Christopher M
Bache, Professor Christopher M
Bache set out to explore his
mind and the mind of the
universe on what will become a
life changing journey with the
help of the psychedelic drug,
LSD, Chris's 73 high dose LSD
sessions over the course of 20
years drew him into a deeper
communion with cosmic
consciousness, pushing the
boundaries of theory and
practice. Chris's psychedelic
experiences took him beyond self
transformation into collective
transformation beyond the
present into the future,
revealing spirit and matter in
perfect balance. Christopher M
Bache, PhD is a professor in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at young town
State University, where he
taught for 33 years. He is also
the adjunct faculty at the
California Institute of integral
studies, Emeritus, I hope I said
that properly, fellow at the
Institute of Noetic Sciences,
sciences and the Advisory
Council of Grof legacy training.
Chris's passion has been the
study of philosophical
implications of Non-ordinary
states of consciousness,
especially psychedelic states.
An award winning teacher and
international speaker, Chris has
written four books, life cycles,
a study of reincarnation in
light of contemporary
consciousness, research dark
night, early dawn, a pioneering
work in psychedelic philosophy
and collective consciousness,
the living classroom and
exploration of collective fields
of consciousness in teaching and
LSD and the mind of the
universe, the story of his of
his 20 year journey with LSD.
This is his story, and this is
his passion. Professor,
Christopher embassy, welcome to
passion harvest. Thank you so
much for being here. My
pleasure. Louisa, it's nice to
be with you. It's so nice to be
with you. I've just read your
book. It's fabulous. I'd like to
dive right in for those that
haven't read it, and the link,
all the links will be in the
show notes, what is the Book
about? And what story are you
telling? That's two questions.
I'm sorry, but
Unknown: Well, I was trained as
a philosopher of religion, and
right as I was beginning my
career at young sound State
University, I met the work of
Stanislav Grof, the foremost
authority of integrating
psychedelics into psychotherapy.
I read his book, realms of the
human unconscious, which had
just been published. This is
Long time ago, in 1978 and I saw
that this work was
extraordinarily important. I
mean, we're undergoing a
renaissance of psychedelic
research now, but Stan's work
comes from the early generation.
He was in the earliest tier of
this research. So I read his
work, I saw what, how important
this was, not just to
psychology, but to philosophy.
And so I just had to find out
for myself what using
psychedelics was using LSD in a
very careful and specific way,
in a very controlled
circumstances, using a
therapeutic protocol, you know,
pioneered by the early
researchers Stan, particularly
what it could teach me about
myself, about my mind, and
ultimately, the mind of the
universe. So I began a 20 year
what became a 20 year journey. I
chose, perhaps foolishly, to
choose a regimen working with
very high doses of LSD. In these
control circumstances, I did 73
high dose sessions
systematically over 20 years,
recording the results and after
I had finished. In 79 I did this
work when I was 30 to 50. After
I finished the work, I took
another 20 years to think about
and digest and process these
experiences. Eventually, 20
years later, in 1999 publishing
LSD in the mind of the universe,
which is this the complete story
from beginning to end of where
this journey took me into the
universe.
Luisa: I said before the
interview, I'm almost jealous,
in a way, what you experienced,
but you did experience such
deep, emotional and physical
suffering, but such deep,
profound insight of universal
truths. Do you mind just
explaining to the audience, and
you do detail this in your book,
what a session looks like.
Unknown: A session. My Sessions
always began in the early
morning. You're all I was always
isolated. I was either in my
home or in my wife's office. I
was always had a sitter who
carefully took care of me and
monitored me. My wife, my sitter
was my first wife, Carl, who is
a clinical psychologist. I'm
always lying down on a mattress
on the floor surrounded by
pillows. I'm listening. I have
my eyes covered with eye shades.
I'm. Listening with earphones to
very carefully selected music to
pace the unfolding of the
session, totally protected from
outside, outside interferences,
internally focused, focused
deeply within and they last all
day. They last basically from
early morning about eight hours
into the late afternoon or early
evening.
Luisa: And I asked you, before
the physical toll on the body,
what was that like, aside from
the emotional aspects and the
spiritual, the physical?
Unknown: Well, physically, I
mean, I'm fine. It's actually a
very beneficial process, because
in this work, when the body
begins, I mean, basically LSD is
an amplifier of consciousness.
It hyper stimulates, hyper
amplifies consciousness. Our
conventional, commonplace
understanding of psychedelics is
quite wrong. We're coming into a
new era of psychedelic research,
the public is being educated to
a deeper understanding of what
these substances do, but they
basically hyper amplify
consciousness. And if you use
this amplified state carefully
and conscientiously, your body
begins a detoxification process.
It begins to pull out of your
system all the things you'd
rather not face, all the things
you're scared of, all the things
you're afraid of, all the things
that basically your shadow.
Classically, you begin these
things begin to come up at you.
And if you confront them clearly
and conscientiously, you
basically can begin to lift
these things out of your system
you go through, eventually, a
death and rebirth process, your
total identity that you had
developed over your lifetime on
Earth, ultimately is shattered
and you are spun into deeper
Transpersonal or spiritual
states of consciousness. If you
continue this work, this cycle
of purification continues, and
the difficult material that you
have to process comes from
beyond the personal psyche. It
comes from deeper levels of
consciousness, the collective
levels of consciousness, the
species mind, archetypal levels
of consciousness. And I know
this is a radical story. I mean,
I really do. I understand how
far beyond most people's
experience this is, and I
understand how off the wall it
is just, I
Luisa: think, I think it's
incredible,
Unknown: but, but basically, you
go through deep, deep, deep
purification processes, which
are well known in the spiritual,
mystical traditions. You're
clearing a lot of material, not
only from your own body, mind
history, but also from the
history of your species and so
on and so forth. And it involves
a lot of physical detoxification
as well, a lot of purification
of your body. The net result,
even though you go through some
very difficult purification,
suffering, multiple deaths and
rebirths, the cumulative effect
is very clarifying on your body
and on your emotions. It's very
uplifting, because when you go
through these intense
purifications, you are spun into
very, very deep, positive,
ecstatic states of
consciousness, which deepen as
the process progresses. So my
body is in good shape. I think
my emotions are in good shape.
It was been an adventuresome and
avengersome journey. I just
wouldn't have missed it for the
world.
Luisa: It's incredible. And
what's interesting, you talk
about the death and the rebirth,
you also talk about the death
and the rebirth of the ego, or
the removal of the ego. And even
more interesting, during this
process, you had to surrender.
But in this process of growth
and evolution, you also affected
the collective consciousness,
which is a very interesting way
of thinking about it.
Unknown: And surprising to me. I
wasn't expecting this at all. I
was thinking when I got into
this work that this was about
personal healing or personal
transformation, personal
enlightenment. But what I found
after going through two years of
this work and going into the
second two years of the work, I
started processing enormous,
vast tracts of pain, I started
being drawn into fields of
suffering that really were like
Dante's Inferno. Just 1000s and
1000s of beings and 1000s of
years of human suffering were
just passing through me, flowing
through me. And at first, I
thought this was a deeper form
of ego death. But this kept on
for so many years, and it was so
collective that I eventually was
forced to consider an
alternative understanding, which
has become my normative
understanding, and that is that
in these very, very intense
states of consciousness.
Something in the universe uses
these states of consciousness to
heal the scars, certain scars
that are collected in the human
collective unconscious, which
history is deposited into the
human collective unconscious, so
that instead of healing my
personal psyche or even former
life trauma. I spent years
healing various trauma that had
gotten lodged into the
collective unconscious. And this
is what I mean, that personal
transformation opens into
collective transformation. Now I
think that all of us are always
hard wired into the collective
psyche, and that all of us, when
we are undergoing various
spiritual, you know, our own
personal issues, we are
simultaneously processing
collective issues that our
healing has an impact on the
collective psyche. It's just
that when you work with
psychedelics, this kind of
becomes intensified. It becomes
paramount. So yeah, I spent two
years doing this collective
healing, and then I was spun
into yet another level of
consciousness where the rules of
the game changed, changed again.
Luisa: I can't wait to hear
about that in a minute, but it's
so interesting, because we
always well, we think of
ourselves with our personal
transformation and growth, and I
want to reach this level. But
little do we necessarily realize
that it's we're working on a
collective level. So that would
also mean that the collective
consciousness is affecting us,
what the collective
consciousness is experiencing. I
mean, obviously we're living in
a crazy time in the world right
now, but it must. We can't
distance ourselves from the
impacts of that as much as we
would like to try.
Unknown: Yeah, well, you know,
we're organically embedded, I
think, in the collective psyche.
Just like we're physically
embedded in the Eco ecology of
the earth, you can't separate us
from the ecology that surrounds
us psychologically. We are
embedded in the collective
psyche. My experience,
basically, has spent a lot of
time exploring the intimacy with
which we are embedded in the
psyche and the ways in which
each of our individual lives are
fractal cells within the larger
life of the species, which is
part of a fractal cell within
the larger life of the universe
itself and the solar system and
the galaxy. So we are
implemented, deeply implemented,
in our collective process.
Eventually, I found that there's
no separation between our
personal transformation and our
collective transformation, that
all of us are players on an
historical stage, all of our
individual issue. I mean,
picture any issue that anybody
is dealing with, no matter what
it is, and it has to be related
to something which is going on
in the collective we don't have
a private issue, but isn't
reflected in some type of
dynamic in society which is
dealing with the same issue and
the way we're kind of like hard
wired together. And I know that
that's not the usual way of
thinking about it. I know that
our conventional psychology says
we're all completely standalone
computers. We're all, you know,
simply working on our personal
issues. But that's simply not my
experience. That's not what
shows in these deep states of
consciousness. In these deep
states of consciousness, it's
like we're networked. We are we
have separate private functions,
but we're also networked into
vast collective processes so
that we're engaging that all the
time.
Luisa: Yes, it's a careful
balance between being autonomous
and all one is it your belief
that we are, in fact, all one,
someone's described it as the
creator having multiple
personalities, which is the
humans. I'm just wondering,
what's your point of view?
Unknown: I think that core
insight that emerges in some of
the religious traditions, the
spiritual traditions that Atman
is Brahman, the essence of the
individual is the essence of the
totality. In my experience,
that's fundamentally true. It's
really true. You know, at the
core of our person is an energy,
a consciousness, an awareness,
an awakeness, and the nature of
that energy is the nature of the
Divine itself, that we are
sparks of the divine fire, and
that all of us, that you know,
oneness is one of the deepest,
most consistent and widespread
spiritual experiences that
emerges in mystical traditions
to experience oneness is a
totally transforming experience,
because out of oneness grows
compassion. Out of oneness grows
a concern for fairness and
justice, and also out of oneness
grows the technology, the
techniques for deepening our
immersion, our community.
Opinion with oneness. So that we
talk about someone being
mystically realized or
spiritually realized, it means
that they have gone through a
process where they become
transparent to the fundamental
oneness of life, and that they
live consciously now, both as an
individual and they are
individuals, and simultaneously,
they have, to varying degrees, a
feeling for our receptivity to
the fundamental oneness of
existence itself, the pulse of
existence as a totality.
Luisa: Yeah, it's really
interesting. We so often get
caught up in our own personal
stories. Yeah, very much. So are
our thoughts our own.
Unknown: They both are and
they're not. I mean, I think
it's a very interesting system.
Logically, we would think it
would have to be an either or,
but in fact, I think it's a much
more complex process. The
thoughts that I'm using right
now to speak to you are my own
thoughts. I'm kind of reaching
into my memories to bring them
to you. But if I if we step
back, if we were to step back
into deeper, more relaxed states
of consciousness, if we would
step into meditative states of
consciousness and deeply quieted
states of consciousness and seek
to watch where our thoughts come
from, we find that there are
actually a number of different
things that influence what
arises from the depth of our
awareness, and many of those
things that influence what
arises are really causes that
are outside my personal lineage,
causes which are collective,
causes which are spiritual,
causes which are historical,
causes which are cosmic, so that
what arises into focus in my
individual awareness, moment to
moment has a pedigree. And this
pedigree, I think, extends
beyond the individual. And if
you I mean artists experience
this. You know, many artists are
creative people. When they write
a poem or when they create a
picture, their experience is, I
didn't do it. It flowed through
me. It came through me. So some
artists won't even sign their
works of art, because that would
suggest that they created it
personally, but their experience
is that something larger created
through them, that blending of a
deeper creativity and the
personal agency, I think,
characterizes all of our lives
in all circumstances, and it
certainly becomes transparent in
psychedelic states of
consciousness.
Luisa: Gosh, I was just well, is
the thought my own? But I was
just thinking, if we have time,
I'd love you to share some of
you know, the pivotal moments
that you share in the book. But
what's fascinating is how you
talk about you transcend time
and space, future, past,
present. It's all potentially
there happening. Now. Do you
mind exploring or explaining
that a little bit more? Because
I think it's absolutely
fascinating.
Unknown: Yeah, that was another
one of the surprises that I
encountered here. Now we know
that physicists talk to us about
linear time is not really the
only way that time moves. That
there are some particles that
move backwards in time, and when
you enter into the massive
compression of black holes time,
you know the physics of time
changes. And in Super string
theory, there are dimensions of
the Universe that are not linear
time, like space. Time is, turns
out that when you go into deep,
deep, Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, you at least, I
Aldous, speak for myself, and I
think this is echoed in other
people's experiences. You
experienced that fact has that
time has different modalities to
it. There are different ways of
experiencing time. So early on
in my sessions, I went through a
series of experiences that
lasted about a year, seven
sessions where when I came
through this profound
purification process, every time
I did, I was brought into an
experience of what I call deep
time, not eternity, which is non
time, but deep time, where I
experienced my entire life from
start to finish as a
simultaneous now. It was like
all the moments of my life were
a giant tree. And my most recent
experiences before death were
the leaves at the outside of the
tree. And this the experiences
which had been repeated more and
more frequently were the big,
giant limbs in the center of the
tree. But all I experienced
myself both with the life. Yet
to come, and also
simultaneously, with my life
already having been lived and I
knew myself at that deep level
in later sessions in the years
following, I entered into deep
time repeatedly, but the texture
kept broadening. I entered into
deep time beyond my personal
life into the life of the
species, I began to have
experiences of the evolutionary
trajectory of humanity. And
again, I know this sounds egoic,
I know it sounds just absolutely
Luisa: crazy to say, but no, it
doesn't. It doesn't.
Unknown: I experience the
trajectory of human evolution,
not as in the future, not as
something which is not yet and
it's in the future time, but I
experienced it simultaneously as
something coming to us, but also
as something that had already
been completed. So there was a
wholeness and a breadth and a
depth of texture when you move
into very, very deep states of
consciousness, for example, when
you move into what classically
we would call archetypal states
of consciousness, deep into the
constitutive principles which
are responsible for kind of
generating space time as we know
it, those beings or those
forces, they live outside of
linear time as we know it, you
know so linear time is how
things behave inside space time,
but as you move to the edges of
space Time, time behaves
differently than we experience
it inside space and time. If you
go into extreme conditions, you
may transcend time altogether,
so that you move into you move
beyond time entirely. You can
move into what some people would
call eternity. Are the eternal
Now, are just completely outside
space, time, reality altogether.
Deep time is different than
that. Deep time is a certain
span of time, whether it's 100
years or 100,000 years,
experienced kind of as a
simultaneous now or experienced,
sometimes accelerated. I've been
in experiences where centuries
were passing by in minutes. You
know, just an accelerated
experience of the evolution
taking place on the planet. I
tried to, this is what I try to
unpack this in the book. Try to
lay it out as carefully as I
can. Yeah, I
Luisa: think it's fascinating.
Is everything happening now?
Unknown: I think perhaps from
some perspectives, from a
perspective, you could say that
everything is happening from
now, but personally, that's not
a very useful perspective. I
find I've tried to think in
those terms, and I find that I
literally cannot make my mind
think coherently within that
frame, because my mind needs the
structure of cause and effect,
even if those, if that varies in
certain places, but it needs a
certain some type of variation
or permutation of cause and
effect for me to understand life
as I know it, on this planet,
when I've gone into deep,
Non-ordinary states, time has
been variable, but has time
completely dissolved altogether.
It's been radically eclipsed at
different moments, but it hasn't
led me to be convinced that
everything is happening,
happening simultaneously now,
forever and ever. I think it's a
more complex pattern than that,
but I don't know. In the end, I
really don't know.
Luisa: Well, that was a very
honest answer. Thank you so
much. You talk about as well
that you saw the whole
trajectory of your life. My
question then is, it's been a
question asked since the
beginning of time, but Well,
what's time? Is everything pre
planned?
Unknown: No, know. I don't think
it's pre planned. I think it is
their probabilities. I think
when we incarnate, for example,
I mean, you know, I believe in
reincarnation, you know, I've
Luisa: written a book on
reincarnation. I assumed you
did. Yes.
Unknown: I think it's an
empirical fact that we that we
incarnate, that we reincarnate,
and eventually you get far
enough along in that process
that you don't reincarnate
haphazardly or randomly. You
reincarnate by choice. You
choose your incarnation
carefully, and that means
choosing the place and
circumstances. And timing of
your incarnation, and you do
that from a perspective in which
you can see a certain trajectory
of what's waiting for you if you
choose this life versus if you
choose another life. And in that
respect, I think there's a
certain probability, there's a
certain a certain inevitability
of certain things coming
together that constitute the
challenges and opportunities of
your life. But that doesn't mean
it's deterministic. It doesn't
mean it's a predetermined
outcome, because if it were a
predetermined outcome, then why
bother you know, there would be
nothing to learn. There has to
be a certain open endedness, if
we're truly going to be
challenged by that possibility
of variable outcomes in order to
learn. And so I think that that
while there are probabilities,
and the closer you get to
certain events, those
probabilities increase, the
farther you are away from those
events, those probabilities
decrease. I think there is time.
I think there is chance
operating in the universe. But I
also think that there is deep
the, you know, the Eastern
traditions call it karma. Karma,
the Paka, cause and effect,
cause and effect. But cause and
effect does not extinguish
choice. It conditions choice, it
qualifies choice, but it doesn't
eliminate the possibility of of
choice. But you have to work for
choices to be free. If you don't
work, if you don't pay
attention, or let's put it this
way, the less you pay attention,
the more likely your choices are
going to be highly conditioned,
but the more you pay attention,
the more you can increase the
freedom in your choosing. But to
do that, you have to pay a lot
of attention. Great
Luisa: answer, and I'm going to
re listen to that. Has your life
played out how you saw it during
your LSD experiences
Unknown: it has now I want to be
careful. It's not that I
experienced that I saw all the
details of my life. It's funny
how I experienced my life as the
sum totality of everything that
I was, everything I had become
everything that I then was, but
there were specific things in my
life that I wish I had had a
little heads up on frankly, you
know, that I didn't see, I
didn't remember all the details,
but it's a deeper reading than
that. It was like a coming to
know myself, in a way which gave
me a deep understanding of what
I'm about, what my the Truth of
My Life is about, and somewhat
about why I'm here and what my
purpose is. Now I think every
one of us carries that knowledge
inside themselves, and it guides
us at a very deep level, at an
intuitive level, when we come to
choice points, if we're careful,
we tune into that, and it does
guide us. This is in that
respect. This is nothing
unusual. It's just a an
unusually intense confrontation
with that knowing that we all
carry within us, in general,
yeah, I it My life has unfolded
along the lines as I saw it at
that time, as I experienced it.
I'm not as I am, I would say the
person that I met, which is now
about almost 40 years ago, 35
years ago, the person that I met
then is no stranger to the
person that I am now,
Luisa: okay, interesting, but
you're a very different person
than when you were 40 years ago.
Unknown: Well, I am, yeah, yeah.
I've paid my dues, gone to work
every day, raised three
children, dealt with all the
uncertainties of life that we
all have to deal with in that
process. I hope I've kept my
wits about me. I hope I've been
learning as I've been going I
Luisa: have to ask you the
question you spoke about the
evolution of the species and you
saw elements of that in your
experiences. Do you mind sharing
that with the audience?
Unknown: This is, that's a big
topic. Oh, okay, yeah, but I'm
happy to touch on it. But okay,
it's was, again, one of the big,
deep surprises of my journey,
because I'd never, ever imagine
that something like this would
become part of this journey.
Again, I was kind of thinking in
terms of the conventional
descriptions of enlightenment
that you find in the spiritual,
mystical traditions, or that
kind of thing. But what happened
was pretty systematically, over
years of work, I began to be
given a series of visionary
experiences. And when I say
visionary, you know, it's. It's
not like they were just visual.
The in these states of
consciousness, you learn by
becoming what it is you're
experiencing. So you become what
it is you're experiencing it.
You know it from the inside. So
when I when I say I had a
systematic initiation into
various visual visions of what's
happening with humanity. I it's
like I dilated, I entered into
absorption with the species mind
in a state of deep time and just
consistently, there was a
consistent message that was
poured into me about where we
were and completely surprised
me, because I, you know, I
didn't give a lot of time
thinking about humanity in this
global sense, but the message
was that humanity is coming into
a turning point. We're coming to
a decisive time in our history.
We're coming to a bifurcation
point in our evolutionary
development, the time when the
past will convert and diverge.
We're coming into a true before
and after advance, a change
which a time in history that
will change us at the very
fundamental core of our
existence, and not simply a
change in our economy or a
change in our politics or our
cultural values, but a change in
the architecture of the
collective psyche, so that all
human beings born after this
period of history will be
working within a different
archetypal structure of
collective psyche, and that this
was a time of profound spiritual
awakening, a time of extra
ordinary change on the face of
the planet that would be marking
history would always be marked
around this before and after
event. This was over and over.
It was laid out very
consistently, deepening it over
time. And there were times when
I was given, I was taken deep
into the future and given short
experiences of what I came to
call the future human, the human
being that we were becoming in
history. But they didn't explain
to me how this was going to
happen, or what form these
things would take, until several
years later, when I had a
particularly deep experience,
which took place in 1995 again,
I did all this work between 79
and 99 but in 1995 I had an
experience that I call the Great
Awakening, very, very difficult
experience. But after extensive
purification, I was propelled
deep into deep time, and I was I
dissolved into the human
species, and I experienced the
death of humanity and the
rebirth of humanity, not as an
individual, but as the species,
I experienced that humanity came
into a global systems crisis, a
period of profound loss and
disruption and turmoil, a loss
of control, a time of profound
destructuring, a time that was
so disruptive and so
intimidating that for a time, it
felt like we would all be dead.
It was an extinction event. But
just when it was at its worst,
the pressure lifted. The storm
passed, and we survived.
Humanity survived, significantly
pared down, but we survived, and
when we survived, and when we
began to pick ourselves up and
put our lives back together, we
had been changed. We had been
changed deep in our core, that
in the depths of this global
crisis, we had found certain
principles, certain values,
certain truths, and lived in
them and these This experience
changed us in a never to be
reversed fashion. Many ways to
describe this process, but at
its core, I think it's basically
a true encounter with the truth
of our oneness, an outbreaking
of oneness in human species and
in human culture, that
experience that in which that
mystics have talked about, you
know, for 1000s of years, the
experience that we are
fundamentally at core, one with
each other and one with life,
and when you have that
experience, then you just can't
hurt people. You don't allow
yourself, you would never allow
yourself your actions to hurt
people. And we began to build a
culture, to build a civilization
out of this experience of
oneness and true. An experience
of humanity, of a world
civilization that did not leave
anybody out. It was completely
inclusive, a world civilization
that worked for all that. This
was a pivot point in our
spiritual development. And from
this and period on, and I don't
know, I was never shown exactly
how or exactly when, except that
it seemed to be a global systems
crisis that was triggered by a
global ecological crisis. Now I
got to say this was taking place
in the 90s, and I was not
reading the global literature.
There was I wasn't reading the
global ecological literature.
You know, now we're beginning to
sort of see you know exactly
what you're talking about coming
in. But this was 20 years ago,
25 years ago, in my last
sessions, in my in the last
couple of sessions, I was given
one more deep, deep, the deepest
encounter with deep time, taken
deep into humanity's
evolutionary future, and was
given the experience of the
deepest experience I had had of
the humanity that we are
becoming. I think we are
entering a time in history of
deep, deep turmoil. But we are
not being punished for our sins.
We are not being destroyed,
though it will feel like it in
certain ways, but we are giving
birth. And certainly All women
know birth is excruciatingly
hard work. Gestation is long,
birth is short and intense. We
are giving birth, and we are
giving birth to the next form of
humanity, to the next iteration
of human life. I think we are
giving birth to a species that
is truly an enlightened species.
And I mean that in a technical
sense, a species, a humanity of
Christ, a humanity of Buddhas,
the humanities of the prophet, a
deeply awakened, spiritually
awakened humanity. And that's a
before and after turning point.
And in this last session, when I
was taken deep into the future
and allowed to experience this
future human.
It is so beautiful. It is such a
magnificent creature that we are
creating in history. I mean,
just an extraordinarily open
heart of pure compassion and an
open mind in deep communion with
the intelligence of the
universe. Just, I think it's
really important for us to have
a deep vision of what what we
are doing in the long term.
Otherwise we would be we might
drown in the sorrow that's
coming. Labor is hard, but this
is we must look beyond labor to
understand that what we are
doing is creating. We're
bringing into existence a future
being a future human.
Luisa: Wow. Well, we
unfortunately, myself included,
or as a collective. We always
grow from suffering.
Unfortunately we have the
greatest growth you also
mentioned the paired down human
is that there'll be less souls
incarnated in a physical form
that you saw.
Unknown: Well, I draw that not
primarily from my experiences,
though it's resonates with my
experience, because I draw that
really from looking at the
ecological literature today,
people who are just plotting the
hard numbers, the demographics,
what is the carrying capacity of
the planet? They talk about the
old earth and new earth. You
know, the old Earth is pre
damage of industrial
civilization, New Earth is post
civilization, where they
estimate that the carrying
capacity could be 2 billion
people. And we're coming into,
you know, 789, billion people,
the push is going to come to
shove. And you know, many, many
people who are not, have never
taken any psychedelics, you
know, are really looking at a
time of deep, deep planetary
disruption, where we won't be
able to feed our population,
given the depth of ecological
turbulence and the droughts and
the deforestation, so on and so
forth. So I mean, just
intellectually, I think we have
ample evidence that we are, we
are coming into a time of great
challenges, and some of those
challenges will take lives. The
key essential question is, How
soon will we wake up? How soon
will we begin to make important
choices to living in harmony
with the planet, living in
harmony with. Each other. The
sooner we start making those
choices, the more, the more we
can reduce the damage that will
be done. We have already locked
into place a depth of disruption
in this on this planet that's
just deeply shaking. We've
already locked it in place, but
we can still pull ourselves out
of this dive, or we can just
blunder deeper into this dive. I
know
Luisa: you didn't necessarily
see time frames, but you talk
about the sorrow. Was there a
trajectory of time for this,
this sorrowful period in our
species history,
Unknown: I think the 21st
Century is, is the beginning of
what I would call the dark night
of our collective soul. Now the
dark night is a technical term
that scholars of mysticism use,
and it refers to a time of a
very, very intense purification
that comes and precedes mystical
awakening, mystical
illumination, the dark night of
our collective time is a time of
intense purification, a letting
go of the past, a purifying of
the past before we can move into
a truly new future. And I think
that the 21st Century is such a
time, I don't think it's going
to be done quickly. I think
it'll take several generations.
We're lucky. Talking about a
huge change here. I don't know
how long it will take, but
clearly things are accelerating.
I mean, there's so many things
are accelerating,
technologically, socially,
intellectually, the internet,
the fact that I'm talking with
you tonight across vast space,
to people, I mean, this
unprecedented, right? Things are
speeding up. How fast it takes,
how long it takes, partly
depends upon how we handle the
pressures that are coming, that
are already being placed upon
us. I mean, we just the Trump
presidency was four years of
denial of the reality of climate
change, we lost a lot of time
during those four years. We
could have been doing better
than we are now. How soon we'll
begin to make serious
commitments to living in balance
with the planet? I think we're,
we're coming into it, and we, I
think we have actually already
entered into the early stages of
these convulsions. I think covid
19 is kind of like a a what is
the term in a symphony? It's
like the overture of a symphony.
It's not itself, the depth of
the disruption that's coming,
but it's like the overture that
signals some of the themes that
are coming. And we all know how
deeply disrupted our lives have
been with covid. Well, I think
it's going to get much, much
worse than what we've
experienced with covid, but
perhaps from covid, we are
beginning to learn some of the
insights and behaviors that will
help us do better when the next
series of crises come
Luisa: that takes me just
briefly on to fear, because I
just feel this so much in the
collective consciousness,
there's so much fear. What are
your thoughts on fear and how to
move through a fear based state?
Unknown: Well, first, we have
reasons to be afraid. I mean,
you know, we've we've not doing
a very good job with a number of
things, and there is a tally
coming. So from a completely
realistic perspective. We have
causes to fear. I fear for my
children, I fear for my
grandchildren, but my deeper,
deeper experiences at the wisdom
that the universe is profoundly
wise, the universe is
extraordinarily intelligent, and
the universe is deeply
compassionate. But to
experience, to really see, to be
able to see the compassion of
the universe, you have to look
very, very deep, because on the
surface the universe looks like
a mean son of a bitch, and on
the surface the universe doesn't
look very intelligent or
profoundly wise. You really have
to be willing to look deep.
Ramakrishna said, if you want to
know God, you must be willing to
look evil in the face. You must
understand that evil is not
something outside of the Divine,
but it is actually part of the
way that the divine manifests
itself, not in malice, but that
the concept that that the divine
acts with great power in ways
that hurt us at times, and that
it feels like evil, but it
actually it's much deeper than
that. My experience in the
sessions is that I was many,
many times drawn into. Been
dissolved into realities so
deep, so large. I didn't have
words to describe it. I mean,
some people would describe it as
the divine I tend to talk about
it as the cosmic mind, or the
mind of the universe. And I
experienced a universe
extraordinarily wise,
extraordinarily intelligent,
just massive orders of
intelligence beyond anything I
had imagined previously. And
that's the intelligence that
lies behind our moment in
history. We are being summoned.
We are being called into a
higher order of existence. We
have to let go of the past. But
the even though the
circumstances of this
transformation are demanding,
they're extraordinarily
important and extremely
exciting. I mean, look, when we
die, we don't want to simply
have had a comfortable life. We
want to have had a life that
means something that really has
challenged us and brought
something deep out of us. And I
think our time in history is
that kind of time. It's not
going to be comfortable, but it
can be very, very purposeful and
very meaningful, and it can be
an extra ordinary adventure, and
that, I think that engagement of
intelligence is much more
powerful to me than fear. Fear
does not, does not move me very
deeply, and like one of the
things that fell away from me
over the course of this journey
is fear of death. I have no fear
of death. And I don't say I say
that truly humbly. I mean, it's
just I'm not afraid of it,
because I've experienced where
I'm going when I die. I've
experienced where people go when
they die. And anyone, any shaman
or any deep spiritual
practitioner, has likely had
these kinds of experiences. And
so I know that I am entering
into a greater intelligence. I
know I'm entering into a
profound love, and therefore I
have no fear. And if you have no
fear of death, then it tends to
sort of sap the strength of all
these other lesser fears that
nibble at us around the edges.
They don't frighten me.
Luisa: So many people, I get
asked this question all the
time, what happens when we die,
or I'm so afraid of death, it's
very comforting from your
experiences to say that there is
no fear of death.
Unknown: I think there's we're
at a time when we have learned
so much about what happens when
we die. I mean, I taught a
course called Transpersonal
studies in my undergraduate
courses, and in it, we looked at
reincarnation research, you
know, just a large burgeoning
body of literature that clearly
demonstrates that death is not
the end of existence. Our
consciousness continues near
death. Episode research,
hundreds, 1000s and 1000s of
people who have had glimpses of
what's waiting for them when
they die. And extra ordinary,
consistent experiences we have,
people like Michael Newton's
work, his books, Journey of the
journeys of the soul and the
destiny of souls, where he
regressed people, not only into
their previous lives, but into
their life in between their
lives, he actually was able to
regress people into conditions
where they remembered their
afterlife experiences. And after
taking hundreds of people there,
he was able to reconstruct a
picture of what happens to us
when we die. And what do you
know? It's extraordinarily
consistent with the Tibetan Book
of the Dead and some of the
great insights that come out of
our spiritual traditions, so
that we're beginning to piece
together and in psychedelic
experiences. You know, any
shamanic tradition will tell
you, you know you can die before
you die. I mean, the saying is,
those who die before they die do
not die when they die. It's you
can die before you die
physically. You can experience
that reality before. I mean, and
because, the reason we survive
the destruction of the body is
not because something had
happens to us at the moment of
death. It's because of something
that we already are right here,
right now, we already have the
spiritual reality alive within
us. We already have access to
the spiritual reality. And when
you tune into that reality
deeply, you everybody
experiences the same fundamental
thing. It's impossible to die
the form that you are can die,
you know, the outer layers can
die, but the inner essence
doesn't die. And you take all
your memory with you, you take
all of your learning with you.
And we don't have to accept this
on faith anymore. We have many,
many opportunities for this to
be a true, genuine.
Intellectually persuasive study,
field of study,
Luisa: and this is a large
topic, but I have to ask this
question. In your experiences,
this constant cycle of life and
death and rebirth and coming
back into the physical body,
what is the purpose of it all,
and is there an end point?
Unknown: Well, big questions,
aren't they? I know. I'm so
sorry. It's okay, fair game.
Well, I don't there isn't an end
point that we can recognize any
more than we can say what the
end point of the universe is,
because billions and billions
and billions of years ahead of
us. You know, we're just and
reincarnation is the same thing.
What reincarnation does is lift
from us the burden of too little
time. What it tells us that we
have an open ended amount of
time in which we will be growing
and evolving. The classic
portrait of reincarnation that
emerged about 4000 years ago is
that you reincarnate.
Reincarnate, you learn, you
become more spiritually
developed, until you awaken to
your divine nature. Once you
awaken to your divine nature,
then you leave, then you achieve
moksha, you escape, and you
don't have to be here anymore.
But that leaves unanswered the
question, what is the purpose of
physical existence in the first
place? Is it simply to get out
of here? And the more we know
about how big the universe is
and how old it is and how
intelligent it is, the more that
model of reality just doesn't
seem to be very persuasive. In
my experience, in the sessions,
a very different understanding
of reincarnation emerged. I had
an experience in one particular
session, which was crescendo of
lots of sessions of work where I
began to have an experience
where all of my former lives
started coming in, and now I'm
familiar with some of my former
lives. I did three years of
hypnotherapy work in which I did
some of this work. But in this
case, all of my former lives
started coming in, and it was
like wrapping filaments of light
around a kite spool. And
eventually, when they came
together, they fused, and when
they fused, there was an
explosion of light, of diamond
light out of my chest. It just
exploded, and it catapulted me
into a state of awareness in
which I was both an individual,
but I was an individual beyond
any frame of reference I had
ever experienced before. And I
think what I was being shown was
what the trajectory of
reincarnation, where the
trajectory of reincarnation is
taking us. It's not simply about
the small, incremental
improvements that we make in our
lives, lifetime by lifetime,
though we do. It's not simply
about learning more and learning
more level by level though we do
eventually, sooner or later, the
soul, which is the consciousness
that integrates all of our life
experiences, all of our lives,
come together and they fuse. And
when they fuse, there is created
a higher order of human being,
what I call the birth of the
diamond soul. I think that when
the birth, when the when the
diamond soul, awakens a human
inside, a human being in earth,
the identity shifts. We no
longer take our personal ego,
our personal private life, as
our identity. We now know
ourselves to be 100,000 year old
beings. We know ourselves to be
a soul. We are a soul incarnate.
We wake up at that level with
our memories intact. This is not
the end of creation. It's not
the end of the process, but it's
a significant turning point. Now
imagine if this is happening, if
this is built into the fabric of
existence, and it's happening
not just to us individually, but
to all of us together, so that
eventually the entire species
goes through a process where
they wake up the diamond soul
awakens inside of themselves,
and they know themselves to be
soul beings incarnate inside
time and space. What a change
that would make in the history
of this planet. And I think
something like that is what we
are in the process of doing in
the birth of the future human. I
think the future human is the
diamond soul we are in a process
of becoming fully self aware
spiritual beings inside
existence. And when we are that,
that spiritually awake truly, we
are living heaven on earth.
Nirvana is Samsara, and we don't
need to go off planet in order
to be in. Spiritual joy. We can
experience spiritual joy right
here, right now. That's what I
think is happening.
Reincarnation is maturing us
toward this, through this, but
then it keeps going another
million years, another million
years. It's just going to keep
going. Wow.
Luisa: Very interesting. Our
lives are just like a pin prick,
and that seems so long that this
is the one moment in time,
really each life,
Unknown: and yet so significant.
And particularly, I think, at
this particular time in history,
many people have incarnated,
caring, in a sense, the karmic
imprint of many lives, it's kind
of like when you're in college
and you get to the end of your
senior year, you start loading
up your courses to finish your
things up quickly. I think a lot
of us are loading up our former
lives in this life, so that we
carry a lot of karma that comes
from deep history, because we
have a lot of work that we want
to do, we want to accomplish. So
this pin prick is actually a
pretty, a pretty rich pin prick
in time, in time in history.
Luisa: That's a great way to put
it. And also removing all the
karmic, what people call it
dead, or the karma that we've
accumulated. I like the idea of
that
Unknown: we are. I think we're I
think we're expunging karma
exponentially. But remember,
we're not simply healing the
past. We're not simply making up
for things that we did wrong.
Most people rise to the karmic
challenges of their life. Most
people, it's like most of the
kids in school, they pass. It's
not a perfect system, but they
pass. They learn. Most souls, I
think, pass the karmic
challenges of their life. So in
every incarnation, they're not
simply making up for things they
did wrong. They're building on
things that they did right. And
so we are. We are growing by
leaps and bounds on the basis of
things that we have learned and
accumulated positively. Sure we
have some cleaning up to do, you
know a little but most of what
we're doing, I think, is we're
learning how to write
symphonies. We're learning how
to love bigger, deeper, longer.
We're learning how to think
Rich, more richly than we have
before. We really are building
on a very positive legacy in our
past.
Luisa: Wow, such profound,
incredible insights. I have to
ask you the question, Why did
you stop your LSD sessions?
Unknown: I stopped for two
reasons, but the most important
reason is I stopped because it
became too difficult to come
back at this time in the last
five years of my work, I entered
a period of communion with what
I call the diamond Luminosity in
Buddhism, they call it
Dharmakaya, the clear light of
absolute reality. I basically
was repeatedly dissolved over
four years into a level of
consciousness that was so pure,
so sublime, so clear, clear,
clear, dissolved into the
crystalline body of the Divine,
drawn into deeper, ever
deepening intimacy with the
divine fabric of existence. As
you can imagine, this was
absolutely deeply soul
satisfying encounters. It
changed me forever. But these
are temporary states. You know,
there are some beings, God bless
them, who can enter into those
states and hold them forever,
you know, and the great
spiritual masters all honor to
them. But when you work with
psychedelics, you only get
temporary access to this
intimacy, and then you have to
come back and integrate it and
digest it. But basically, I was
taken over the years so deep
into the divine, so many times
that it just became too much of
a heartache to come back into
time, space, existence, and I
knew that I had to stop this
work, and I had to spend the
rest of my life digesting the
blessings that I had already
been given and to draw them more
deeply into my heart and mind. I
couldn't keep going back into
it, and so I made a deal with
the universe, and the deal was
that that she would not draw me
this deeply back into her again
until I could stay with her
forever. And that was marked the
end of my journey. So I've spent
the rest of my life continuing
to reflect on these things, to
ponder them, to understand them,
because I'm, you know, full Oss.
I want to understand things, and
I want to share them, and I hope
the story can be useful to
people, some people who do who
are themselves, psychedelic
journeyers. And so maybe there
are some lessons that can be
helpful to them, but I hope that
most people who read the book
will not be psychedelic
journeyers, but the journey can
still be helpful to them,
because it will show them
something that will resonate
with their own deepest
intuitions. It'll show them a
cosmology. There's a picture of
our universe. And if it's true,
I think it's true, it will
resonate with that understanding
that we carry deep in our hearts
and in our souls, and therefore
it will support them as they go
about their own life, following
their own destiny into their own
spiritual fruition. That's my
hope.
Luisa: Well, I just have to say,
Chris Professor Bache, I think
you're I love you. I think
you're amazing. What profound I
mean. I've read your book, but
speaking with you, it's just
incredible. On a final note, is
there any question that I've
missed and there's something
you'd like to talk to the
passion harvest audience about?
Unknown: I would advise people
not to do what I did. I chose to
work with very high doses of
LSD. I pushed my system very
hard. It was more taxing than I
thought it was going to be in
the beginning, and along the
way, I realized that there's no
reason to push yourself this
hard. So what I would advise
today for those who do want to
work with psychedelics in a
spiritual manner, to work with
lower doses, to work with
gentler psychedelics and to not
push themselves as hard. And I
lay this all out in the book The
reasons for this and whatnot. So
my advice would be, maybe learn
from my mistakes as well as from
my successes, and don't do what
I did, because if you push as
hard as I did, it really does
come to it takes all of your
energy and all of your life to
navigate the journey that you've
done. It's like, you know, if
you climb a mountain, it takes
up years and years of your life.
This took years and years of my
life, and I wouldn't have traded
it for anything in the world,
but I know that there are
certain costs that come with
that, and I would encourage
people not to choose that
particular route. Other than
that, I guess I would offer, I
would just leave with a witness
to the profound wisdom that is
in by embedded in our bodies and
in our hearts and our minds, a
wisdom that's embedded in the
very deep evolving structure of
the universe and the stars that
mesmerizes with the pictures
from the Hubble of the galaxies
and The and the supernovas and
the in the nebula that the way,
those the feelings, that those
pictures stir in us and awaken
in us, those feelings are true,
and that our lives do
participate intimately, deeply
in that wisdom, right here,
right Now, every day, we are
embedded in that wisdom, that's
my story, and I'm sticking to
it.
Luisa: Yay. You're amazing,
Professor Bache, thank you so
much for being on passion
harvest. I've just loved talking
to you, and I'm so honored to
speak with you, and what a
wonderful, powerful message
you're sharing with the world.
So thank you so
Unknown: much. Thank you,
Louisa, it's been a wonderful
conversation with you. Thank you
for having bye for
Luisa: now, bye, bye. If you
like this episode, please do
subscribe for weekly passionate,
inspirational interviews.