Chris Bache: You. Well, hello,
Richard. It's good to continue
our discussion. You know, in our
previous discussion, we sort of
started the discussion of
reincarnation. We looked at the
evidence for reincarnation,
these extraordinary children
from around the world. We began
to unpack that evidence into a
deeper understanding of the
rhythms of life and the stages
of human evolution that
reincarnation makes possible the
restoration of the theme of the
meaningfulness of the challenges
that we find embedded in our
life, and the opportunity to
actually deepen our therapeutic
interventions in the places
where we are stuck, the places
where we're Holding pain that
are rooted in our deeper
history. So now, today, we take
it farther. We begin to look
deeper into the significance of
what are we? What's the
significance of the fact that we
are reincarnating beings in a
universe that obviously supports
and nurtures and created this
reincarnation dynamic.
Richard Rudd: That's a huge
difference, isn't it like to to
be in a to be in a living in a
universe that is nurturing us,
you know, that has a kind of
paternal maternal energy, you
know, surrounding it, that has
such a different, such a
different framework to be born
into
Chris Bache: Yeah, yes. And, you
know, I want to mention at the
outset that sometimes
reincarnation thinkers go in a
direction of of thinking that
every little bitty thing in our
life has a determined quality, a
deterministic quality. But I
don't think we necessarily need
to go there, because chance is
one of the powerful elements of
this universe. And so we can
affirm meaning, and we can
affirm intentionality without
putting every detail of our life
into that press and ask, well,
what's the meaning of this and
what's the meaning of that? To
affirm a larger scope of
meaning. Still, in a world where
there are chance and there are
variables and there are
uncertainties, what's important,
I think, is understanding that
the universe pays attention to
how we respond to chance events
as well as intentional events,
that our learning and the
quality of our response is
carried forward, and does this
credit, regardless of the origin
of the challenges that we're
facing.
Richard Rudd: Yeah, absolutely,
I just, funnily enough, today,
recorded a short meditation and
and in it, I I asked people to
kind of imagine the universe
with its with it, with
crisscrossed by its fields of
karma, you know, of like, you
know this, like, almost these,
these ley lines through time and
space that kind of have this
karmic energy. They're rippling.
And the whole of the cosmos is
rippling with these fields. And
then I asked each person, well,
whoever's meditating to send out
one really beautiful thought,
like just just from the depth of
their souls, send out a really
beautiful thought into that, and
see the universe respond to
that, and see how it enters the
field, and how the universe
maybe kind of sighs and expands
and, and how it reaches every
single tiny area and almost like
it opens up synapses, yes, in
some way, and, and just the the
power of the incalculable power
of something like that, you
know, dropped into the into the
ocean of, you know, time, space,
yeah, and, and, you know, I
found that, like a really
powerful contemplation to do,
Chris Bache: yeah, absolutely. I
agree that's been very much my
experience in my own work with
psychedelics, that there were,
there was nothing that I did
working at deep levels that was
mine alone, that was private,
and that the pain came from a
larger collective web, and the
healing spread out into a larger
collective web. And that really,
those exercises, the meditations
that you're describing, I think,
really are important for
changing the sort of a tilt and
how we live in the universe,
because according to just our
physical senses, we have this
feeling often that life happens
to us. Life is something
independent to of us, and then
it just happens to us, and then
we're victims of it, and we
respond. But when you begin to
send out energy into the
universe, when you begin to send
out healing and love into the
universe. You watch the universe
respond in immediate and then
indirect ways. Then you begin to
shift into the sense that you
are living in a dynamic field.
You are part of a dynamic field,
living in a field and at a very
deep level, on the subtle level,
you are creating your universe
as you go once you begin to
understand that still it doesn't
mean you're free of all the
karma that's coming at you from
the past. It's still working its
way through the system, but
increasingly, the balance of
your life tilts from being kind
of the passive recipient of
things that you personally
didn't start to being the
generator of the life that you
are inheriting now.
Richard Rudd: Yeah, you're no
longer a victim. You're, you're,
you're a creator. Yeah, yes, we
got this great question. We
thought we kind of inject into
this talk, which is what happens
to us when we die. So shall we?
Let's explore that. I mean, you
know, other, many other cultures
we, I think we wanted to mention
the Tibetans, because they seem
to really have a handle on some
of these things, Egyptians as
well. But you know, Tibetans
perhaps a little bit more
contemporary, because they're
still here, practicing very much
those, those teachings, the
Bardo teachings and
Chris Bache: psychotherapists
are now exploring this
territory. Joel whittens first
book, Life between life explored
this and Michael Newton's work.
In his books, journey of souls
and destiny of souls are very
systematic attempts to explore
through deep states of
regression, of spiritual
regression, what happens to
people when they go through the
death process? So really, we've
got two halves of life. We've
got birth to death, and then
we've got birth a death to birth
and missing this side. But
really, you have to understand
the whole circle to really
understand what happens. So,
yeah, let's jump into it. Yeah.
Richard Rudd: So obviously, the,
you know, the Tibetans, have
coined this phrase, the Bardo.
The Bardo, which is this in
between state or but it can also
be used to describe a
transformational experience, you
know, because that's life is
filled with transformational
experiences, but particularly
when you're moving through a
threshold, across a threshold,
you know, like death or birth,
are classic thresholds and and
they sit there as kind of almost
an allegory of all
transformation, don't they?
Death and birth? So, you know,
because we have so many deaths
and births even within one
lifetime. So it seems like a
kind of obvious logic to expand
that allegory out beyond
individual births, and you know,
and and and see it everywhere,
throughout the entire cosmos.
And I know you've experienced
this very profoundly in your in
your psychedelic journeys, like
this constant you've described,
like those constant states of
transformation that, or you've
been through them in those, I
mean, you know what? I'm this
constant rebirth.
Chris Bache: Yeah, the yes. I
mean, when I started the work, I
thought there was just one
death, ego death, that would
then launch you into the
spiritual universe. But what I
found is, course, the spiritual
universe has many, many layers
to it, and just because you're
operational at certain layers
doesn't mean you're operational
yet at deeper layers, and you
actually have to go through
another metamorphosis of death
and surrender to be reborn into
that another layer, and so on
and so forth. And that reflects
the Tibetan idea of Bardo. Bardo
really means a discrete layer of
consciousness, and so when
they're describing the after
death journey, there are
multiple Bardos that manifest
themselves. Now we in the West
have tended to use the term
Bardo to expand on that, and
basically let the Bardo
represent the sum total of all
things that happen to us when we
die on the other side. And
that's a perfectly acceptable
use of the term, but their use
of it is in terms of stages of
that progression. So there's one
Bardo you pass through. Another
Bardo you pass through. There's
the Bardo of the hungry ghost to
the Bardo, the heavenly spirits
and things like this. But the
basic pattern, I think, that
they identified is the same
pattern that the
psychotherapists are identifying
too, that when we die, we go
through a period of reunion with
our soul, with our and our soul
lineage, and the first thing
that takes place is that we
debrief from our most recent
life. We basically process the
life that we just lived in the
context of absolute love, and a
love so deep is not even a
matter of forgiveness, but. We
experience the totality of our
life, all of our shortcomings,
all of our good deeds, in the
context of infinite love, and we
have the opportunity to look at
our life and see what we did
well and see what we didn't do
well.
Richard Rudd: And we had the
whole notion, don't we have,
like the life flashing before
you as you die, like this kind
of replay in tight in the
timeless dimension. No, because
there's so it makes perfect
sense, like for us to go through
that deep reflection at the end
of something, and it's what we
do in life, right? Yeah. So,
yeah,
Chris Bache: I think the
Near-Death Experience of the
life review is a snapshot of
what happens, kind of in a full
death experience of just a
detailed reliving of every
detail, every nuance, far more
details than we can keep track
of inside time and space, and we
See how our life rippled out and
touched other people. We
experience how our evil deeds
hurt and how our good deeds
helped. And so we experience the
totality of our life in the
seamless fabric,
Richard Rudd: and we experience
them without a physical body. So
we experience them in a subtle
body, which is much more
intense, yeah, like the astral
body, or, as it's so called, or
the mental body, the subtle
layers, the causal body, you
know, the without the
physicality, the intensity of
those emotions that we probably
feel, or we review, yeah, have
given rise to this notion of,
like, eternal damnation from,
you know, the Christians, for
example, or or even, like the
eternal bliss realms of the
Buddhas, Buddhists, or heaven
and hell. And, you know, because
there's this sense of eternity,
I think it's a correct
intuition. You know that,
because when there's no time
when that when you're out of
time and space, in that sense,
you're in that place of grace,
then then an experience of, you
know, of the harm you've caused,
or the hurt you've caused, could
feel like it, you know, in that
moment, in that timeless space,
could feel like it's infinite.
You know, I've caused, like, an
intense pain, and then seeing
the ripple of that pain into a
life, and how it, how it carries
on through that being, yeah, and
then finally gets worked out. I
mean, I don't know what level we
experience, but I imagine we
experience a lot of the of the
subtler dimensions of our
karmic, you know the passions of
our karma, but pretty, very
intense,
Chris Bache: yeah. But then what
locks in this experience, this
phenomenology of eternity, what
locks it in as a metaphysical
principle, is the mistaken view
that we only live once, so we've
had our chance, and there's
absolutely no chance to correct
it. So if you're going to be
accountable, and if you're going
to, you know, be accountable to
good and you've screwed up, then
you're punished forever and ever
and ever and of course,
fortunately, no one finds that
when they actually get into the
the deep, the depth of it, the
past life therapists don't find
that. The Buddhists don't find
that that we do, we are
accountable, we are responsible.
We do experience the pain we
cause others, but that's so that
we can learn, and that's so that
we can come back and do better
next time and better next time
and grow and grow. Yeah.
Richard Rudd: I mean, I'm from a
lineage of of of distillers in
my family, and so I like the,
you know, I look at it
intuitive. This is my intuitive
reading of, perhaps, you know, a
colorful way of maybe what, how
this happens is that there's a,
there's a distilling process and
in and in that or a fermentation
of some form, so that the
grosser matter starts to fall
down back to Earth in a way like
this. Is the notion of having
these subtle bodies, where the
lower bodies, the astral, you
know, those lower en energies
that we've created, fall back
into the lower planes, and then
something higher gets
crystallized, the distillation
of our life. All that was good
about it, all that we've
learned, is being distilled into
this pure, kind of Quintessence
that then stays as a and adds to
us, our soul's trajectory. But
then, but then the lower, all
that kind of elemental energy
that sinks back into those lower
planes of being. They, they also
carry our karma, you know. So
those, those droplets, if you
like, of karma, sink back down
and they, they, you know, we
still have to redress them, you
know, although they, they, my
understanding is that they move
into the. Collective field as
well. So every act that we or
every word we speak, let's say,
or every thought we have, goes
into the collective so the you
know, it's we are all co
creating the the karma of
humanity, the collective karma
of humanity. Yeah. And then we
have to return to, to pick up
where we left off. But we have
this enhanced soul, you know,
this, this, this, you know, that
we've learned from. So when we
return, there's more awareness
present. So there is this
continuity, you know, and and
and we and we know, the other
way I see it is that there's,
you know, our lives are
trajectories. They're like arcs
that I see there's an arc, it's
like an arc. It's curving. It's
always moving, if you looked at
it. But it might be a spiral, or
it might have one of these
Kundalini shapes underneath it,
not a straight line, and that,
that is what we that's what
never ends that arc. We follow
that arc, and it goes through
this portal and it continues.
And that's the lineage, that is
what if you're able to trace
that arc in your inner being,
then you can trace your lineage,
where you've come from and where
you're going, and your memory
can travel down that arc. Your
awareness can travel down that
arc, which enables you to
remember or to predict, in the
case of Tibetans, you know, to
predict where you'll return.
Yeah, because, because the
awareness is aware of the of the
arc, not just in its own life.
Because if you, if you look at
an arc like in within one life,
it may do that. But then if you
can see it, if you can project
it beyond this life, you can
then you know, your awareness
can predict intuitively where
you're coming back. Can even,
maybe even further than predict.
Maybe you can even create, you
know, where you would are going
to return in some respect. So
anyway, that's those are ideas.
Chris Bache: Yeah, you know,
I've never been very interested
in tracing my genealogy, but I
have been interested in tracing
the genealogy of my soul, yeah,
which is what you're describing,
just reaching back, and
basically what you might think
of as deep remembering,
remembering who you are, who you
have been and there. And when
you do that, you do have a
certain sense of trajectory, of
kind of developmental process.
And you're pointing to the
collective, I think, is
absolutely right. What we're
what we're learning is the
individual and the collective
are evolving together. They are
functionally separate systems,
but they are deeply intertwined.
So everything we are doing as an
individual seeds the growth of
the collective, and everything
the collective is doing seeds
the growth of the individual, so
that when I leave, I really do
believe that when I leave space
time when I die, and even if I
were to leave the entire system
altogether, all of my
experiences, all of your
experiences, will be held in
perfect and perfect, I won't say
duplication, because we are
human beings, and everything we
experience, the human species
gets to hold on to, and
therefore our life experience
becomes part of its life
experience. Our love and
understanding becomes part of
its love and understanding, and
it is part of its generative
matrix, out of which it gives
birth to the next generation of
human beings. So it's a it's a
both hand situation
Richard Rudd: here. It's
beautiful, like the notion of
the Akashic field that is just
the red that is constantly
remembering and growing. I love
that idea, yeah. And you know
that the another idea I really
like is the notion that comes
from the Tibetans as well, this
notion they call Tarma, yeah,
which my interpretation of it is
a word I might use is
transmission. It means treasure.
And term are like teachings in a
way or wisdom, teachings that
are kind of waiting for specific
teachers in time and space. And
the story that is through the
Tibetans is that they would a
lot of the tama would were that
their lineage Tama were dropped
by their great teacher,
Padmasambhava, who was the
second Buddha. And he kind of
emanated these Tamas into the
future. And like dropping them
like, kind of a bit like depth
charges, you know, at different
levels of depths of time, and
that they would go off at
certain points where, where,
where further emanations or
disciples of his or teachers, or
really, they're kind of aspects
of his greater consciousness, or
of that being, that lineage, you
could say. But. So to say. And
then they would pick up, and
they would, they would go off
and be, be discovered at certain
times, in certain places and
periods. And this was a great, a
big under it was a big shift in
my understanding when I really
understood about these tema
because that's sort of what
happened to me. I had this kind
of opening up, that was just
hanging there in time and space,
and then this wisdom memory came
rushing through me, and then I
had to spend the rest of my
life, and I still am figuring
out what I'd received and and
living according to it. And I
think that's an, it's I
mentioned it not just because
it's part of my my story, but
because it's a, it's a lovely
little sort of idea of how, how
subtle and rich are the layers
that that survive time and
space, that kind of, you know
that. And it brings us, perhaps,
to that notion of involution
that we that we've been thinking
about, yeah, which maybe we
could dive into that. But what
is involution? Chris, tell us?
Chris Bache: Well, first of all,
I want to, I want to stop for a
moment, and first to celebrate
your receiving of the terma, of
the gene keys. You didn't make
those. You receive those, and
you unpack them. You take your
responsibility for your half,
but you only have half. The
other half is like the seed that
comes from above. And once you
understand that reincarnation is
a cycle that has a bottom half,
an incarnational half, and a top
half, and just as there are a
community of beings in the
bottom half of the cycle,
there's also a community of
beings in the top half that
there's layers and layers and
layers of spiritual beings. It's
not just reincarnating human
beings, but there's angelic
presences and enlightened
beings, presences and all sorts
of beings who are here to help
us gestate in our gestational
cycle. And so just as there are
human beings above to help us.
There are the teachings above to
help and infuse our teaching so
that there are these gems of
ideas, gems of empowerment, that
and so once we have the
understanding that a human being
who becomes aware of the
dynamics of reincarnation, aware
of the deep evolutionary
trajectory of the soul and soul
communities, the way the
Tibetans have. Then they
naturally begin to track their
great beings through time, and
they track the great teachings
through time, and they become
sensitive to these diamonds
dropping in to our minds. It's
specific. And the deep, the
deep, significant patterns to
this process. So for me, in
addition to the detail of the of
these ideas, of that there are
term as teachings, and that
there are tulkus, you know,
read, self consciously
reincarnating beings. The deeper
fabric is to understand, begin
to understand the depth and the
grandeur at which reincarnation
is operating. It's not simply a
matter of who we were in the
17th century, and it's really a
matter of it changes the
parameters of our dialog with
the universe, and therefore it
changes our sense of what we
are, because we are a being that
travels through time. We are a
being that has absorbed has been
in the spiritual world many
times, and we are incarnating
more and more of these diamond
teachings into our body, into
our heart, into our mind. And
that opens up the that opens up
the playing field of human
experience. I think it just
opens up and, you know, we I
teach at a university where the
religion of secular
enlightenment is that the
universe appeared by chance.
It's been driven by random
mutation. There's no meaning to
your life. It's all accidental.
And when you die, you're dead.
That's it. When your brain
stops, you're dead. And that
just completely it just is such
a crushing philosophy. But this
which starts on an empirical
basis but then expands through a
deeper appreciation of the
dynamics of spiritual
traditions. It restores meaning
back to our lives. It allows us
to play in a meaningful
landscape of engaging the wisdom
of our life with the wisdom of
the universe entering. And the
involution is that downward flow
of meaning and purpose and
beauty and truth into our life.
And then evolution is our taking
it and seeding it and growing it
as best we can into the
circumstances of our life.
Richard Rudd: We. Yeah,
beautiful. I mean, I sometimes
look at evolution as the future
burrowing into the past, and
evolution as the past spiraling
towards the future like so
you've got these two forces, but
you might also look at it as you
know, like Aurobindo. You know
who I know. You also love Sri
Aurobindo, amazing kind of mind,
and how he, you know, he
describes involution as as
seeds, kind of sown deep within
matter. So within matter, the
spirit is there asleep, like,
take a rock, like a piece of
lump of granite, or a volcano or
a mountain, you know, inside
that mountain is, is a sleeping
kind of consciousness of such
beauty. But it's, it's just
waiting. It's waiting for its
time, you know. And everything,
like a plant, has it, and you
can see a little bit more of it
in a plant, and in a bird, you
can see it more clearly, like
it's, it's taking animation. And
then a mammal, it's like even
more, because it looks at you in
the eyes, and it has, even some
of them have, you know, have
that emotional flavor that
humans have, like dogs and
horses. And then in the human
it's, it's much more like
obvious, because you can, you
know, we can do this. So the
spirit is, you know, there's
that notion that it's in like,
like this, the this, the gems
that you speak of, like
everything is a gem in matter.
Every tiny atom contains the
seed of a spiritual truth, yeah,
and it's just everything is
waiting its time. Everything is
on this evolutionary ladder and
and where evolution meets,
evolution is kind of the eternal
Now, yes, just constantly, as
you said, constantly creating
and just recreating itself, and
also from the notion of
involution and evolution, you
can, you can solve at some way.
I don't know if that's the right
word, but you can, you can
penetrate the the old chestnut
of free will and determinism.
Because if you look at it from
the involution perspective, you
might say, well, it's all
predetermined, because it's all
just sitting there waiting for
its moment to come alive. But
from the view of evolution,
nothing is predetermined.
Everything is like being created
on you know, from this view. So
the two of them together, like a
funnel meeting, are like this.
That's the paradox for me, of
you know, that's divine science
that Aurobindo, by the way,
just, you know, really nailed. I
mean, if, if you're able to read
him, which, which, not the
challenges. Like the layers of
subtle nuance in that man's mind
stream in terms of how he
penetrated this information is
extraordinary. Yes, I know he's
inspired both of us.
Chris Bache: And yes he has, yes
he has, yeah, and I think you're
right. I think in some ways,
it's our everyday experience
that there are aspects of our
life which are highly
conditioned, and it's our
everyday experience that we are
not completely subservient to
those conditions. We have a
cubic centimeter of free will,
which we can expand into a cubic
meter of free will. We choose
how we choose to meet the
circumstances of our life,
whether we incubate choice,
incubate a space where we look
at the options and really
examine deeply what we want to
do, what we want to be and enact
out of that choice, and that's
something we can expand on. I
mean, that's that's how I sort
of see what you're doing in gene
T's and correct me if I'm wrong,
you're helping people make more
informed choices by giving them
an opportunity to sit deeply
with the core, the karmic core,
the swirl of their being. So
they make choices on how to
engage and define the outcome of
that
Richard Rudd: exactly because
you have in jinkies is very
simple, actually, because you
have these three layers that,
you know, Shadow gift and city
and city is, that is the is the
involving seed, you know, or the
way I describe it often actually
is, it's the shadow is the seed,
the gift is in the center, is
the fruit, is the is the flower,
and then the city is the fruit,
and the fruit also contains the
seed. Yeah, so there's this
whole process of awakening
inside us, where the shadow
suddenly you know our what we
learn from our karma, what we
learn from our mistakes, what we
learn from our challenges,
becomes this incredible treasure
that you know, and as we unlock
it and forgive ourselves and
you. Learn and evolve. Then, you
know, we begin to, we begin to
kind of access those heightened
states of consciousness. They're
actually buried in the in those
very dense places in creation.
And that's our role as humans,
to kind of find those dense
places and be an intermediary to
help unlock them, you know, so
that you know that's an
incredible responsibility.
Chris Bache: Yeah, my sense is,
over the course of long time,
the shadow the shadow seeds
become less. They get
evaporated, yeah, in the process
of reflective awareness and so
the creative seeds become more
and the opportunity to become
increasingly transparent to the
intelligence of the universe
increase. And if we extrapolate
that, if that's true, not only
for us individually, but
collectively, I mean, and
clearly the human race has a
long way to go before it makes
all of its shadow seeds, because
it seems like we have so many
shadow seeds that are driving us
now. But if we just step back
and give the benefit of the
doubt and assume that what
happens for the individual,
which we've seen, can happen for
the collective, and that
humanity as a whole is in the
process through these
magnificent, deep collective
dynamics of cooking its past
seeds and transcending its the
limitations of its past and
moving forward in time, then we
have reasons to hope that What
the greatness of beings that we
see in tulkus into intimate
dialog with Termas is something
that all of humanity is aspiring
to, and all of humanity can
become, that, that we can
become. We are in the process of
becoming a truly a species of
enlightened beings, a species
where we live in the light more
than living in the shadows. I
think we're coming out of the
shadows of history into a
deeper, deeper, better tomorrow,
Richard Rudd: particularly as we
start to understand the universe
a little bit more or or, or the
parameters of the universe, and
we look out, you know, I know
you've got some wonderful slides
you want to share, but which I
think would be a great backdrop
if you want to share them.
Chris Bache: When I when I think
about the topics that we're
talking about today, like, where
is reincarnation taking us? What
is the larger scope and purpose
of rebirth. I turn I just
collect these pictures from the
NASA. They send them around
every day, and I collect them,
and I meditate on these
pictures. I try to envision the
enormous distances involved and
the millions and billions of
stars that are involved, and the
life that's burgeoning on so
many of these planets in so many
of these systems, so that the
sheer fertility, the profligate
fertility of the universe, and
the scale that the universe is
thinking of in order to create
and to manifest orders and
orders and orders of evolving
life on this magnitude, and then
to appreciate that We are part
of this, this has been the
great, great burden of a one
time through metaphysics, the
belief that we that this genius
and beauty that we're seeing in
these pictures, if our life is
meaningless and if it's all
random chance, we don't get to
participate in this greatness.
But if reincarnation is true,
and if we are really not limited
by the time that this little
body lives, and if our mind is
going to grow for countless,
countless, countless
incarnations, then we become
intimately part of the
generative creativity that we
see around us in these vast,
magnificent images
Richard Rudd: of the universe,
and this then becomes our
playground. You know, you know,
without the physical body, this
is surely where we live. This is
our playground, and it could be
even within the physical body,
you know, at some deep level,
and as a hologram, you know that
could be a deep truth that we
come to. You know that, as
above, so below truth, yeah, and
I know you've experienced. Some
of that yourself and your
experience, your you know,
journeys, and so have I. That's
a fundamental truth I hold at
the core of my being, that you
know and and in my teachings,
also I we have this profile
called a hologenetic profile.
And I name it that because it
is, it is a map of the, you
know, of the inner workings of
our being. But it, it kind of
it. It has a fractal reality
that corresponds way beyond, you
know, this microorganism here,
of of one body. It is replicated
throughout the cosmos. Yeah. So,
yeah, a lot of the great
alchemical teachings of, you
know, the Taoists, for example,
have explored this in their
deep, you know, studies of and
meditations, where you go within
and you find the galaxies and
the stars and where they exist,
in the in the glands of the
body, and how everything has a
correspondence, ya know, and
and, and therefore knowing those
correspondences allows your
awareness to travel into that
reality and outside your
physical body. You know that
that's you know, as many people
have well experienced that in
dreams or in astral projection
or deep meditation or
psychedelic journeying. I mean,
feel free to share some of your
experiences in that.
Chris Bache: Well, you know,
I've done that as carefully as I
can in my book, LSD, in the mind
of the universe. But I think the
invitation is to appreciate, I
mean, look, we only became
conscious of the mother universe
about 5000 years ago. We began
to have be sufficient discipline
to drop beneath the conditioning
of our of our individual egoic
mind and to tap into that stream
of consciousness that we share
with all life. We've been
walking upright for 5.8 million
years. We've only we've been
operating with our larger brain
about 200,000 years. Writing
came in about 5000 years ago,
the Upanishadic breakthroughs
came in about three, 4000 years
ago. But these are nothing
compared to the billions and
billions of years that lie ahead
of us. We're just waking up.
We're just waking up to who we
are, and so naturally, we kind
of get confused given the
enormity of what we're growing
into. But I think the meditation
exercises that you're describing
and those philosophical and
spiritual traditions which have
begun to recognize the
correspondence between the above
and the below, naturally we
begin to enter into exercises
where we intentionally sort of
reinforce the hybrid nature of
our life, that we are a
spiritual being and we are
physical being. We are both pure
light and we are pure green, and
there are correspondences in our
body which correspond to the
correspondence that the
realities out there, and the
more we can internalize and
reinforce them and strengthen
them in our meditational
exercises, then we become a more
conscious mixing pot, a more
conscious kind of Mortal and
pestle, integrating the above
and the below. And if we keep
this up for a few 10s of 1000s
of years and a few millions of
years, I mean, I sometimes would
tell my students, only serious
question we should be asking
ourselves is, what do you want
to be in a million years?
Because you're going to be here
in a million years. So let's get
down to it. What is our deepest
hearts desire? What can we
Richard Rudd: do? The
fundamental question I heard a
couple of weeks ago, I heard a
really interesting talk by Roger
Penrose. You know him? Yeah,
really imaginative, top level
physicist in the world today.
And he was saying how, because
there was this this, there's
this notion that universe is as
it's expanding in physics, it's
getting further and further
apart and slowing down. It's
going to reach steady state, and
then we're all going to end up
in this kind of slightly
distant, dead, lonely kind of
stopping point. And and he, that
wasn't his, that's not his
intuition, or at least the way
he describes it, is that when
you reach that stopping point,
it. It's, it's the same as if
you've gone incredibly fast, as
if you everything's come
together again, because one end
of the spectrum meets the other
end of the spectrum. So you
wouldn't be able to tell if
things are slowing down. It
actually might be that they
speak, they look like they're
speeding up. And anyway, so he,
this is my paraphrasing what he
said. But the thing that really
blew me away from from a
physicist to say was that he
said the way he would understand
it is that the logic of the and
the and the kind of elegance of
the universe would be such that
that, but that, that kind of
condensing point would then give
birth to another universe out of
itself, like which seems to be
the elegant logic that the
universe already does. As we
started by saying rebirth, and
then leads to another birth and
another eon. But then he even
went further, and he said the
background radiation that we see
with through our furthest
telescopes that can now see like
these, the very, very beginnings
of the universe. He said, there
are certain objects that we're
seeing, and then I can't quite
remember what he called them,
but there are certain shapes and
patterns and things that you're
seeing, and you see them over
and over again. And his, his
assumption was that those were
the leftovers from the previous
eon, from the previous universe
that we're seeing and and it
that really blew me away. I was
like, wow, that's for a
physicist who's willing to kind
of who's who's kind of reached
the top of his game. He's able
to kind of take a few leaps. But
that really seemed
Chris Bache: to me to be I've
heard Irvin Laszlo describe the
once you reflect on the
extraordinary precision of the
unfolding of our universe in the
Big Bang that just you know, the
magnitude of the perfection of
the balance of elements that had
to be present in the first
picoseconds for it to unfold as
it has. Then. His hypothesis
was, well, do we think that this
is the first time the universe
has tried this? There have been
expansions and contractions and
expansions and contraction, and
the universe is learning. And
perhaps this isn't the first big
bang. Perhaps this is the 1000s
Big Bang, and it's gotten, it's
learned from its previous
experiences. And that's that
background radiation, the traces
which are there,
Richard Rudd: and it's
constantly ironing out flaws and
perfecting and perfecting and
perfecting itself, yeah.
Chris Bache: But of course, this
this wide view. I think it's
rich to take the wide view, to
take the deep view and to look
at very special, developed
beings who are kind of pushing
the edge of this large view. But
I want to bring it back down to
Okay. How does this impact me
here today? How does this help
me live with the immediate
problems that I'm dealing with,
or the with the immediate
choices that I'm living with,
you know, and I think it does in
the sense that, by it, it's an
invitation to look at our life
as An intentional, intelligent
convocation of circumstances,
not as a meaningless and not as
an blind, deterministic
combination of circumstances,
and if we engage our life
circumstances as a an
intentional challenge, chosen
us, chosen for Us, By Us, at a
time when we knew more, and we
start to make choices in terms
of out of a deeper sense of
engagement, that our choice does
matter, even if we don't see how
it changes things immediately,
we can trust that it does change
things in the Long term, then I
think we will find that life
changes the circumstances of our
life changes things that were
hard become soft, things that
were bare, and becomes richer.
That's your experience, I'm
sure. With with Gene
Richard Rudd: keys, yeah, and it
gives us like, for me, it gives
us like, a different kind of
backdrop with which to tackle
the problems of the world, you
know, so the problems that we
see today around us that worry
us so much, it gives us an
empowered view from a much wider
view, like to look we've just
been looking at. Those cosmic
background images. And then you
come to the world today, and you
look at this tiny, little blue
planet with its problems, and,
you know? And they're very real,
and and they and they, and
they're causing a great deal of
suffering. They always have
done, you know, but they're now
more they're more easily seen
than ever before, yeah, and
we've enacted them globally
because of our technology. So we
are, you know, it means that for
me, I'm constantly reminding
people that, you know, action
that comes from a state of trust
is very different from action
that comes from fear. Yeah. So
if you can, if we can dive into
that field of wider trust, and
we begin to make friends with
our own death, you know, instead
of being, it being something
that's kind of, you know, like
it's coming, you know, I'm
running out of time. Instead of
like that view, having this long
term view as an individual and
and even, like, what I'm doing
is as a community, like, as a
com, how about if a whole
community of people on the same
wavelength play with this
together, like, we're all going
to come back, you know, we're
going to return, and we're going
to return into this same I mean,
that's why I've created these
teachings. It's I haven't
created. They've appeared
because we can come back into
them and we can begin to like
and the teachings are just the
teachings. They're just enable
us to kind of give a focal point
so that we can do our work, our
continuous, progressive,
evolutionary work as
communities, rather than like,
okay, you've done this great
work, and then you've gone and,
yeah, I might be reborn, but
where? Yeah, but if you're
reborn into the same community
of beings, of souls who are all
committed to transmuting karma
of the planet, and come in with
different gifts and genius and
skills in different locations
around the world, but we're
interconnected through the
internet and through a body of
teachings that kind of have a
resonance in our soul, so we
recognize them again, even as a
child, you know, and
synchronicity helps us to find
them. Suddenly we are. It's a
different playground again. You
know it's like, you don't have
to say goodbye to all your loved
ones forever. You're you're
going to remember them in
different way. You're going to
bring more of that awareness
that through the transitionary
Bardo, and bring and the more of
us that do that, that incarnate
the memory through the Bardos
forwards in time. The more it
kind of i, this is my my
intuition, the more it will open
up the Bardos themselves, you
know, so that more and more
people can remember. And it's
all a game of memory. I think
that you know, like the more
awareness we we the more we play
and participate, the more that
memory opens up. Because memory
is a strange thing, isn't it?
Like even individual memory, you
can, there are memory tricks you
can do to you know, and you can
and therapeutically, you can
take someone back into their
memories, you know. So there are
things that you can do to
enhance memory, and there are
things you can do forwards in
time to ensure that you don't
forget. You know, there are
triggers, you know that you can
you know? I mean, there are lots
of ways of playing with this,
but there are things you can do,
as the lamas, do you know the
tulkus? You know they they
sometimes leave objects that
they retrieve in the next life.
Yeah, you know. And, and there's
lots of tricks within once you
know the time that you know,
once you kind of found the way
through the wormholes. I think
you can play more as and then we
can bring more and more
awakening, you know, into the
collective you know. And I think
that that changes everything it
does.
Chris Bache: I think we're
shifting slowly from living an
ego based life which is grounded
in this incarnation to living a
soul life which is grounded into
this much, much deeper life in
the universe. It always struck
me as significant that in the
classical story of the Buddha's
enlightenment, and when he went
through the four watches of the
night in one of the watches of
the night, he saw all of his
former lives. They all became
living part of his awareness now
to see your former lives, to
remember your former lives, is
not simply to remember who you
were, but you bring all of that
life experience into who you
are. So for me to see, to
remember your former lives is.
To become the soul which which
gathers all that knowledge and
all that experience into one
place. And when he did that, he
became transparent and
shattered. He stopped the
suffering. And the suffering is
fundamentally living, small,
living as if this body is the
only thing that is you. And I
think this is happening
historically. We are, as you
say, the more we bring that
memory forward, the more we live
that memory, the more we see
that memory into the future.
Another way of saying this is to
say we are practicing the skills
of soul inside time and space.
And as our soul gets stronger,
we begin to remember and have an
intuitive feeling for
relationships that we have a
deeper history with. And if, if
people come at us as enemies,
well, let's heal them. Listen,
I'm sorry what I did to you,
whatever it was, let's get let
me make it up to you, but more
and more allies come and because
there's a waking up is a social
process. It's a generative
process which has never, ever
been private at any time in
history. And I think this is
what's happening. I think the
soul is waking up inside time
and space that the human species
is basically growing up on a on
a scale the likes of which is
really comparable about like
200,000 years ago, when we made
the jump to our bigger brain,
except now the physical plant
isn't changing, but the
awareness that is supported by
the physical plant seems to be
changing exponentially. So I
know that you and I share a
vision of history that we're
entering into a very, very
challenging time of a time of
darkening shadows. So I hope in
our next conversation, we can
begin to put together our
understanding of the dynamics of
this period of history that
we're venturing and the dynamics
of soul growth that
Richard Rudd: we both affirm so
deeply. Yeah, and how those two
fit perfectly together, what
you've called The Birth of the
diamond soul. And I also happen
to call it the diamond
awareness, yeah, and it is that
memory that transcends the
lifetimes and and, yeah, that
maintaining that memory between
lives. It shows, I mean, for one
thing, you know, suddenly, many
people who I, I'm engaged with,
like they're suddenly excited by
being here and by returning, as
opposed to, I want to get out of
here, yeah, which has been the
prevalent kind of feeling among
spiritual communities. I want to
get out of here. You know, I,
this is my last incarnation. I'm
off, and that's, you know, I
think there's a more
compassionate view, and I think
a more exciting view that, you
know, we can actually bring, you
know, and you know, it's like a
warriors view as well. Spiritual
warrior like this place needs
us. It needs us here to do this
work. So yeah, I think that's
why we're having these
conversations. For me,
Chris Bache: I don't think the
creative genius that gave birth
to the galaxies and planets
inside the galaxies and solar
systems would inculcate and it
created reincarnation. We didn't
create it. The religions didn't
create it. Nature created it.
And I don't think it would
create reincarnation to grow us
to an awareness of our first
inkling of our deep, deep
spiritual essence, with the
purpose being, okay, then you
can go, then you can go. I think
we missed it. We don't
understand that awakening is
part of is a process which
really is part of the
transformation of time and space
itself that we are here to
change. We are changing the
world. It really is heaven on
earth. Is what, the process is
about, yeah,
Richard Rudd: and the prophecy
on the prophecy, let's leave
that as a seed for next time.
And it sounds good. Yeah,
wonderful. Thank you, Chris.
What a fantastic
Chris Bache: and I'll just leave
with this thought. I wonder what
our personal farmer life history
is that we meet in such ease and
fruitful dialog you and I, so I
honor the history between us,
whatever it is
Richard Rudd: I will contemplate
that. Yeah. Much. Love. Great.
Thank you.
Unknown: You.