Stephen Gray: At the end of
Chris's talk, during the this
break, Chris will be signing his
new book, and I don't know if he
was going to tell you this or
not, so I'll tell you the book
is called LSD and the mind of
the universe, and it's based on
his experiential work with LSD,
and he got the publisher they
were going to publish it, put it
out in December, and he got them
to agree to put out an advanced
printing for this conference. So
this weekend is the debut of the
book. Yeah, right. And I don't
know there's going to be enough
copies for all the people that
will really want this book,
because I've read the book I
offered, because I'm so enamored
of Chris's work, to write an
endorsement for it. And so he
stuck me in there with some of
the other big shots that gave
him endorsements. And so I've
read the electronic version of
this book, and it's a mind
blower. I'm not kidding. It is a
mind blower. So give a warm
welcome to Chris Bache, please.
Chris
Chris Bache: Give me just a
second folks to hook up my
technology. I
your fingers crossed.
Okay, can you give me PowerPoint
on all three? Okay, all right,
is my is this mic working? Is it
working now? Okay, Mercury
Retrograde, right, all right,
okay, okay, great. And we'll get
it on the screen. Okay, thank
you. All right, how the
technology moves forward. It's
wonderful to be here with you
again, after last year, this is
such a wonderful community. When
I was here last year, I spoke to
you about a book that I was just
finishing, that I was calling
diamonds from heaven, and it
describes a 20 year journey of
using high doses of LSD, 73
sessions over 20 years to
explore the structure of the
universe. That book is now here.
Do we have it? Okay, let's see.
Do we have it here? Oh, come on,
work for me. Okay, let's see
one. Here we go. There it is.
Publisher changed the title, but
in my heart it will always be
diamonds from heaven.
I want to say up front that I'm
not sure that what I did was
wise, honestly. I mean that I
pushed myself extremely hard on
this journey harder than was
probably good for me, but I've
come through it intact,
reasonably So, and I'm really
looking forward to sharing with
you where this journey took me
and to share it with the world.
And it's not because I think my
experiences are in any way
unique or special, but they are
a particularly, I think, well
focused exploration of the
structure of the universe. And I
want to say clearly that I did
this work, not as a therapist,
and not really seeking therapy.
So all honor and deep respect to
all the psychedelic therapists
in the room, this is a different
agenda. What I was primarily
seeking I was trained as a
philosopher of religion, and
what I was primarily seeking was
an understanding of our universe
as deeply as I could get by
sinking deep into my own
consciousness, and in those deep
states of consciousness,
exploring the structure, the
deep structure of the universe
itself. Now I want to ground
this story in the context of our
collective psychedelic
experience. Let's see, Is my mic
on yet? Do we this? No, this
one? No, okay, sooner or later,
it will come on. I like to walk,
but okay. Do. Is it on? Now it's
on. Okay, good. Pump the volume
a little bit, okay. How many we
have so many people working in
so many different psychedelic
mediums in this room, right? So
many different substances, so
many different forms and so many
different agendas. All honor to
the psychedelic community and
all the work that we are doing
collectively. What I'm bringing
to you today is the story of one
particular journey into the
universe, one particular method,
one particular format, which
does not negate in any way, any
of the other dimensions, other
dimensions that we're exploring.
It is simply one voice in our
collective expression.
So let's go into it. Let's see.
I got two clickers here, which
one is going to work.
Okay? Looks like it's just as a
winner. Okay. This is my
psychedelic lineage. My
psychedelic lineage basically
grounds in Stan Grof work. When
I was 29 years old, fresh out of
graduate school, just beginning
my academic career in Ohio, I
met Stan grofwork, his work
realms of the human unconscious,
and then his book, LSD
psychotherapy, which is this
fundamental manual for working
psychedelic sessions, changed my
life, turned my life around,
pointed me in a completely
different direction, and it has
become my entire life's work.
Now, in in terms of the sessions
themselves. Of structuring
sessions, I want to emphasize
I've never tripped. I've never
gone to a concert on LSD. I've
never spent the night, all
night, tripping with my friends
and talking about things. It's
not that those are bad things.
Those can be fine. But in my
work, every time I took LSD, I
was working in a very, very
carefully controlled
environment. I was isolated. I
was in my home. I was are in my
wife's office. I was totally
perfected, protected from the
world. I did always solo work. I
didn't work in groups. There are
advantages for working in
groups. There are advantages for
doing solo work, just owning
mine was always solo work, which
allowed me to go to follow
exactly where the experiences
were taking me and to push
myself in that direction,
wherever it would take me in
Stan's work. Are we not getting
Ha, okay, come on. Okay,
clearly, two different
therapeutic modality that Stan
outline, psycholytic, low dose
therapy, psychedelic, high dose
therapy, psycholytic, low dose
maybe about 200 micrograms,
where the psyche peels itself
layer by layer, we move into it
layer by layer sessions, up to
about 100 sessions psychedelic
therapy, very, very different
therapy, very concentrated, very
intense experiences. The goal is
not to work through all the
layers of the personal
unconscious, but to sort of blow
through the psychodynamic level
of consciousness and to trigger
an experience of Transcendence,
an experience. Basically, they
were trying to trigger near
death episode experiences,
working with people who were
terminally ill they were going
to die, and they were working
with the anxiety that they were
facing as they were going
towards the death. This form of
therapy was limited to three
sessions in Spring Grove
Hospital, no more than three
sessions. So I came along and I
thought, Well, okay, if it can
be done safely three times, it
can be done safely more than
three times, and it can be done
safely more than three times,
but I found that it was a much,
much more demanding protocol
than I had anticipated in the
beginning, and it took all of my
research, my resources, to
basically manage what unfolded
in this journey. This is not a
therapeutic journey. It's a
journey of cosmological
exploration, and therefore it
requires something of an
Explorer's constitution, and it
also requires something of an
Explorer's preparation, an
Explorer's position in life,
where you have the opportunity,
where you can push this deeply,
this far beyond the edges,
beyond the maps, where most
people have gone. When I got to
the end of this journey, and was
writing up my accounts, and was
looking back over the whole
thing I realized, well, I
thought I was just doing an
extended course of psychedelic
therapy, high dose therapy, but
what I realized was that this
process that I had gotten
engaged in went so deep and went
so far and generated
complications that were so
intense i. Had to give it a
different name. So I call it. Do
I have psychedelic exploration?
The method is the method of
psychedelic therapy, total
isolation, always working with a
sitter, carefully selected
music. You know, the whole works
there. The difference is the
number of sessions involved. For
me, 73 sessions. I did three
sessions at the psychodynamic
level. I did three sessions
about 200 micrograms, and then
after that, all of my sessions
were at 500 600 micrograms.
Again, this is not a protocol
that I recommend. I wouldn't do
it that way. Again, I would do
it differently. I would balance
the plant medicines more with
the synthetic psychedelic
medicines. I would really only
push myself periodically with
high doses, rather than pushing
myself so relentlessly. In that
way, I have worked with
Psilocybin, I have worked with
Ayahuasca and salvia divinorum,
a number of plant medicines. I
did most of that work after I
stopped my LSD work. But LSD, in
the mind of the universe, is
really focused specifically on
what happened on this high dose
journey. I want to emphasize
that the circumstances in which
I did this work were kind of
unusual in that they were very,
very stable and concentrated and
focused. In all of my work, I
had the same sitter for all
these years, the same set and
setting, same same intention,
same location, all in Northeast
Ohio, same substance, same dose
level and the same recording
process, always recording every
sense, every session, as
completely as possible within 24
hours of the session. Okay, what
this did? I've come to
appreciate. When you stabilize
your work in this way, when you
eliminate as many variables as
possible and you're using the
same methodology and the same
consistency, it stabilizes the
conversation that opens up
between you and the creative
intelligence of the universe. It
stabilizes the communion so that
one session leads to another
session, leads to another
session in a very coherent,
intelligent manner, even though
you may not understand all the
details of the continuity when
it's unfolding, when you're
looking out over a longer period
of your work, you can begin to
understand the patterns of
continuity that you are in
dialog with, in a sense, a
single intelligence in this
process. I say that carefully,
because there's so many layers
to this intelligence. There's so
many forms of this intelligence.
But in the end, when you see the
the continuity across sessions,
it you're can't help but feel
like you're engaging a single
creative intelligence. Now, I
kept detailed records of my
work. I have about 400 pages of
session notes, again, recording
the session always within 24
hours, because you know what
it's like two or three days
later, things are not as clear
as when you do it right. The day
after, I kept track of all the
dates of the sessions. I even
plotted the astrological
variables late in the work, I
used astrology to choose the
dates of my sessions. I was
working, on average, about five
sessions a year. Now I worked
for four years. I stopped for
six years for reasons that are
not important to go into now
they're in the book. And then I
picked up for another 10 years
of very intense work. I worked
about five sessions a year. And
so I looked when I became aware
of Rick Tarnas and Stan Grof
hypothesis of the relationship
between the outer planets and
transit astrology, global
transits and my psychedelic
sessions, I wanted to study
this, so I looked at that,
tracked at those variables, and
there's an appendix on that
issue in the back of the living
class of LSD, in the mind of the
universe, I keep wanting to Say
diamonds from heaven. I have to
retrain myself. Now, the story
I'm telling in LSD, in the mind
of the universe is not primarily
a personal story. There was a
personal story. There was
personal healing, there were
personal insights. But what I
found was that when I was doing
this work, the personal
components generally tend to
manifest in the beginning of a
session and at the end of the
session, when I was leaving
space time and when I was coming
back into space time. That's not
entirely correct, because
sometimes a whole session was
spent in personal healing. But
in general, after about the
first 15 sessions. Years when I
was at the peak of the sessions,
as indicated in these large
circles in this series of sine
waves, which represent a series
of sessions. When I was at that
those peak hours, I was
operating far beyond personal
reality. Okay, that's the story
I'm trying to tell in LSD, in
the mind of the universe, I've
dropped out a lot of the
personal story because from a
philosophical perspective, that,
from a therapeutic perspective,
that's relevant, but from a
philosophical perspective, it's
the large story which is the
more important story.
A lot of work at the medical
level. At the therapeutic level,
really focuses on ego
dissolution, transcending the
limitations of your physical
body, entering into a deeper
communion, into mystical
experiences. What I found was
when you when I did this work,
it wasn't just one cycle of
Death-Rebirth. Now, in this
image, the drop at the bottom of
the circle represents egoic
awareness, our time space
awareness the line. Everything
below the line is physical
reality. Everything above the
line is Transpersonal reality or
spiritual reality. A lot of
work, a lot of discussion
focuses on that first circle,
the Death-Rebirth of ego, and
that's an important place to
focus. It is the fundamental
transition. What I found in my
work was you actually go through
multiple levels of death and
rebirth. And it's not ego dying
over and over again. You're
going through death and rebirth
processes which take place at
different levels of the
universe, at different levels of
the creative intelligence of the
universe, and the deaths and
rebirths at the higher levels
are different than the death and
rebirth at the beginning level,
when you're shedding time and
space, when you're shedding your
identity built up in time and
space, they're harder to
describe, because you know the
levels of consciousness that
you're born into. In the
beginning you're born out of. At
the end, when you're being born
into the species mind, it has a
certain set of qualities and
characteristics. But when you
are shedding the species mind,
when you are going beyond the
collective psyche, when you are
entering into archetypal
reality, that is a different
pattern of death and rebirth.
Now I follow, I use Stan Grof
category. Stan talks about
psychic level, Transpersonal
experience, high and low,
psychic high and low, subtle
level, high and low, causal
level. That's a kind of
convenient category. But of
course, how can we possibly
describe the full spectrum of
the divine experience, of
spiritual experience, with
simply three or six categories?
These are simply rough
approximations which are useful
in order to describe certain
transitions that took place on
this journey, the 19, when I got
to the end of the journey, and I
was kind of working and
crunching all the experiences
and putting them all together
for the book, I realized that I
began to count up how many
fundamental, deep Death. Oops,
oops, sorry, I'm jumping ahead
of myself. These cycles of death
and rebirth are kind of really
like Tauruses. You kind of break
through, you open up, you expand
into a new level. And then there
is a sense of gathering in
everything that took place,
blowing through into another
level. And then you explore that
level, you become competent and
stabilize states of
consciousness. At that level,
there's a kind of a gathering in
and then, if you follow the
process through, takes you into
yet another death and rebirth
process into a deeper level. And
one of the ways I kind of image
this in terms of a nuclear
explosion. Now, this image
triggers very, very deep
responses in us, and it should.
This is, this is an image of
humanity's insanity at one
level, but I don't want to. I
want to, don't want to go there.
I want to use it simply to make
one point, when you go through
deep, deep death and rebirth
processes where you are
shattering every level that you
have known and in not only in
earth, but everything that you
have known. In some sessions, it
drops you deeper into the
universe, and it allows levels
of reality to come into your
awareness which were not in your
awareness before. They were
always there, but you were not
experiencing them. And there is
something like that that happens
with a nuclear explosion. When
this explosion drives deeper
into the atmosphere, it brings
out levels of the atmosphere
which. Previously you could not
see. And something like that
happens with the LSD work or any
kind of deep psychotherapy, deep
psychedelic work. It brings you
into levels that previously you
were not aware of. Now, the
dualism here is, is, I want to
dissolve the dualism now,
because the nuclear explosion in
the center and the levels of
reality one is entering are in
this image, are two different
things. Now dissolve that
duality, because when one dies
at that level, you literally
dissolve into that field of
reality. You dissolve into that
stratum, that stratum of
reality. But we're not talking
about bombs here. We're talking
about the universe exploring the
nature of the cosmos itself.
When I got to the end of my
work, and I was kind of counting
up out of all the deaths and all
the purifications and all the
purgations. How many core
fundamental levels of reality
did I go through? I counted
five. Here they are. First, the
death of self, transcending our
time space, identity, our egoic
reality. After that, something
that took place at the
collective mind, transcending
the individual mind. Something
is taking place at the level of
species consciousness. After
that, something that took place
at the archetypal level, at the
archetypal dimension of mind.
And then something that took
place at what I call causal
oneness. Now oneness, of course,
comes up many, many levels.
Oneness can come up in the first
ego death. Oneness is a
fundamental truth, and it occurs
in many different forms. There's
something distinctive and unique
about causal oneness, or oneness
at causal level reality, because
here you're dealing with there
is no outside to reality. When
you're in causal oneness, you
are not experiencing oneness.
You are in the condition in
which the universe experiences
itself as being fundamentally
unified with no core divisions
whatsoever. At any level,
physical, spiritual,
reincarnational, it's a
fundamental core oneness of
reality. And then at the last
level, what I call diamond
Luminosity, what Buddhism calls
Dharmakaya, the pure light of
absolute reality. So let me use
these five categories and then
show you how these lay out in
the chapters of LSD, in the mind
of the universe. And then I'm
just going to share some
observations on each of these
categories as we go through just
to kind of give a quick overview
death of self, there's a chapter
crossing the boundary of birth
and death. I'm going to go back
into these in more detail in a
minute, but just to give you
where it is in the book. Now
there is a chapter one, which is
the chapter on methodology. It's
a rather long chapter in the
book, because I really wanted to
be very, very clear on the
methodology that I used and some
of the ways of working with
psychedelics at this level. And
there's a chapter after this
called a session day, because
someone had asked me, why don't
you just kind of take us into a
typical day and show us what
happens? And so I did. I kind of
wrote a narrative of a typical
session day, but in terms of the
levels of consciousness, those
three levels of consciousness
really kind of function at the
death of self.
My wife is taking care of me, by
the way. I didn't mention I
forgot astrology, working with
astrology and psychedelic
sessions really, really
interesting insights emerge. My
wife, Christina, is a
professional astrologer, and she
kind of helps me understand some
of the archetypal dynamics that
are operating in some of the
session material.
Okay, collective mind. There are
three chapters that have to do
with the collective mind, the
ocean of suffering, sort of the
challenging, purifying part of
working with the species mind,
deep time in the soul. Is an
initiation into the universe.
I'm going to come back to these
in a minute, archetypal mind.
There is a chapter the greater
real of archetypal reality calls
a oneness. The chapter, a
benediction of blessings. Then
we move to diamond Luminosity,
the chapter diamond Luminosity.
But before I discuss diamond
Luminosity, I have a chapter
called The Birth of the future
human, which actually describes
a series of visionary
experiences that started at the
initiation of the universe and
continued all the way into the
final chapter, into from session
22 to session 70, is one of the
most consistent recurring
themes, what's happening to
humanity? Where are we going?
What is our historical time in
history? What's happening at the
deep structural level? And then
diamond Luminosity. And then the
last chapter, final vision,
where I was given the last, what
I call the last of the great
visions of the journey. And then
the goodbye sessions, the wrap
up sessions. So let me go back
and just offer a few
observations on each of these
levels. First, let me check my
time. Okay, that's not bad.
We're okay.
First, crossing the boundary of
death and birth. How many people
here know the work of Stanislav
Grof? Okay, then you know
exactly what I'm going to be
talking about here, because this
is the perinatal level of
consciousness. This is that
level that is the boundary level
between space, time,
consciousness and first
Transpersonal reality. When I
got into this level, I felt like
a poster child for Stan's
perinatal level of
consciousness, intense, intense
physical purifications, fetal
sensations, reliving aspects of
birth, tremendous psychological
existential angst, questioning
the fundamental meaningfulness
of life, confronting the
meaninglessness of life, and
then eventually ego death, a
complete shattering of egoic
reality. The ego is a tough son
of a bitch, but in the final
analysis, it's not that hard to
take apart. It's harder to heal
than it is to shatter. It's kind
of curious. But on these last
two sessions, this is two and a
half years work in 10 sessions.
At the end of these sessions,
the last two sessions, it just
took me and snapped me like a
twig. I started the day as a
white male, highly educated
academic, obsessed with the
meaning of life. It totally
inverted all of those variables.
It turned me into women, turned
me into women of color, turned
me into women at the laundromat
with no prospects. Turned me
into women who had no interest
whatsoever in philosophy or the
meaning of anything of life at
all. Of course, it wasn't women
that were the problem, of
course, and it wasn't a lack of
education that was the problem.
It was what it was the social
identity that I had internalized
and accepted as what I am that
was the problem, and the
universe forced me to become the
opposite of what I was, and just
snapped me. And when eventually
I let go and surrender to that
experience, I entered the world
of women under the arm of the
Great Mother, and I was taken
through the experience of
hundreds and hundreds of women's
lives. It was just an
extraordinary transformation in
my own experience. I wish every
man could have the experience,
and I'm sure many of the men in
this room have had that kind of
experience, of experiencing so
deeply the inner essence and the
inner experience of the so
called opposite sex. Now I
believe in reincarnation. I've
written a book on reincarnation.
I think we've all lived lives as
men and women, but what was
happening here was I was not
being invited to reclaim my
former lives as women. This was
different. This was saying where
you are going. Gender does not
exist, let go, and so I let go
and I entered into spiritual
reality. What happened next,
much to my surprise, is that
things didn't get easier. Things
got harder after going through a
trans. Mission, experience in
which my compassion was expanded
and open to the suffering of the
world. I entered a domain of
collective suffering and anguish
and and pain, which deepened
session by session
systematically, and it deepened
for two years. It took two years
and 14 sessions to go through
all of this work. There was a
year of the ocean of suffering
before I stopped my sessions for
the six years. I stopped for six
years, and then I started again
six years later, under
completely different a different
time in life, different set of
expectations and different
astrological transits, but at
the other side of that six year
gap, the ocean of suffering
started exactly where it had
stopped six years before, which
I think is a measure of the
intelligence and the
intentionality of the
consciousness that's directing
our work. So hmm, when the ocean
of suffering opened, at first, I
thought that this represented a
deepening of my ego death. I
thought I was being, you know,
kind of cleaned up more. And
this is kind of implicit in
Stan's theory. He see, he
recognizes, and he's, he's
witnessed these collective
ordeals, but Stan sees these
collective ordeals, or at least
he did. He saw these collective
ordeals as being drawn in
through resonance to ego death.
All right, so it's ego death
which is really the primary
driver. And when you get into
ego death in the context of the
collective psyche, you can tap
into some of the suffering of
humanity that's still stored in
the collective psyche, and it
seeps into your experiences
through resonance. That's what I
so I went with that
interpretation at first, but
what I found was that this went
on for so long, it was so
extreme, and it lasted for so
many years, and it involved so
many millions and millions of
beings, that I decided that this
could not be correct.
Eventually, I came to the
conclusion that these sessions
were not trying to sort of
purify me or heal me or
transform me. These experiences
were aimed at nothing less than
the transformation of the
collective psyche of our planet.
It was about healing the entire
planet in some way, shape or
form, somewhere in working with
very, very intense states of
consciousness, something happens
that there is a flip. And what
had started out in my mind as
personal transformation was
taken over by the work of
collective transformation. Now I
don't think anything anyone did
this to me, nobody. It was no
trick that was done to me. I
accept responsibility for this.
This is simply part of my karmic
contract in this lifetime, and I
think it's part of the karmic
contract of a lot of people in
this room. The work you take on
in your deep, deep work is often
disproportionate to anything
that makes sense in terms of
your personal life story, even
your personal former life, life
story. Many of us get into work
so so deep that you have to open
up to a deeper understanding of
what's actually taking place in
these sessions, especially at
this time in history. If we were
doing this work, maybe 500 years
ago, maybe not so, but this
time, at this time in history,
the work of the hour is
collective transformation. Our
species is going into a near
extinction event. We do not have
time to fuck around. We are
getting this is serious work
here, and if you are open, I
yes, if you are open and willing
to let this work come through.
And I'm not saying everybody
should be, and I'm not saying
that it's necessarily a healthy
thing. In many circumstances, it
can be overwhelming and it can
be intimidating, and you do not
want to go there. But if you're
open and if you're capable, and
if it is part of your karma
contract, the work we do in
these deep sessions, I think
there are more bodhisattvas on
this planet than we might think.
Initially, the work we do is for
our collective transformation.
Now, in my experience, working
at high doses, every session
kind of breaks down into two
phases. There's a purification
phase and an ecstatic phase.
There's kind of the dark, hard.
A death, dying kind of phase.
And then there's the static
phase, if you in reference to
this work, James Excellent talk
this morning about shadow work
and engaging the shadow in
working as I did in a non
therapeutic modality. One of the
great gifts I learned from Stan
Grof is to completely,
absolutely surrender to whatever
is taking place in your sessions
and let it take you as far as
wherever it wants to take you.
Now, remember, these are not
tripping. There's no confusion
in the outer world. There's
nothing going on in the outer
world that's getting into my
inner space. I know that
anything I am confronting is
coming entirely from within or
through within. If you submit my
experiences, if you submit
completely to whatever is taking
place in that context, it will
take you deeper and deeper. It
will take you into sometimes
unspeakable anguish and
completely inexplicable anguish,
into chaos, into just terrible
suffering confusion. But if you
let it do that, eventually that
will come to a crescendo. It'll
peak, and then it'll take you
through to something that lies
on the other side. You enter
into the ecstatic phase of the
session, into the teaching phase
of the session, into the
cosmological phase of the
session, even if the next
session, you may come back
around and enter back into the
suffering again. But if you go
through this process, into the
surrender, death and rebirth
process, and let it take you,
there is a deeper, deep,
underlying dynamic that's maybe
not be clear to you at the time,
that unfolds itself over time.
Often you cannot understand
what's happening to you in the
pain part of a session. You
cannot understand the logic of
the pain until you have moved on
to the next stage, because often
these transformations, it's not
until you're looking from a
higher state of consciousness
that you can understand what you
are engaging at this lower state
of consciousness, you understand
it's really important to follow
this all the way through,
because if you follow the pain
all the way through, What
happens is you go from suffering
to resolution, to peace, and
what you internalize, therefore,
is the entire cycle, and this is
what prevents the suffering from
being lodged in your system as
unintegrated trauma or some kind
of something you have to deal
with. I have gone through
terrible, terrible suffering. I
don't have any negative
ramifications or After Effects
of that suffering, because you
internalize the suffering.
Resolution, peace, suffering
resolution, you learn to trust,
to trust the cycle, and to trust
that there is an intelligence
that's behind this dynamic
process. When I came out of the
ocean of suffering in that first
year's work, I was spun into
what I call deep time, and I was
given the experience for one
year, seven sessions over and
over again, consistently,
methodically, laying out, I
experienced the total, the whole
of my life from beginning to end
as a simultaneous now deep time.
I called it whole time first,
and then I called it deep time.
Deep time is not eternity. It's
not timelessness. That's
something different. Deep Time
is moving into a state of
awareness where you can
experience different spans of
time as simultaneously present.
I experience all the time
moments of my life as
simultaneously present, and I
experience it like a tree. The
deepest themes of my life were
the deep branches which had been
received, the biggest branches
which had received most of the
energy the my most recent
experiences were the leaves at
the edges of the before I died,
were the leaves at the edges of
my of The tree, but all of them
being simultaneously present in
you, when I first went into this
state in the 11th session, when
I came out of it, I couldn't
remember it. It was the most
meaningful experience of my life
hours before, but when I came
out of it, I could barely
reconstruct the edges of it. It
took me months to recover the
pieces of the session, but what
I found was, if you go back
again and again and again at
that edge, to your living edge
in your sessions, what I found
was you understand more. You're
able to remember more things
that didn't make sense in the
beginning. Be. Begin to make
sense. The pieces begin to
cohere. Fragments begin to
become integrated. Gestalts.
This is an important
epistemological point. When you
break through into a new level
of consciousness, you often get
fragmented. You can't maintain
coherence because you're in a
totally different cognitive
reality. But if you go back with
clear focus and intent and clear
setting isolation, clear
setting, you go back again and
again your cog. You learn to be
aware in levels of consciousness
that, in the beginning, just
swallowed you. You learn, I
learned how to stay conscious in
deep time. And this is something
which happened again and again,
when I would break through to a
deeper level of consciousness,
there was often a fragmented
quality. I couldn't remember. I
could only get details that hold
on to details. But over time,
those details began to coalesce.
They began to become complete
patterns of understanding
reincarnation was this whole
inside of my life from beginning
to end was all kind of saturated
with insights of karma and the
intentionality, the deeper
intentionality that binds us
into the world of time and
space. I wrote life cycles, not
mentioning psychedelic work, but
my first book, life cycles is
about reincarnation and the web
of life. For me, reincarnation
is just a fundamental axiom. If
you don't understand
reincarnation, then you just
don't understand what the hell
is going on in this world. You
just have to to see the deeper
patterns.
Six year break, had two more
children, wrote a book, got
promoted. Six years started
again. Ocean of suffering starts
exactly where it had stopped
before, but now in the ecstatic
portion of the sessions, totally
different world. It started me
completely beyond personal
reality. I was given a series of
seven initiations into the
universe. It was as if it was
not as if it was the creative
intelligence. Some creative
intelligence took me and
basically gave me a course in
cosmology, 101, it just took me
through and gave me a series of
experiences that, ch, that
deepened my understanding of
what's going on in the universe.
Now I name. I give each of my
sessions a name, because I'm
trying to hold all of my
sessions in my mind all at the
same time. So I give them a name
that reflects the pith of the
session, and I actually will
break my sessions into bullet
points as well. So here are the
names of the sessions that were
that I deal with in the chapter,
the initiation into the
universe. The first you and I
creating was an exploration of
the very the co creation of the
universe, the I won't go into
the details. So attempting can't
go into the details. Just the
book, the cosmic tour was just
an extraordinary tour of the
universe. This intelligence that
took me somewhere would show me
things, show me how things were
working. Sometimes I didn't
understand it come back for me,
and everything would get bigger,
and then I would understand, and
it would take me on. It was just
extraordinary journey. Council
of Elders was actually a session
which was teaching me how to
keep my cognition coherent with
respect to levels of reality.
It's really important when you
have a substance that allows you
to break through multiple levels
of reality, you have to train
yourself to keep your experience
coherent with respect to levels
of reality. That was part of a
training exercise. Dying into
oneness was an experience of
just repeatedly dying in deeper
and deeper death, death by
death, deeper into oneness, the
master plan, I'll come back to
healing the collective wound was
basically kind of an orgy of
pain and suffering, and then I
was spun deep into archetypal
reality, and the collective
suffering, the ocean of
suffering, never returned. It
never returned. Now it's not
like the world isn't suffering.
It's not that there isn't pain
in the collective psyche. But my
work with the ocean of suffering
was time limited, and we went on
to another level, and what I
learned later is that you don't
abandon your species when you go
deeper beyond. The ocean of
suffering, or deeper beyond the
pain of the species. You
actually become more useful to
it by in the beginning, you're
sucking pain out of the
collective psyche, but later,
you're pouring grace and joy and
insight into the collective
psyche from higher levels of
consciousness. I have to speed
up. I'm getting the time
signatures here, the greater
reel of archetypal reality. When
I entered archetypal reality, my
identity as a human being began
to fall away from me. I found
out that we have an identity, a
deep, deep, visceral identity,
which is deeper than our
individual egoic identity and to
die as a human being is deeper
than to die as an individual
human being. And if in order to
go into archetypal reality, I
had to literally cease to
function at a cognitive level
that had anything to do with
human cognition, I had to be
willing to give that up in order
to learn how to acclimate into
flows of reality that were
radically, profoundly beyond not
only my individual existence,
but beyond human existence. I
moved outside the human field
two levels of archetype of
reality, one high, platonic
level, where I experience
something like what Plato is
pointing to, except that Plato
describes archetypes as eternal
forms in the mind of an
unchanging God. That's not how I
experience them. I experience
them as vast, living, massive
beings that were just so
overwhelmingly I could not wrap
my mind around them. They're
just totally beyond my capacity
to comprehend. I could touch
them experience pieces, but they
just were far, far too large at
a lower level of archetypal
reality, at a lower subtle
level, entering deep into the
collective unconscious of
humanity, deep into the species
mind, experiencing patterns
that, experiencing the human
species as a single being, and
experience networks of
intelligence weaving together
our individual efforts, our
individual minds, our individual
karma into larger patterns,
which were how the species as a
whole lived and breathed. I
think I was being given a crash
course on how our species works
as a single organism in order to
prepare the way for what came
next. I at archetypal reality.
Here are the sessions that I
address,
and notice how much cleansing is
taking place at this level. The
28th session was an
extraordinarily positive
session. It was of my first
contact with causal level
reality, tremendous ordeal, but
then spinning out into causal
level reality, incredibly
beautiful, clear, gorgeous
experience. The next three
sessions were just grueling
Ordeals of purification. They
went on for hours and hours and
hours and lasted three sessions
over six months. What I came to
understand eventually is that
deeper states of consciousness
are higher states of energy.
When you shift into a deeper
state of consciousness, you are
entering a higher level of
energy, and you have to
acclimate to that energy, and
that takes time and work. You
have to go through a series of
purification processes,
cleansing processes, and it's
hard to describe, because
they're not personal
purification processes. You
literally have to purify
whatever you are at the time in
order to stabilize consciousness
at these deeper levels of
reality. And this repeats itself
over and over again, so much so
that I came to dread the session
after a breakthrough session
when I have a breakthrough the
next session was usually a
turgid carrying out the garbage
kind of quality, right? But you
go through that, you go clean it
up, clean it up until you can
come back into that level of
consciousness and maintain
coherent cognition at that level
of consciousness, I began to
have experiences of
reincarnation as a collective
process, I began to experience
the human species as a single
organism that was growing itself
evolving itself by incarnating
all billions and billions of its
precious beings simultaneously.
Exactly, I began to understand
certain patterns of
reincarnation as an evolutionary
driver, not just as I had always
thought of the reincarnation as
an individual story, the
individuals, person grows,
matures, makes individual
choices, hopefully good choices.
But here I began to experience
reincarnation as an evolutionary
driver, an evolutionary dynamic
that operated at the collective
level simultaneously with the
personal level. And at that
point, the wall between personal
karma and collective karma came
down completely, and I realized
that there is no such thing as
private personal karma, personal
karma and collective karma are
all deeply intertwined. And I
wrote dark night, early dawn, in
order to answer the question,
Why did my suffering go as deep
and as long as it did in my
sessions? And the answer is
because, at this deep level of
consciousness, the boundary
between the individual and the
collective becomes very, very
porous, and if you are willing
to, you become an agent of
collective transformation in
this process, hurrying right
along. After a year and a half
and eight session No, a year and
a half and 11 sessions at the
archetypal level, I entered into
a year of extraordinary
blessings. I entered into causal
oneness. It was just non stop
joy. There are four sessions
that I address in the book
describing this, the forest the
birth of the diamond soul.
Singing the universe away in
Jesus' blood, first one is
experience of oneness. Shunyata,
emptiness, no self in me, no
self anywhere in the world.
Singing the universe away was an
experience of entering into the
primal void, what Stan calls the
meta cosmic void, the domain of
the formless, out of which the
light emerges that actually
gives birth to the physical
universe. Jesus's blood was an
experience of extraordinary
cosmic love, just being loved
like I've never been loved
before in this lifetime, the
birth of the diamond soul. Let
me pause just for a second
there, because it's really
important. 11 years before, I
had experienced my life as a
totality, from start to finish.
Now I began to experience where
I began to experience all my
former lives coming together.
They were just coming in fast
and furious, and it was like
wrapping a filament of white
light around a kite spool, and
at a certain point, when they
hit critical mass, and when they
hit critical mass, they fused,
and when they fuse, they
exploded into a diamond light.
It was my first contact with
what I came to call diamond
light, and it was an experience
which was showing me where
reincarnation is taking
humanity, not exactly where, but
how it works. Reincarnation is
not simply making incremental
improvements in our life,
lifetime by lifetime, adding a
layer, adding a layer. It's true
we do, but at a larger level,
sooner or later, if we keep this
process up, we die. We remember
who we are, we're born. We
forget, we learn we die. We
remember we're born. We forget,
we learn, if we keep this up,
lifetime after lifetime, sooner
or later, the soul, the larger
consciousness that holds all of
our lives, wakes up inside time
and space, not just in the
spiritual reality that we return
to when we die, but it wakes up
inside time and space that I
call the birth of the diamond
soul, just to Put a language to
it, other people have spoken
about this. I think it is, in a
sense, spiritual awakening. In
the deepest sense we it is the
emergence in history of a fully
integrated being that is
integrated hundreds of 1000s of
years experience and has now
been jumped into a quantum, a
higher level of awareness and
functional functionality, with
tremendous expansion of
compassion for other human
beings, because we we've had so
many lifetimes of experience
with each other and a profound
transparency To the universal
creative intelligence. It's just
it is a turning point in the
evolutionary story.
I'm being pushed on time and
absolutely right to be So, and
this is the most important
chapter. The Book, the birth of
the future human when I started
this work in 79 I didn't think
much about the future of the
human race. I didn't really
understand much about the ego
crisis we were going into. This
is 1979 and yet this became one
of the most consistent recurring
themes of my work, a series of
visionary experiences that kept
showing me over and over and
over again. Humanity is coming
to a turning point. Humanity is
coming to a profound revision of
its foundation. Humanity is
coming into a time of great
awakening over and over again.
Great Awakening the turning
point of history, a before and
after moment in time. The
visions of awakening is a
collection of six visions that I
pull out of different sessions.
I just group them together in
order to tell the story in a
coherent fashion. But I had not
been shown how the universe was
possibly going to pull this off.
How are we going to make this
transition? And then a year and
a half later, I went into
session 55 the Great Awakening
session, where I was taken deep
into deep time, but not personal
deep time, deep into collective
deep time. And I went into the
future, and I experienced the
death and rebirth of our
species. I wasn't a human being
when I experienced this, I was
the entire I had merged into the
field of the collective psyche,
and I experienced this crisis in
history as the species will
experience it. I experienced a
crisis that brought us to our
knees, a deep and profound
unraveling, a shattering of life
as we had known it, a profound,
frightening time. But out of
this process was born an
extraordinary being, a
transformed humanity, a shift in
the fundamental blueprint of the
human psyche. And this was being
done not at the surface level,
but at the deep level of the
collective unconscious. This is
a shift in the blueprint of our
species. I was also given a
series of initiations into how
this was actually going to be
pulled off, and I don't have
time to go into it, maybe at the
workshop retreat I'll be doing
next week where we talk it has
to do with understanding the
dynamics of the collective
psyche, understanding non linear
systems, understanding how
systems are ch affect our how
systems functions when they're
driven into non linear states.
We have a good understanding of
what happens to physical systems
when they're driven into non
linear states. Well, the human
species is the human unconscious
is a fundamental, unified
psychic field. My sense is that
the great suffering that we are
entering is going to energize is
going to be so widespread and so
long lasting, it will literally
energize the collective psyche
as never before in human
history. And when it is
energized by such terrible
suffering, it will be capable of
transforming itself in an
historically unprecedented
manner, and it will give birth
to the future human. And I
believe that the future human
will be the diamond soul. Our
future is already encoded in our
past. Meaning that nature has
been preparing us for this
event. Has been preparing for us
for hundreds of 1000s of years.
We have been growing. We have
been collecting information,
collecting experiences, going
forward, going deeper. Labor is
a long I mean, birth, excuse me.
Gestation is a long process.
Birth is a relatively fast
process. Reincarnation has been
gestating the future human for
generations after generations
after generation. We are coming
into the time of birth. It's a
hard time, it's a scary time,
it's a Near-Death Experience
kind of time, but it's a
process, I think, which is
giving birth to an extraordinary
creature, just an extraordinary
creature. All right, my time is
used up, so I have to just pop
this very quickly the diamond
Luminosity. You.
Will you give me five minutes of
your break? Okay? When I
finished the greater reel of
arc, when I finished the
benediction of blessings, I felt
completely satisfied. I felt
like I had given something in
the ocean of suffering work, and
I had been rewarded by more than
I could possibly imagine. I felt
completely at peace. I had known
oneness. I had been drenched in
cosmic love. What more could you
ask for? But there was still
five years of work to go, after
going through yet one more very,
very intense death and rebirth
process at a cosmological level,
I was spun into the domain of
absolute, transcendent clarity,
light, light as I had never
known light before, absolutely,
absolutely clear. Just the
Buddhist to write, just touching
it once, just touching it, once
can undo centuries of wandering
around, lost in Samsara,
extraordinary purity, dissolving
into the crystalline body of the
Divine, becoming light, becoming
light, your mind completely
dissolved into the light which
is the primal light before
existence, before physical
existence manifests. The
sessions. There were out of 26
sessions over four years, I
entered this reality only four
times, four times in 26 sessions
in between those four times more
purification, more purgation,
just tremendous cleansing,
cleansing, cleansing, and also
interesting healing, personal
healing, which really surprised
me, because I would have thought
personal healing would have come
sooner, But here I was suddenly
involved in personal healing
after years of working at the
collective level, and it took me
a while to understand why things
were unfolding in this order.
Not time to talk about there.
But there was a logic to it.
There was an intention to it. I
entered into the diamond
Luminosity two times. I went
into deeper and deeper into the
diamond Luminosity. And then the
last two diamond Luminosity
experiences were not about going
deeper into the universe. It was
about the diamond Luminosity
crunching itself deeper and
deeper into my physical body,
crunching itself into my psyche,
into my into my psychological
awareness, but literally going
right into my physical body and
changing the physiological
structure of my cells. That's
what it felt nice. And the pivot
came in the middle when I was in
the 50th session, and extremely,
the deepest I ever went anywhere
in the universe. So I was in
this blissed out, incredibly
beautiful place, and all of a
sudden, everything pivoted 90
degrees, and I saw a reality
that was extremely far in the
distance. I saw whole worlds in
the far distance, and a light
hit me from that reality. I call
it the absolute light, just to
differentiate it to it
something, it hit me, and it
absolutely shattered me. And
that's when I understood, this
is an endless journey. I had
thought I had picked up the
idea. I had believed that this
journey, you do it to get
somewhere, to get there, as an
end point to the journey you get
home and it's either oneness
with God or entering in the
primal void. But there's a
point. There's an end point. At
this session, I let go of that
idea, and I realized it's an
endless journey. The Infinite is
much, much larger than any of
our spiritual traditions have
ever been able to grapple with,
yet it is an infinite process,
and that's why I would be much
gentler with myself if I were
doing this work again.
I've learned that the process is
not to try to get to the end of
the end of the line. The process
is simply open up, let as much
of the creative intelligence of
the universe into you as you
possibly can. Let it transform
you, let it break your heart and
open your heart, and then be
patient with the slower pace of
our organic transformation. The
last the final vision gave me
one last vision, the final
capstone of the entire 70 of 20
year journey. It gave it was the
capstone of the birth of the
future human. It took me deep
the it. It was, put me through a
terrible strip down, took me
deeper into the time than I had
ever been taken before. And it
gave me an intimate experience
of the future human. It gave me
several different lessons, and
it gave me an experience of the
universe as a diamond maker. I
experienced a swamp, a very dark
kind of mud which is represented
the top soil of reincarnation,
where everything, all individual
life forms, were dissolving,
reconstituting, dissolving,
reincarnating, dissolving,
reincarnating. And then there,
there were these sparks of
bright light shooting off into
the universe. These were diamond
souls. These are fully
integrated souls moving into the
universe, centers of integration
capable of integrating more and
more levels of consciousness
that the ego could alone could
never integrate. The universe is
a diamond maker. The universe is
growing sparks of diamond
Luminosity, and it makes no
difference to it or makes it
makes a difference, but it makes
no difference whether it takes a
million years or a million years
for this process to come to
fruition. It is a very, very
patient process. It has created
the cauldron of creativity, and
it is taking us deep, deep into
places that we can only imagine.
The last session, the last
chapter is coming off the
mountain, which I won't talk
about, but I learned that coming
off the mountain was as hard as
going up the mountain, walking
away from such intimacy with the
divine, walking away from such
profound immersion into the
divine reality, it's hard. Once
you have known the joy of
dissolving into light, time and
space, can begin to feel kind of
dried up, not very interesting.
It took me 10 years to really
get back into time and space, to
be grounded, to be in to be
comfortable being who I am, what
I am, for the remaining years of
my life here, I don't know
whether I would have been able
to make it back fully if it had
not been for the love of my
wife, Christina.
Thank you for letting me share
this joy, this story, with you.
It's a joy to bring it to this
particular community. We're
going to be doing the workshop
Friday, Saturday, which I hope
we'll have more time to go into
it. And one of the things I want
to experiment with is, can we
use guided visualization to open
these places which are
universal, they lie in all of
everybody's hearts and
everybody's experience, in
addition to having a
conversation about psychedelics
and protocols and methodology
and the different experiences
that different people have
gotten into, in addition to
that, we're going to explore
using guided imagery and deep
relaxation to sort of activate
some of these deep places inside
that live inside each of our
hearts. Thank you very much. You
Unknown: you.