James Jesso: You foreign. Hello
everyone. Welcome to Adventures
through the mind. I'm your host,
as always, James W Jesso, this
podcast explores topics relevant
and related to psychedelic
culture, medicine and research.
And I'm going to start this one
off with a question. Have you
ever wondered what 76 high dose
LSD sessions over the course of
20 years might teach a person
about how to make sense
spiritually of a global crisis
and perhaps the collapse of
civilization as we know it.
Well, if you wondered about
that, you're in luck for this
episode, because that's exactly
what we're going to talk about.
We're talking with Christopher
Bache, the author of this book,
LSD and the mind of the
universe. Christopher M Bache is
a professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he has
taught for 33 years, a fellow at
the Institute of Noetic
Sciences. He is also adjunct
faculty at the California
Institute of integral studies
and on the advisory board for
Grof Transpersonal training and
the Grof Foundation, an award
winning teacher and
international speaker. He is the
author of three books, and he's
been on the show previously, oh,
I forgot to get the number of
that episode one second, Episode
89 mapping consciousness with
high dose LSD, where we talked
about, essentially what this was
all about. His, his 70, excuse
me, 73 high dose LSD journeys
over 20 years, and what he
experienced and what he learned
about the nature of reality and
the nature of the universe
throughout the course of it. Now
this is sort of a follow up from
that, from that interview, and
it was intended to be, as you'll
hear in the beginning, a
discussion of various different
themes of the book, but pretty
quickly, it focused on a
particular aspect of the book,
which is that while Chris was
having experiences of deep time,
which is sort of like you can
imagine experiencing the entire
course of The human existence as
a singular moment, or the entire
entirety of time and space as a
singular thing, for example,
although he does a better job
explaining it, he had a vision
at one point of what he called
the birth of the future human,
and it coming out of basically
extreme cataclysm, in some sense
or another, a long phase of
extreme strife and grief and
suffering and challenges that
pushes humanity into its next
phase of evolution. And Chris
considers where we're at now to
sort of be the start of that. So
what initially was going to be
me just taking quotes out of
this incredible book, turned out
to be a discussion with with
Chris about the crazy situation
we seem to be in as a planet
right now, and what, from his
perspective, is a is the sort of
spiritual meaning of it, or how
we might approach it
spiritually. And yeah, so that's
what we talk about now. This
interview was actually recorded
in September of 2020, I'm not
entirely sure why it took me so
long. You know what? I'll tell
you why it took me so long to
get it out is because I was in
the interview. I actually was
going through a difficult time,
and at some point it became less
of an interview and more of a
young man pleading to an older
man for some sort of wisdom to
make sense of crisis, make sense
of the challenges personally and
existentially, that I felt like
I was facing in the moment and
still kind of feel like I'm
facing, and maybe I was a little
embarrassed about that. I don't
know. But either way, now is the
time that it's coming out, and
some of you might seem to see
some similarities in some of the
topics to some recent
controversies in the five Meo
DMT world. But none of this is a
response to that. This is was
actually recorded. What is it
now? April, so like more than
six, more than six months ago.
So yeah, that's for context.
It's happening. This was
recorded September 2020, another
point of process about it is
that Chris's sound is not always
super great. There's some
banging, some knocking in the
background. Did my best to clean
it up, removed a lot of stuff
that you won't hear, but bear
with it a little bit. In fact,
there's one point where he's
saying something super
meaningful, and it is like some
loud thing comes in the
background that's so distracting
at this moment. That feels like
just such a like a pinnacle of,
like the value of what he's
offering. It just like, it's
just an interesting sort of,
like reality dance moment. But
anyway, so that's those. Those
are the caveats, and that's,
that's the interview we got
today with Christopher Bache
before we get into it. I want to
give a big thanks to my Patrons
on Patreon, without whom this
podcast would not exist. So
thank you. The people whose
names are listed on the screen
here on YouTube have been giving
significantly some of which for
a long time, their names are
also in the show notes to this
episode, wherever you're
catching it. So thank you so
much, patrons. And if you're not
yet a patron, please become one
by heading to patreon.com
forward slash James every Jesso,
James W gesso, or you can give a
one time donation through Paypal
or cryptocurrency. Listed links
that are listed in the
description to this episode. So
thanks so much for helping
support the show financially,
and not not only just for me and
for you, but also when people
donate, it allows other people
who are enjoying the show, who
don't donate in order to enjoy
the show for free. Because it's
free no matter what this is,
sort of like, on good faith, I'm
producing it for free, and if
you like it, toss me some money,
and I'll keep making it
regardless, you know or well, as
best I can. Okay, so that's all.
That's all for this intro. Stay
tuned to the end. I got a
special announcement, but here
we go. But here we go. This is
my interview, my second
interview with Christopher Bache
here on adventures through the
mind. Enjoy. So Chris, I had
been, I had been going through.
I had been going through, like,
the extensive amount of notes I
have, like, I'd listen to our
first podcast again, and I went
back through the notes I took
when I was in your workshop in
Vancouver, and also was going
through the book. And I just, I
kept wondering to myself, like,
what, what's the course here, I
felt like, in our first in our
first interview, I had the
ability to to have listened to
your talks and had paid
attention to the way that you
structure your lectures, and
then sort of utilize that as the
LE, as the, as the, sort of like
as the path to walk, having a
sense of how you start, what you
talk about, and where you go,
and then sort of use that as the
way. And I didn't have that this
time, and so, and if you're okay
with it, I thought we might be
interesting, because I have your
book here, and as you can see,
I've had, I've had quite a
Unknown: time book, yeah. Author
loves to see it, yeah? Very
Yeah. I moved, I moved
James Jesso: on to little tabs,
because I was like, Well, you
know what? As much as, as much
as most like authors like, oh
yeah, write in it, fold up the
pages, whatever works. I just
kind of grew out of wanting to
destroy the paper that holds the
book. Yeah? So I thought maybe
it would be fun, if you're open
to it, that I would just go into
some of the things that I've
felt really moved by or relevant
in your book, read the piece,
and then be like, What is this?
And have you sort of like, speak
to that. Would that feel cool
for you?
Chris Bache: Sure that's fine,
great. And I'll tell you too
that now that came out, books
out, first round of interviews
and all that stuff covid hit,
stepping back digesting people's
first reactions, I don't think I
sent you a copy of an article
that I just sent to Cy MedNet In
unit in England, basically, I'm
calling it a post script to LSD.
In the mind of the universe,
it's responding to people's
first takes on the book, first
round of experiences. But in
that process, I'm finding that
there is a whole nother tier of
the implications of these
potentials, which I just feel
like I'm beginning to want to
get into. It's like nothing new.
And at the same time, the sheer
the sheer audacity of the claims
concerning the limits and the
revised limits of human
experience, what we're capable
of, and the import of entering
such deep intimacy with the
consciousness of the universe.
It's all just sinking into me at
a new level. So that's a
constant conversation. I'm
really glad to be doing this
second bite at the apple,
something different, and there's
been a whole lot of first
interviews. And I'm glad to see
I'm glad to spend this time with
you, and happy to see where we
James Jesso: go. I. Cool is
that, is that something that you
feel because I'm I'm ready and
willing to adapt? Is that
something that you feel like
you'd like to get into? Or is it
something where, if I pick a
section of the book, it can work
as a reference point, even for
your sort of like the second
tier of your considerations on
the impact of the book?
Chris Bache: Yeah, let's do I
trust it'll it'll come up where
it's relevant in our discussion.
Yeah, because it floats in the
back and it's not like a
specific set of themes, it's,
it's
portly, partly, it's the
enormity of the vision of
history that's involved, and it
seems like we're getting into
that episode, a period of
history faster than I thought we
were going to be getting into
it. And partly, it's simply the
sheer scale of the of the
undertaking, but it'll come up
when, as it comes up, it'll flow
as it comes up in our
discussion. I trust our
discussion.
James Jesso: Well, I mean, I
think it's right here, right
now, because this is something
that definitely came up for me
as I was reading near the end of
the book. Because I read it, I
read it this year. I read it
during the 2020, pandemic
lockdown. You know, it was one
of the things I was I was
immersing myself in while I was
locked away from the world.
Really no different than I would
have been otherwise, except I
didn't have social events to
unfurl into, you know, at the
end of the day and on the
weekends. Oh, not to mention all
the existential, you know, like
gravity of it all. But one of
the things is, you get to a
point where you, you, you're
talking about this, sort of,
like, this, I'm not using your
terminology here, or maybe I
accidentally am, because I
forget what it was. But
something about, like, basically
being this rock tumbler, and
that this, this future human, is
going to emerge out of, like
deep strife and struggle and
pain and yeah, these sort of
like this, look at what will
become history as being an
event, Not too similar,
something analogous, analogous
to the cleansing process of your
psychedelic explorations, and
strictly So, yeah, and so, as I
was reading it, I was like, Man,
I kind of feel like, I kind of
feel like, on one level, I'd be,
I might be foolish to think
we're already there despite how
bad this is. This is nothing,
you know. This is ultimately
just a virus, right? And just,
yeah, yeah, but, but how do you
feel about it?
Chris Bache: I think of it as an
overture. It contains some of
the key elements of the symphony
that's coming, but only in
short, abbreviated forms. It's
mobilizing us. I think what's
coming is going to be much, much
worse, but if we learn this is
sort of disoriented us a lot,
and it's given us a lot of
lessons, and hopefully it's
giving us learnings, teachings
that will help us in what comes
next. But you're right, this is
just this is just act one, just
an overture.
James Jesso: Yeah, stress test
is how I heard it described
early on, like this. This is a
stress of course, it's it has
evolved well and beyond just the
pandemic, we have sort of the
total dissolution of what was
once thought of as of objective
reality due to the impact of
multiple what I have heard
described as multi level
narrative warfare and the
destruction of deep, considerate
or coherent thinking and dialog
because of social media and how
the news and then the, you know,
all the populism and
nationalism, and also the big
push back against these types of
things as Well, especially black
lives matter and stuff like
that, yeah. But, and at the same
time, it's like, this really is
not nearly as bad as it could
get, or maybe will get, yeah,
Chris Bache: yeah, I think so. I
think you're right. In fact, let
me grab a book to bring it up
here to bill, because I'm
probably going to want to
mention it somewhere in this
process. And I'd like to have
the cover to show you Sure. This
is a book I went to get Dwayne
Elgin's last book, choosing
Earth. It's lifetime, literally
a lifetime, of research going
into it. And he gives he has a
he's a social activist, and a
very detailed decade by decade,
what he thinks is coming. And he
really marshals. He's been
tracking the large scientific
data global health of the planet
people for a long time in. And
he has a he really lays out a
time of increasingly tight
collapse over the next several
decades. He really thinks by
2050 we're going to be more than
halfway into the great collapse.
So I just want to bring it in to
mention it when it comes up.
James Jesso: Yeah, that's, um,
so then what's coming up for me
right now is it, is this
question of, of and I for
listeners, you know, if yes, if
they're hearing and getting your
work for the first is this the
first encounter with you? This
might be all of a sudden, like,
whoa. How are we already on the
deep end here, but this is very
much a continuing conversation
between you and I, and then also
with your work. Yeah, I noticed
what comes up for me is this,
this, this, you know, the
immediate like, what do we do?
What do I do? Kind of like that,
sort of quick to problem solve,
fix, action now forward, rather
than how did we get here? What
does this mean? How did we how
do we come to understand what's
happening prior to even coming
to understand what an action
based solution is? And I'm
curious for you where, where you
see that process of coming to
understand where we are is,
yeah, something akin to, you
know, you're mentioning about,
you know, something about a lot
of lessons here. What do you
think these lessons are? What
are we learning? And, in fact,
perhaps, what does it appear
from where you're sitting that
we're not learning out of all of
this?
Chris Bache: Yeah? Well, I don't
I have to be careful. I'm not on
the front line. I have only
second hand information from the
news accounts. As I watched
people react and respond, we're
learning a number of things. One
of them is we're learning the
fragility of our of our system.
We're learning our
interconnectedness, how systems
that have functioned quietly,
side by side, seemingly
independently, they're not
independent at all. They're
quite interdependent. We're
learning a lot about supply
chains and how our where our
resources come from, and we're
learning that that people who
have very modest jobs, from some
socio economic viewpoint, to
have very important jobs when it
comes to maintaining the health
and well being of our of our
collective so I think we're
learning interdependence. We're
learning our entire life can be
turned upside down much faster
than we thought it could. We
don't have as nearly as much
stability as we think we do. I
think we're learning something
about the limits of patriarchal
ego, and I think Trump is the
embodiment, I hope, of the last
gasp of the patriarchal
monarchy. We're learning how
ugly ego is, just how really,
really ugly it is, and we're
learning a lot about where to go
and where not to go when we come
into crisis. This polarization
is taking place, the resort to
violence, how quickly we move to
violence? And it's like we take
almost any issue, no matter how
trivial, like mass, and turn it
into an issue which leads to
people killing each other. I
mean, it's just the mirror. What
we're seeing in the mirror is
not very complementary. It's
pretty ugly. The way I sort of
see the larger landscape, of
course, is that,
in so many ways, it's ego that
built our culture. And by that,
I mean simply, it's a human
being at a level of spiritual
development which identifies
with their body, has a certain
level of self awareness, but
that self awareness stops pretty
close to the edge of their
fingers and toes, and they still
are looking out rationally,
looking out for their well being
and the well being of a small
number of people near them and
around them who basically look
like them or related to them in
some fundamental way. Ego is a
magnificent thing, a beautiful
thing, an important thing, but a
world built by a species that's
operating out of egoic awareness
is a divided world. It's a world
of haves and have nots, and we
can't get more extreme in the
presentation to ourselves, and
then the haves and have nots in
Dwayne's book, I came across the
statistic that five people own
as much of the world's resources
as. Half of the world, five
people have half of the world's
resources. You just can't have
that big a disparity of haves
and have nots. And it's just
being this illness is just
blasting this into our faces.
Who's suffering the most and
who's suffering the most are the
poor in persons of color. So a
lot going on, but this is just
warm up. This is just the first
wave. I think, I think maybe the
first wave might have been
actually the credit crisis of
2008 because that taught us some
things, and it also sucked a lot
of liquidity out of the system.
We have much less, much fewer
financial resources to fight
with than we did before. And now
this is getting deeper. You
know, national debt increases,
but certainly we are, if not in
the first round, we certainly
are in a significant second
round.
James Jesso: I mean, for for
listeners again, who don't know
like it wouldn't appear as
though this conversation is
couched in your 20 year journey,
your 40 year journey as a
philosophy professor, and a 20
year journey with high dose LSD
sessions, and the book that were
we were referring to earlier is
your book on those journeys, as
well as a number of other books.
And I'm just curious, because
what I'm seeing in the world,
which is mostly the world that
is mediated by a screen at this
point is not the kind of place I
really want to be both in. I
don't both in the sense of, I
don't want to be where it
appears we're going. I don't
want to be a part of a system
that does the things that it
does, you know, like the I don't
I don't like the fact that I'm a
part of this disgusting,
distorted thing, and also what I
see from the behavior of the
people around me. And there's a
lot to be said about how social
media algorithms and and
isolation and mental health
crises, acknowledged or not, are
contributing to this, but I see
a lot of toxic behavior, a lot
of toxic people, a lot of toxic
discussion, sort of, like,
draped in this sort of, like,
this sort of self confidence,
self righteous, almost
Machiavellian style, like
moralism, of like, the good
versus the evil, and the good is
me, And anyone that disagrees is
like the violent devil I must
cast out and and whatever else.
And I don't feel good about what
I'm seeing about the world, and
it makes me want to just like,
hide away inside now, yeah, that
said couching this in
psychedelics and looking at it
as as a large psychedelic I'm
using air quotes for listeners
process that's happening
collectively on a global scale,
not just with humanity, but
we're although we don't know
what the feelings and the
thoughts or perspectives are the
birds and the salamanders and
the and the whales and whatever.
You know they're going through
that with us. So it's like a
planet. It's like a planetary
experience, right? Yeah, that
when I see these parts of myself
in a psychedelic session, it's
no more comfortable by any
means. It's equally as ugly,
yeah, you know? And I want to
hide away from that too. And
yet, yeah, one of the things you
talk about in your book is that
you we need to learn as a part
of the psychedelic journey. We
need to learn how to not turn
away from our pain, or from that
pain, I mean, like the pain of
touching a hot fire we turn away
from, but this kind of pain that
we learn to turn towards it. And
I'm wondering if you could just
that's not a clear question, but
can you just comment on Yeah,
yeah.
Chris Bache: You know, the
starting point of serious
psychedelic work is taking
complete responsibility for
one's own shadow and and you
just go into a room, close the
door, lock the door. You're
inside by yourself, nothing
there but you and your mind. And
you go into the parts of your
being which are at least
initially, the most daunting,
the most intimidating, the most
frightening, the ugliest ones we
like to acknowledge, the least
you know, and but the commitment
is there to take that on, to
enter into it, when we see that
ugliness being manifested in the
world around us by people who
are not have not yet taken
responsibility for themselves,
and they are still. In this
exterior mode, where the shadow
was really outside of them, the
evil and the darkness and the
really ugly things were outside
of them. That's a very different
world, isn't it? And I think
this whole process of breaking
down, this breaking down process
that we're going into is
basically going to be breaking
down that defense that we have
to thinking that, you know,
we're the good guys or and the
other people are the bad guys.
And eventually we're going to
have to come to terms with the
fact that weird. We did this. We
created this imbalance. We have
benefited from it. We are
continuing to generate it in the
cars we drive, in the lives we
live and the lifestyles we
aspire to. We have done this. We
will we have done it. There's
going to come a time eventually
where there's no place else to
look but we have to take
individual and collective
responsibility for the pain that
is that is alive within us and
lives of everyone around us.
That really is a pivot point, I
think, when we just stop blaming
the other, stop blaming previous
generations. Stop blaming so on
so forth. We really settle in.
We're not there yet. Some of us
are there yet. I mean, I think
the psychedelic community
understands these things,
because that's how you make
progress in psychedelic work, is
you confront the shadow. Now,
when you go into the work, you
know that the more you purify,
the more you cleanse, the deeper
the reward, the deeper the
ecstasy, the deeper the
teaching. So the more you
purify, the deeper the
communion. Once you learn that
not only do you become more
comfortable facing the shadow,
but you actually actively
embrace the shadow. You active,
actively embrace pain and
suffering, not because you like
pain and suffering, but for two
reasons. One is because you
learned that the deeper the
purification, the deeper the
ecstasy. And you don't like to
suffer, but you like what's on
the other side of the suffering.
But the second thing is, you
embrace the pain and suffering,
even knowing that a lot of it is
not yours, because out of the
same compassion that every
father has for His children,
every mother has for her
children, and every teacher has
for all of their children
eventually that everybody has
for other people. And you
embrace the pain, not counting
whether it's yours or somebody
else's, but because by doing so,
you are helping somebody. You
are helping other beings that
you may never meet. And my
experiences has been that if you
do that, if you are willing to
take on more than your fair
share of suffering, you reap
more than your share of benefit.
You the universe responds. It
can't help but respond. And I
think that's going to be
happening with us,
generationally, this generation,
the next generation, the
generation after that, is going
to go through suffering, more
than their share of suffering
compared to previous
generations. And after they stop
kicking and screaming and begin
to get down to taking it on and
just doing it, I think they will
experience the blessings that
come from that deep generosity,
that that profound existential
choice to work with the given,
even when the given is terrible,
even when it kind of crushes
your personal life, but you
Still dedicate yourself to the
good of the whole. And in that
process, something begins to
change. Something shifts inside
your person, and the more
complete the surrender to the
process, the more complete the
commitment to that process, I
think the deeper and the faster
the transformation is in our
individual lives and our
collective lives, so that as we
move deeper into this and come
through it, I think
generationally, we will learn
what every psychedelic journeyer
learns, that we confront the
shadow there is Riches on the
other side of this ordeal, and
there's no other way to get to
it. And in the end, you the
irony is, you kind of end up
where you were in the beginning,
except you're all cleaned out.
You're just all sorts of this
gunk is out of your system. So
you are you, and you are where
you were before. Or but you
literally are living a different
life because stuff that you
hadn't realized was compromising
you and burdening you is no
longer there, and something new
has taken its place. I think
that's where we're going to be
going. It's going to take time.
James Jesso: There's a lot that
has kind of come up there for
me, as you were talking around
like the the complexity of the
situation and how each different
person and demographic is coming
at this differently, you know.
And then the confusion of what
is good or what is not, you
know, and then the kind of
getting into, you know, like, oh
yes, I'm gonna put myself in the
pain of this, you know, does
that look like being around
people? Like, does that mean
getting involved in places
where, you know, I'm interacting
with toxic people, you know,
there's, there's all these weird
sort of complications. And as
I'm listening, I'm I'm I'm
efforting to hear it from a
larger perspective than what's
happening right now, you know,
because if I think about
generations that suffer, I'd say
that right now, my demographic,
even my local community, you
know, is not suffering nearly as
much as people in the hardest
hit areas of the United States
with covid and not nearly as
much as people who are in
poverty or who are, you know,
are oppressed by systemic racism
or sexism or whatever it is. You
know, especially, of course,
systemic racism is a huge and
important issue, and very like
strong right now issues of
police violence and all the
rest. Yeah, but even then, it's
like, is, is that I'm just like,
trying to, trying to break out
of the thinking that wants to
immediately point to small
examples that don't fit into the
larger generational narrative.
And I'm wondering if there's, if
there's something there that you
want to comment on about, about
how the what you just said
applies to the acute as much as
the bigger picture. Yeah, you're
Chris Bache: certainly right. I
mean, in my local community,
we're not suffering, not badly,
and I'm retired and I'm the
hive, and lost my job, I don't I
know where my next meal is
coming from. And a lot of people
that's not true. And then if we
just expand the horizon, the the
hundreds of 1000s of people who
are migrants, who are
ecological, migrants who are
fleeing disastrous
circumstances, people whose
whole lives fit inside a bag, a
suitcase that they're carrying
everything they value in the
world. I mean, it's just the
upheaval. We don't have to go
very far to find it, but even if
it is far from our local
community, I live in a strange
world in that way. I mean, we
all watch television. We all try
to keep abreast of the larger
patterns that are out there. But
inwardly, because of the
psychedelic work, because I've
been dissolved so many times
over so many years into the
collective breath of humanity,
and because I've been drawn into
the collective Shadow Work, The
Dark Night of the collective
soul work, and have gone far
beyond The collective psyche
outside, as outside of the
Collective Unconscious into
larger patterns of time, deep
time, evolutionary time, which
you might think of as geologic
time. My insides are tuned a
little differently because I
sort of on a smaller scale, when
I see human beings, I don't see
human beings the way other
people tend to see human beings.
I see souls. I relate to human
beings as incarnations of souls.
And so I'm always tuning to the
soul quality of a person. And in
that respect, for example, we
can see young people who are
truly old in their heart and
mind, and we can see old people
who are like children in their
hearts and minds and everything
in between. So when I think of
the people and what we're seeing
on the streets and the people
riding around and pick up trucks
with carrying weapons, and I'm
seeing souls that are in a long
they're in one phase of a long
evolutionary journey at the
souls progression. And I have a
sense of some approximate sense
of the large scale of the self
education. Education, self,
maturational process, and some
of the stage points along that
that scale, and I don't bring
that as a model that allows me
to judge people and rank people
and classify people, but I
approach people. I approach
people knowing that their entire
current incarnation is just a
short phase of their larger
learning process, and so I
understand the challenges that
they're facing within this
larger context, within this
larger matrix. The tricky part
is you can get so absorbed into
large perspectives like that
that you can lose the immediate,
immediate suffering. You can
lose sight of what it actually
feels like to be undergoing the
privations right here, right
now, of many people. So you have
to live in both morals at the
same time. Yeah, at hand and the
large scale, my professional
work and my psychedelic work has
focused me on the large scale.
James Jesso: Chris, I
unexpectedly really have to pee.
I'm just going to take a take a
little me, and I'll be right
back.
Unknown: Okay, okay, wow, okay,
so free all of a sudden, much
better.
James Jesso: Yeah. So there's a
lot of inner conflict that's
coming up for me as a as I'm
listening to you, that part of
me is like, yes, and another
part of me is like,
does this like? It's the smaller
wind. It's the smaller frame of
like. But does saying it this
way? Does that? Does that equate
to passivity? Does that equate
to, you know? Like, you know, if
this is all a part of a larger
process, is me just looking at
myself, you know, like, is that
actually doing anything? I know,
if I look at a large picture,
yes, of course, it's doing
something. You know, I'm
whatever, helping to evolve and
churn my soul. And by doing good
as best I can, I help sort of
bring goodness into reality
more. And then it can be sort of
like in engaged in other
people's realities or whatever
else. So on the on the one
level, I'm like, Yes, but on
another level, like, is that
really enough? There's a lot of
sort of psychedelic rhetoric
around, like, if we just gave
more people Psilocybin, then
we'd stop burning down the
rainforest, you know, if we, or
say, Ayahuasca, then we stop
burning down rainforest. We give
people enough Psilocybin, you
know, then we'll, we won't vote
in authoritarian leaders, right?
Yeah. But I think that that that
type of thinking, on some level,
feels really, it feels really
foolish, you know, to think that
if I just do the work that's
going to make big changes in the
world, that that's going to
properly address things, and
yet, there's this whole other
layer, which is like, but can I,
Can I really do any good as a
part of a social movement if I'm
showing up with hatred in my
heart and anger and just and
projection and just looking for
someone to blame for my
suffering, you know? And some
people are showing up because of
that, some, not all. Obviously,
I don't think the movements are
inspired by this. I think
they're inspired by a very
appropriate response to
injustice. Yeah? And then a
whole other layer of me is like,
Oh, if I say this wrong, will I
be canceled because of that sort
of like, yeah, Blamey
hatefulness in the heart. So
again, these aren't clear
questions. I almost like, I feel
like I'm just like, baring my
soul to you, Chris, like, Help
me understand.
Chris Bache: I understand. I
really do. Because if your
spirituality, if your genuine
spirituality, leads you away
from social engagement in the
world, then I don't think it's a
very mature spirituality,
because mature spirituality
leads to that place in the heart
where we contact the heart of
all living things. And when we
contact the heart of all living
things, naturally, we want to
help all living things. And so
the natural progression of deep
spiritual work, when it succeeds
is to be socially engaged in
some form or another, whatever
we feel particularly called to
some people are called to
medicine. They're going to do it
in medicine. Some people are
doing it with high tech, online,
international discussions. Some
people they're doing it in all
sorts of different ways. But.
The important thing is that we
find what it is that feels like
our niche, our particular
contribution to make, and we do
it. And you're right, if we do
it, when we do it, we'll
probably end up finding that
maybe we aren't as clean as we
thought we were going in. Okay,
so we step back, we clean, we
work that part. But yeah, I
understand the tension it I
would feel it more if I were a
young man like you. I'm older,
and I'm in my 70s, so in some
ways, I've had I've made my
decisions around those things.
I've made my choices, and mostly
I'm past that active time.
Except as a teacher, you know, I
write, I teach, I talk, I do
what I can. But other people my
age, they're on there, on the
front lines, they're much more
active on the front lines. They
really are plowing those fields.
They really they are getting the
vote out. They are working very
tangibly and practically to
bring about a better world.
No standardized rules for the
engagement, but we can feel when
there's a feeling in our center,
when we are aligned with our
place in the world and our place
in the movement. We've got a
balance point between inner and
outer, sheltered and exposed,
and so we're self correcting
that we're self correcting
beings. And what's most
important, I think, is not rules
of inner outer, or how to engage
and how, what, what not, what
not, but tuning into that point
in our center, which is our
connecting point to the larger
intelligence, which is always
trying to draw us towards deeper
and deeper levels of engagement
with itself, and that means with
the fabric of humanity and or
non human life forms, as you
Say, that are also being
affected a million species going
extinct, you know, as we stand
here, as we sit here, yeah,
James Jesso: I've been, I've
been sitting with the, you know,
we're, we were going to open up
your book, and maybe at some
point we will. I have been
sitting with the first thing I
wanted to open the book to the
first, the first part of the
book that received a red tab,
which was particularly important
for quoting or reference,
as I have coordinated the color
coding here and wondering How
much it applies
in the sort of like the the
comparing between a deep
psychedelic work or deep
psychedelic journey, and the
journey that we're on right now
as a as an entire planetary
organism facing the the
Increasing layers of collapse
and catastrophe and crisis that
is just funneling more and more
out of the year of clear vision.
And the part is about one of the
greatest risks of psychedelic
work, as you have put in the
book, being ego inflation. And
I'm curious looking around at
the world, that both people in
the psychedelic community, so
maybe it's a real micro scale of
like this is happening in psi
culture, you know, and then the
larger scale of like this is
what's this is what I'm seeing
play out in the in the big
characters, like the big
characters, like the
representations in the media and
so on and so forth. Yeah, I'm
just curious about your comments
on that.
Unknown: Well,
Chris Bache: you know, I'm
essentially a hermit, and even
though I am a member of the
psychedelic community, because
I'm involved in psychedelics and
thinking about them, and I don't
really have a lot of living
contact with the psychedelic
community. You know, you go to
conferences. You know, used to
go to conferences. You have
workshops here and there. You
teach here and there. But the
actual number of people from
this large community is
relatively small. You get
impressions from the books. But
again, since I'm older, I'm not
keeping track with all the
latest articles. I really will
just pay attention more to the
important books that come out,
not the small stuff. And so I
don't know really what's
happening in the psychedelic
community. E S, so I can't
generalize about that. I think
that in some ways, we're moving
into a psychedelic period of
history, and it may be starting
at low dose psychedelic history,
but we're going to be moving
into high dose psychedelic
history when there will in low
dose work, you may engage
voluntarily. You know the ego
dissolution process. In high
dose work, you will be engaged
whether you volunteer or not.
You will be go put through the
meat grinder. And I think we're
coming into a period of history
where right now we may choose
how to engage or how to pick the
pain, particular pain that we're
going to take on. There's going
to come a time. It's going to be
the Charles choices are going to
be made for us. We're going to
be surrounded by catastrophic
consequences of the historical
policies that we set in motion
for decades and hundreds of
years. So it's going to be, it's
truly like a hurricane coming
off shore. I mean, this is like
everybody's going to be
affected. Everybody's going to
be touched. It's not going to be
a pick and choose situation.
Unknown: So
Chris Bache: I think that the
great danger of psychic work is
of psychedelic work is psychic
inflation. That is, we think we
have we've had a deep
experience. We think we've
become a deep person. We've had
a great experience. We think
we've become a we are a great
being. And that, of course, is a
fool's delusion. Whether the
psychedelic community is in that
position, I don't know, because
I think you know, if you do have
that attitude, then your own
psychedelic sessions are going
to knock your feet out from
under you harder. It's going to
take you down. So you learn
pretty quickly that that's a
that's a dead end street to go
and it becomes much, much more
basic than that. And it's not
about having extraordinary
experiences. To me, it's not
about, I mean, it's not about
having ecstatic experiences or
having to me, it's about doing
whatever is necessary so that 48
hours after your session is
over, you're living a better
life than you did beforehand. So
you're either you spend your
psychedelic session, either
taking a vacation to Italy, or
you spend it carrying out the
garbage. Carrying out the
garbage is what's going to give
you a better life two days after
your session is over, and if you
carry out the garbage, well,
then you're going to see some
extraordinary things on the
other side. So for me, the real
work is carrying out the
garbage, that's I mean. And so
why would you ever want to
become more conscious than we
already are? If the consequence
of being more cost conscious is
to take more responsibility for
the garbage that you are part
of, it's in your system and it's
immediately around you. So when
you become more conscious,
you're going to have to do more
cleaning. So for some, I know
that other people don't
necessarily feel that way. For
them, psychedelics are a way to,
you know, access joy. And you
know, you access great joy,
great things, but when you come
by those great joyful
experiences of communion or
great cosmic insights that flow
into you when you come by them
through hard work, then I don't
think it then tends to lead to
psychic inflation so much
because you know the price
you've paid to receive these
blessings. You you understand
the deeper process, and that the
intelligence that gave you the
blessings is teaching you is,
you know, taking you along, step
by step. And so you these
blessings are not given out
lightly, but they're given out
intentionally. And if your if
your psychedelic work is is
really disciplined, and it's
really part of a spiritual
practice for you, then
everything that you're given is
also laying the foundation for
work that you're going to do and
gifts you will be given later,
because your entire relationship
with the universe is one of the
maturational development, and
once you kind of feel the rhythm
of this maturational development
over the course of years. Years
in your work, then that just
puts aside, it draws to a close,
all this sort of psychic
inflation bullshit. Because it
you know that that's just ego
dancing, and ego
Unknown: is the obstacle,
James Jesso: the the question
that's kind of like me, we've
kind of done this interesting,
sort of, like dance and quasi
pivot, you know, from these,
like, big, sort of global
crises, acute issues that we're
in right now and then, sort of
like, sort of like a larger
cosmological perspective of the
transformation of the human soul
over millennia, ultimately, and
that possibly we're in the we're
in the beginning of this great,
painful, suffering churning that
will eventually Polish us up on
the other side to becoming What
in the book you call the future
human, and now we're sort of,
like, back into that, kind of,
like, we've pivoted into, like,
direct psychedelic work. And I
don't know if this question
feels, I don't know if this
question is, is sort of almost,
um, like, trite in a way,
because it's, so general or
what, but I'm just holding it,
and it feels like I gotta ask
it, which is given where we are,
given what's happening. And
maybe you've already said this,
you've already answered this
somehow, but given where we are
from the perspective of the deep
psychedelic work that you've
done, you know, what does it
mean to be a good person right
now? What is it? What does it
mean to be what does it take,
you know, yeah, man,
Chris Bache: it's a large
question. I
I think of a half dozen ways to
answer that question pop into my
mind, and all of them are wrong,
so I'm kind of sifting through
layers. I
in some of my deepest
experiences, there are moments,
there are times when, and even
after a session, but under the
influence of the learning of a
session, when something just
falls away, something opens
and I experience the world truly
as living and Breathing as one.
I feel like my feet are rooted
in the earth the way a tree is
rooted in the earth. I look down
at the grass, and I feel
complete continuity of being
between everything around me and
my own being. I feel us
breathing the same air. I feel
us all different species sharing
the same moment in time. I feel
the pulse of the universe in its
utter simplicity, not paying
attention to any of our
divisions of species or moods or
incarnations or anything like
that, the entire universe just
being itself, and I am part of
that in grateful it's not even
communion, because communion
implies a subtle duality, and
this is when all of that falls
away and a great transparency of
being opens. From within that
position,
I experience an opening of my
mind, kind of a delicious sense
of presence. It gives me an
intimacy with grass. And then at
a deeper level, I experience an
opening of my heart. Art in
which the idea of harming anyone
is the farthest thing from my
mind, and the idea of helping
everyone is the most natural
thing in the world. It's not
being good, it just it's it's
being alive within this reality
of oneness. So to me, goodness
is simply an approximation, or
it's a, it's a it's a compass
needle that points in the
direction of this fundamental
truth of oneness. And the truth
of oneness is all these
derivatives that flow from it
circumstances. But at essence,
it's very, very simple. And I
think compassion, goodness, in
that way, fairness, justice, are
all aspects of oneness. Are all
kind of fractal manifestations
of oneness. So what does it take
to be a good person today? I
think it takes a willingness, a
commitment, to serving a
collective good to serving a
good that's not private, that
opens up to future generations,
that opens up to people who are
unlike me and species who are
unlike me, just an honest
confrontation with What is in
order to bring about a better
life for other beings. I know
this is very simple, but to me,
goodness is is is simple. It is
that simple. It gets complicated
in the enacting of it, but in
the at its core, it. It's an
action that comes out of
oneness, and if it's not coming
out of a deep grounding in
oneness, then maybe there's
something not to trust in it,
because deep goodness comes out
of oneness. I think. Now I don't
know if this really addresses
the depth out of which your
question is coming, because I
understand
Unknown: the true,
Chris Bache: the true angst, not
angst, but the true kind of
quandary from which that
question comes, but the deepest
answer I have in response to it,
I'm afraid, is just a mystical
experience, a mystical
experience of oneness, in which
that context goodness just
becomes an insignificant
component, a spontaneous
component, just like the way you
react when you see something
beautiful. It's just, it's an
arising. It comes up inside of
you. Goodness is simply an
arising that comes up inside of
you when you're in the condition
of oneness.
James Jesso: I have a, have a,
maybe a more sort of serious
response, and I have a more
joking response. And the more
serious response is along the
lines of, like, what, what does
it what does it look like to
what does the dance look like?
You said, it becomes difficult
in the enactment. You know, what
does the dance look like between
Okay, having that experience?
Because I've had that
experience, and I can tell you
fully 100% honestly, that
anywhere from 10% of the time to
99% of the time, I'm not there
at all. There's no sense of it
whatsoever in my experience, you
know, and I am and I'm not in
the ground of that as I'm as I'm
as I'm showing up in the world.
And I'm wondering, yeah, you
know, in the same way that also
the playful response was, so we
all should all take 500 mics of
LSD, right? No, no, in the what
does it look like to have had
that experience? Because the way
that you speak about it, and I
think naturally, it makes sense,
like when you're there, goodness
just flows from you, right? It
is the most organic and natural
expression of being in the world
is when you're coming from that
place. And yet having a deep and
profound experience doesn't make
you a deep and profound person.
Experiencing oneness doesn't
mean that you now walk through
the world inspired and infused
in all your actions. You know
oneness just streams from your
fingertips, and every
interaction is a blessing with
the world from the depth of the
oneness. I have embodied simply
by taking enough mushrooms to
touch it once. So what does it
look like then? I mean, maybe
this is a question around
integration, yeah, what does it
mean to remember that, and what
is it into to catch ourselves in
forgetting?
Chris Bache: Yeah, that's that
is, you know, we we go up on the
mountain, we see some things, we
may be given some blessings, and
then we come down, and then we
have to go to work on Monday
morning. And that's over and
over again. It means a matter of
constantly engaging, being aware
of how you're engaging, checking
yourself, recommitting yourself
to doing a better job, over and
over and over again. For me,
much of it was in my work as a
teacher you know, constantly,
always enjoying it, always
loving to be with the students,
always wanting to do it better,
but constantly catching myself
making assumptions, making false
inferences, not doing a good
enough job, being a little
tired, letting my students down
on a particular day, coming back
and trying to do better, coming
do better the next day, Do
better, the next week, better
the next semester, over and over
again, trying to live up to the
things that we know to be true.
Integration is a is a strange
term. I'm not sure. I'm glad
that the psychedelic community
is paying more attention to
integration, because it's
really, really critical. But and
there are dimensions and aspects
of integration, and the word
integrate carries us a certain
distance, doesn't, doesn't carry
us so far, but it's it's hard to
live our visions. It's hard to
live the truth of what we've
seen. It because it commits you
to constantly being aware, if
you take the time to remit to
pay attention to yourself, how
bad a job we're doing at living
those truths. But that's just,
that's the nature of the beast,
though we just it's constantly I
mean, if we are, if we live
around people who are really
good, people who really have a
deeper natural instinct for
goodness and kindness and
generosity than we have, then it
makes it easier just to sort of
face our own shortcomings,
because we have someone that we
can look at and say, Ah, that
person doing this better than I
do. So this gives me a measuring
stick. I can do better. I'll do
it better tomorrow. I'll keep
working on it. And that's why,
you know, in the Buddhist
tradition, spiritual friends,
people who are also have
committed themselves to
awakening. That's really one of
the great Sangha community is
one of the great pillars of
progress. So, yeah, you're
right. It's wonderful to have
the experience, but we don't
walk around in that state, but
we practice and practice and
practice, and then maybe 10
years later, we were in a little
bit more. 10 years later, maybe
we're in it a little bit more,
but practice and practice and
practice. And if we ever think
that we're really there, then
all we do is ask our young
children, and they'll remind us
that we're not really there as
far along as we think we are,
our our kids will set us
straight.
James Jesso: Or perhaps, or
perhaps we could, I think it was
a Baba Ram Dass said, If you
ever think you're spiritually
awake and go spend a week at
your parents or something like
that. So maybe it's the other
way around.
Chris Bache: Yes, yes, as
James Jesso: you were speaking,
I it was funny, because a
question started forming, and
then you had said something that
I was like, Oh, great. I can
point to exactly that to ask
this question, which is around,
you know, being around people,
spiritual friends, right? The
question is, partly goes back to
what you said around, like, if
your spiritual practice means
running away from, like, not
engaging in the world, then it's
probably not a very mature
spiritual practice. And I agree
and respect that very much. And
then so there's a balance
between, you know, like being in
these spiritual having spiritual
friends and so on and so forth,
but then not isolating oneselves
and only that experience, but
also engaging in being in the
world right, or being right in
the world of the world, Pardon,
pardon the reference. Yeah,
yeah. But then, right now, it
feels as though, and I think in
many ways, this is because so
much of our social interaction
is mediated by screens and the
info. Of social media
technology, as well as the
influence that, in one way or
another, every interaction we
have is also informed by, is
that person a loaded covid gun
or whatever it is, it's, it's,
it's inspired by this sort of
weird things. We have this
situation where we're not coming
together, right? And so there's
a lot of toxic interaction.
There's a lot of charged
emotional charge, a lot of
embodied emotional energy that's
very tense. You know, there's a
lot of being exposed to how shit
the world actually is, right?
Now. There's a lot of beauty in
the world, of course, but that's
not what we're having shoved
down our down our throats, or
shoved through our eyes and so.
So the actual interactions with
the world, be they screen,
mediated or not, is now in this
landscape of a lot of people,
understandably so, very
contorted by the situation, very
contorted by the context. And
it's in that, you know, in that
contortion, that we generally
aren't operating from oneness,
right? So save for isolating
ourselves and only our little
friend group, that everyone's
spiritual and with the oneness
and yada yada, which ultimately
is serving those people there,
but only to a certain extent,
and not anybody else, and then
being sort of in the world,
trying to be a person of
goodness and oneness, but
encountering a lot of toxicity
and close mindedness and
shunning and and cancel and all
the rest. Like, how does a
person walk this? What does that
walk look like?
Chris Bache: It's good question,
isn't it good question? It's
going to look different for you
than it will for me, and it'll
look different for different
people in different
circumstances.
I mean, I really years ago,
decades ago, my life was as real
as my students. And so wherever
I was on the weekends, however
deep I was on the weekends,
whatever spiritual practice I
was doing at six o'clock on
Monday morning, at 10 o'clock, I
was with my class, and I was
teaching in an open enrollment
University, people who were
first generation college
educated in a burned out steel
town where opportunities were
few and far between, and this
was front line education in
America. And you, you it was
hard work, and we worked hard
together, so I had to be on my
game, engaging the world in my
role as educator, constantly
confronting their assumptions,
encountering the engaging the
biases that they would bring to
the discussions of the topics
that as A professor of religious
studies, I was teaching, and so,
you know, I would laugh at my
friends tease my friends who
were teaching graduate courses,
maybe three graduate courses a
year at their institutions where
I was teaching nine quarter
courses an academic year and
then courses During the summer.
It's really different kind of
world. So if I were answering
your question 15 years ago, when
that was my life, the hermit
quality of my life would be
balanced by my particular slice
of the pie that I was
responsible for, which is
helping these young people come
to deepen an understanding of
the world and of themselves in
the disciplines that I was
teaching. Now I'm in a different
time of my life. Now I am out of
that world. Now I am retired
from that world and so and I
buffer myself from a lot of
screen time. I really don't
engage. I mean, I really like
you say it is so toxic, it is so
confused. I don't think it helps
me to immerse myself in that
toxic confusion. It doesn't help
me maintain the clarity that
it's my responsibility to
maintain in my life, so that
when I do engage people, I can
be useful to people coming out
of the space that I've that I am
most comfortable with or not
most comfortable but I most
appreciate.
Unknown: So
Chris Bache: I don't have to
engage people nearly as much as
you do, and not nearly as much
of people who are going to work
nine to five, they're front line
on the covid scene, and they're
riding a bus, they're riding a
train, and they're having to
make all these. Decisions about
who and what, and what can I
say, and where should I sit, and
how do I breathe, and all those
things. But the principle is
always the same. I mean Teresa.
Mother, Teresa, she worked with
the poorest of the poor. She
started her work by basically
dragging people off the streets
of Calcutta so that they could
die with dignity in some small
place. We engage the world as we
are, as it is, as circumstances
are right now the circumstances
is this pandemic that we are
involved in, and the political
polarization that's being
generated by that pandemic,
people are grabbing that world
from so many different places,
so Many places, that
generalities are hard to come
by, except I come back again to
that sense of inner integrity
that kind of tells us when we
are on and off course with
ourselves, whether we are
aligned with our with our deep
being, Whether we're out of
kilter with our deep being, and
even in my isolation, I have the
feeling of whether I am aligned
with my deep being or whether I
am not aligned with it, in terms
of, Am I living myself my life
in a way that will put me in the
position to be of maximum
benefit when I give this talk in
two weeks, or something like
that, that it's not something
that happens on the day of
presentation. It's a whole. It's
with your life. It's an is in
tuned with your deepest
aspirations and your deepest
truths of what you know and
believe, so that when you are
called upon, you truly have
something to give, which is
yours to give, and that that
that tuning into that center
place takes place whether you're
in the subway or whether you're
at home by yourself. It's just
tartar in the subway.
James Jesso: Yeah, I think, I
think one of the things that's
coming up for me is something
along the lines of, you,
Unknown: what that looks like
for different people,
James Jesso: and what that looks
like for different people looks
like to me from where I'm coming
from, based on where they're
coming from, because there are
people in this world who feel
like they are doing exactly
that, and what they're doing is
putting, you know, taking their
guns out for walks and screaming
At people for wearing masks,
right? Or they feel like they're
doing that thing, but what
they're actually doing is
propagating neo Nazi white
supremacy. Or what they're
actually they think that they're
doing that thing, but what
they're actually doing is
something emotionally violent,
immature and toxic, which is
canceling and anybody who
disagrees with them and feeling
reinforced in the righteousness
of their beliefs by other people
on the internet agreeing with
them and them all bonding by
bullying this person who has a
different opinion from them,
right? And that they feel like
they're doing the good thing
too. And so I want to be able to
say that I know that me not
doing those things is me doing
the good thing, and that my
inclination is to think that
what they're doing is not the
good thing. But then am I? Am I
invisibly making myself a fool
to think that I understand what
goodness is, and that my
goodness is more good than their
good. You know, is, there is,
is, I mean, there's that
question, and then there's a
larger question of like, is it
all good? You know, is actually
them doing that good? Because
goodness exists larger than the
frame of reference of what
might, of what our immediate
sort of like, acute socio
political, even life span, time
frame seems to state is good
because we're incapable of
recognizing, let alone the
second and third order
consequences of our of our
decisions. But the 50th, 60th,
the the seven generations,
consequence of our thinking, you
know, is all of this good, and
if all of this is good, then
what does it matter? What I do?
Chris Bache: Once again, you're
pushing into deep territory, you
know, in the in the highest
level of Buddhist teachings in
Tibetan, Buddhist teachings in
Dzogchen, they would basically
radically qualify goodness or
the good that you know it's
like, doesn't make any
difference whether you're doing
good or not doing good. If
you're truly aligned with the
absolute essence of all things,
it puts you in a different kind
of category in relative to good
and not good, but until you are
living into that, in that
absolute condition, best to do
good, you know, because that's
the closest approximation we
have to that absolute condition.
And I think one of the things
that so I'm not willing, though
it is from that perspective, one
could relatively profoundly
relativize good, and I
understand that my own personal
orientations doesn't go in that
direction, to say it's all good.
I mean, I understand that it
could be that we all think we're
doing good, but I'm not willing
to say that all that we are
doing is all good, and one of
the things is injuring other
people, injuring other people,
physically, psychologically.
That, to me, is a marker of not
good. That's one of the places
where you draw the line, because
oneness is all embracing and and
it, and the first rule that
comes out of that is non injury.
I think the people who are doing
the things that you describe,
they had been doing it for a
long time, but right now,
they're doing it more publicly
than they were doing it before.
Before it may have been more
private and surreptitious and
individual, but now they've been
given permission in this greater
social reinforcement and
platforms on social media that
reinforce an echo chamber and
whatnot that reinforce those
patterns. But the fact that
people are self selecting and
reinforcing different patterns
and all of that's taking place,
doesn't mean that there aren't
still choices of good for
goodness to be made, and it
doesn't mean that goodness is
eliminated as a reasonable and
rational and spiritually rich
criterion for which To look at
our behavior and ourselves doing
various things, lynching, even
though it may be believed as
being good is not good, it's a
it is a not good, and a lot of
people Who did it believed that
they were doing good.
Unknown: Ah, when
Chris Bache: we wake up, when we
begin to wake up through which
whatever means when we are
touched by a passage from
scripture, or whether we're
touched in an arc in an
Ayahuasca session, in whatever
form, when we wake up
constantly, over and over again,
genuine waking up produces
gentler people. It produces
Kinder people, more
compassionate people. It doesn't
improve. It doesn't produce
homophobic people. It doesn't
produce people who are violence
and inflicting violence on other
people. It always produces
gentler, more respectful people.
Now that doesn't mean that
doesn't mean that we necessarily
don't fight for justice, and we
don't confront injustice as with
what force we need to but the
core balance is towards an
equality of that the that has a
gentle component to it, a
compassionate component. So then
the question becomes, how do you
confront the not good? Knowing
all the things we know about how
people believe that they are
doing good, how do we confront
the not good in a way which
doesn't perpetuate evil or
doesn't encourage more divisions
in the world? That's obviously
very, very difficult question,
and only can be done piece by
piece, by the person, in
circumstances, in specific
circumstances. If I step back
and try to generalize, then I'm
just, I'm just blowing smoke.
You know, this can only. Be done
from really people who are
living in the circumstances and
making decision whether to go to
the protest, whether to counter
protests, how to address
violence when it meets you on
the street, so on and so forth.
Unknown: Do you think that the
but the what feels like the the
James Jesso: almost ubiquitous
rise of what is often called Bad
Faith arguments and the almost
total
Unknown: devolution destruction
of discourse
James Jesso: as a consequence of
basically all conflict being
received of and responded to as
a form of abuse.
Unknown: How?
James Jesso: I'm not sure what
the question is here.
Unknown: What is the question
here?
What role do you see? What role
do you see conversation, open
discourse between the various
expressions of self perceived
good
James Jesso: as playing in the
evolutionary process we're in as
as humans and
Unknown: and how do you balance
that with the the
James Jesso: understandable
limitation of, well, I'm not
really particularly interested
in giving a voice or a space for
a hateful racist or a hateful,
whatever, and a violent person
to have a voice. I don't want to
speak to them. I don't think
that they should have something
to say. What is, what is the
balance there in the course of
doing good and trying to bring
about goodness in this world?
Chris Bache: That is a large
question, again, a huge
question, of which I have a very
limited framework from within to
respond to it. Partly here, my
background is I'm an academic.
And I'm an academic in the
history of religious thought, in
the history of philosophical
thought, in a discipline that
prizes engagement, it prizes
discussion, it prizes
collaboration and conflict as a
vehicle for determining greater
truth. I've gone through
multiple revolutions in my own
thinking, the hardest pivot in
when you move from a worldview
with certain sets of assumptions
and a certain way of seeing the
world, the hardest pivot is the
first one, because that's when
you let go of a sense of being
grounded in reality and you have
to step back and when you pivot
in certain fundamental beliefs,
then you suddenly realize that
what you had taken as reality
was just a model of reality, and
you're dealing with models and
models when the second and third
and fourth time you make that
pivot, as you continue to shift
and grow, it does get easier,
because You realize you know,
you discover that you're living
within a matrix of assumptions,
a paradigm of assumptions. So
I've gone through being a
conventional Christian to being
a non Christian, to being deeply
informed by science and the
scientific worldview to
challenging some of the core
axioms of a reductive
materialist interpretation of
science through the psychedelic
work, and I've been in dialog
with people all the years, all
these stages, not only my
students, but all the faculties
and colleagues and People who
I've spent my entire academic
career, disagreeing with and
still managing to be friends
with and working with students
and allowing them to voice
opinions in the room, which I
find abhorrent, and yet it's
essential for them to be able to
express the. Themselves, if
there's ever going to be a
chance of opening up a
possibility that they can see
the world from a little
different perspective. But all
of that is within a certain
frame of reference in which
there is a set of rules about
the give and take and the limits
of give and take what's
happening today is a very
different world in this
sheltered world that I've been
functioning in inside a
university. This is, as you say,
it's a dissolution of standards.
It is a radicalization of
everyone's got the right to
their own position, and every
position is as valuable as any
other. And in the end, it comes
down to might makes right, or
the vote of the majority,
however coerced and contrived,
that is, this a very different
world. And when I tried to
fathom that world, I think we
are living in a time. I mean, we
know it. We're in a time of
paradigm change. We are in a
time when certainties are
becoming uncertainties,
constants are dissolving. So
many reference points that
people have used to orient
themselves are being changed. I
mean, science changed so much,
and now science has changed
itself so much. When it began to
point to 96% of reality is
invisible, dark matter and dark
energy. How the hell do we live
in a universe like that? How do
we live in a universe as big as
the universe is we're
describing. All the religions of
the world have all come together
in one valley. It's like rivers
have come together into one
valley, and just meeting each
other as we have in the last two
centuries, has forced, for
anyone who's paying attention,
has forced a radical
reassessment of all of our truth
claims, of all of the
certainties that we've had about
what we know to be true, and
what we know God is doing with
the world and what and when we
look when just in this
complexity of plurality that
we're dealing with, just within
a mindset of disciplines, it
opens up, it taps into this
deep, deep uncertainty that,
well, maybe we really don't know
what God wants, and maybe we
really don't know what the truth
is. And maybe we really have to
go look not only in our sacred
scriptures, but in their sacred
scriptures, and in their sacred
scriptures to even begin to deal
with some type of approximation
that might become more adequate
than it was before. And so many
of these things are missing
right now, this sort of self
awareness of the limitations of
one's paradigm, of our cultural
embeddedness that's missing from
much of this discussion so but
we see it all in acting out.
We're at a time of a falling
apart of values. We can't even
count on nature to be whole
patterns that it had held for us
for all these centuries. The
weather patterns are different,
the rain patterns are different,
the heat patterns are different.
Not even nature is allowing us
to stay in the comfortable
domain. Immigration patterns are
different. Racial balances in
our country are different. So
many differences, so many
things. People are scared,
people are unstable, people are
grabbing they're hiring to hold
on to. And from one perspective,
you can say yes, yes, yes, good
luck with that, because it's
going to keep falling apart.
It's going to keep getting
worse. And if you're not able to
deal with that. You're going to
suffer enormously. If you keep
trying to hold on to old values,
you're going to suffer terribly,
and you're going to cause
suffering, and that suffering is
going to come back on you. To
me, it's not just that the world
is a dirty and uglier place than
the academic university is
because the academic university
can be a pretty, dirty and ugly
place in its own form, in its
own genre, but underneath our
culture, the constants are
falling away. The legs are being
kicked out from under the table.
This just tremendous
uncertainty, and truth has been
a casualty of that. Truth has
been a casualty of that process
as well a sense of feeling
truth.
Unknown: But
Chris Bache: we'll get through
it. We have no other choice,
because this is a truth that we
live in. We live in a
pluralistic society. We live in
a sexually pluralistic society.
We live in a in a society of
multiple truths. We live in a
culture of multiple truths. We
live in a world of expanding
truths, of just expanding
horizons, over and over and over
again. It's very uncomfortable.
To live in such a fluid world,
but if we're not good at it now,
we better get good at it within
the next generation or two,
because this is not going to
change. We're not going to go
back into the tried and
comfortable world of the past.
We are only going forward into
new and uncertain territory, and
we're going into it together. We
have to kind of grow up.
We have to grow up. We have to
stop acting and arguing like
adolescents. We have to start
acting and arguing like adults,
and adults have a time horizon
and a perspective that you don't
have when you're an adolescent,
and adults can hold their temper
more and they don't cause injury
like adolescents do. And so it's
grow up or die time. We have to
grow up. We have to stand up. We
have to measure up
Unknown: to this,
Chris Bache: to the higher
demands of growing truth. Yeah,
because truth is growing, truth
is expanding, we're trying to
keep up with it hard time.
James Jesso: Yeah, this, this
whole conversation. I just, I
mean, I keep throwing really
hard questions at you, and
incredibly, I'm just, or
increasingly, like, this is all
so difficult. I mean, you think
these questions are difficult,
the fact that we even are asking
them means we're in a reality
that is far more difficult than
even just looking and forming
the questions, right?
Chris Bache: And you're asking
me questions about things I
don't really know much about. I
mean,
James Jesso: ask me, What about
that? I wrote a book about I
know it's so funny. I thought I
was gonna ask you about
psychedelics. I'm sitting here,
I feel like I'm in satsang or
something, and you're just like,
what does it mean to be a good
person? Grace. How do I face the
meta crisis?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, we're
all in this together. We are all
in together. All your listeners
and all the people who are not
listening, we're all in it
together. No What's wonderful
about this conversation, and the
conversations that you encourage
is that it pushes beach bulls
boundaries in a safe and
respectful way. It invites them
to become more self reflective,
more self aware. It invites them
to read more books and to learn
more and to become less reactive
and more integrated in their
presence. That is a mode of it's
not just the content that comes
from these kind of discussions,
which can be useful to people,
but the mode of the conversation
itself, the mode of disciplined
inquiry. It's, you know, yes,
you read the books, you've done
your homework. You know what the
issues are that we're going to
talk about. But the quality of
engagement is itself a model for
how we need to do to move
forward where we're going, you
know. And that's a great value.
James Jesso: Well, thank you. I
kind of feel like I recognize
that in myself, in the sense of
what I'm attempting to produce
and also in what I'm consuming.
I'm, you know, like I'm kind of
just coming out of this place
where my response to all of this
at first was like, okay, my
nervous systems on overload. I'm
going to play Playstation, and
I'm going to just like, do the
absolute bare minimum of just
like I had a bunch of podcast
things recorded, and I was just
like, doing the bare minimum,
just trying to do the podcast
all recorded out. And then at
some point, increasingly, I'm
removing myself, because I don't
have the ability to participate
in the generative social
discussions I previously was a
part of in my community in the
same way, and I'm looking to
find myself and surround myself
the type of quality of
conversation and topic of
conversation and and angle of
addressing the topic and the
quality, because otherwise, you
know, I am the five people I
spend most time with or, I mean,
that's a pretty strong
generalization, but if the five
people I'm spending most time
with is whatever happens to be
trending on Twitter and and
Facebook, Which is like, the
algorithms basically push for,
like, maximum attention, maximum
attention grabbing, and what
Tristan Harris calls like a race
to the bottom of the brain stem,
and it's all limbic hijacking
and all the rest and the it's,
it's just like a it's just a
dynamic of outrage in one way.
Or another, then that's the
world I'm in, and that's the way
I'm gonna engage things. And I
see that I want the podcast to
be something different. You
know, it's psychedelic, I mean,
but it's not, you know, it's
like, it is about psychedelics,
but it's more about being
someone who uses psychedelics
and has a psychedelic
perspective, trying to make
sense of life in real life. And
I'm trying to also surround
myself with the types of
conversations and discussions
and topics that are helping me
stay in that so I can keep being
a part of and contributing to
that kind of world. Because I'm
looking at this, this balance
somebody I've been really
listening to a lot recently,
Daniel schmactenberger talked
about trying to, well, it's kind
of hard to really know if I ever
understand what he's saying,
because he's saying, because
he's I feel like he's way too
smart for me, or I'm not smart
enough, or something. You know,
it's real humbling listening to
talk, listening to him talk
something along the lines of,
like, trying to find that place
between, you know, recognizing
what's it, what's going wrong
with the world, and all the
things going wrong, and what am
I actually able to do? Like,
what am I actually able to do?
Yeah, rather than trying to
solve what's wrong with the
world, being like, Okay, I got a
sense of it. But what am I
actually able to do? And, and
right now, it feels like this is
what I'm actually able to do.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I understand
that, and I don't do Twitter
feeds, I don't do Instagram. I
spend very little time in social
media altogether. So at the
cost, at the risk, of separating
myself from the pulse of where
people are. Where I Live is not
where most people live, and one
of the reasons I live in a
different place is because of
psychedelics. When I when I
experience what's happening,
it's within a different
historical horizon than most
people experience what's
happening, and when I am
concerned for the people who are
suffering, even that is from a
different perspective, because
of the psychedelic experiences
that have taught me to recognize
the different levels of being
that are present in a human
body, the Different levels of
soul inside a human body, and
then to recognize even the
different levels of soul
maturation which are in a
species in an historical period
and that's contextualized within
an intimate experience of the
aliveness of the universe, that
the universe is alive at core,
in every blade of grass and
every every gyration of the
planets, in the movement of the
galaxies, it is alive and its
intelligence. And its
intelligence is constantly
knocking on the back of our
mind, constantly asking for
permission to enter and to
infuse us more with its
understanding, to attend that
deeply to The invitation that
the universe gives us requires
stepping out of Twitter feeds
and Instagram feeds and this
buzz, buzz, buzz, which is
important, but if you want to,
it's like if you want to
understand where we are in our
universe and where we are in the
galaxy and where our galaxy is,
you have to go out at night
under a dark sky with no
surrounding lights and and let
your eyes adjust to the darkness
and stay focused there for a
long time, and then listen very
carefully. And it's the same way
with inner knowing. Inner
knowing requires a stepping back
out of the give and take of
daily discourse, tuning in
deeply. And I've been blessed in
that I've my life has afforded
me an unusual amount of time to
do that without taking on monk's
robes. You know that's so my
whole experience of the
challenges that we're facing,
all of them, are really not
based on earthly wisdom. You
know, there's, I try to frame it
as best I can, earthly wisdom,
but my framing, my deepest
understanding of what's, what
are really the challenges that
are we're facing, and what's
really driving the social
context that we're in? You know,
they come out of my psychedelic
work. They come out of a very,
very different perspective than
even a time space perspective.
Or I would say that the time
space perspective is. Is at best
50% at best 50% and the other
50% or more really comes out of
an intimacy, I don't want to
say, with the divine, because
that brings us back to the
culture wars. How do we define
God? But in so that's why I talk
about the mind of the universe
and intimacy with the generative
intelligence of the universe, an
intimacy with the creative
intelligence of the universe
that, to some degree, has taken
me under its wing, because I was
willing to pay the dues to
snuggle up inside there and
You never look at life again,
Unknown: as you know,
Chris Bache: after you've been
into those intimate places, when
you've been dissolved into the
into the deepest pulse of life
that you've ever known, you
never experience life the same
way again. And if you've, if
you've nurtured a deep and long
connection to this deeper
knowing which Transcendence
history in a profound way.
You never, you never experience
life the same way as you did
before. You now have a It's not
like you have the answers or you
have the knowledge which solves
things, but there is a there's
an intimacy.
It makes you very sensitive to
how much fear drives things. And
when you, when you've dissolved
all the fear that you've ever
been asked to dissolve, when
you, when you dissolve all of
that. And you enter into those
territories which in which there
is no fear and there is only
truth and only insight and only
understanding and only love and
compassion. Then when you come
back out of that and you look at
life around you, so much of it
is driven by fear and so little
understanding, and so many
people are afraid of dying, and
so many people are afraid of
losing this, that and the other,
because underneath it, they're
fundamentally afraid for their
own existence, for their just
they're afraid of dying. And if
you lose that, if you are no
longer afraid of dying, and
you're no longer afraid of that
deep destructuring, whether or
not you are challenged by short
term destructuring or not, you
come at it from a very different
perspective. You just live it
from a different way. So to me,
you know, LSD in the mind of the
universe is a psychedelic
memoir. It's a whole life's work
that is reflected there. It's a
it's a journey. That's why I
like the title diamonds from
Heaven better, because it it's a
story of a journey of deepening
intimacy. And when you, when you
come out of that, you I remember
when I would do a session, and
at the end of the session,
someone I would pick me up at
the end of the day and take me
to where I would be that night.
And once in a while, we had to
go buy a grocery store. And as
you can imagine, there are few
places stranger to be than an
American grocery store after
you've come down from a serious
psychedelic session, it's like
being in Disneyland. I mean,
it's like in the strange,
strange world, something as
simple as a grocery store can be
that's our work, though, isn't
it? When we go into this space,
we enter into deeper intimacy
with whatever it is that's
driving the universe, and then
we come back and we try to live
our lives as best as we can.
This is what reincarnation does.
Reincarnation plunges into. It
pulls us out, connects us to
spiritual reality again, plunges
us back in, and then we go out
again and back and forth and
back and forth. A psychedelic
session will do the same thing,
but on a smaller orbit. It
basically kills the earthly
life. It shatters the earthly
life and opens us up to what
it's like to die into this great
surrounding world. Old, and then
after the session, we come back
and we're alive inside time and
space again. And then a few
months later, we'll shatter out
into outside time and space. So
we're reproducing, reenacting
the dynamic of nature in
reincarnation and whatnot. Once
you do that enough times, and
once you incarnate enough times,
then you you cease to to relate
to the world the way you did
before. And in much of this
aberrant social behavior that we
see around us, what I see is so
much
Unknown: youth. Is
Chris Bache: so much
inexperience, is so much
naivete, maybe badness, but more
than badness, I see something
that makes me feel terribly sad.
I see people not knowing better?
And if you ask, why don't they
know better? At core, I'm
looking at a soul, and I think,
why does this soul not know
better? And at core of that,
it's like Jesus. They're babies,
they're children, they're
adolescents, they just haven't
matured enough to really
understand the deep reciprocity
that exists between human
beings, which leads to a respect
of human beings, no matter what
they are, no matter who they
are.
Unknown: That's well,
Chris Bache: that's
childishness, really. And
psychedelics grow us up. I mean,
if you do them right, if you use
them carefully, they accelerate
our maturation. They don't make
us perfect, and they don't fill
us up with, you know, eternal
truths, but they do force us to
become more mature than we were
in the beginning, if we if we
engage them responsibly,
James Jesso: well, that might be
a good place to call to a close.
Feel like that was a really
great way to end.
Unknown: Chris, I want to thank
you for
James Jesso: sitting down and
addressing a bunch of questions
that a couple, maybe a little
bit for the most part. 80% of
this had nothing to do with your
book. I didn't even open it up
as to what's the plan. And I
really asked you to go to the
edge of your thinking. I feel
like I really asked you to go to
the edge of your thinking today
on some difficult questions. And
I feel really, I feel really
nourished by what came of it,
and I trust that my listeners
will will feel the same, or at
the very least something,
something will come up worthy of
talking about. So I really
appreciate your time today,
Chris,
Chris Bache: you bet I trust our
conversations. I trust what
comes out of them. I trust where
they go. I hope they're useful
to the people who tend to tune
into your podcast. It's always a
joy to talk with you.
James Jesso: James, thank you,
Chris. I'm going to show your
book here for those who are
watching on the YouTube LSD and
the mind of the universe. It's a
very good book, and
Chris Bache: I'm going to put a
plug in for a book of a friend
of mine, because if, if you are
concerned about the birth of the
future human, and if you're
concerned with the historical
crisis that we are entered, and
you want deeper understanding,
my book gives a psychedelic
vision of where we are and where
we're going. But this book,
let's see if I had, is it
showing here?
James Jesso: Yeah, I see it
choosing Earth, humanity's great
transition to a mature planetary
civilization.
Chris Bache: Yeah, Dwayne Nelda,
and you can see, it's not a big
book, it's a thin book. It won't
take you a lifetime to read it
really, really, really fine
book, looking at where we are,
where we're going, and how to
navigate the times we're
entering.
James Jesso: Very kind book.
Cool. Thanks for the suggestion,
Chris. Last thing, is there
anywhere, given how damning we
were of social media throughout
the course of this interview,
are there places on social media
that you'd like to direct people
towards?
Unknown: Well,
Chris Bache: in a couple of
months, they can go to Chris
bache.com the website will
eventually appear there. I'm so,
I'm so social media. Out of it,
I don't, haven't fulfilled my
responsibility to have the
website up and done. They can
reach me at my university email
address, which is cm Bache, my
initial cm bache@ysu.edu they
can contact me there for the
time being, but in a couple of
months they'll be able to go to
Chris bache.com Great.
James Jesso: Well. Thank you
very much, Chris, and looking
forward to the next
conversation. Me too, James. Is
always a head cut. Okay, thank
you for tuning in. Check out
Chris's book. LSD, in the mind
of the universe. It's beautiful.
I loved it, as you can see here.
You know, so many tabs, so many
underlines. I loved it. I also
love talking with Chris. So he's
a great guy. He's seemingly a
great guy, and he's got a lot of
wisdom, and check out his book.
Additionally, if you like this
episode, you can share it with a
friend, and if you'd like to
support the show financially,
Patreon is a great option, where
you can pledge a monthly an
amount to be sent forth monthly,
as little as a cup of coffee
once a month. Everything is
something, and it all adds up to
allow me to earn income while
dedicating myself full time to
the show and to the larger body
of psychedelic research that I'm
putting into and out into the
world. And I had mentioned there
was a special announcement after
the interview, so I'll just let
it out now, which is that I'm
going to be taking a two episode
break for the next little while.
So if you're new to the show, is
a great opportunity to go back
through the archives. If you're
not new to the show, I will be
releasing some content patrons.
I just released an update on the
Patreon feed just for you, which
includes some insider
information, but also includes
some exclusive content that's
just going to be for you guys as
well. And yeah, so I'm taking a
two episode break to sort of
like clean house metaphorically,
not so much literally. My house
is pretty good, but definitely
metaphorically. And yeah, so
that's all, thanks for tuning
in, thanks for listening all the
way to the end, and I will see
you on the next episode of
adventures through the mind. And
until then, take care. You. You.