Chris Bache: CH, well, here we
are again for our third
discussion, and we tend to
typically gave the topic for
this discussion limitless time,
because we now want to bridge
into the deeper questions
surrounding reincarnation, the
deeper perspective, where is
reincarnation taking Humanity?
Where is this constantly
learning and recycling and
recycling creating new and new
platforms in our incarnation
experience. Where is it going?
Where is it taking us? What
might the deep future look like,
and most importantly, how might
that understanding shift how we
engage our life, right here,
right now? Yeah.
Richard Rudd: Yeah, very deep
questions to follow. Where
should we begin?
Chris Bache: Well, we should, I
think we should acknowledge that
each of us have a deep
experiential basis that we're
kind of bringing to this
discussion. You know, we're not
simply thinking about it,
philosophizing about it, and
speculating about it, we have
deep convictions born out of
unusual experiences.
Richard Rudd: First, it's true,
it's why it's in way, what's
brought us together around these
to do these dialogs, I think.
And I was just explaining to you
know, that to discriminate the
difference between knowledge and
wisdom, you know so although we
are we've explored strains of
knowledge in this wisdom is is
different from knowledge. It's
the opposite, in a way, because
for me, the way I understand
wisdom is it's is it? Wisdom
comes through Revelation. It
comes through listening. It's a
it comes through being passive
and then receiving, whereas
knowledge is something that you
do opposite. Do you go after it,
you chase it, you hunt it. You
know you're, you're, you're
going towards it, instead of
allowing it to come towards you.
And so you get different
information through revelation.
And it's not information in the
same way, it's cellular, so
that, you know, so my
experience, you know, that's led
to me being me and doing what I
do is because I have always had
this, you know, cellular
understanding, cellular knowing
of what's coming for humanity,
and, and, and it's always, it's
quite hard to hold that. I'm
sure you relate to that, Chris,
it's quite hard to hold it,
because it's not everyone else
has it. And so it puts you, it
puts me in a I'm more relaxed
than most people I know at a
fundamental level, because I
have this knowing that
everything's going to be fine,
and I can't explain that knowing
or even why it was given to me
to have it. And I know that many
people listening to this will,
will not, will have a resonance,
you know, and have had
breakthroughs and visions where
that has come to them. So, you
know, I want to, I think it's
really good for us to
acknowledge it, that we carry
this, this other dimension. And
you obviously through your work.
I mean, tell us a little bit
about, yeah, it would be lovely
to hear
Chris Bache: I completely share
what you're saying, because I do
carry an unusual knowledge, as
you do now. At the beginning of
our series, we talked about the
evidence for reincarnation. So I
was in my professorial mode
there the intellectual digesting
of this evidence, and the middle
the second conversation was kind
of a blending of that type of
knowledge and the type of wisdom
that arises in my psychedelic
work and in today's discussion,
I feel like I'm standing
squarely within that other side
of my life. I'm a visionary
Shaman. I'm a psychedelic
visionary. My understanding
comes out of the careful
distilling of conscientiously
engaged Non-ordinary states of
consciousness again and again
and again, purifying and
purifying and allowing the
universe to take me deeper and
deeper into what I experience as
into itself and into its
intention, into time, literally
into deep time, and giving me
experiences which were never
intended to be just for me, they
are planted in me to hold and
then. To pass on, as so many of
you know, anyone who has these
deep experiences, you know
they're never just for us. We
hold them for for the larger
collective so I do like you. I
have a feeling for what's
happening in history, where
we're going, and it does tend to
i to it gives me a calm and a
relaxation, even as we enter
into very difficult and trying
times ahead.
Richard Rudd: Yeah, I think so.
And I think both you and I have
that same kind of you know,
knowing, I suppose that birth is
an intense event and and we're
coming to a birth point, you
know, we're even in the canal
and contractions are occurring,
and in the same way that, you
know, I understand individual
awakening. When awakening comes
into a body, you know, and it
comes spontaneously, it kind of
comes through contractions, in a
sense, so often, before you have
an experience and a
transcendental experience, there
are kind of shudders, and then
there's openings and closings,
there's there's condensing and
and intensification of shadow
material. And then there's a
kind of opening up, and then
there's another birth
contraction. And the
contractions come closer and
closer together, and eventually
there's a kind of a deep opening
to, you know, an epiphany of
some form, like something that
shakes the core of your being
and and maybe fires within your
DNA, so that it's something that
just sets you alight and changes
you forever. You know when, when
those revelations come? And so,
you know, I think that that's,
that's what's happening on a
planetary level as well. It's
beginning to happen as a
collective and your writings,
Chris, particularly, through
your your you know, your mind of
the universe. Diamonds, book, it
describes so beautifully, this
process of like coming into
coming down the birth canal,
what it doesn't do, obviously,
and what neither of us can do is
fill in the details, you know,
and only time can do that. But
we'd like to give a bit of
backdrop and and both empathize
with the intensity of the
suffering that is already here
and is most likely going to be
ramped up to want to empathize
with that, but at the same time,
we want to present this, this
knowing that we have that gives
people hope more than hope,
actually, but it also provides
some hope, doesn't it like there
is a purpose to the events that
are taking place on our planet
right now and right now is
whenever you're watching this,
you know, because one can, you
know, one can only imagine more
events occurring as This canal
opens up.
Chris Bache: So, yeah, yeah, you
describe that process of the in
breaking of the vision and the
being drawn into the the deep
experience of Revelation.
Because, you know, deep visions,
deep insights, cannot fit
themselves into small
containers. And so when nature
or the divine or the universe
invites us into a deeper
experience, a more conscious
understanding of life, it has to
purify ourselves. And you
describe that contracting
process, and it is our past.
It's everything about us which
keeps us small, being burned up
inside us in order to allow
ourselves to be taken shattered.
It's in my context, it's the
Death-Rebirth cycle to die to
everything within us which holds
us where we are, and to be
reborn into a larger world and
and that can happen again and
again, taking us deeper and
deeper into that, knowing it's
like any spiritual path, there
are no shortcuts and there's no
easy way into this. It's always
a very exacting and a very
demanding, demanding road. But
the fruit of that road is, well,
it's it's personal and it's
collective. It expands around us
in all sorts of subtle and
mysterious ways. And we are part
of a lineage, each of us in our
own ways, a lineage of people
who have asked for more and who
have been given more and have
paid the price for being given
more. Uh, and you're right. This
is my work started as thinking
of my psychedelic work as kind
of a personal healing or
personal transformation or
personal awakening, and that
just got shattered in the light
in the first few years. And
everything about my work kept
opening up into collective
VISTAs, collective spaces, being
drawn into the collective
psyche, going through collective
purifications and opening up
into insights about our
collective developmental
process, experiencing
reincarnation, not simply as an
individual soul journey, but as
a species journey, that's a
journey that our entire species
is on, evolving itself through
the systematic reincarnation,
generation after generation,
moving forward and then being
Given a certain understanding
about that, this reincarnation
process for us, individually and
collectively, is coming into a
crescendo. It's coming into some
type of profound breakthrough,
and you've languished it as a
birth, and I think that's
absolutely correct. And birth
involves labor, and it involves
a change from one state to
another state for a child, it's
a change from a water being to a
land being. And we are, I think,
are growing from a state of
individual egoic awareness,
where our identity is
fundamentally our body, mind,
ego, into a soul awareness,
where all of our former lives
are coming together in a in a
tremendous fusion point there,
as our knowledge of our past
deepens and as we heal the
traumas of our past that we're
all carrying and our past lives
become more integrated, and we
integrate not only their pains,
But their virtues, their great
assets, their capacities, and
all of this begins to take
place. And it's like our lives
come together, and eventually
they hit a fusion point, and at
that point, the soul becomes
one, totally, as I've
experienced this, there's an
explosion of light and an
explosion into a higher order of
individuality with a different
threshold, a different sense of
communion with the surrounding
intelligence of the universe and
the intelligence of the Divine.
But and it's a different to me,
if humanity is going through
this process, which I deeply
believe it is, that's what my
visions have shown me again and
again. It represents a new
foundation for the human story,
a new phase of the human story,
just as profound as when we made
this jump about 200,000 years
ago to a brain that's 50% bigger
than the brain that we were
carrying before, allowing us to
think and do things that we
could never do before. This is
something which is going to
change the fundamental
archetypal architecture of the
collective unconscious.
Richard Rudd: Yeah, beautifully
said. It kind of brings two
things I'd like to say in
response, which are really
reiterations of what you've
said. And the first is that many
people watching this, you know,
if you're drawn to this kind of
material, there's a very good
chance that you have said, Yes,
you know, to receiving, to
transmuting more shadow
material, you know, more than
more than one lifetimes worth,
and and I remember those dark
days of my kind of past in which
the shadow, the level of shadow
inside my body, seemed
insurmountable, you know, and
seemed endless. You know,
whenever I would meditate, I
would just find endless weight
and heaviness and oppression.
And, you know, like so much of
it, that it was just, it was
just this big, thick clot. And
how would I ever, ever burn
through that? And gradually over
the years, happily, you know,
for me, and it's lightened and
and so I, I've, I've seen the
light at the end of the tunnel.
And, and I say this because I
know that many watching this
will also have that experience
of grappling with a weight
inside the physical, emotional
reality, mental reality that far
outweighs us. You know, the kind
of individual wounding patterns
of one life. You know, whatever
they are, you know, and that's
not to kind of. Of, you know,
put them lesser, but it so, you
know, we've taken on more and,
and, and the reason we've taken
on more is because we are, we
are capable of taking on more.
So if you feel that heaviness
and weight in you, it's because
you have the capacity, the deep,
overwhelming, you know, the love
that's great enough to burn
through that. So I say that to
encourage people continue on in
your transformational path and
not to lose hope. And the other
thing I wanted to say is, you
know, when you look at times
like this, like birth, and as
you said, there's something that
emerges that is completely new
when you when we're looking at
life as it is today through the
lens of history, we See a
continuity. You know, we see
this continuity, this fairly
unbroken continuity with blips
and ups and downs and cycles
repeating and and we see that
through the patterns of our
recorded history. And the one
thing we never you never see in
birth, is you can't see beyond
the break, because at some point
there's a break in the
continuity, and then something
completely new is born. As you
said, it's an it's assembled out
of all the elements of the old.
It's condensed. It's revealed
from all those elements coming
into a symphony. And so it's
completely different. It stands
on the shoulders of all that, of
all that's great, and all that's
been suffering, and all of that
is suddenly kind of compressed,
like the beginning of the
universe was compressed into
this tiny space and then set and
that's what happens, is this
incredible compression. And then
there's this opening, as you
said, an expansion of vast
light. So what I'm pointing
towards Is that what's coming
has no similarity to what we
have now. You we cannot. You
know, with our wildest
imagination, we can begin to
approach it, but it you have to.
You have to really, you know you
never see a break in the
continuity coming. You always
assume, all of you humans, it's
our way we see things. Have
always been this way. They'll
always continue. Maybe, you
know, we're going to continue
along this path, and then we'll
get robotics, and we'll get
technology, and we'll get this,
and then we'll go to the stars.
And, you know, we think in the
way that we've been trained to
think until the one of these
Crux points comes, and then it
just smashes everything. And in
a way, a whole new epoch begins,
something completely new with
different technology, you know,
and we're the technology, you
know, we are the technology.
I've been saying this to be all
like it's inside us, you know,
our DNA has capacities, and
dreamed of capacities and and so
I think it's really important
that people grasp that that
what's coming bears no
resemblance to what has been.
You know,
Chris Bache: yes, I completely
agree with you. I mean, this,
this is what happens in a
psychedelic session as well. I
mean, I first, I completely
affirm what you're saying about
the weight and the burden that
so many serious practitioners
are experiencing. And I think
it's because there, there's a
lot of their past, which is past
lives, karma which they're
working and clearing now. But
it's also collective karma that
great beings. And I think there
are many more hidden saints than
we might think there. They have
taken on responsibility for
working on behalf of humanity as
a whole, so that they are they
are engaging darkness that comes
not just from their personal
history or soul history, but
from our collective history. And
we have to get through this
period quickly, we have to bring
about this transformation, or
cooperate with this process.
Because, as every mother knows,
you don't want the fetus to get
stuck in the birth canal. That's
not a good place to be. We want
to move, keep everything moving
through. And I think that many,
many, many souls incarnating in
this period of history, saw what
they were getting into, knew
what they were getting into, and
chose to do this work, because
this is the work of birthing a
new humanity. Is great work. And
you're right. It's a
discontinuity in a session. When
you go deep, deep, deep into the
pain, it just looks like it's
never, ever, ever going to end.
You can't imagine how this will
ever reconcile itself. And then
there is a breaking point.
There's a point of absolute
surrender, of absolute cost
paid. And then there is a waking
up, waking up in a new reality,
which is not an extension of the
old reality in any way you
can't. Get to this new reality
by refining, purifying, even
healing the old reality it is.
It is being catapulted in
something which is a
fundamentally new genre of
experience, a new set of
capacities. My experience, in my
sessions, when I've been taken
deep into the experience of deep
time into the deep future.
That's how I had experienced the
course of Humanity as well, that
we seem to be first many, many
visions, over and over and of
course, my visions, these are
old. I mean, I started having
these visions in 1991 so these
are pushing 30 years old now,
but a series of visions that we
are coming to a turning point.
The pace of the past is not,
could not be used as to measure
the pace of the future, of
turning a before and after point
that after this historical
transition, we would be
operating at a completely
different psycho spiritual
structure. We would be
generating a different
civilization, because we would
be different beings. We would
not be confined and fragmented
the way we are now. I mean,
basically our relationship with
nature that we are experiencing
now that the damage that we've
done to nature was done by a
species operating out of the
egoic level of consciousness,
which is a fundamentally, which
is a brilliant level of
consciousness, but it's
fragmented. It's fragmented from
each other. It's fragmented from
foundational from the foundation
of life itself, a species which
is operating with a healed heart
and a healed mind, an open heart
that embraces the great breath
of its own experience and human
experience, and an open mind
which is open to a deeper
communion, a deeper taking in
from higher orders of
intelligence, higher orders of
knowing such a being lives in
the world differently than a
human being does today. The soul
lives in the world differently
than the ego. The soul knows
that the world that it leaves is
the world that is coming back to
so it takes better care of the
world. The soul knows that its
relationships have a depth of
texture and history, and you
don't walk away from any
relationships. And so you take
more care of all of your
relationships and of all the
people in that you're related.
Because this is an ongoing
developmental process, and I
think we are coming into a point
where the irony is, life is not
giving us any option except to
go through this transition.
There's no going back. The Earth
is not going to allow us. We've
done so much damage to it. This
damage is coming up to us now we
cannot continue living even in a
simplified version of how we
have gotten here, we have to
reach into something entirely
new, something radically new.
And I think you're right that
this is happening on the
outside, and we are being called
to a new relationship to the
earth on the outside, but we are
carrying within our hearts all
the problems that have gotten
here, gotten us here, and we are
carrying all the values and the
potentials and the insights
which are which are taking us
beyond this into a different
order. It's all inside. And you
and I focus our work on the
inside dance. There are other
people whose work is to focus on
the outside dance, to bring out
the changes in the outer world,
to get us through all are
needed.
Richard Rudd: So true. And you
know, beautifully put, and you
know the inner transformation
that you've just described. I
mean, one thing that I am
reminded of, like those, if you
if you know anyone's saying is
familiar with any of
Shakespeare's plays,
particularly the comedies and
the tragic comedies, you know,
like in some of those plays,
everything that can go wrong
goes wrong, and the wrong people
fall in love with the wrong with
the wrong people, that
everything gets twisted round.
It's like one of those
nightmares where it's just like,
and you've got to act four, and
usually there's five acts, and
it's still a complete mess. And
you're and, as in the audience,
you're going, Oh my God, how is
this ever going to be resolved,
and then he does this magical
thing where suddenly there's a
kind of strange attractor that
comes in some force or some
event that just suddenly
triggers all these like sub
events that makes everyone end
up with the right person, and
everything just gets. Yield, and
is happily ever after story, but
it happens very quickly, you
know, always right, compressed
in the last moment. And in a
way, it's a bit similar time,
because we've had this long,
slow, you know, build up to
create this, this mess, yeah,
and then there's this sudden
kind of, you know, cataclysmic
energy at the end that then just
in which you could never quite
see how these are, all these
things are all going to be
resolved. But they get resolved
and in a completely different
way from what we were expecting.
So, you know, and one of the
things that you spoken of a lot,
Chris, is the speed at which
things happen. And we can see
that in natural systems that or
we you can just see it in water
boiling, you know, it's the most
obvious one. Perhaps, you know,
you look at the water and
nothing seems to be happening,
and nothing seems to be
happening, and you put more and
more heat into it, and then some
bubbles start to appear. And
just the first little bricks of
bubbles on the surface. And
then, of course, suddenly, when
it hits that one boiling point,
everything just erupts. And you
have steam, you know, and this
water starts to just change its
state. And it's such a simple
metaphor, but it's so true
throughout the whole of nature.
And if you look at the whole of
humanity and history, you know,
in a way, that's what those
that's a period, that's that
we're reaching, and we'll begin
to see that more and more. And
the scientists are pointing to
those things like the like the
ocean, for example, is capturing
a huge amount of CO two and, and
it's, it's called the sink, you
know, it's just, it's sinking
down deep into the deep ocean
where, where the where that CO
two is being stored. And it's
slowly building up and building
up and building up until the
ocean will be able to no longer
capture any more CO two. And
from that point onwards, and
it's it's allegedly already
occurred, it weakens its ability
to store CO two weakens, and
therefore all the CO two that
we're creating suddenly explodes
into the atmosphere and and it
looks like we've been in this
hiatus, you know, and we have,
because there's this illusion
that we've been okay, and then
suddenly everything speeds up
much more quickly than anyone
could possibly have conceived,
you know. And except, you know,
some of the scientists who
really know that, who've really
analyzed the data deeply and and
also, you know, cross, people
who work across multiple fields,
you know, systems theorists and
people who really see the
interconnectivity of different
systems, can see the whole and
sit and have an edge. And, of
course, mystics like us. So
there are, you know, many who
are kind of predicting very,
very quick change that can be
very destabilizing for this
planet. And, you know, I know
you, you I'd love to hear what
you saying, what I want to say
about this and but, and we don't
say to alarm, but to prepare,
because it goes alongside the
the Inner Awakening on the as as
the as the inner birth takes
place something on the outside.
The structure has to decline. It
has to fall away in order for
this new to come through. It's a
universal law and and it's
essential. You know, as you
said, we we can't repair the old
system. That doesn't mean we
shouldn't try and repair the old
system, because there can be
one. You know, hearing all this,
you can think, Well, I'm not
going to do anything. Then I'm
just going to sit here. And
that's an understandable
response, and yet it's not a
truly compassionate response,
you know, because compassion
also involves passion, and we
need to stand up for what's
right and for justice, and and,
and what else. What is the
purpose of being here, you know?
So we need to continue forwards
and use our passion wherever we
are called to do so that's part
of our responsibility, and
that's part of what it means to
be an awakening being, and yet,
at the same time, we can have
this other part of us that
knows, well, I'm going to do
whatever I can while this is
collapsing, you know, I'm going
to give, I'm going to serve in
the best way I possibly can and
and that's how you know that you
will always be in the right
place. You'll always be in a
safe place. And when I say safe,
I mean safe in the sense that
you're aligned with the. Core of
your soul and its destiny. You
know, that's a safe place to be,
yeah,
Chris Bache: yeah, that place of
alignment, yeah. You know the
way that speeding up process
worked itself out in my in my
sessions, and it had to do with
understanding the field dynamics
of consciousness. I have just
enough understanding of chaos
theory and non equilibrium
systems to have a rudimentary
understanding of what physicists
or chaoticians but understand
when that when a system gets
more and more energy poured into
it. It reaches a state of non
equilibrium, or far from
equilibrium. And when it's in
that condition, like that water,
which is getting more and more
energy poured into it, our
bathtub, when you keep
increasing the quantity of water
that's going into the tub, and
the ripples get CH, they start
to change. We come to a tripping
point, a tipping point to
bifurcation point where the
system has too much energy to
maintain its current structures,
and it does a flip into a
different organizational
pattern. It goes through this
bifurcation point. It chooses a
different future. It flips into
a higher organization pattern.
And when physical systems reach
non equilibrium points. They can
do extraordinary things. They
can produce new particles. They
can produce orders of coherence
within themselves that would
have been impossible at a lower
energy state in my in my
visionary experiences, I was
given to see that all of
humanity. We are all fractal
nodes within Unified Fields, a
field of consciousness. There
the human unconscious, the
Collective Unconscious is a
field, and it is an energetic
field which reflects all of our
individual experiences, and when
enough individual experiences
become untenable, when they
become so painful, we just reach
out in desperation for a
different solution to the
situation. It's not just we
individually who are going
through this type of ordeal of
transformation, but all of us
collectively, we've never had
anything happen in history,
which is comparable to what's
coming at us now. Because when
we've had hurricanes or great
natural disasters, they've
always affected one part of the
world, but not the other part of
the world. But the global
systems crisis that seems to be
imminent, being driven by a
global ecological crisis, is
going to affect all continents,
all people, all places, that's
going to push humanity into a
different experiential field.
And the point here is that the
collective psyche is going to be
energized by all of this
disruption. It literally is
going to begin to boil
underneath us, underneath our
individual minds. And my
understanding of what's
happening is, is that in
evolution, there are kind of
multiple levels of evolution, at
least, say two levels of
evolution. We and I are being
born over and over again. We're
born or 100 years at a time. We
live 100 years, 100 years. But
underneath those 100 year
cycles, there is a learning
taking place. There is a
developmental process taking
place. We usually refer to this
as the soul. So the the
individual ego incarnates, but
the soul is growing, becoming
more becoming more, suffusing
our lives. But the same thing
happens collectively, every
generation, every generation,
billions and billions of people
are being born, but there is a
learning gathering underneath
them that is collecting all of
their learning in these deep,
deep, collective archetypal
structures. That's what's coming
to boil, not just our individual
incarnation, but that underlying
structure is coming into a high
energy state. And I think it's
it's coming to a state where the
the sheer energy of our
suffering, the energy of our
despair, or the energy of our
anxiety, is driving us through a
breaking point where suddenly
we're going to be flooded with a
different kind of common sense,
a different common sense, a
different set of priorities, a
different set of values, a
different experience of each
other. The only way I think that
we can go as far as we need to
go in order to save ourselves
and the planet in little time as
we have, is to understand the
dynamics of the collective
unconscious, the field dynamics
of consciousness and the how
fields operate in non
equilibrium systems. At least
this is what has come through my
Vishnu. Your experience over and
over that that we are coming to
a point where there is a crisis,
which builds an intensity until
it looks like all is lost. It so
much disruption, so much loss of
control, so much death challenge
at a very deep level. But when
it's at its worst, it begins to
pass. We pick ourselves up. We
somehow rise to the challenge of
this crisis. And in rising to
the challenge, we are changed.
We are profoundly changed, such
that, as we become start to come
out of this period of history,
we find that what our nature,
the nature that we are carrying,
is not just a different set of
attitudes, not just a different
set of beliefs, but a
fundamental, a fundamentally new
way of Being conscious, a new
organization of our
consciousness emerges. Something
has shifted in place, and we
find that things which were not
easy are suddenly easy. Things
which are out of reach are
suddenly within reach.
Possibilities are emerging much
faster than we would have ever
predicted. That's the type of
transformation I think we're
looking at a truly a rebirth of
humanity. So that's in my work.
I call it the birth of the
future human. You know, it is
truly a demarcation of a
different kind of human being
emerging now. I think our
history is creating this. It's
reincarnation which is coming to
a phase of fruition. And I think
we can get insights in or
glimmers of what the future will
look like by looking at the
Great Beings of our past, the
great saints, the great
prophets, the great
incarnations, the Christ the
Buddhas, the prophets, those
great beings who have always
called us into a higher order of
existence. Those are prototypes,
I think the prototypes which
give us an inclination, an
understanding of what we are in
the process of becoming as a
species collectively. I think we
are truly becoming a species of
Christ, a species of Buddhas, a
species of of Prophets. You
know, with that magnitude, that
tremendous scale of heart, I
don't know how long it's going
to take us to make this
transition. Clearly, the
ecological crisis, which is
fermenting, is a crisis that's
going to be deepening for
generations. It'll be at least
three generations, four
generations, before we hit the
peak of these of this crisis.
But I think we will come through
it. And I think we're not
talking 1000s and 1000s of
years. We're talking we have to
make this within a few 100 years
to make this transition. And I
think the 21st Century is the
key century of the of the
unraveling. It is the where we
make key choices that shape our
future. And one of the other
things that happens in non
equilibrium systems is that
individual changes, small
changes, can catapult into
massive outcomes. So the
butterfly wing in China sets off
a hurricane across the planet.
That metaphor that individuals
who have achieved within
themselves something of which
humanity is aspiring to change
for solving these large
problems, the impact of
individuals increases
exponentially in non equilibrium
systems. So just in contrast, if
we look just to the past, we
say, well, the individual can't
do anything. We're being
overwhelmed by just these
overwhelming historical forces
are coming at us. It's just the
opposite. As things intensify,
the individual becomes more
significant, a more significant
player. So beings who achieve a
wholeness within their person,
they achieve a robust soul
consciousness in their person
have a tremendous catalyzing
effect on people around them
coming to their own version of
that deep experience as well.
Richard Rudd: Thank you. I love
listening to you when you go off
on a transmission. I was
thinking, you know, if you were
to ask yourself, what one what
one thing? If there was one
thing that happened on this
planet that could change
everything in. Quickly,
overnight, what might that one
thing be? And inside me, the
answer was, is that for us to
see through the veil of death?
You know, because the moment one
person sees through the veil of
death, fear is no more. It just
isn't. There is no fear, because
that's where fear resides. So
the the intensification of the
energy you're talking about, the
suffering that you know, the the
love, all of it pouring towards
this one kind of point, this,
you know, it's, it's the only
thing that has the power to
pierce that veil, that veil of
death. And so what I would
expect, and what I have sort of
seen in through the gene keys
and through my teachings and
transmissions, is that more and
more people will gradually, as
this boiling takes place,
experience their consciousness
you know, having the ability to
transcend life, birth and death,
that cycle of life you know, and
be able to that consciousness
and the will retain the memory
between life, birth and death,
and carry it across. And what
that, you know, because that's
that's the that's pure
awakening. And when a being has
that layer, that level of
awakening, and they're sitting
there manifesting, or standing
there just moving around, being
who they are, and that is being
emanated. It is electrifying.
It's electrifying to anyone
else. It's it's catching. It's
contagious. You know, the the
transmission of wisdom and love
and awakening is contagious. You
know, most people will know
this. You go near one of these
beings and you can feel it, it
crackles in the air. And so the
more and more that is occurring,
the more and more this veil of
it will be breaking down, and
then fear will start to leave
this planet, gradually, person
by person, person by person,
generation by generation. And I
even believe deep inside myself
that that will enable children
to come through, to be born
without the wound of humanity,
you know, just be born awake,
you know, and therefore not have
those not have to go through
this journey. And, of course,
those children are us. Those are
our future vehicles, yeah, and
they will be born through those
awakened ones, you know, because
it if you have two awakened ones
coming together to bring a
child, then you have a clear
conduit, you know, and, and, and
that's a vessel that you might
want to jump into, yeah, to
experience, and then more and
more of that and that. So in a
way, you could almost perceive
that that's how the awakened
consciousness will colonize the
gene pool in humanity,
literally, like a, like a, like
a virus of love. You know, it
would just begin to spread, and
it's, and it's non
denominational, it doesn't, you
know, it's everywhere. It's in
the weirdest places. It's in
the, you know, tiny little
communities, because it's, it's
everywhere. It can't, it can't.
It's not, it's not fixed on any
chosen people, you know, as in
the past. It's, it's it so it's
going to wake up, you know, I
always liked that one liner that
Jesus left behind him where he
said, You know, when I return, I
will return like a thief in the
night, you know? And I
contemplated that for many, many
years, and one day I just saw
that, I was like, Oh, wow, yeah,
it's coming. It you can't stop
it. It's secret. It's hidden.
It's everywhere. It's a thief in
the night. It's just going to
arrive. And it's this, you know,
new human that we're talking
about. You know, this is the new
human that we've both seen, and
I think many people are sensing
here already among us in its
potential. Like you mentioned,
the Buddhas and things. And one
thing probably that I loved more
than anything else in your book,
Chris, is when you describe the
future human. And I was left
with this image of all these
Buddhas sitting down, meditating
and stuff, and then this one
human standing in the middle of
them, standing on its own two
feet, and that was the future
human. And I thought, you know,
I feel like that's such an
enduring, iconic symbol of
what's coming, because we're no
longer, it's it's no longer the
journey of meditation and
spiritual awakening and the
spiritual journey and this
awakening. Through
transformation of the shadow.
Suddenly that's come to an end,
you know. And suddenly that
being is standing, you know.
There's no practice anymore
other than living. And then then
that human really begins a new
humanity, because there's no
more awakening process. There's
the layers and layers of
creative expansion, always
infinite creative expansion. And
there's and there's playfulness,
and there's, you know, new
layers of engagement within the
you know, within the construct
of reality. You know, you know,
all these levels and dimensions
and fields that we can explore,
you know, through a new way. And
I and what I really see clearly
is as that's as the age of
suffering comes to an end. You
know, we have a new field, and
it's bliss. You know, we have
learned enough from suffering.
Now is our chance and
opportunity to learn from Bliss,
because bliss is the other side
of suffering. It's the same it's
almost the same thing. It's all
that suffering leads to Bliss,
and yet bliss is just the other.
It's like the white hole to the
black hole. You know, it's like,
you go through a black hole, you
come out the other side, there's
this white hole, and it's and
and it has as much depth and
juice as suffering does, you
know? So that there's, you know,
there's a similarity to them,
but it's a new it's a new Muse
that humanity has, you know, so
when we sit in that bliss and we
move through that bliss, we're
moving through the highest
aspects of our consciousness,
and that then has to all be
explored, all of it, because
bliss, Like suffering has layer
upon layer upon layer upon layer
upon layer and dimension and
dimension and dimension and and
it, you know, there's a whole
epoch needed again just to
explore bliss. So that's why, in
a way, if you can hold that in
your heart and your mind as we
move through these very
difficult you know, decades
ahead and century centuries,
perhaps few centuries agree. By
the way, 21st Century is seems,
it seems to be the one. The next
century, you know, seems to be
the one. And you know, remember,
that's us, you know, like, we'll
be there. I mean, I say to
people, you don't miss this, you
know, like people saying, like,
Oh, this is my last incarnation.
Okay, well, make sure you come
back for that one. You don't do
all this. And then the reward,
yeah, so all things are possible
at that stage, and I think it's
really good to bear these things
in mind as we're moving through,
you know, intense periods.
Chris Bache: Let's, let's allow
ourselves to look deep into the
future of this future human.
Because whatever, whatever
transformation we're going
through, and we are going to,
you know, we agree we're going
through this acute
transformation. We're giving
birth to a new order of human
capacity, however long it takes
us to do it, you know, a few 100
years, whatever the human story
is, not stopping. The
evolutionary drama is not
ending. This is simply going to
be a new platform within which
the human story will continue to
develop. I think you're right
that we have been evolving out
of through learning from
suffering. That's been the great
teacher in much of our learning
of the past. But I think, and I
think you're right, we are
getting past that. We're growing
out of that, just as we're
growing out of our fear of
death. You know, if there were
one thing that I wish I could
give people from my sessions, it
would be to lose the fear of
death. Because if you're afraid
of death. You just have your
whole cosmology upside down. You
just don't understand what's
going on. You know, death is the
great death is graduation. Death
is the great respite. Death is
the great reward. So we're
coming into this, this period of
deep transformation, of living
out of bliss, living out of joy,
exploring out of bliss and joy.
And I think you're right, it's
going to take us a long time to
experience the levels and levels
of creativity that can come out
of that. So the divine project
has brought us to this crisis,
the evolutionary, natural.
Right, however you want to
envision, the Dow project has
brought us to this crisis. Is
taking us through it. We're not
doing it. I mean, this is much
larger than you or I, or any
individual collection of people.
Nature is driving us through
this metamorphosis. Nature has
just decided we're ready, we're
time. We're going through this
thing, new platform, new
beginning, but it's not going to
stop. We're here for another
million years. We're here for
another billion years. So I
think we should really look
deeply at understanding that
we're not only talking about a
kind of new humanity as we can
imagine it. Now, from our
limited position, we're talking
about a new humanity beyond our
capacity to imagine, because it
is so different. One of the
things that happened at the very
the last vision I was given the
last session, is the session
that I call diamond vision,
because in the session, I was
given a 10 minute experience of
being able to see 1000 times
more clearly, more precisely,
more exactly, with More
discrimination that I'd ever
been able to see before wasn't a
hallucination, it was just
absolutely I could not imagine
that I had accepted the dull
experience of ordinary vision as
real vision, and when it
disappeared, I realized I had
been given an experience of
seeing the way the future human,
that all future humans will see
it. This isn't just a
transformation of our heart and
a transformation of our mind.
It's a transformation of our
senses, that that our touch and
taste and vision and hearing is
is going to be more and more
refined, more subtle, more
exquisite. The capacity of
consciousness to heal the body,
to keep it on an even keel, to
transform it, the capacity of
consciousness to infuse and lift
the body into ecstatic states of
creativity. I mean, we're just
getting started into actualizing
some of the higher potentials
that are already built into the
human form, but are being
activated by this evolutionary
process setting us on fire. And
then the question becomes, well,
what might lie down the road,
and we can loath ourselves and
maybe projections and fantasies
about that. But the the only
thing that's really important is
to understand, I think, the high
stakes of what's involved here.
We're not trying to simply fix
or heal humanity. We are on the
threshold of birthing a
different order of human
existence, which is going to
become the new platform for yet
still more higher orders of
human existence. This is a
hugely significant undertaking
that we are about. It's not
simply trying to rectify a short
term pass. It's a cascading
effect into a very, very
different future. It's a very
high stakes game with very, very
great rewards that are coming in
this time. If our nature is
truly infinite, as I think we
agree it is, if Brahman and
Brahman is Atman, the essence of
the individual is the essence of
the Divine, our nature is
infinite, then reincarnation
gives us an infinite amount of
time in order to unfold and To
activate our infinite nature. I
think if we qualify it
carefully, we are learning to be
Gods. We are learning how to
create on a scale that we've
never envisioned, except in in
our mythologies or in our
science fiction mythologies.
Richard Rudd: Yeah, so true, so
true. And one of the things that
I have seen, and my way of
describing that mythology is,
you know, we are, you know, and
I'm not the first person to
explore this, you know, it's
these different species or
races, or, you know, that are
kind of evolving on our planet.
And we've been through these
before, actually, you know, so,
so, and we're part of a much
deeper epoch story than we
realize. And we may have even
forgotten previous epochs, and
because of the break in
continuity between epochs is so
massive, you know, so. Yeah, but
each time we go through one of
these portals, we include and
transcend more of we remember
more of what came before. So I
feel that's also potential that
we remember more of what came
before as we move into what
we're becoming. And in a way,
from my understanding, is that
this is almost like the, the
final stage, or cresting of
humanity's epoch, you know, and
I because it's, it's It then
moves into, you know, the the
culmination of this next since
we're looking far, far, far, far
ahead, the culmination of this
next species, you know, is our
collective harmony with the
whole of Gaia. You know, it's
coming into absolute harmony
with the entirety of Gaia. So,
so taking our highest seat as
the consciousness of Gaia, and
as the the gardeners of Gaia, as
the stewards of Gaia, you know,
as as inseparable from the
tiniest ant. And, you know, like
everything being part of our
highest, you know, capacity here
and the beauty of Gaia. So we
haven't yet seen, you know,
maybe at the very beginning, you
know, we haven't yet seen Gaia,
you know, as a in her flowered
flowering state, fully
flowering, you know, with all
her essences, just released in
perfect harmony, and us being
able to move through the garden
and sup the nectars of
everything here, all of that,
and each animal and each
creature and each having their
place, and you know within us,
you know, because they have a
place within us. We are, you
know, there's no separate
separation anymore. And so
there's this incredible
crystallization of the harmony
of all the architecture of life
on Gaia. And my feeling is that
this next phase of our evolution
is about the weaving together of
Gaia, you know, of all those
creatures and things and
understand. So every one of us
has a specific weaving role in
that to weave back together
certain neurological pathways
that are unique to us that only
we could weave because only our
creativity wants to go there. So
we follow our creativity, and it
weaves together some aspect of
Gaia, and then all of us
together, doing that creates
this beautiful tapestry of
wholeness. And the other aspect
to this that I've seen is, as
the process continues, there's a
timeline. It's straight strange,
you know? It's almost like a
spiral, the arc of time. And as
we get closer and closer towards
perfection, the timeline closes
in on itself more and more and
more so, in a way, time itself
is being condensed. And when you
get to that final, this is a
lovely joke, when you get to
that final crystallization point
of perfection, time itself
dissolves. It's it's so in a
way, my joke is that when you
finally get to heaven, it stops.
Everything stops. It's like it's
finished. It's like there's no
it would look like, from our
vantage like, well, there's no
time to enjoy it, but actually
there's infinite time. So that's
when humanity finally
Transcendence, humanity, you
know, and and then there's
another one of those epoch
shifts in which you know and
it's beyond our comprehension.
You might even say, we then
leave this sphere, you know, our
consciousness then moves to
another sphere we're, you know,
and Gaia is left with, you know,
she's not left alone, because
it's a chain, right? So now the
animals start to kind of
crystallize, and their their
evolution starts to continue and
flow. So, so everything ratchets
up, and that even the rocks and
the minerals are kind of moving
up a layer. Everything is
interconnected. So consciousness
is is is embedded in everything,
but it, it awakens in these
layers, in these contractions,
and then we move somewhere else,
somewhere, you know, somewhere
else. We're beyond the time,
space continuum that we've
graduated from, this chain of
evolution, this epoch, you know,
and then we suddenly were in
this, ah, we realize we're,
we're nested as part of
something far wider, because
we've remembered, oh, we're
galactic, you know, guy was just
like our playground, our it was
just that was another birth, you
know, and then we're in a
galactic world. And so it goes
on, and so it goes on, and so it
goes on. But that's, you know,
when you go far, far, far ahead.
And like, I know you've been
Chris, you know, you it's so the
the tapestries are so vast that,
you know, but they're fractal,
right? So they're repeated right
down. So when you look at, you
know, it's like Blake saying,
you know, eternity in the in a
grain of sand, in a wildflower,
you know, it's like it's in
everything, the same fractal
patterning is embedded in all at
all levels. So it's just these
waves of wider and wider
awakening and creativity. And
that's, you know, that's where
we're that's where we're going,
and that's where we are, and we
never leave the present moment.
That's the beauty. We never
leave the freedom of the present
moment, even when we're in
crisis, you know? And that's
what's going to become, in a
way, for me, the most important
thing is, as the crisis comes,
we never leave the present
moment, and we never forget
where we're going. You know that
this is all for, for a purpose.
So that is the, you know, when
we have to swallow the pill of
suffering, of intense suffering,
that's the other pill we take.
That kind of the medicine that
reminds us that the suffering
is, is, is it has Grace embedded
in it, yeah,
Chris Bache: I love hearing you
go. When you go, you really go.
And I love because I feel so
deeply resonant with what you're
describing. This earth, this
solar system, is part of a
galaxy which is part of a
Supercluster of galaxies, time
space is part of a universe
which is part of a larger meta
universe, which is part of
another larger universe. We are
going through this very, very
exciting, very important
transformation. Humanity is
going through this tremendous
transformation, and yet there
are other species around the
galaxy going through their own
transformations, and so we don't
have to deny any of that. We can
affirm all of that while also
paying tremendous attention to
what's taking place. How do we
take full advantage of the
growth opportunity that this
time in history is giving us
right here, because my
understanding is we choose our
incarnations, so that everyone
who listens to this video chose
to be in in history, right here,
right now. They chose to be part
of this traumatic moment, this
birth moment, this ecstatic,
exploding moment in history,
they chose to be part of it, and
they are exactly where they
chose to be in order to have the
greatest impact on positive
outcome. That it's not a matter
of searching for what should I
do, or how do I respond? Look
under our feet. We are already
planted. We have the talents, we
have the relationships around
us. We are already where we can
do the most good if we're
willing to take responsibility
and act really do it, and that's
what you're talking about, being
centered in your your we know
when we're centered in our role
in life. We know when we're
centered in our work, even if
we're suffering at that moment.
We have a deep confidence that
this is what we're to do.
There'll be so many distractions
being offered to us to not pay
attention. Distract ourselves
with movies, distract ourselves
with this, that and the other.
It's when things get hard. It's
going to be very inviting to be
elsewhere. But if we are really
here, right here, right now,
putting all of our endeavor into
this moment, that is the fastest
way to move through the harder
part and into the joy, into the
bliss, into the cooperation,
into the collaborations, into
the opportunities for our
individual work to be to meet
with fellows on the journey and
compound into larger and larger
projects We won't get there by
allowing ourselves to be
distracted. We get there by
complete commitment to our
circumstances, where we are as
we are, and I think you're
right, in that deep penetration
of the present, we get glimpses
and touches and tingles of the
whole structure of the meta
universe, which is also pouring
its all of its energy into the
present. We we meet Heaven only
in the present. We meet the
galactic super structure in the
present, in this moment, in this
grand kind of collaboration.
Connection with destiny. So
we've wandered a long way from
our early talking about, well,
what's the evidence for
reincarnation? But it the
communion with the universe is
what drives both of us. I think
you know, the deep communion,
the opportunities for deepening
the communion, for letting go of
all the things that get in our
way, and going into a deep a
deep sharing of the Divine
breath, a deep communion of the
divine joy, to really let it in
as deeply as we can possibly let
it in in the years that we have
remaining, and then our next
incarnation and our next
incarnation. Beautiful.
Richard Rudd: Chris, thank you.
I don't think I could add
anything to that. I think we've
I don't think there's anything
else needs to be said. Is there?
Chris Bache: Well, maybe not
here and now, but certainly in
another time and another place.
Wind it up again, and we'll
launch. I love our discussions.
I love this guys with you. I
love what happens when we get
together.
Richard Rudd: Yeah, me too. And
I think, you know, our various
different communities will
hopefully come together and
explore these things in new and
creative ways. That's certainly,
I think, my intention to
continue this, this dialog in
all kinds of different ways, and
to invite others also into this
dialog, to explore, to create,
to come up with, you know,
proactive creative roots
forwards in the world,
depending, you know, what is
coming to us. And you know,
there's a lot of, the lot of
great genius that's being drawn
to these kinds of discussions
and these communities. And when
the genius comes together, is
capable of so much and and I
know that you know many, many,
many hearts are wanting to come
together and be of service as,
as you said, you know to be be
of the greatest service. So I
think there will be
opportunities for lots of, lots
of things in the times ahead. So
I want to really personally
thank you for being a great
inspiration to me. And why it's
really Yeah, confirming many of
my deep, held knowings and and
kind of matching me along the
journey and, you know, and
sometimes just really pushing me
a little bit further as well. So
I really appreciate that.
Chris Bache: And likewise, it
works both ways. Yeah, much love
and blessings in your work and
just the joy to spend time with
you. It truly is it opens me up.
It invites me forward. I receive
much from our conversations.
Richard Rudd: Likewise,
absolutely you
Unknown: you.