Unknown: A guy I was speaking to
at an integration circle. He
mentioned he had a mystical
experience where he encountered
none other than Ganesh, the
elephant god of Hinduism. After
your journeys, how would you
reflect on sort of the meaning
of encountering, say, a
particular form of a deity or or
something like
Chris Bache: that, when we
experience realities that are
beyond us, or consciousness,
dimensions of consciousness that
are beyond our own. And when
we're tapping into those
qualities that are like infinite
compassion and infinite
intelligence and infinite
creativity, these are qualities
that we tend to associate
historically with various
deities, and it's not surprising
that our mind would put together
the qualities of the
phenomenology of the experience
with the qualities of the
deities which we may or may may
have had experience exposure to
intellectually and sometimes we
counter deities that we haven't
they're not part of our own
personal lineage and may not
have been part of our they may
not have been something even
that we knew about. It comes
completely out of left field,
and yet it bears the form of a
culture's form of this deity
like Ganesh or Jesus or Mary, or
the Prophet Muhammad or
something like that. So my
understanding of it is that when
you are working or when you are
engaging entities or forms that
have this quality of an entity
that is identifiable in our
historical traditions, my sense
is that we are engaging a
collective thought form or a
spiritual being that is wearing
the clothes of a collective
thought form. And by collective
thought form, I mean, if you
have millions and millions of
devotees that meditate and pray
and offer devotions to a
particular deity, form which has
been identified in their
scripture, which is painted in
their culture, statuary is all
of this form. If you have
millions and millions and
millions and millions of being,
over 1000s of years, in
devotional attachment to these
forms, or devotional focus on
these forms. I think it creates
a certain structure in the
collective psyche, a collective
thought form. And I don't
minimize those forms. I think
they're extraordinarily
powerful, including secular
thought forms like greed, power,
anger, those you know, very
powerful in our system. So when
we encounter the deity in a or a
deity in a particular form, we
are either encountering a
spiritual principle which is
beyond form, which is wearing
the form of this collective
garment, or we're experiencing
the collective garment straight
out in itself. Either way, the
collective psyche is implicated.
The collective psyche is part of
our experience which is all
perfectly normal and perfectly
well and good. I think at the
same time, I would hold out that
it is possible to go beyond all
collective thought forms and to
go beyond human history in one's
experience. And when one does,
those forms tend to fade away. I
know there's a lot of discussion
of entities, because
particularly DMT and DMT
derivatives often expose people
to entities. And I'm not
suggesting that those entities
aren't real or the entities
don't exist, but to me,
personally, and again,
limitations, but personally
those entities reflect different
levels of reality, that as you
go deeper those level that that
kind of granular quality of lots
of individual beings tends to
yield to levels of reality which
are less granular, fewer
individual beings, kind of
constituting the population of
those levels of reality and
opening up into vast tracks of
consciousness which are less
individual, less entity, like at
least it is In my experience,
yeah,
Unknown: that definitely seems
to resonate in terms of it being
sort of a matter of levels. And
after seeing sort of where you
go in those levels, it makes a
lot more sense that at some
point, even those dissolve and
become something different.