David Lorimer: A warm welcome,
everybody. I'm tuning in here
from the Cathar area of South
West France. As many of you will
know, my name is David Larimer.
I'm the Program Director of the
scientific and medical network.
So Chris, Chris, I've known
Chris for a long time, and he's
he taught for 33 years at the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, and is also
connected with the CIS
California Institute of integral
studies and Noetic Sciences, and
he's an advisor to the Grof
legacy training, which I'm also
involved in. And he said he
writes here that his passion has
been the study and the
philosophical implications of
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, particularly
psychedelic states. And I'd like
to add a plug, as it were, for
his book that isn't on this
particular theme, the living
classroom, an exploration of
collective fields of
consciousness and teaching. And
this is particularly fascinating
in terms of the synchronicities
that seem to arise in Chris's
teaching with his students, and
he may refer to that in passing.
So his two books that I've read
and reviewed, this is the
initial one here, Dark Knight,
early door, and I think that's
exactly where we are
collectively at the moment. And
then his book, prize winning
book, LSD, in the mind of the
universe. And many of you will
have read his article in the
current issue of paradigm
Explorer. So Chris, I'm really
looking forward to this
presentation. Very warm welcome
from us, and we can't wait to
hear what you have to say.
Chris Bache: Thank you, David,
let me shift into screen
sharing, if I can do this
correctly. Good. Okay. Well,
thank you David, and thank you
everybody. It's an honor and a
pleasure to be here with you
tonight, and I really look
forward to sharing with you the
experiences that I'm reporting
in this book, LSD and the mind
of the universe. Now David has
framed our conversation this
evening as a question of whether
we can all participate, all
access the cosmic mind, I'm
assuming, using psychedelics.
Well, I believe that we all can,
but whether we all should is
another matter entirely. In
contrast to the early idea that
psychedelics represent a
shortcut to mystical experience.
My concern is that the
psychedelic journey into the
Cosmic Mind is extremely
demanding and must be approached
with great care and caution. In
LSD, in the mind of the
universe, I try to describe as
clearly and carefully as I can,
experiences that opened in 73
high dose LSD sessions conducted
over 20 years when I was a young
man between 30 and 50 years old.
And this was 1979 to 1999 I
spent another 20 years thinking
about these experiences,
digesting them, mapping them,
and pondering their
implications. I hope that the
visions that I brought back from
this journey will be useful, not
only to other Psychonauts, but
also to those who would never
take a psychedelic themselves.
Because what's important here is
the vision of the cosmos that
they contain, and a vision of
where humanity is in its long
evolutionary journey and the
turning point that we're coming
to now I want to say up front
before we begin that I'm not
sure that what I did was wise. I
pushed myself very hard on this
journey, harder than was
sometimes good for me, and I
sincerely do not recommend this
protocol to others. If I were
starting this journey over
again, I would be gentler with
myself. I would work with lower
doses and gentler psychedelics,
but I made it through intact,
and I would not have missed it
for the world. I also want to
say that I know that what I'm
presenting tonight is a radical
story. I know it raises many
questions that we won't get to
speak about tonight, about the
reality of these experiences,
about how this path compares to
other spiritual paths. But this
radical nature is inescapable. I
believe that psychedelics
represent a genuine turning
point in philosophy. A true
before and after advance. They
give us more than new insights
into consciousness and more than
a new therapeutic method for
healing the wounds of the
personal psyche. As important as
these things are, the critical
use of psychedelics gives us a
new philosophical method that
has two parts, first, immersing
ourselves into temporary states
of hyper aroused consciousness,
and second, stepping back and
critically analyzing our
experiences there by moving back
and forth between non ordinary
and ordinary states of
consciousness, we can gather and
distill new insights into the
structure of reality. Now, of
course, this method is not
really new, is it? It was
present in the Eleusinian
Mysteries of ancient Greece and
in the Ayahuasca ceremonies of
Brazil that date back 1000
years, but they are new to us,
new to our scientific culture,
and that's the point we are
witnessing, I think, the
emergence of a true psychedelic
philosophy. So let's begin my
psychedelic lineage is rooted in
the work of Stanislav Grof. I
was a brand new faculty member
in 1978 when I first read his
book, realms of the human
unconscious, and my life pivoted
that was followed quickly by his
book LSD psychotherapy in 1980
in which he laid out the method
for working with these
substances. Now, Stan has
demonstrated that LSD is a non
specific amplifier and catalyst
of consciousness. It does not
give us specific experiences.
Rather, it hyper sensitizes
one's consciousness for six to
eight hours at a time.
Everything that follows hinges
on how we use these hours. Now.
Stan's work clearly
differentiates two different
therapeutic modalities,
psycholytic therapy, low dose
therapy and psychedelic therapy,
high dose therapy, in
psycholytic therapy, the mind is
peeled away layer by layer,
uncovering the different layers
of our shadow and taking us back
deeper and deeper into our
unconscious. In psychedelic
therapy, this is a very
different protocol. It was
developed and used at Spring
Grove Hospital. It was limited
to three sessions maximum, and
it was designed to trigger a
near death type experiences
among patients who were
terminally ill. Well, I thought
if you could use this therapy of
hyad Working with high doses
safely three times. You could
use it working safely more than
three times. So during the years
I was doing this work, I simply
saw myself as doing an extended
course of psychedelic therapy.
But when I came to the end of
this journey and was looking
back over its length, I came to
appreciate how radical this
undertaking had actually been.
This went beyond psychedelic
therapy as it was originally
conceived and practiced, and
therefore it called for a new
term to avoid confusion, and so
I've named it psychedelic
exploration. Now I worked at 500
to 600 micrograms. This is a
very high dose level. The method
is the method of psychedelic
therapy, complete isolation and
complete protection from the
outside world, trusting your
care to a sitter, wearing eyes
shades and working with very
carefully chosen music to pace
the opening and closing of your
session. The difference is the
high number of sessions, in my
case, 73 times. Now I think that
the stabilization of the
protocol and minimizing the
variables that I followed in my
session contributed to the
stability and clarity of the
psychedelic window that opened
in my sessions. I always
followed the same protocol, the
same set and setting, the same
sitter, who was my former wife,
my wife at the time, Carol, who
is a clinical psychologist, the
same substance, the same dose
level, even the same location
and the same recording process.
I think this provided a very
stable reception platform that
allowed my sessions to develop
clean. Clearly over time. Now I
did this work as rigorously as I
could. I kept detailed records,
making an exhaustive,
descriptive account within 24
hours of each session, I tracked
the dates, and that's Rick
Tarnas is a good friend of mine,
and I've learned, as we've all
read his book, psyche and
Cosmos, I track the astrological
variables to see what the
interplay was between my
experiences and the astrological
transits. I want to emphasize
that the story that I'm telling
in LSD, in the mind of the
universe, is not primarily a
personal story. It's primarily a
cosmological story. The personal
is the least important in my
experiences. After the first 10
sessions or so, the portion of
the experiences that were
relevant to my personal life
tended to come up in the
beginning and endings of the
sessions represented by these
small circles that are drawn at
the beginning and endings of the
sine waves, which represent
psychedelic sessions. When I was
coming back, leaving and coming
back into space time, I often
had many insights and many gifts
given me about my personal life.
But when I was in the peak hours
of psychedelic arousal, I was at
the top of these waves and
experiencing. I was having
experiences that far transcended
my personal life as represented
in these larger circles. And
that's the story I'm telling in
LSD, in the mind of the
universe, that's the
philosophically interesting
story that is the universal
story. And it's a story which is
basically telling the
developmental sequence of
experiences over these hilltop
perspectives.
Now there are many ways in which
you can use psychedelics. Let me
identify three uses. First is
using it in a to for therapeutic
healing, to heal the wounds of
our personal psyche. This is the
dominant form in which
psychedelics are being used and
studied today. Second is to use
them for spiritual awakening to
cultivate that radical,
transparent condition of our
being in which we stand
completely conscious, completely
naked and completely receptive
to the ever changing field of
experience. The third usage is
cosmological exploration. These
are distinct, if mutually
reinforcing, undertakings, how
you use psychedelics, dose
levels, circumstances, set and
setting are different in each of
these settings, and I think it's
important to make sure that we
don't judge one project by
criteria that are relevant to
another project. Okay. Now, in
these experiences, when one
works with very high doses of
LSD, one goes through a series
of Death-Rebirth experiences. In
this image, the drop at the
center, underneath the line
represents our egoic
consciousness, our private
consciousness. Everything above
the line represents spiritual
reality, Transpersonal
consciousness, the first
Death-Rebirth experience, takes
place at the interface of our
time, space consciousness and
the beginnings of spiritual
consciousness. And it's usually
referred to as ego death. It is
the complete destruction of our
personal time, space identity,
and the beginning of an opening
into spiritual reality. But if
we continue this process, if we
press deeper and deeper into
spiritual reality, we go through
more deaths, more cycles of
death and rebirth at the
psychic, subtle and causal
levels of consciousness. To use
terms that Stan uses. Now I have
no vested interest in a
particular cosmological map that
delineates the various strata,
strata of Transpersonal
consciousness. Here, I'm simply
trying to make a point that as
you go into deeper levels of
consciousness, you come to
certain gateways, and at these
gateways, you must give up
everything, everything you have
known up to this point in time,
in your journey, in order to
enter into the new fields of
consciousness that are beginning
to open to you. Now, one does
not simply enter into spiritual
reality and pluck these
experiences from the universe
like one plucks an apple. A tree
drawing on Jorge Farrah's
insights in his wonderful book,
revisiting Transpersonal theory,
I hold that all psychedelic
experience is participatory.
This means that our being evokes
in complex ways that portion of
the universe that we encounter
our mind acts as a seed crystal
that catalyzes a certain set of
experiences from the cosmic
mind's infinite potential. As we
are gradually purified and
transformed by this process, it
evokes still deeper experiences
from the universe. In my
experience, one session more or
less started where the previous
session stopped, there was a
gradual and consistent unfolding
into deeper and deeper levels of
reality. This may not be true in
other people's experiences. It
simply is true. Let me give you
a different image for this
process. LSD is often likened to
the atomic bomb, which was
invented in the same decade.
Here I'm using the nuclear
explosion as an image of the
type of come bus combustive fire
that is generated in a long
series of sessions, that
generates this cycle of death
and rebirth. And as this cycle
continues, it activates and
brings into our conscious
awareness deeper levels of the
of the universe, just as this
nuclear explosion brings into
visible form different levels of
the atmosphere there were always
there from the beginning, but
were basically hidden and
invisible. And it is the power
of the psychedelic dynamic that
brings these dimensions of
existence into our into our
conscious awareness. Now we're
not talking about nuclear
explosions. We're talking about
an exploration into the mind of
the universe, an exploration
into the cosmic mind. When I was
at the end of my journey, and
looking back over its length,
identified different strata,
different layers that I had
entered systematically over the
course of these 20 years. And I
would count five of them, the
first having to do with my
personal mind. The second having
to do with collective mind, the
mind of our species. The third,
having to do with archetypal
mind. The fourth, causal
oneness, and the fifth, diamond
Luminosity. So what I'd like to
do now is simply take you into
the book, chapter by chapter,
with just a few highlighted
comments of the content of each
chapter, just to illustrate,
just to invite you into into the
dialog that you will find
unfolded in LSD, in the mind of
the universe. So first the
personal mind. There is the
chapter crossing the boundary of
birth and death. This refers to
crossing what Stan calls the
perinatal level of
consciousness. Now there is a
previous chapter, the chapter on
methodology, where I lay out the
method of the work. Then there
is a chapter three in which I
basically take the reader into a
typical session day to show them
what it's like. But content
wise, we begin here. Now, if
you're familiar with Stan Grof
work, and I'm assuming most of
you are this is classic
perinatal material, deep
confrontations with death and
fetal sensations, severe
existential confrontations,
tremendous perinatal seizures,
purifying the body and the
emotional field, culminating an
ego death. And in ego death, our
identity, our time, space,
identity, is just turned inside
out. In my case, my ego death, I
was forced to become the exact
opposite of everything I had
ever known myself to be. The
Universe just reached down and
snapped me like a trick a twig
in the beginning of the day, I
had always known myself as being
male, as being an intellectual,
being college educated, and
being passionately interested in
the meaning of life. In this
session, I was forced to become.
Complete opposite of all these
things, and it was as if the
universe was telling me where
you are going. Gender does not
exist. I had to let go of
everything I was in order to go
into what was coming next. And
what was coming next really
surprised me in what I later
came to call the exercises of
collective death and rebirth and
first, the ocean of suffering.
Over the course of two years, I
was repeatedly and
systematically immersed in
experiences of collective
anguish that shattered all my
frames of reference and
completely dwarfing the previous
phase I entered a notion of
suffering that eventually
expanded systematically to
encompass what appeared to be
the entire history of the human
species. The dying in these
sessions was almost entirely
collective. The surrender that
was demanded was the ordeal of
repeatedly opening to the sheer
enormity and savagery, savagery
of this ocean of pain. Now
first, I thought this
represented a deepening of ego
death, but it went on for so
long and it involved so many
beings that eventually I changed
my mind. I came to the
conclusion that these collective
episodes were not primarily
aimed at the transformation of
my personal consciousness. They
were aimed at healing some
portion of the collective
unconscious of humanity, healing
scars accumulated through
history and still carried in our
collective memory.
Now, in my experience, in a
session, there are essentially
two phases. There is the first
phase, the cleansing phase,
purification phase, and the
second phase, the ecstatic
phase, the ocean of suffering, I
said, lasted two years.
Actually, it lasted one year,
and then I took a six year
break, and then it I started
again, and the ocean of
suffering resumed in that first
year, when I went into the
ecstatic phase of the sessions,
I entered what I came to call
deep time in the chapter, deep
time in the soul, when I would
come out of the ocean of
suffering, I entered a state in
which these seven sessions gave
me an experience of my life as a
completed whole, as a totality,
from beginning to end, the
visions were stable and
systematically developed. Each
session built upon the previous
session. The sessions, their
sequences were repeated,
unfolding in greater detail and
with deepening emphasis. Now, I
found that it was an
extraordinary challenge to hold
on to these experiences of deep
time. The first time I came back
from deep time, the experiences
which had been the most
meaningful experiences of my
life. At that point in time, I
could not hold on to them. My
mind had no hope to place that
with repetition, when I would go
back to the same state of
consciousness again and again, I
was able to hold on to more and
more of the experiences. And
this is an important
epistemological point. You have
to train yourself to stay
conscious in these deep states
of consciousness, you have to
undergo a rigorous, systematic
commitment to learning how to
stay awake in states of
consciousness that, in the
beginning, completely swallow
you a pole, but if you practice
you can maintain epistemological
clarity in these states. So
during this year, I had many
teachings about reincarnation,
about karmic cause and effect,
and the deeper intentionality
operating in life. And then I
stopped my work for six years
for reasons that I describe in
the book. When I resumed six
years later, the ocean of
suffering started exactly where
it had stopped before, and
continued to build in intensity
over the remaining year, seven
more sessions in a different
time of my life with different
expectations and under different
astrological transits, the ocean
of suffering began exactly where
it had stopped, which I think
reflects the depth and power of
the intelligence. And
consciousness that is directing
these episodes, certainly not my
intelligence, something larger
than my intelligence. When I
went into the ecstatic portion
of these sessions, I entered a
completely different reality
than deep time in the soul. I
entered, in a sense, what I came
to call an initiation into the
universe. It did involve
transcending time in different
ways, but I was given a
systematic series of initiations
into the universe and into the
creative intelligence behind the
physical universe. The sequence
was deliberate and well crafted.
It felt like an infinite
intelligence was educating me,
reminding me of things long ago
forgotten, but now in need of
being remembered. Now little
note I give my psychedelic
sessions names. I take detailed
notes, I break them down into
bullet points, and I give them
names, because my intention is
to try to hold all of my
experiences in my mind at the
same time. And so when I see the
name of the session, it reminds
me of the content of the
session. So the names of the
sessions that I address in this
chapter are this. We don't have
time for me to go into these
sessions beyond what I've
already said. The name suggests
some of the content. It was just
an extraordinary philosophical
adventure being taken by what
appeared to be the creative
intelligence of the universe,
deeper and deeper into the
mysteries of creation and deeper
into humanity's destiny. When
the ocean of suffering came to a
culmination in this session 24
healing the collective wound. I
was spun into archetypal reality
in the chapter the greater real
of archetypal reality. Let me
see if I can there we go. This
lasted one and a half years and
11 sessions. It I was entering a
reality that immediately and
consistently was more real felt
more real than physical reality.
It was a domain behind physical
reality and the source of the
structures that exist inside
space and time. When I first
entered archetypal reality, my
identity as a human being began
to fall away from me. I learned
that we have a sense of a sense
of species identity that is more
basic than our individual
identity, and surrendering this
species identity represented a
deeper form of surrender and a
deeper death than ego. Death to
die out of human consciousness
was to begin to exist in a
domain of consciousness
completely beyond the human
species field. This transition
was marked with extremely high
levels of energy. I was plunged
into white hot lava flows,
exploding Sun fare flares,
liquid fire pouring through me,
completely consuming me, very
different from the death that I
had gone through in the
perinatal level of
consciousness, my experiences in
archetypal reality, basically
could be broken down into two
categories, two levels, one at
the highest subtle level and one
at the lower subtle level, at
the higher subtle level, which I
would call the Platonic level, I
encountered living forms
responsible for creating space
time and the core structures
within space time, they were too
vast for me to grasp. Even in my
expanded psychedelic state, I
could catch only glimpses of
them. I saw them as galaxies,
billions of light years across
massive structures, but this was
simply the best my mind could do
to wrap itself around the
realities that I was
experiencing. These were
archetypes, but not Plato's
eternal ideas in the mind of an
unchanging God, but vast living
dynamic forces embodying higher
orders of intentionality and
power and operating on a
different order of time
entirely, at the lower, subtle
level, at a. More Jung Ian
level, I was immersed in the
living tissue of our species
through a long series of
experiences. I was repeatedly
experiencing our species as a
single organism interlaced with
an intelligent network of meta
functions. I experienced all of
our individual minds as nodal
points within the collective
mind. I experienced all the
issues that we confront in our
life, both psychological issues
and biological issues, as all
part of a larger living tapestry
of cause and effect weaving
throughout the entire species, I
experienced our collect our
individual bodies as cells
within our larger collective
body,
and I began to have experiences
of reincarnation as a collective
process. Up to this point in
time, I had already experienced
reincarnation, or thought about
reincarnation in terms of a
personal, soul generated process
and that and it was about our
individual evolution and
confronting individual karma.
But I had many experiences
during this time of our entire
species, reincarnating with
Common Cause, I began to
experience billions of human
beings incarnating over and over
again, and driving the evolution
of our entire species forward. I
was given many insights into
into the dynamics of collective
purification and collective
transformation. And this is why,
in my book, Dark Night early
dawn, the fundamental theme of
that book has to do with the
processes, the dynamics of
collective transformation. Dark
Night early dawn is about the
collective dark night and the
early dawn is about our
collective transformation and
history. This was simultaneously
a Numinous, Numinous experience
and a devastating experience to
experience billions of lives as
cells within an organism that
was evolving itself on the face
of our planet was just a
devastating experience and an
ecstatic experience. Now the
titles of the essay, of the
sessions that I address in this
chapter are these.
You can see how much cleansing
is involved, even at this rather
advanced level. And this
reflects an important truth.
Deeper levels of reality are
higher levels of energy, and
when one wants to enter, if you
want to enter and stabilize your
consciousness at these deeper
levels of reality, you must
adapt to and adjust to this
energy. It's like mountain
climbing. When you climb a
mountain, you're adapt. You're
adjusting to less oxygen. When
you're working through deeper
levels of consciousness, you're
adjusting to more energy. You
must literally become a being
who can sustain these high
levels of energy for eight hours
at a time. Session 28 was my
first and brief contact with
causal level reality. It was an
exceptionally clear, dramatic
and beautiful session, but just
touching the purity of causal
level reality was so intense
that it triggered hours and
hours of cleansing that lasted
over three sessions stretched
over six months. The cleansing
was some type of purification
process that was making it
possible for me to return to
this level of reality, but to
maintain coherent cognitive
focus at this deep level, which
then led to a rather startling
experience, the flash of God in
session 33 after this, I entered
an extraordinary year of
immersion in causal oneness, in
a chapter that I call a
benediction of blessings. It
lasted one year and eight
sessions. So after spending 18
months exploring archetypal
reality, which, of course, is
very quickly, I mean, I just was
moving through this material,
just touching base, just moving
through very quickly the year.
That followed was one of extra
ordinary blessings. It was a
veritable benediction of
blessings as I entered the great
depth of causal reality. And
these are the names of the
sessions that I address in the
book. These were preceded by
more experiences of death and
more experiences of fierce
purification. The forest was an
experience of causal oneness, of
Shunyata, emptiness of self, no
self in me, no self in any
other. Just as sun and sun and
air moves through in a forest
without paying any attention to
the particular type of tree that
it's moving through. Singing the
universe away was an experience
of the primal void that lies
beneath our universe and gives
birth to it, day by day, second
by second. Jesus's blood was an
experience of cosmic love, the
most intense experience of love
that I had ever known in my
life, and then the birth of the
diamond soul. And let me mention
something about this, just very
briefly, because it it's really
a pivotal was a pivotal session
for me, and it comes up later in
the book. Previously I had
experienced my life as a
completed whole. Now, 11 years
later, I experienced all of my
former lives being rewound, one
by one, coming together and
being rewound like winding kite
string on a spool until
eventually, the spool exploded
in a burst of light, fusing all
the strands together and giving
birth to what I came to call the
diamond soul. The diamond soul
was composed of many lifetimes,
but it was more than the sum of
all their years. This experience
showed me. I think where
reincarnation is taking us. It
would take us too long to go
into in great detail, but
basically, I think the visions
of reincarnation that we have
lived with over the last 2000
years are are incomplete. They
haven't they have a vision of
that we're we're growing
incrementally, lifetime by
lifetime, becoming more knowing
more becoming more
compassionate, becoming more
intelligent, incremental
adjustments. But I think that
there is more at foot underneath
this process. Eventually we
there comes a time through the
constant expansion and
contraction, through dying and
returning to the soul and being
born and contracting into the
ego and buying in the soul and
coming back into the ego.
Eventually, there comes a time,
I believe, where all of our
former lives come together as
one, and when they come together
as one, they catapult us into a
condition of being which is not
simply a refined and purified
future life. It is a being
catapulted into a different
order of life, a different order
of being itself. I think what is
happening over the long story of
reincarnation is that the soul
is being born inside time and
space. This is what I call the
birth of the diamond soul. Now
from here, I went into the
diamond Luminosity work. Now
notice I've skipped chapter
nine. I wish I had actually
written these in a different
order. I wish I had had 10
before chapter nine. But I'm
going to skip over nine for the
moment, because the work went
into the diamond Luminosity
material. The benediction of
blessings felt like the closing
of a great circle. It gave me a
feeling of deep completion, a
sense of inheriting blessings
for work done in the ocean of
suffering. I had given something
to the universe that was mine to
give, and the universe had given
me back more treasures than I
could hold. I felt complete and
utterly satisfied. I had no idea
where the sessions would go
next, but there was still five
years ahead,
after going through yet one more
intense cycle of death and
rebirth, I was spun into a
brilliantly clear radiance that
Buddhism calls Dharmakaya. I
came to call it the domain of
diamond Luminosity. Now, I had
known light many times before,
but this. Was an exceptionally
pure light. This domain
captivated me so completely that
it extinguished any interest I
had in exploring the other
levels of existence that had
previously fascinated me. This
was a different order of reality
altogether. Its clarity was so
overwhelming, its energy so pure
that returning to it became my
sole focus in future sessions
over the next four years and 26
sessions, the diamond Luminosity
domain opened to me only four
times, and these are the four
sessions that I describe, that I
present in this chapter.
My understanding is that the
diamond Luminosity is an extra
Samsara reality that is, it lies
outside the Bardo, outside of
Samsara, outside all the cycles
of physical reality and the
Bardo realities of psychic
reality, the pure light. It is
the pure light from which the
universe arises and returns. It
is Dharmakaya, the clear light
of absolute reality. Now, in
between these four Immersions in
Diamond Luminosity, there were
many intense episodes of
cleansing and personal healing
in general, there were two
movements during this four year
period. There was first a
movement of going deeper into
diamond Luminosity, and then a
movement to diamond Luminosity
began to crunch itself more
deeply into my physical body.
And the turning point for this
was session 50. I only began to
understand what was happening
after the fact. Always, I had no
control over what was happening
in the sessions I had basically
went along with whatever the
universe was, wherever it was
taking me, and only figured out
after the fact what was taking
place. In Session 50, I was as
deep into the universe as I ever
went. In any of my sessions, I
was in the clearest, most
sublime state of diamond
Luminosity that I had ever
known. And then in that session,
everything in my visual field
pivoted 90 degrees, and I saw a
reality far into the distance
that looked like luminous
galaxies, and a ray of light
from that reality hit me, and it
absolutely shattered me. I call
it the absolute light, just to
give it a name. But what it
showed me is that the universe
that we are exploring in these
deep states of consciousness is
endless. I would never get to
the end of the divine mind. I
would never get to the end of
the cosmic mind, even using this
powerful method of exploration.
This was a turning point in my
thinking, because I had adopted
the belief that I inherited from
other people, that there was an
end point to this journey, that
there was a point that you came
to which represented your
ultimate destination. Some had
described it as oneness with
God, or as the return to the
primal void. But I had
experienced one oneness with God
many times, and what I learned
is that there are many
permutations and degrees of
oneness. And I had entered in
the primal void several times,
and I learned that there, too,
there are degrees of void. When
I first entered the diamond
Luminosity. It came. It brought
such a feeling of Homecoming,
such a feeling of absolute peace
and contentment. I thought that
I had finally found what I was
looking for. I had finally found
my ultimate destination. And
then practically I did. It
completely satisfied all my
philosophical and spiritual
longing. But just at the peak of
this satisfaction, the universe
showed me that it is an Infinite
Journey. It is an infinite being
that we are exploring in our
lives. This both first shattered
me and then relaxed me into
infinite wonder. And this is one
of the reasons why I would be
gentler with myself if I were
doing this today, because one of
the things I've learned on this
journey is that the goal is not
to get somewhere, to get to a
particular state of
consciousness or particular
state of being. The goal of
this. Work, I think, is to open
up to the universe and let as
much of it as possible into your
being, to let as much of the
love and as much of the
intelligence and as much of the
power and consciousness into
your being and stabilize it and
hold it and live your life,
living by its truths. After this
session 50, the next sessions
really seemed to take me into
the diamond light, but the
diamond light was crunching
itself deeper and deeper into my
body, changing even what I think
of as the physiological
structure, the cellular
structure of my body. And now to
the chapter I skipped over the
birth of the future human. When
I began this work in 1979 I
never imagined that humanity's
future would become part of this
story, but now I think this may
be the most important chapter of
the book, because it speaks of
our children and our children's
children, as far as we can see,
it speaks of a crossroads
humanity is coming too, and of
powerful forces taking us into a
future that will change us at
the deepest levels of our being.
In this chapter, I summarize
bits and pieces of experiences
and visions that actually go all
the way back to the initiation
into the universe material and
run all the way through up into
session 55 these are the
sessions that I discuss, that I
present in this chapter here. I
collect the pieces of visions. I
extract them from sessions 23 to
47 and gather them together in
what I call the visions of
awakening, there are six visions
of awakening. Are six themes
that kept showing themselves
over and over in these visions
concerning humanity's future.
The themes of those six visions
are divine love all humanity
that the universe is trying to
awaken all humanity that is
being enacted by guiding
intelligence that's guiding our
evolutionary process, our
species as a single being, again
seeing the awakening as not
simply a number of individuals
awakening, but our entire
species going through the
awakening process, the theme of
collective purification, again,
through the dynamics of
reincarnation, that we are
undergoing a collective
purification, and finally, the
experience of the future human
being given the grace of
experiencing the future human
that is being born in history.
But nowhere in these visions
over these four years, nowhere
in these visions was it shown me
how this was going to take
place. The vision was that we
were coming into a period of
profound spiritual awakening, a
shift in the fundamental
architecture of the collective
psyche, a shift that will change
the foundation of human
existence on this planet. But it
had not shown me how. And then
in session 55 right in the
middle of the diamond Luminosity
sessions, I was taken deep into
deep time, and I was given an
experience of the death and
rebirth of humanity, well, of
the death and rebirth of
humanity, for there to be a
great awakening in the human
heart, in our collective human
heart, there must first take
place a great death. We must be
emptied of the old before the
new can fully emerge. I believe
that the 21st Century will be
such a time. It will begin the
dark night of our collective
soul, a time of emptying, of
intense anguish, of loss of
control and breakdown, a
collective purification unto
death that will last
generations. But through this
hard labor, we will give birth
to something extraordinary, more
than just a new civilization.
What is emerging is nothing less
than a new order of human being
through the global systems
crisis, our planet is giving
birth. Us to the future human
and when I first described these
themes in dark night, early
dawn, it sounds quite
appropriate for our times that
we are living in now. But I
would just remind you that these
visions were taking place in the
early 90s. The Great Awakening
session took place in 1995 25
years ago. At that time, it was
completely beyond my purview
that we were going into such an
enormous watershed moment in
history,
in my visions concerning the
human where humanity is, it was
as though the transformation of
humanity as a whole was the only
thing that creative intelligence
really cared about. Everything
else, my life, our lives,
everything we are struggling
with in history, was part of
this larger project. It was the
context that framed all of our
endeavors. It was the work of
the hour. Now my visions did not
give me any details of when and
where, so don't ask. It showed
me the fact of this collective
awakening. It took me into the
collective psyches experience of
this death and rebirth, and it
gave me insights into the
mechanisms of our collective
transformation. There's probably
not time here to discuss these
mechanisms, though I think
they're really important, and it
has to do two things with the
unified field, that the
collective species mind is
underneath all of our individual
experiences, and the perception
that then the enormous suffering
that is being that will be
generated by a global ecological
crisis leading to a global
systems crisis. This suffering
will impact not just
individuals, but it will
actually stimulate the
collective psyche so deeply
it'll shift the collective
psyche into what we would call
nonlinear conditions. And we
know something about non linear
systems from physical systems
when they are shoved into non
linear states. And there is a
parallel between what can happen
to a psychic system, a field of
psychological energy, and what
happens to physical systems when
they are both shoved into non
linear conditions, heightened
creativity, higher self
organization, the capacity for
rapidly accelerated change and
small inputs leading to enormous
outcomes.
The final vision to bring the
journey to a close, just
touching it very briefly.
Actually, the seven, the three
sessions that I discussed in
this chapter, the final vision,
this was one of the most intense
sessions that I went through
anywhere on my journey. In it
the universe put me through a
strip down that was more violent
and more radical than any strip
down I had ever gone through at
any other time in my journey.
And it did so, I think in order
to catapult me more deeply into
deep time than it ever taken me
before. I won't try to reproduce
or tell you much about that. I
will invite you simply to look
at it in the book itself. It was
the final vision given me as a
capstone to the long story of
where humanity is going. It
showed me things about the
evolutionary process that I have
held dear to my heart ever
since. It showed me things about
our universe, that our universe
is a diamond maker, making
diamond souls, and it cares very
little whether it takes a
million or billion years for us
to interest, for it to produce
the souls that it is creating.
And it gave me my deepest
experience of the future human,
an extraordinary being, just,
just an extraordinary being. The
last chapter is coming off the
mountain. This chapter was the
longest to write, and in it, I
describe two things that I have
struggled with and confronted in
the years after my journey. I
ended
the first I called the deep
sadness I had been given so many
blessings on this journey, I
thought that I could simply step
away and spend the rest of my
life digesting these treasures,
but in the years following my
sessions, I began to experience
a deep existential sadness I had
been taken so deep into the
divine, into the divine expanse,
so many times, that I was
suffering from a loss of
communion with the divine. Once
you have known the joy of
becoming light, once you have
experienced the ecstasy of
dissolving into the crystalline
body of God, life on Earth, can
begin to feel dried up. I found
that I no longer wanted to be
here, and this is similar to
what some people who have near
death episodes experience when
they return here. They are
plunged deeply into the light,
the divine light filled with
overwhelming love, and then
suddenly they're back on Earth
with all the limitations of
earthly experience. It's hard to
make that transition. I knew
that I was every moment immersed
in the body of the Divine. I
knew that she was the root and
the flower of my existence. But
this knowledge did not save me
entirely from the pain of being
separated from the full
intensity of her presence. It
took me about 10 years to become
fully grounded and comfortable
living inside space, time again.
But there was a second factor
contributing to my disharmony,
and this is what I call the
sickness of silence. Because of
our restrictive laws around
psychedelics, I was not allowed
to speak about my experience to
others. I am a natural born
teacher. I love to learn new
things and share that knowledge,
but I was not allowed to teach
from my psychedelic experiences
in the Department of Philosophy
and Religious Studies, I had to
keep silent about the most
philosophically meaningful
experiences of my life. How can
you behold under such
restrictive conditions, over
time, this enforced silence made
me sick inside. Living in a
psychedelic closet is just as
damaging to your soul as living
in any other closet where you
are forced to deny your true
nature, writing LSD in the mind
of the universe, and speaking
openly about my psychedelic
experiences, as I'm speaking to
you tonight, is, is been, has
been part of my personal path to
becoming whole upon this earth
once again, to become in my
Public Life what I have been in
my private life, and in closing,
I'd like to leave you with this
thought. I still have many
questions about what it means to
integrate experiences such as
those that I've been describing
tonight. I think we are still in
the early stages of
understanding how entering such
extreme states of consciousness
is affecting us in the long
term. What does it do to a
person to hold the kind of
memories that I am holding? What
does integration even mean in
this context, how does a time
bound person, a time bound being
exquisitely tuned to the
conditions of space time, absorb
excursions into deep time? How
does a finite being digest our
forays into the infinite? What
is the residual impact of
merging with all of existence
after we have returned to being
just one among many? I am asking
more questions than I have
answers for my life has become a
living experiment in these
matters, with the outcome still
being determined. But I say
again, I would not have missed
this journey for anything in the
world. It has been the
philosophical and spiritual
adventure of a lifetime, and I
take great. Joy and sharing it
with you tonight. Thank you.
David Lorimer: Thank you very
much indeed, Chris. If you could
just stop your screen share.
That would be good. There we go.
My eyes, I'm on. Well, I don't
know how many of you have read
Chris's book or his article and
the earlier book, which I read
20 years ago, dark night or
early dawn, but it's, it's, it's
a pretty shattering experience
to read, let alone go through.
And one of the things that I
felt was that Chris has done
something on our undertaken this
journey on our behalf, so that
we can borrow, in inverted
commas, some of his insights,
which I think are hugely
important for our own
understanding of who we are and
where we're going. And so I just
two, I'm just going to make two
or three observations, then
we're going to have a break and
then come back for back for
questions session. One of the
main questions you can ask
about, what Chris has been
talking about, is, does what he
is conveying here give us access
to the deep structure of
reality, or to the deep, deeper
structures of reality. And this
is something that we ask in the
Galileo commission report, in
which Harold argues in the
affirmative, in other words,
that they do. And this would
correspond to the third bar of
Jeff Kripal, who was with us a
couple of weeks ago. Now, do
these experiences have important
implications for understanding
of consciousness and reality?
Well, my answer would be
absolutely. But obviously,
everybody has to make their draw
their own conclusion, and what
you'll find, what I found is
that I have an extensive
background in near death and
mystical experiences in terms of
the literature, which many other
people on the call also have,
and it's consistent with all
that, but it takes it a bit
further, in fact, a lot, and
it's a kind of Ultimate Gnosis,
or knowing by identification,
and then observation is that we
are clearly living in
apocalyptic time here at one
level or another, and about the
evolutionary prospects and the
birth of the future Human has an
extraordinary resonance, I
think, at this time, and it's
something that Ann bearing was,
he's on the call tonight, who
was referring to last week. And
so it'll be very interesting to
see how people feel about that.
We've got a lot of questions
that have come up already and in
the chat box, but we'll get some
live contributions and so Chris,
wonderful. Thank you very, very
much indeed for sharing that so
lucidly. Paul from Poland, you
have a question?
Unknown: Hello, yes, I'm Hi,
Chris, a very nice presentation.
I mean, you know, whenever you
use the word universe, something
just sticks in me. As an
astronomer, I know galaxies. I
know stars, clusters of
galaxies, vast physical spaces.
That's what universe means to
me. Now, I have a universe in a
very different way, but I doubt.
But again, you know, I question
whether it doesn't see when,
again, when you say, God, I
don't universe, you know the
universe? It's a place where,
well, anyway, it's a long
subject. I think I've asked my
question anyway, if you could
elaborate a little by what you
mean by universe, so that yeah,
Chris Bache: you're absolutely
right, Paul, you've caught me
out on this. I struggle with
language. I struggle with how to
describe some of these realities
that I've entered. I don't like
using the word God. I don't use
it much, but I use it once in a
while, and I don't like using it
because it carries so much
baggage from history, and what
most people mean by God is not
what I mean by God. And so I'll
use the word divine sometimes,
but that's just a bit of a ruse,
because there it comes back to
the same but I'm trying to strip
the concept free of the
historical accumulation. So to
me, I collect pictures of of
galaxies. I collect, collect
pictures of nebulas. And when I,
when I move into meditation
practice, I just will play them
over and over and over again,
because this is my God. This is
my divine and it what I'm
referring to. What my experience
is is not to the outer body of
the Divine, though I was taken
into exploring some of the body
of the universe. But if I were a
physicist, and I would love to
have degrees in physics and go
into these states, because they
this consciousness could have
shown me so much more if I had
degrees in astrophysics and
degrees in quantum theory, just
my mind was not tuned to that
type of knowledge. I'm talking
about the consciousness which is
the the consciousness of the
universe, the consciousness
which has given birth to the
universe. And I'm just scraping
the edges of it. I'm just
touching the pieces of it, my
experience of it is certainly
limited by what I can understand
because, and again, what I would
love to do is have 100 of our
best, brightest, most talented
scientist, artists, social
activists, going into these
states in a systematic fashion.
I mean, can you imagine a
protocol if we had 100 of such
people working one day a month
for two years, what body of
knowledge they would come back
with and would be able to share?
It's never the experience of the
any individual which is
important. It's the experience
of our collective of our
collective genius and our
collective talent as we are
engaged. So I stretch language.
I stretch language. It's as big
as the universe. It's, it's
deeper than time, it's, it's
more intelligent than any
intelligence I can ever been
able to touch inside time and
space and the compassion, which
is the emotion of oneness. It's
when the quantum physicists talk
about, you know, the implicate
order, the oneness that
underlies all manifest
existence, that implicate order
has a wholeness, that when I
touch it, it just explodes me
with love, because love is the
emotion of oneness. But I don't
mean love in an ordinary sense
of love, but it's kind of the
closest approximation I have. So
you're right that I am using
universe in a borrowed fashion,
and I'm using it in an
extrapolated fashion.
David Lorimer: Thank you very
much. I think it's I mean, what?
For those of you who've read the
book, you'll you'll understand
that the or the books that, for
me, the way that you, you
articulate these ineffable
experiences into language gives
me the sense that I'm I'm as
near vicariously as I can get to
that Gnosis, the understanding
from within and in the Galileo
Commission, we talk about
exploring inner space. And so in
that sense, you're a Psychonaut,
obviously, of exploration of
inner space. So thank you very
much for that question. Next
question is from our president,
Professor, Bernard Carr in
London.
Unknown: Bernard, Oh, hi there,
Chris, good to see you, and you
too. First of all, thank you for
well, for taking this, this
cosmic journey, and then for
coming to, coming back to tell
us all about it. It was
absolutely engrossing. I noticed
at one point you said you rather
wish you had a degree in
astrophysics, and then you will
be able to in another way. Well,
I have a degree in astrophysics,
and I rather wish I had a degree
in psychedelics. But my question
really is a follow up to Paul
kind of it's this question about
the use of the word universe,
because there's sort of a
distinction between your
constant references to humanity
as a species, and then your
description in cosmological
terms, Where you know even your
images are from cosmology, and
you said that in some sense that
you that was poetic license. But
on the other hand, it does seem
to me that if you really are
contacting in that greater
reality, that cosmic
consciousness, you really will
be contacting if you like, a
cosmic level of consciousness,
not just the terrestrial level
of consciousness. And if, for
example, one studies the
writings of Buddha, when Buddha
in the vasuti Marga, when he had
his experiences, he was very
explicit in the fact that he was
experiencing realities beyond
the normal terrestrial, you
know, the galactic and the
cosmic and things like that. So
my question was this, although
you're always referring to
humanity, humanity is something
which, by definition, is very
much linked with Planet Earth.
Did you ever feel that actually
what you were encountering was
something on a scale much larger
than humanity? In other words,
that it really was cosmic.
Chris Bache: Yes, absolutely.
And again, I wish I had your
degrees. The universe could have
taught me so much more than but
when I entered in dark, into
archetypal reality, and I said,
I died as a human being, as of
my species identity. From that
point on in the journey my
sessions basically took me
outside of the operational range
of our collective psyche,
outside of human experience,
outside of human history, when I
began to move beyond the
collective psyche, everything
associated and held within the
collective psyche began to fall
away. All our understandings of
God, all our projections of God,
all the the flotsam and jetsam
of history just fell away, and I
moved into these hyper,
increasingly clear, hyper clear
states of consciousness harder
to describe because so
contentless. And I don't think
I, I think we can be very
cavalier about language, and I
and I apologize if I've
contributed to that, but I think
when we talk about universal
mind or cosmic mind. These are
huge, huge concepts, and I would
say that the only part of that
mind that I know and learned
about was the part that it
taught me about. There was a
consciousness which took me in.
There was a consciousness that
taught me, broke me down, count
me, grounded me up into dust,
and took me deeper and deeper
into itself. But even so, I know
I was only experiencing pieces,
aspects, fractal manifestations
of its totality. So my language
peters out at that deep level.
In when I moved into diamond
Luminosity, I had a very clear
perception of moving outside of
Samsara, outside the Bardo, into
a reality that's truly even
outside archetypal reality.
There was a period when I was
born into archetypal reality,
and then there was a process in
which I was born out of
archetypal reality into into a
level of reality which pre
exists before archetypal
reality?
Unknown: Yeah, non physical,
yeah.
Chris Bache: Thank you very
absolutely non physical.
David Lorimer: I'm just going to
take an observation from the
chat from Sri about in your
journeys, did you get a sense of
why we seem to learn only
through pain and suffering the
divine heritage we come from or
must return to? Why was this
path into matter, back back to
into spirit, necessary? And of
course, that's sort of 64,000
and it reminds me of this, which
you will have heard before,
probably, that there are only
two reasons we change,
desperation or inspiration,
where we certainly change, if
we're desperate and we can
preemptively change, perhaps if
we're inspired. I mean, for me,
this is part of the kind of
gnostic myth that we forget, we
fall into darkness, we try and
return to the light, and we
forget who we are. We then have
to try and remember who we are.
We go to sleep. We have to wake
up. It just seems to be how
things are constituted. Is that
your view? Or do you have
another
Chris Bache: I agree with you,
and this is my experience. Is
when I would go deeper and
deeper and deeper into these
levels of reality. I always
experienced it as a remembering.
I was remembering. I was
remembering, and I didn't. I
don't have any sense that in
forgetting that that was a
tragedy, or that was somehow my
mistake, or some cosmic sin, or
some, you know, original sin, it
seemed to be part of the natural
order of things. There is the
greater and there is the lesser.
When we come into the lesser, we
forget, but we have to remember,
everything that we're describing
is constantly changing. It's
constantly evolving. So that I
don't think, I think, I think we
have had a tendency to sort of
freeze our level of evolutionary
maturity and to form judgments
around how we got here, where
we're going and what we're
doing. And we have to let go of
all these sort of fixated
fragments, because the human
being as Sri Aurobindo. Said, is
a transitional being. We are
moving from what we were to what
we are becoming. We are
changing. Life is changing.
Planets are changing. Our
species is changing. We are in
movement. And so why things are
the way they are isn't on isn't
something that we can answer on
an absolute scale. It's
something we can only answer on
an evolving try to answer an
evolving scale. But that, of
course, requires expanding our
time horizon enormously. When a
geologist helps us expand our
time horizon and helps us
understand plate tectonics,
that's extraordinarily exciting,
or when a physicist helps us
understand the evolution of
galaxies, it's extraordinarily
exciting. This is something
similar. We have to expand
beyond our personal
consciousness to to have
something about the
intentionality that's
manifesting itself in this ever
evolving, magnificent universe
that we are part of.
David Lorimer: So we need to
tune into that part of ourselves
that we not take any more
questions. By the way, we need
to tune into that part of
ourselves which knows, as you
said, that we're here. We're
here for the ride. No, fasten
the seat belts, or maybe not
fasten the seat belts. So we, if
we, if we're really centered as
we go through this process, and
then we'll get the guidance we
need, both individually and
collectively. But we need to
listen to that, that guidance,
and we need to enable the new
shoots. And there's so much
creative thinking going on. I
was in a group this afternoon on
the spiritual spirituality and
Education Alliance and and so
there's a huge amount of good
going on that we don't hear
about, except in positive news.
Humanity rising. Thank you.
That's also humanity rising, and
all the ubiquity University. And
so we need to keep ourselves
buoyed up, I think, by by by the
positive things that are going
on, but also, as you say, face
down the negative with with the
kind of courage that you
demonstrated in your journey.
And so I think I thank you on
behalf of us all for the journey
you took and for bringing back
these treasures, these gems that
we can actually appreciate, and
we can appropriate some of these
for our own journey and
understanding just because you
have made that journey. And so I
really salute you for that, that
Odyssey, I mean, you could
translate it into the hero's
journey and just just a point of
information for people. I
mentioned Thomas troward moment
ago. This is a book here which I
would recommend as a good
starter for from Thomas troward.
It's called The Wisdom of Thomas
troward, and it has four of his
main sets of lectures in it. He
was a judge in India, and you
can really get to grips with
this stuff. And so I do
recommend he talked about self
recognition. When the universal
became the particular in us,
then we had to recognize
ourselves back again as the
universal. And so he was
actually talking about these
things in his own way, no 100
years ago. So we're all trying
to catch up with a perennial, as
it were, and live through it. So
everybody on the call. Thank you
so much for coming and being
part of this evening. I hope
you've been inspired by it. I
hope that you've learned
something that you can apply to
your own lives to your own
journey. And and Andrew, thank
you very much for all the
coordination. Jess. Jessica
cornet, thank you for all the
help with the publicity. And
Chris, thank you so much for
sharing that deep wisdom, which
we really all need to take on
board in the the rapids that we
are entering at the moment. So I
look forward to seeing everybody
on a future event. And good
night everybody, and God bless
much love and light to you all.
You.