Unknown: Hi everybody, welcome.
Rachel Fleming: Lovely to see
you wherever you are in the
world, it's a beautiful evening
here in Devon, England, so thank
you so much for joining us
tonight. You could be out in the
sunshine, but it's lovely to see
you. And welcome to anyone who
is watching on the recording,
and I think there will be quite
a few of those. So we are
talking about contemporary
animism tonight. This is a talk
in our contemporary animism
program. We are really delighted
to show you an interview that we
did some time ago with a chap
called Chris Bache Colin. Is
going to introduce him a bit
more in depth, but just to say
that he took part in our
contemporary animism Confluence
back in February, and we just
thought that what he had to say
was just so hopeful at a moment
when we as a species, as a
community of species, are
looking at a fairly dark night
of the soul with all the climate
change news and social crises,
and it just seems that that
Chris's vision is just one of
hope, and we really hope you'll
enjoy it. What we're going to do
tonight is basically play you
the interview. It's quite heady.
I'll just warn you, there's a
lot of talking, and it goes for
about 15 minutes. And what we'd
really like to do is for you to
watch it, to go in and out of it
as you like, and then to stay
with us for 1015, minutes
afterwards, if you're
interested, to and just share
some of your feelings, the stuff
that might have come up for you
as you were watching it, just to
See whether you Yes, you like
it, whether you're excited as
us, or whether it's not for you.
So without further. ADO Colin,
can I, can I ask you to
introduce Chris also, just to,
just to give you the logistics
of Chris, he is a professor of
theology, retired from one of
the American universities, and
he's the author of several
books, all of which are
wonderful. The first one is
about reincarnation. The second
one is called dark night, early
dawn, which was fantastic. And
his most recent one, and the one
that he will be talking about
tonight, describes his research
method, which he'll tell you
more about, called LSD in the
mind of the universe. Colin,
over to you.
Colin Campbell: Thanks, Rachel.
Good evening, everyone. Yeah. I
mean, I don't almost know where
to start, because, well, let me
start by saying this. It was
about, I think, a year ago, a
little more relatively recently,
I stumbled upon the title, dark
night, early dawn. And I was
particularly struck by the
subtitle, which is steps towards
a new ecology of mind. And that
for me, just rang massively, and
I simply had to get a hold of
this book and read it, just
because of that, because,
because that's just such a huge
passion of mine, in the sense
that I think that what we are in
search of in These times and
amid the very particular
conundrums and transformations
and all that we're up against in
both crisis and other terms, as
a human collective, what we're
faced with is a kind of a RE, a
redo of what we conceive of as
our relationship with existence,
with life, with the rest of the
natural world and so on. So the
idea of a new ecology of mine
really appealed to me. And I
must say, I wasn't disappointed
by the book. It really, I think
it's a it's a seminal piece, to
be very honest. I think, you
know, he was saying some really
profound things, and things
which are very close to my heart
as well, in terms of finding
ways into, in an experiential
way, reinvigorating much of what
we've lost over over the i.
During the process of kind of
secularization,
industrialization, globalization
and so on, finding a way of of
re entering, re accessing that
and revivifying it, bring it,
bringing it back into our into
into being, part of our kind of
search for what Being human
means now and here forward, you
know, and I was, you know, for
me, there are lots of ways of,
kind of entering into this, but
of course, the primary way of
exploring into it is to is to
kind of delve deeply into what
it means to be human. And part
of the problem we sit with
presently is that we're so
drastically distracted in the
world that we've created for
ourselves presently. And I mean
by that the primarily the
industrialized world, we're so
distracted, you know, by our
outer concerns that our inner
environment, or what we broadly
refer to as our inner
environment, and what I would
call our pre industrial
ancestry, which, of course, is
dynamically within us, but has
somehow fallen beneath the level
of our everyday interactive
awareness. You know, where that
that, unfortunately, as we
question this, this conundrum of
how we move forward as a
species, how we re negotiate our
relationship with the nest, the
rest of the natural world, how
we confront, or at least engage
with some of the more dramatic
crises that we face as a
humanity now, you know, we need
to, we need to find ways of
bringing back. What I conceive
of is that as that part of us
that has been sequestered off,
that pre industrial aspect of
who we are there, which has kind
of been labeled regressive and,
you know, primitive and all
sorts of names that we use, in a
sense, to sublimate it and
trivialize it and depreciate it
and throw it out of the the kind
of, I don't quite know what to
call it, but the engagement with
where we're at and so, you know,
when I came across Chris's work,
and I've read some of his
subsequent work, and of course,
before that, I was a great
follower of Stan Grof work, out
of which a lot of Chris's work
comes, you know, I just think
that this is an incredibly
important way of delving into an
a radical way. I also say I'm
very deeply of the belief that
our engagement right now with
the state that we find ourselves
in as a humanity requires a
radical, potent engagements. You
know, we can't really afford to
dabble around on the edges of
things. So if we're going to
look at finding contemporized
forms of our pre industrial
ancestry, if we're going to look
at experiential exploration,
deep delving into who we are,
what we are, and our broken
relationships with the natural
world. There has to be a
radicalness to this, because
it's urgent. It's desperate, in
fact, and and so you know, with
Grof work, and with with Chris's
writing subsequently, and his
experimentation and exploration,
his deep and profound, in my
opinion, courage in the way he's
gone in, I think this is just,
you know, it's such a profound
part of what we are, certainly
what I'm passionate about in
this time, in terms of the kind
of work that we're doing, as
Rachel said earlier In our
contemporary animism program,
and trying to rally, you know,
interest in an experiential
exploration of what re animating
ourselves might mean, might look
like. And I just think that, you
know, I think that this is what
you're going to see tonight in
this talk, is the absolute tip
of a profound iceberg. If we
could put it that way. You know,
as he it's well worth reading
his work. It's well worth
looking at Grof work as well.
It's very much, in my opinion, a
critical part of the kind of
exploration that I think is most
needed at this time. Pardon my
bias on this, but I really do
believe this, so that, having
been said, I'm going to pass
back to Rachel, and I'll be very
interested to hear some of your
reflections at the end. Thank
you, fantastic.
Rachel Fleming: Thank you,
Colin, so we'll dive straight
in. I have just asked him, so
we've just started, and I have
asked him. Um, just to tell us
about his research method and
how he how he came to the vision
that he will then tell you about
later on in the interview, and
how that fits into kind of the
animist world that we're
exploring. So it starts in the
middle of sentence is his first
sentence, so you've only missed
about two or three words, but
yes, that's where we'll start.
So I'm going to hand over to you
now, Gabby, and enjoy. I find
him very mind blowing. But see
what you think, Gabby, go. Thank
you. You so
we're not getting any sound.
GABBY I
I know this works because we
checked it earlier. So sorry.
What's the what's the problem?
Rachel, we're not getting any
sound on it. Is anybody getting
any sound on it. No.
Oh, after all, after the
introduction, that's going to be
disappointing if you can't hear
him.
Unknown: Any insights here,
because I'm not exactly sure
what's going on.
Rachel Fleming: You want to give
it another junta press go again.
Chris Bache: Share in the
animistic community is the
belief that nature is infused
with consciousness, fused with
mind and soul. And of course,
now we know how vast the
physical universe is, and the
question becomes, how large is
the mind of the universe? How
deep is it? And so I was just
out of graduate school in 1978
in my finish in philosophy of
religion, and I met the work of
Stanislav Grof, who many of you
know, one of the foremost
thinkers in the Transpersonal
psychology community, in the
psychedelic community, and I
read his book, realms of the
human unconscious, and my life
pivoted with that book, because
I immediately saw that his
research was relevant, not only
to clinical psychology, but also
to philosophy that it would he
was offering a method to
actually, safely and
systematically explore the
deepest levels of consciousness
we're in lay the answers to the
philosophical questions that I
was carrying coming out of a
training and Religious Studies.
So in 1979 I began what became a
20 year journey, working with
LSD, and there was a 1979 LSD is
what Stan had done his research
with, and that's what I chose to
continue with. If I were doing
it today, I would have a more
diversified cocktail of
Ayahuasca, civil side and more.
But I worked with LSD, and I
chose to work with very high
doses for reasons that are too
complicated to go into now, but
that had a profound impact on
the work, because it not only
changed how deep the wind worked
the work went, but it changed
how wide it went. The field of
consciousness that I took in
these transformational exercises
expanded with the power of the
state of consciousness that I
was entering to enter into these
exercises. So basically, I did
this work in standard grafian
protocol, totally isolated from
the world with a sitter, a
trained clinical psychologist,
sitter. I did it at home, in a
controlled environment, totally
internally focused, not in any
with any contact with the
outside world, amplifying the
states of awareness with
carefully selected music
designed to empower the states
of consciousness in which you
basically just Shatter your mind
in essentially working at these
levels, you just Shatter your
mind, and your mind dissolves
out into subtler and subtler
forms or aspects of reality, and
it became a. Systematic
exploration of what I think of
as the mind of the universe. I
hesitate to call the divine,
though sometimes I do. It's just
because the divine has so many
culturally infused qualities in
history that I'd rather avoid.
So I think of it as the mind of
the universe, and I did this
work for 20 years, always
keeping very careful records and
whatnot, and then I digested
those experiences for another 20
years, because this is these are
not immediately transparent
experiences. They're very
complex and interwoven, and they
involve many levels of reality
being orchestrated in the same
kind of titles that surges of
these states. And there was a
systematic instruction. I found
that one session more or less
started where the other session
stopped. When you work in this
systematic fashion that was
progressive deepening and
deepening and deepening. And so
it just took years for me to
understand what the universe was
showing me and where it was
taking me, and I was being shown
things. I mean, I always had a
sense of a systematic encounter
with an intelligence that was
orchestrating my experience in
dialog with me, not taking any
form, never taking any any deity
form or any archetypal form, but
always when pressed, dissolving
into deeper and deeper layers of
infinity. Anyway. So that is,
cumulatively, the story that I'm
telling in LSD, in the mind of
the universe.
Rachel Fleming: Would you say,
Chris, that this is an objective
reality, that if anybody that
did a similar method, I mean, I
think, I think what you did was
incredibly brave. But would
would everybody kind of reach
this unfolding that you did
using that method, or was that
not possible to say?
Chris Bache: I think I think it
is possible to say, I think Stan
Grof work allows us to say it,
and where he's dealing with
integrating the experiences of
1000s of people. And I'm only
talking integrating my
experiences, but my experiences
fit comfortably within the
larger matrix that Grof is work
has explored, and it's a
complicated answer, because on
the one hand I want to say yes,
and on the other hand, I have to
qualify that immediately,
because when you begin this
work, these substances only
amplify consciousness. They
don't give you an experience,
they don't take you a particular
place. They amplify your mind.
And because each of us has a
different life story, then the
mind which is amplified is
different, and we therefore,
when an amplified mind engages
the deeper mind of the universe,
what comes forward will be, in
the beginning, somewhat unique,
and will reflect our individual
history. And that's why these
substances are very helpful for
healing. They evoke our
unconscious, and therefore they
evoke our problems. And it's an
individual experience. But if
you keep going farther, if you
press to the limits of your
time, space, identity, if you
press to the limits of what your
individual history can hold and
go through this transformation
we call ego death, then you
begin to open into spiritual
reality, farther removed from
your own personal history, and
that's when the experiences
begin to overlap. That's when
they begin to converge. Now my
understanding is that spiritual
reality is not simply something
you enter and pluck fruit from,
like plucking an apple from a
tree. It's interactive. It's
always interactive. So there's a
participatory quality to our
experiences. So the mind that we
bring to the encounter access a
seed catalyst that crystallizes
a certain set of experiences
from the infinite potential of
the mind of the universe. And
then as we internalize those
experiences and are purified by
those experiences, it changes
the seed mind, and then we it
catalyzes an even deeper level
of secrets from the universe. So
it's a both and situation
participatory. But once you
understand the cycle of
participation, then I think the
universe that we discover is
coherent and consistent. My
universe is the same universe
that is discovered by
contemplative monks, the
mystical traditions, the near
death episode traditions. There
are degrees of depth, and then
we have to be careful, because
you can reach a point where you
think, Oh, this is what the
reality is. And it turns out,
well, no, this is what reality
is at this level of reality, but
you can pop that and go into a
deeper level of reality, and
things change a bit.
Rachel Fleming: One thing that I
find really exciting about your
work is that we talk about
practices. You know that finding
the right practices, to find the
cracks kind of in ourselves to
get back to a much more porous,
expanded way of being. And yet,
these practices take repetition
and tenaciousness and
everything, and you have used a
different method here. You've
used what, what one might kind
of think of as a fast track to
some of these experiences. I
mean, it's a very difficult
method, and I'm sure not one
that you would kind of recommend
to a lot of people, but that
that feels, for me, where the
excitement of your work is as
you fast tracked a lot of slower
practices and possibly got to
the edge of the map that a lot
of these contemplative practices
have got to I feel as though
you've managed to go further
than than much that I've seen
before on kind of what the
underlying nature of reality is.
Would you say that's true?
Chris Bache: It is a fast track,
except it's a fast track that
doesn't allow any bypassing. So
the fact that it's a fast track
means it's a much more intensely
concentrated track. So
purification, which in the
conventional spiritual path,
would be drawn out over years,
can take place within days, and
as any woman who's given birth
knows, a short labor is not
necessarily an easier labor.
It's just much, much more
intense. And this is true for
this type of practice, too. The
purifications that one goes
through in order to acclimate to
these subtler and cleaner and
clearer states of reality, those
purifications and
detoxifications are extremely
intense. I mean, they send you
in convulsions across the floor,
in throwing up, constantly
coming and going, and they
require a systematic
purification of your lifestyle,
just as any traditional
spiritual practice does. And I
want to emphasize that the
states of consciousness that I
touched for hours at a time, we
usually only learn about these
realities from the work of
contemplative mystics who have a
certain sense that they abide in
these realities. And I emphasize
that this is a practice, not of
abiding. It's a it's a temporary
access. It's only temporary
immersion in these states. And I
don't want to confuse temporary
immersion from abiding immersion
all honor to the Great Ones who
abide in these realities. You
know this is different. This is
temporary access, very, very
intense purification. But you
don't come away with permanent
access embedded in your nature
to these realities. What you
come away with are seeds of
Transcendence, or seed
experiences, which you then have
to nurture within your your
daily spiritual practice. You
have to nurture them within your
embodied, physical existence.
And I also want to mention that
these practices in the earlier
times in history have tended to
be associated with the
dissociative spirituality. So
the goal was to get up into
Transcendence and get away from
Earth, you know. So these are
the up and out cosmologies of
the last five Axial Age,
religions in the last 5000
years, the cosmology that
emerged in my work is very
different. It wasn't about
getting Transcendence. It was
Transcendence and service of
incarnation, Transcendence and
service of deeper integration.
It was about opening up and
letting in as much of the
universe as possible, and then
going through the
transformations that would allow
this energy to live in the
historical body, and giving me,
at one point, insights into
where the evolutionary
intelligence was taking the
human family as a whole. I began
this work thinking in terms of a
personal model of
transformation, but things
happen that just shattered that
model, and I began to understand
that I was had been drawn into a
collective transformation, and
that my my so called individual
work, was part of a collective
process, which then naturally
yielded some insights into our
collective family, human family,
evolutionary trajectory,
Rachel Fleming: fantastic, and I
want to ask you that. That in
great depth in a minute. Because
for me, that's kind of the
exciting thing that you
discovered, if you like. But
first of all, I'd love to ask
you about the aliveness and
intelligence in the universe.
Then we are talking about the
aliveness and intelligence in
everything around us, you know,
and humans being just one load
of that that just kind of as is
everything an animate world and
animate universe. I just
wondered if you could summarize
your understandings of the
aliveness in the universe and
how layered that is, and how
deep that goes, how big it is,
yes, what did you
Unknown: What did you mean?
Chris Bache: Oh, you're asking a
lot, because, you know, the
universe is so vast, and the
mind of the universe has so many
layers to it, and those layers
are, of course, all complexly
interwoven, and it's all alive,
and it's all intelligent, and
it's it's everywhere we dig into
the universe, of course, we
discover aliveness and
intelligence. We're finding that
we can't dig in anywhere and not
encounter this intelligence,
this living intelligence. So
when you dig into the mind of
the universe, you find layers of
intelligence operating there.
There are layers of intelligence
operating in the biosphere,
operating in the incarnational
rhythms of a planet I began to
experience at one point, for
example, reincarnation, the I
had gone into, sorry to cut so
many corners here, but there's
no way to do it except jump into
it, go into states of
consciousness in which time was
radically dilated, not eternity,
not timelessness, but radical
dilations of time and dilations
of personal boundaries, so
dissolving into my human family,
becoming the human family, and
from that perspective,
experiencing reincarnation, the
pulse of reincarnation, taking
place, All of us together as a
single organism, incarnating
generation by generation. And I
experienced whole lifetimes,
incarnating in generations,
living their lives, dying and
returning into the spiritual
reality. And there was an
intelligence to this entire
process, so that all of our what
I had previously thought of as
individual karma, individual
challenging, individual
transformation. All of our
individual karma was part of a
vast network of exquisitely
tuned collective karma, and our
and history was expressing the
rhythms of collective
transformation through the
medium of our individual
transformation, just one
example, and then going deeper,
beginning to experience the
pulse of the entire universe as
a single living organism. And
when you when you dissolve it
into that level of oneness. You
know, the Buddhist have a word
for it. They talk about Nirvana,
blown out. Self is blown out, or
Shunyata, emptiness of self.
When you experience the world as
one in any scale, then you
experience that there are no
permanent boundaries between
yourself and the world. So
literally, there is no private
self. And so the self kind of
pops and life runs through you.
You run through life, and the
whole of life breathes as one.
It breathes together. As
Plotinus said, So, everywhere
you touch it, the world is
intelligent. At the very end of
my journey, in the 70th session,
out of 73 I did 73 sessions. In
the 70th session, I was taken
deep, deep, deep into what I
call deep time, farther into
time than I'd ever been, taken
before and given a series of
visions. And one of those
visions had to do with
experiencing, in some way, from
my perspective and my history,
the large story of what was
happening in the universe, and I
experienced reincarnation. I was
experiencing the same deep
pattern, and I experienced stars
of light shooting out of time
and space shooting into the
universe. And I understood that
these were what I call. Diamond
souls. These were the fruition
of a reincarnation process
creating a diamond pure soul
that could explore the spiritual
world in dimensions previously
unavailable to it that time and
space was creating diamond souls
over vast periods of time, so
layers and layers and layers of
intelligence operating at
different levels.
Rachel Fleming: So when I read
your book, Chris, I mean, it's
literally mind blowing. I mean
it, it's kind of it feels as
though it's science fiction, or
it's in the realms of science
fiction, and yet, for me, there
was nothing in there that didn't
sound right. You know, it just
kind of has that feeling, ah,
yes, I understand this, and it
feels right to me. And I'd love
to talk to you about the
evolutionary process. You
touched on it a bit there, but
let's go into that in more
detail, but first of all
reincarnation, because that is
something that obviously we
don't all feel is true, but you
did earlier work on the subject
of reincarnation, and just
before we go on to the
evolutionary story that you've
seen, could you talk about a
little bit about reincarnation
and your work on this and why
you believe that that is what's
happening.
Chris Bache: Well, I did. I
wrote my first book on
reincarnation because I thought
it was such an essential
principle, because our
philosophical roads divide. If
you think we only are on earth
one time, but we're on Earth
multiple times, those need to
different visions of reality,
and today, I think we have
overwhelming empirical evidence
that reincarnation is simply
true. It's a fact of life. I
think Ian Stevenson at the
University of Virginia and his
study of young children around
the world who have spontaneous
memories of their most immediate
life, he's just documented
hundreds and hundreds of these
children. And his research has
been challenged, but it's still
it's holding up. And I think he
is the Charles Darwin of
reincarnation studies. And then
we have past life therapies,
people coming in, highly
qualified people healing, using
past life access to past life
memories, to heal present life
traumas. This, to me, is just an
empirical fact of life. So after
living, it takes a long time to
sort of live in a reincarnation
universe, to understand the
implications of the fact that
there's this pulse of life and
that all of us have been here
multiple times, and all of us
have deeper histories with
place, with people, with
projects, and that we're always
starting something and we're
continuing something in one
lifetime, and we're doing
something that's going to be
continued in another lifetime,
that this overlapping complexity
so that I don't see little
children as little anymore. I
don't see old people as old
anymore. Sometimes little
children are deeply old in
Seoul, and old people are
sometimes very young in Seoul,
and you just tune to a different
level. Now, I had that in the
early stages of my psychedelic
work. And in the early stages of
my psychedelic work, I was taken
into some of the nuts and bolts
of reincarnation and karma, and
then that became kind of ground
one as I began to be taken into
the human family and to
experience the human family
evolving and growing through
reincarnation. This, to me,
reincarnation is simply the
higher octave of evolution. It's
the cutting edge of evolution in
our particular species, where
evolution tends was trying to
change whole species.
Reincarnation is evolving
individuals within certain
species. And I don't think just
human species. I think somewhere
lower down the line,
reincarnation begins to turn in
just state. And then the
question becomes, well, where is
reincarnation taking us, if we
are reincarnating so many times,
where are we going? What's
what's the whole project of it?
What's the purpose of it? And to
determine to answer the
question, what's the purpose of
a reincarnating species is
complicated, because once you
understand that every human
being on the planet is
reincarnating with a purpose,
its specific purpose, then you
realize the full breadth of the
living experience of human
being, the breath of what's
being learned. That what
humanity is learning is just
enormous. And when we try to
say, well, this is the purpose
of life, we have a tendency to
sort of take a purpose that we
can identify with and maybe over
generalize it to encompass all
purposes. So we really have to
look at the whole of the human
family and gestate the whole of
the things that people are
learning to even begin to come
up with some generality that
encompasses them all you see
what I mean? So, so in some
cases, we can be learning love,
we can be learning generosity,
we can be learning strength of
self. We can be learning
physical defense. We can be
learning surrendering physical
defense, what one person is
growing into in one lifetime.
Another person may be growing
out of and both of them are
living their truth
Colin Campbell: at a process
level.
Chris Bache: Most of the Eastern
religions basically say, Yes,
you grow, you activate the
chakras. You bring higher and
higher levels of consciousness
online. But when your
consciousness opens up to divine
essence, when it opens up to the
you that is more real than any
of your individual, private
incarnational use the divine.
You the essential. You. When you
open up to that, then you reach
enlightenment that the Hindus
call moksha. Means you can
escape, you can leave. So once
you wake up, then let's get out
of here. There's better places
to be than Earth. So that's an
up, and not cosmology. But what
happened in my sessions was
different than that. I reached a
point about halfway on my
journey when all of my former
lives began to come into me. I
was in a again, a kind of a
pregnant time, reality of deep
time, and my former lives were
coming in and were coming in,
and it was like wrapping a
filament of kite string around a
spool. But that's string was
human experience. It was whole
human lifetimes. And they kept
coming together, and they
reached a critical mass. And
when they reached a critical
mass, they fused into one. When
that happened, there was a
tremendous explosion of energy,
and a diamond Luminosity
exploded from my chest. And
that's when I began to
understand, and was shown, that
we make progress incrementally,
lifetime by lifetime, as we
incarnate. But the goal is not
simply to make incremental
progress. The goal eventually is
that all of our lives come
infused into one and we become,
on earth, a being who has
100,000 hundreds of 1000s of
years of history in it, awakened
within it, and empowered within
it. That is the being that we
are becoming, and that is a
different kind of being than an
egoic being. It's the vast depth
of its heart is deep is bigger.
The breath of its mind is
bigger, the texture of its
social relationships is bigger,
and its relationship to nature
is different because it knows
that the world we leave is the
world we inherit. It has a
deeper, embodied texture of its
relationship with nature. And my
discovery was that this is not
simply a path of individuals.
This is simply a story of
individual spiritual awakening
that we are all going through
this transition. We are all
giving birth to the diamond
soul. The entire species is at a
point in its history where it
can no longer afford the luxury
we're trying to live on this
planet in the fragmented egoic
state. When the world order is
created by egos, it leads to a
fragmented order that serves
some and not others. But when
the soul wakes up to the with
the profound compassion of its
history, the soul lives on this
planet differently than the ego
does. And I think we are coming
into a very profound, tumultuous
period of history, which I think
of as a birth process. It will
feel like a death process, and
it is a death process. It's it's
basically destroying the culture
that was built by the ego, and
destroying the ego which built
that culture, and in that
process of dying to that which
is small, giving birth to
something new, giving birth
literally, to a new stage in the
human story, not on. A new body
politic and New Economics, and a
shift I think, is taking place
at the depths of the collective
unconscious. The plate tectonics
of the collective psyche are
shifting in that Jungian sense,
deep, deep down inside the human
psyche. This transformation is
taking place so that all human
beings who are born after this
transition will be living their
individual life within the
matrix of a different collective
psyche. That, I think, is the
work of the hour. That's what we
are working to, and part of this
to actualize, and part of this
is reawakening to Divine
Presence, which we've stripped
out of nature tried to
unsuccessfully, but reawakening
to this common ground that we
have with nature, to This
intelligence that surrounds us
and saturates us.
Rachel Fleming: Wow, Chris. I
mean, I'm imagining people
hearing this for the first time.
It's kind of difficult to get
your head around it. And I want
to bring what I want to bring
Colin in in a minute. So to
summarize, in my kind of terms,
and what you're talking about,
really, is, is the evolution of
the human species individuals
and collectively, towards a
position where we can remember
our entire history. So if we
take reincarnation as a given,
then we're evolving towards a
place where we can remember past
our past incarnations on this
earth. And, you know, Colin, can
I bring you in here? Because
there's something that you talk
about, you know, in reanimating
ourselves, we need to have a
completely new cognitive
framework. You know, that that
the the way of connecting to the
intelligence in the universe is
so foreign to us now that we
need a whole different framework
to kind of be able to wrestle
with with that kind of
information. What's your feeling
about what Chris is talking
about? I know you've read the
book too, and I know you love
it. So biased question here, but
yeah, from your perspective,
Colin Campbell: Thanks, Rachel.
Well, first of all, I really
wanted to say how much of an
honor it is to meet you, Chris.
I have to say the encounter with
your books, and the first one I
encountered was dark night,
early dawn. Was was really,
well, tectonic in nature for me,
and I'm filled with questions,
and was, and have been all the
way through reading your books
and re reading them and reading
them again, and thinking about
and brewing on it. And a lot of
the questions I really want to
ask, I have no idea how would
even articulate. I can feel them
and I can sense them, but how,
and I, you know, so, I mean, I
can see, feel myself at the sort
of edges, you know, of my, what
I call my present cognition.
Because, you know, I was, I was
lucky enough to be born into and
brought up within a traditional
indigenous culture here in
southern Africa. And through,
through my childhood, lived in
wilderness and among people who
had a very, very particular
relationship with wilderness and
a cosmology that came out of
that. And subsequently, I find
myself, you know, in
Unknown: in the
Colin Campbell: worlds of post
industrial world, trying to
reconcile that part of me with
the part of me I find myself in
now and finding that it's very
difficult to bring it feels like
in a certain sense, that there
are two cognitive frameworks
within me at some level, and
that somehow I'm tasked with
trying to reconcile these two
parts of myself and reading
reading through your books. I
you know, where I found myself,
find myself back into the
cognitive system, really, that I
grew up in, and that forms a
kind of an under structure
within my experience now and but
I mean within that, then I have,
I have questions. I mean loads
of them, which, which your books
really, really brought up in me,
and among them, among the most
difficult to articulate are
questions around time and and
the notion that somehow or
other, you know, so
reincarnation is not something
that really comes into the
cosmology is here in southern
Africa, and yet it does.
Implicit in certain terms.
Unknown: But I'm really
Colin Campbell: so as we look at
this idea of reincarnation, the
cognitive framework that I would
perceive it from here, as we
speak about it, relies on a
sequence of time that speaks of
a past from which we come and a
future to which we go. But what
happens if we take that out, if,
in fact, if, in fact, that's
nearly my present cognitive
framework. But you know, how
would we understand
reincarnation and the notion of
a trajectory towards something,
if time in its kind of sequence
from beginning to seeming
culmination, or some such thing.
If that wasn't the case, yeah, I
don't know if I'm making any
sense.
Chris Bache: It's a good
question. If you if we eliminate
the arrow of time, then
reincarnation begins to look
like multi incarnation, not
reincarnation. Some people have
conceptualized as we're living
all of our lives simultaneously
in a and we're interacting. All
these lives are active and
interacting in a way that
befuddles the logic of linear
development, and it requires a
different kind of logic. And
I've tried to think in that
world multiple times, and I
basically keep coming down to I
can't do it. I mean, I literally
cannot live in a world where
Multi incarnation makes sense. I
can't make it make sense. Now,
another little thread Robert
Monroe, from the Monroe
Institute of Applied Science,
out of body guy you know, has
been wrote three wonderful books
in the out of body state,
exploring the universe daily
from the out of body state. He
says, You reach a point in your
spiritual development, where you
discover that you can incarnate
in any time period you wish. So
soul forward does not mean time
forward, right? So you can
incarnate in the 10th century
BC, and next you can incarnate
in the 20th century. AD, so
permeability of time that you
see how that continues the
concept of linear development,
but it flexes on the concept of
times, absolute linearity. For
myself, I've gone through so
many permutations of time,
moving into deep time where you
can I experienced my entire life
in the early stages, birth to
death, simultaneously present.
Absolutely. I was experiencing
the whole of my life, the end
and the beginning and all of its
development as a simultaneous
later. I was taken into periods
of time where 100,000 years were
being lived out as if it were
one minute. It's convinced me
that the universe has many
modalities of time built into
it, that when we move into
deeper dimensions of reality,
there are different modalities
of time that are available.
There all that which you would
think. And it does make me
receptive to the idea of letting
go of a concept of linear time
and linear development. And
somehow I try to reconcile the
fact that from the universe's
perspective, there are multiple
modalities of time, so that the
universe can show me the future
from its time which is and can
give me the experience of
knowing the future as something
which has already happened and
simultaneously which is yet to
happen, and at the same time, at
the same time, hold on to some
notion of the value and the
challenge of something
approximating linear
development. And I think my best
take is that life chops it's its
challenges to it chops the
learning into bits and pieces,
and we can't learn it all in one
lifetime. We can't do it all
simultaneously. It's easier if
it's just broken down into bits
and pieces. And if this, if this
challenge of linear development,
is coming to a fruition, and is
coming to a diamond soul, a an
awareness that holds all of its
time moments in its present
consciousness on Earth. This, of
course, is not the end of the
developmental story, of the
linear story, because in a
million years, will be far.
Other in a billion years, will
be farther still the universe
just getting warmed up, you
know, is that we have no reason
for thinking that the universe
is is in anywhere near the end
of its evolutionary story. We
know it's really at the early
stages of its story. So I think
of time is one of the great
gifts of evolution.
Individuality is one of the
great gifts of the physical
universe. Time is one of the
gifts of the physical universe.
Behind that lay lies
permutations of metaphysics that
put that are more fluid with
respect to time. But inside
space time, I think there is an
approximate linear arrow of time
which serves the soul's purpose,
which serves some deeper cosmic
web. And yet, at the same time,
when we are in the linear
development if we open up to the
universe, if we open up to the
universe's sense of time, we
often get these flashes of more
than more than the present. You
know more parallel dimensions of
time. So your question makes a
lot of sense, and it's, it's a
substantive question.
Rachel Fleming: Can I ask one
Colin, or do you want to come
back on that? Okay, so yeah,
great. This is the problem with
your work, Chris, we need to
keep trying to we're out in kind
of like inarticulable terrain,
aren't we, when we get to that
you what you call the diamond
soul, then when there's this
moment of remembering what, what
are The other attributes, what
are the other kind of what does
that bring? Other than
remembering and wholeness? You
know, did you have an experience
of what else?
Chris Bache: Well, first of all,
I think full consciousness is
what we return to when we die.
So while we're in the Bardo
Earth, Bardo, earth, kind of
stage. When we die, we return to
whole consciousness. So it's not
something we're unfamiliar with.
It's something we are familiar
with. And then we precipitate
out of whole consciousness into
part consciousness, egoic
consciousness, and we return. So
it's a it's a constant accordion
kind of effect. We die as we get
large, we're born, we get small,
we die. We get large. We're
born, we get small sooner or
later, if we just keep them for
a few 1000 years, 100 million
years, sooner or later, large
wakes up inside physical
consciousness, and so it's
simply a consolidation of what's
taking place naturally and
normally. It's just a stage in
this process, the times that
I've been carried into deep time
and experience temporarily my
diamond soul, and then the
diamond stole the soul that's
emerging as an archetypal
imprint, an archetypal form. You
Yeah, it's hard to describe
because of the enormity and the
beauty and the joy we're looking
we're talking about a human
being that's completely healed
of all the wounds of history.
That's healed of all the
terrible things we've done to
each other, men and women and
wars and violence, healed all
those scars, healed a tremendous
breath of communion with the
natural world, an intimacy with
all life forms, not Only then, a
breath of companionship with all
life and with other human beings
and with human community and
with natural nature's community,
but an openness of the mind able
to take in more directly, enter
into deeper communion with the
intelligence of the universe. I
mean, the genius of the universe
has all the answers to all the
technological limit questions we
want to have answers to, and we
just are not able to download
all that knowledge. And the
diamond soul is a more complete
and higher. Potency of human
being that can enter into deeper
downloads from the divine
intelligence. But it's not only
an expansion of heart and an
expansion of mind, our physical
senses are also amplified by
orders of magnitude in the very,
very last session. After 73
sessions, the very last session,
the universe gave me an
experience of what I call
diamond vision. Suddenly, in a
kind of a late, late session,
wind down, clear space, my
vision became 1000s of times
more cute and sharper than it
had ever been before. I could
see things, details, gradients
of color, sharpness and
precision of form. I could just
see. I was amazed that I ever
had accepted this fuzzy stuff as
real seeing. This was diamond
clarity seeing. And then after
10 minutes, it went away, and I
was seeing the way I normally
see. And that's when I
discovered, I realized what I
was being shown is that we tend
to think of sensation as kind of
a biomechanical process, but
it's actually a conscious
process, and the more
consciousness which is is
present in this body, this body
has built into it the capacity
for infinitely higher levels of
sensitive experience, Touch,
hearing, seeing, sensitivities
of all manner of physical
sensations. So it truly is. It's
heaven on earth in the body, so
that the body participates in
the qualities of heaven without
having to leave the physical
existence. That's why, I mean,
it's not an up and out
cosmology. It's bringing it in
deeper and deeper and deeper,
changing, literally, the
physiology of the body, to allow
it to operate in this ecstatic
state, which becomes the normal
state. Yeah, that's a child, I
think, is it's worth the labor
that we're going into to give
birth to and we are going in a
terribly, terribly severe labor.
Our past is being stripped away.
Will be stripped away. We will
lose all capacities that we
associate with normal and
minimal existence. This is what
happens in all mystical
traditions, in all psychedelic
traditions, literally, the small
has to be broken ground, to
dust, stripped and dismembered
in order for the new to awaken
within us. And this is happening
now, historically, where we're
entering into what I think of as
the dark night of our collective
soul. The Dark Night is an image
often used for a hard time, but
it's not a hard time in John of
the Cross, the dark night of
self is a hard time. The Dark
Night of the Soul is a very,
very intense purification time
which immediately precedes the
awakening of full illumination.
And the dark night of the of the
collective soul is a time of
intense purification, intense
loss of reality as we have known
it up to this point in time, and
I think out of the out of the
pain and suffering that's
coming, it's going to crack US
Open and break us down to our
center. And in this ordeal, we
will not survive, but we will
give birth to that in us which
is more beautiful, more
ecstatic, more competent, more
plugged in. I think we truly are
becoming a species of Bud,
species of Christ and prophets.
These are the models we've had
trying to give us some for
vision of what's happening in
the early years. We could not
imagine an ordinary human being
reaching that level of
excellence. But now we're
beginning to understand through
reincarnation, over and over and
over and over again, slowly, we
grow into that level of
excellence, which is simply a
level of transparency to the
essential condition which in
which we experience life in. The
irony is, we experience what's
always been happening all the
way along. It's always been this
way. The universe has always
been one. The universe has
always been filled with
intelligence. We have always
been empty of self. But somehow
we distracted ourselves from
thinking that that's not there.
It's always been there. So we're
waking up to the paradise that
the universe already is. We just
been missing it,
Rachel Fleming: Chris, I just
find your experience and your
vision just such a hopeful one
as we move into what we see as
ecological crisis and societal
crisis, and I just again, as I
felt quite emotional, said at
the beginning it was just one of
the most inspiring books, or the
most inspiring book last year,
but what one of the most of my
lifetime? You know I and I'm
sure Colin would agree with me
on that. So it's so wonderful to
hear you speak. We have 10
minutes. I wondered if anybody
had any questions, I appreciate
it's quite a lot to take on
this. Please do raise your hand
if you have anything to ask
Chris. Also to say, we've
invited Chris back, Chris back
later in the year to be with us
a bit more, so there'll be more
opportunity to talk with him.
Does anybody have a question?
Otherwise, I'm going to pick on
Colin again, because I know
you've got to list Colin,
Unknown: Rachel, maybe I can
speak to the question I put in
the chat. That was really for
Stefan, but it was kind of a
tiny, tiny gesture towards some
sense of rightness and these
much, much bigger movements that
we can't even begin to fathom.
And then Chris used to spoke on
that, on paradigms that I've
never heard before, and part of
me feels so extremely joyful,
and like Rachel, I'm kind of
want to weep at the same time.
And as we are entering this dark
night of the soul, which I think
most of us kind of know, we can
feel it, and it's as I don't
know, you know, I feel like
small and I'm a mother of three
kids, and I, you know, and I'm
trying to understand how to be a
mother in this moment in time
and to love my children well.
And I'm not very sure how to do
that. So it's a very human
thing, but it's the sort of
smallest fractals of all the
other things, if I can make any
sense in that, and I just
wondered if you could speak to
that a little bit. No.
Chris Bache: Couple thoughts.
One of them is, first, I
absolutely identify with what
you're saying. I have three
children and Karen, parenting is
of the age, and the age we're
going into is going to be
different than parenting of the
age we're coming out of.
Because, you know, we're trying
to inculcate a different set of
values in our children as we
internalize these values
ourselves. And I think that's
how nature works. Each one of us
is a cell within a fractal cell
within a tissue of consciousness
and the tissue of the body. And
we are as we actualize the
future in our individual lives,
we catalyze an actualization of
the future in our collective
lives. And we do it not simply
by example. We do it because
every person who internalizes
and becomes the future that we
know we need to become, they
become a seed catalyst which
psychically activates the web of
transformation in people they
will never know, they will never
meet, necessarily, but it's
there. Just as we have been
nourished by the ancestors, we
have been nourished by other
people who are making
transformation. Our
transformation nourishes other
people. This came up in my
sessions multiple times that the
states of consciousness I was
entering into were being fed
into the collective psyche.
We're filtering into the
collective psyche. So when we do
ritual at dawn, when we do
rituals of embracing the sun as
as a representative of this
larger collective intelligence,
when we do rituals of
conservation and cultivate a
lifestyle of using less and
doing more. When we actualize
those things, we make it that
much easier for the entire
species to hold to actualize
those things, until eventually
we come to a tipping point right
and. At the tipping point, the
Uncommon Sense starts to become
common sense in this you know,
this transformation is not
something that's going to happen
to us, though. I think there is
a way in which nature knows what
it is doing. We are not
generating this transformation.
Nature is doing it. Nature is
taking us through it, but we are
cooperating with this process,
and it's not going to be handed
to us. We have to create it. We
have to create it out of the
fabric of our being, where we
are living. And here's a very
another consoling thought. When
you look at the reincarnation
literature, you look at the near
death episode literature, one
thing becomes very clear, we
choose the incarnations that we
find ourselves in. So at a time
when we knew more, we knew what
we were getting into. We knew
what this century was going to
be about. We knew that the dark
night of the soul was coming
upon us, we made a choice to
incarnate where we did and to
become the people that we are.
We and so therefore each one of
us carries a component of the
transformation that humanity is
trying to make. Each one of us
is the question is not, what?
What can we do? The question is,
do we have the courage to do
what is within our reach to do?
Because what is within our reach
has already been decided by the
soul. Okay, so parenting is a
big part of this transition.
Everything that we're doing,
art, medicine, knowledge,
communication technology is a
big part of this transition.
We're working it as we go.
Rachel Fleming: Thank you,
Chris, thank you. Thank
right. Thank you so much for
sticking with us. I can see some
hands up here just to say we
have rocketed over time. We were
going to edit it to be less than
an hour, but when we came to do
the editing, we found that we
couldn't, and I really wanted to
include that question at the
end, because it's very much
brings it down to what can we
do? So apologies for that. We'd
love you to stay a little bit
longer to to kind of share your
thoughts. I saw two hands up
there. One was Carol, another
one was Isabella. Carol, would
you like to go first if you
unmute yourself?
Gabby, Can you unmute Are we all
so the technology
Unknown: you can everyone can
unmute themselves. Fantastic.
Carol, lovely to see you. Thank
you.
Yeah, I'm sort of rendered
speechless, but, but I wanted to
ask what I thought I heard Chris
say was at the end there was
that our task is to tune in to
who we really are in this
lifetime and live that, and
that's the best we can do.
Because my first question was,
what? What ritual can I do? What
task you know would would
accelerate this process? But it
sounds like, from what he says,
that that's not what it's about.
It's about living what we've
dreamt in for this lifetime.
Would you agree with that or
comment on that?
Rachel Fleming: That's certainly
what I heard. And actually, if
you read the book, I think
that's pretty much what he's
saying as well. Colin, would you
like to comment on that?
Colin Campbell: Yeah, I think
that is very much what he's
saying. I mean, you know, a lot
of what he says in the duration
of this talk, it's a it's a tiny
fragment of much, much bigger
body of work dating back into
Stan grofs work and so on. So to
really get a sense of what each
of the little statements he
makes, the importance of what
he's saying. It's kind of, it's
helpful to have, have, have,
have that within the context of
the much bigger picture. But I
think, you know, as I was, as I
was, we were coming to the end
of. This, I suddenly thought
back, and I thought I made a
mistake when I during the
introduction, I said, I spoke of
the subtitle of his book as
being the new ecology of mind,
steps towards the new ecology of
mind, when, in fact, it steps
towards the deep ecology of
mind. But, but I think that you
know that that's that, having
listened to the talk, you can
probably realize why I made that
mistake. Because we're, we're in
a moment now which is
unprecedented. I mean, any
moment of experience is
unprecedented. We are. We are as
individuals, as a collective, as
a globe, as a universe. This is
an unprecedented moment, and
yet, at the same time, we come
out of a long, long, long, long
history that this, this new
component of who we are is So on
one level where we're pulling
back into work we were
potentially and what we once did
much more effectively, I think,
is we, we go back into our our
historic roots, our experiential
historic roots, our psycho
spiritual historic roots, and we
draw into informing this present
moment. Those what we've
gathered in that time, but then
in that moment, also we we
potentially translate it into a
response to the newness of where
we are now. And I really think
that's the task of our time. And
the part that we're not doing
very well at the moment is this
reaching back into the vast form
of who we, who we are is, is,
kind of is expressed also in our
long, long, long, long, long
history, our trajectory of where
we've come from to get here. So
so I think that you know, the
totality of who we are is is, as
Chris points out, it's kind of
always there. It's always
naturally going on. But we we
compress ourselves into a
fragment of that, and a lifetime
is in a certain sense that, but
equally and as importantly, I
think, this particular time that
we're in now, you know what I
tend to refer to as an
industrial, cultural, globalized
time is even more so, you know,
because I think we've we've
condensed ourselves and
retracted ourselves, retracted
the notion of who we are into an
even tinier fragment than we
might have done previously. And
so I do think what we're tasked
with right now very, very
fundamentally, is remembering,
on the one hand, which is going
back and finding ways of RE,
entering into what is inherently
in us, which is our past, which
is dynamically still present in
us and active in us, and at the
same time, springing out of that
into a dreaming of who we are
now and what is asked of us in
this in this moment. What is,
what does it mean now to be in
this newness and this, as Chris
so beautifully puts it, this
tectonic, profoundly, all
encompassing seeming change of
what it means to be human, and
presumably what it means to be a
universe at some level. So I
think what you're asking is an
incredibly important question,
and I think it's a huge one, and
probably one which needs a
considerable amount of
pondering, but I'll say that for
the time period.
Unknown: Yeah, my experience in
this lifetime is many, many
different ways of being, and
I'm aware of the sort of small
self that just gets on with the
everyday life and doesn't and
isn't really doing much, but
then there's part of me that is
doing Much more interesting
stuff, or much more spiritual
stuff. My question with that is,
can I relax and let that happen?
Will it happen or should I be
focusing? Should I be there's
always this worry, isn't there
that the world's gonna win? We
haven't done enough, and all
that kind of anxiety that comes
from the industrial setup here.
But no answer. Probably
one to brew on, yeah. Women's
always brewing. Yeah. Before,
Isabella, you had a question,
you're gonna have to unmute I'm
afraid.
Yes, brilliant. Thank you. Um,
it's my name is actually
Christina, but I'm on my laptop.
Sorry. So that's why the Zoom is
named Isabella. It's maybe more
of an observation, or I don't
know exactly, but I have to
admit that I haven't read that
book yet, but I had many of my
own experiences of LSD and
Ayahuasca when I was young, and
it has certainly informed my
life. And I would, you know,
completely agree with so, so, so
many things that he said up to
now, and I have been thinking
about this a long time, but
never very scientifically, but
just try to live by what I had
experienced and learned. But one
thing always puzzled me,
because, like he said at the
very beginning, it is the taking
of the of the drugs is a
shortcut to an opening into a
world, in a way. I always felt
that, and I always felt that it
has kind of helped me to have a
bigger understanding of the
universe and of many, many
things that he has been talking
about, and in particular, to all
these connections, and to the
connections, also to my ancestry
and to the wisdom of my
ancestors and and I always felt
an obligation, in some Ways, for
some strange reason, to try and
share this with others. And in
my case, I did try to do that
mostly through art. But then my
observation was that we are all
on so many in different stages
in our lives and in our I
suppose I don't know in that so
called Journey, or, you know,
whatever, that it's very, very
difficult to often try and
explain all these things that we
can actually see and all these
connections to people who may
not have had the privilege of
being opening the mind. And so
I've often wondered, if we say
we about the collective well,
does that actually really exist?
You know, is that, does that
time that we are apparently
entering exist as a collective,
or is it just some who are at
the certain stage in their
rebirth or reincarnation, or
whatever it is. And you know,
does that actually, is there
even a sort of a time of that,
or is that some, somehow an
illusion we have created for
ourselves to try and understand
things? I don't know. I'm not
sure if I make myself clear.
It's really difficult to talk
about these things.
Rachel Fleming: I'm thinking of
what he was saying about if, if
the individual does it, then it
kind of adds to the collective,
and I'm just thinking of Rupert,
sheldrakes, Morphic resonance,
Colin will be able to kind of
talk more about that. But I just
wonder if it's that kind of
process at work that once the
individuals start, then it just
becomes easier for the
collective. Is that what you're
saying? Christina, I may have
understood,
Unknown: yes. I mean, I'm not
sure what I'm saying. It's more
that I'm asking. I've often, you
know, there is, there is maybe
this, this worry or this doubt,
because I have become very, very
aware, and hopefully tried, at
least very hard to live my life
in a way that being very aware
of every thing you say, and
everything every gesture one
does, and, you know, every
pebble you drop into the pond
has a has a, you know, yeah, it
does make some sort of a little
wave, perhaps, and it touches
things, and it changes things.
It changes the universe, if you
wish. So there is that
awareness, but I'm not sure that
that awareness is really the
same for everybody. And yes, it
does make a big difference, but
at the same time, we are
worrying about an age we are
entering, and I do, don't get me
wrong, and I like, you know, to
think about this, but at the
same time, I'm sort of thinking,
hang on a minute, in a way that
doesn't really make sense in the
big scheme of the universe,
because it has all it's already
there. It has already been it's
already, you know, whatever
comes, it's not a particularly
new entrance into something,
because some people are at this
stage, and others have this or
some, you know, we have already
had it's, It's not the same
exactly, but it's, it's not
necessarily very specific, just
to our very lifetime here and
now, because the same pains, the
same choice, the same thing, has
been experienced a million,
million times four in A way, and
it is, in the end, about the
individual, which also has been
historically named so many
times, like interestingly, what
Carl says it is, it is like the
Greek poets have been very clear
about saying and become who you
are, in a way, and that's that's
development, isn't it, that to
have that understanding of the
universe and of the vastness and
of the lack of of boundaries, in
a way, and that everything is
interconnected, absolutely
everything. So I don't know
anyway.
Rachel Fleming: Thank you so
much, Chris, and I'm sure that
we could, like really explore
that we have about six minutes
left. Theresa has got a question
before I come to you, Teresa, I
just wanted to say as well, just
in case people have to go. So
Chris is going to come back as
part of our contemporary animism
program, which starts again
July. We have a new intake every
year, so we still have some
places on that. Somebody was
saying that they'd love to,
Jackie, you were saying that
you'd love to explore this kind
of subject more. That's what
we're hoping to do in this
year's program, breathing
workshops, absolutely again.
Jackie, you're saying that it'd
be wonderful to have a breathing
workshop. I'm hoping that we're
going to do that as part of this
program as well. But yes,
absolutely. Breathwork certainly
for me, it's where it's at.
Yeah. So Therese, I wanted to
come to you, and if anybody has
one, put up your digital hand,
and we'll try and get them in.
Unknown: But there's lovely to
see.
It's just a comment. I don't
know. I haven't read his books.
I haven't actually heard of him
before, but it's just an
observation of something that he
he said that even though he kind
of rejects the transcendent
thought of or the thought of
transcending earthly, bodily
reality like you find in much
Eastern thought, he still
presents an idea that, by That
fits very neatly with our
Western thought of evolution and
development, and I'm not sure
quite what I think about that.
It's like he takes something old
evolutionary thoughts and
rejects it, and he presents
replaces it with another one.
And I don't know, I guess I'd
like to see more of using his
experience as a way to accept
that time isn't linear, and
things exist at the same time in
different layers, here and now,
and not necessarily for a means,
but just that, this is how it
is. I'm not sure if I'm making
much sense, but
Rachel Fleming: yeah. Do you
have a response on that? Colin?
Colin Campbell: Well, I think
you opening a, it's a kind of
door handle thing where we
could, we could spend the rest
of the night on this topic.
Rachel Fleming: Yeah,
Unknown: sorry, it's
Colin Campbell: very important,
and I think you're raising some
very interesting question, and
kind of harkens back into my my
question, or. On time and how we
perceive things, you know, and
when we we have this notion, I
think that as Western, well as
humanity, that we have a certain
way of perceiving time and that
that's what being that's part of
being human. I don't agree with
that. I think that the way we
perceive time, and the way we
perceive the nature of
sequential events is very
characteristic of a particular
moment in our history as human
beings, and is definitely not
necessarily the case in our
earlier states, and perhaps
won't be in our future states
either. So so in a way. But what
we what we are, what we have to
struggle with is the fact that
we are indeed immersed within
this framework that we call
present existence, you know, in
the particular cultural, socio
cultural, kind of framework that
we're in. And, you know, and so
when we have these
conversations, you know, we're,
we're tasked with modulating to
other views and other
perspectives that we might have
within us and within our history
and so on. You know, circular
dynamics, as opposed to linear
dynamics and so on. But at the
same time, I think we, we're,
we're also tasked with coming
back to risk with rest within
where we are in order to not get
completely lost in the
transitive process that we're
trying to do. So, you know, I
think that, I mean, I don't
really, I wouldn't know how to
answer the question exactly,
but, you know, I think that we
I'm opening a can that could
last forever. Now, let me stop
there, but I think it's a really
good question, and I think it's
an interesting thing to ponder
further. Yeah, thank you.
Rachel Fleming: Which we're
gonna have to do because it's
time or it's time a long time
ago. Actually, I do apologize
for keeping you longer than you
were expecting. Lovely to see
you. Look we have a small little
group that made it to the end.
Unknown: Yes.
Rachel Fleming: Dunno what more
to say, really. That was Chris
Bache. Check out his books. Have
a look at our contemporary
animism program. If you want to
do more of that kind of
conversation, we also do a lot
of embodied stuff as well. It's
not just all talking. So lovely
to see you tonight, everybody,
and
see you very soon. Bye for now.
Thank you Gabby, thank you
Colin,
Unknown: thank you very much.
Thank you. Bye. You. Thank You.