Chris Bache: I think when we
die, everything we've learned
and all the good we've done and
all our mistakes, but basically
our learning goes with us when
we die, and at the same time,
it's retained within the
collective psyche of our
species. So all of our
experiences are preserved by the
individual consciousness that
continues their learning once
they leave time and space. But
because they are a member of
this species, and because this
species has a mind which is
integrating all of the conscious
experiences of all of its
members. That means all of my
experiences and everything I've
written about and everything
we're talking about here,
they're not lost to humanity
when I die, but they are
literally hard wired into the
collective psyche, the
collective unconscious, right
now. That means that I think we
have to think quantum, kind of
in a quantum fashion, rather
than an atomistic fashion. When
we think about what happens to
these fields as the physical
body comes and goes, physical
bodies come and go. Souls
endure. Species have a soul.
There is a species soul. There's
an Akashic field Laszlo talks
about. You could even describe
it as an Akashic Soul of the
Universe. There's this
tremendous kind of network of
consciousness which is
constantly integrating the
experiences of all of its
members. Yeah. Yeah. So I can, I
could imagine any number of
variations of what happens to
these fields after we are no
longer on the scene. Yeah.