Andrew Holecek: Everybody.
Andrew holochick here, and I
simply cannot contain my
excitement about my guest for
today. Dr Christopher Bache. And
so with a brief introduction,
we're going to launch into what
I believe will be quite a
revelatory, I hope, provocative
conversation. So Chris PhD is
professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown,
Youngstown State University,
where he taught for 33 years. He
is also adjunct faculty at the
California Institute of Medical
studies, Emeritus fellow at the
Institute of Noetic Sciences and
on the advisory board of Grof
legacy training. Chris's passion
has been the study of the
philosophical implications of
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, especially
psychedelic states. An award
winning teacher and
international speaker, Chris has
written four books, life cycles,
a study of reincarnation in
light of contemporary
consciousness research, dark
night, early dawn, a pioneering
work in psychedelic philosophy
and collective consciousness,
the living classroom and
exploration of collective fields
of consciousness and teaching
and LSD and the mind of the
universe, the story of his 20
year journey with LSD. Chris is
a father of three. About You,
ianna practitioner, and lives in
Weaverville, North Carolina with
his wife, Christina Hardy, oh my
gosh, Chris, where do we start?
Right? First of all, thank you,
my dear friend, for for taking
time out of your busy schedule
to talk with us. It's a
pleasure. Really. I've been
looking forward to this one for
a while, and so oh my gosh. Just
some preparatory comments before
we launch in. I have read a fair
amount over my years. I consider
myself a bit of a an academic. I
love to read. I love to devour
books, and I have to say, I have
never read anything like your
last book, LSD and the mind of
the universe, and so out of all
the books that you've written,
this is the one I really want to
focus on, because it's no
exaggeration to say that it
really stretched my mind open,
challenged me. And maybe we can
talk about some of the areas
where I was challenged created
both tremendous resonance with
my own path and also some
dissonance. And so that's a
great way to make modern music,
right? So maybe, maybe we can
create a symphony of sanity with
with some questions to you, of
which there is no shortage, but
one kind of preparatory comment,
there's a term by the Eco
philosopher Timothy Morton that
I really quite like. He talks
about hyper objects, and he
refers to this in relationship
to climate change. When you have
something that is just so
enormous that is really
difficult to wrap your mind
around it, it just defies
description. It's literally mind
bending, mind stretching, and
then maybe even mind blowing,
and it's no exaggeration that
your book and your journey is a
hyper object to me, and I can't
tell you how it's impacted me
and how I want to really get
into some of the nitty gritty of
what you went through. But in
order to give our listeners even
a rough idea of what we're going
to be talking about, perhaps
give us a long elevator pitch.
Okay, so this is we have 1000
floors to a sand, right? So this
is a long elevator pitch. Share
with us, if you would, a little
bit about this book before we
get into the weeds, and I start
exploring particular topics with
you, yeah,
Chris Bache: well, I know it's a
radical book, and I think we are
at a pivot point in history, and
I think that psychedelics
represent a major transition
point, a true historical before
And after point with respect to
philosophy, not just psychology.
It generates not only a new
therapeutic protocol for healing
the personal psyche, but
literally, a new way of doing
philosophy. It's not really new,
because it goes back to the
elysinian mysteries and the
Ayahuasca traditions in Brazil,
but I got involved in it right
out of graduate school. I had
just finished my PhD from Brown
University. I went to work in
Ohio, at Youngstown State. I was
looking around for where to
begin, where to continue my
research. I was a pretty deeply
convinced agnostic at the time,
and I encountered realms of the
human unconscious. Stan Grof
first book, and that was a
turning point in my life,
quickly followed by his
methodology book, LSD,
psychotherapy. This was 1978
when I began graduate school,
and I saw the significance of
his work for philosophy, for my
tradition. Tradition, which was
philosophy of religion. And I I
knew that I needed to do this
work, that this would the people
making the most substantive
contributions to my discipline
in the future would be people
writing out of an experiential
basis, not simply an
intellectual basis. So I began
to work privately. I split my
life into two. On my day job, I
was a traditional academic, you
know, teaching courses, grading
papers, going to meetings and
all that. And in my private
life, I began a 20 year journey
working following Stan Grof
protocol. I ended up working
with high doses of LSD for
reasons I described in the book.
This is a very aggressive
protocol. It's not a protocol
that I would recommend today at
the end of the journey, but I
basically did 73 high dose LSD
sessions, let me say that each
session was completely isolated.
I was separated from the world.
I was in what I call the
psychedelic Kiva, a very
protected environment separate
from the world, lying down with
the sitter. My sitter was a
clinical psychologist who also
happened to be my wife, through
all of my sessions, wearing eye
shades and with headphones,
listening to very carefully
selected music to support the
deepening of the process. So
that's where I began. I worked
for four years. I stopped for
six years again for reasons that
I give in the book, and then I
resume for another 10 years, and
the method, the psychedelic
method, as a philosophical
method, involves systematically
expanding the boundaries of
one's consciousness. And let me
say that we understand that
psychedelics in general and LSD
in particular, represent is an
amplifier of consciousness. It
doesn't give you any specific
experiences. It amplifies your
consciousness. Makes you
hypersensitive for a number of
hours at a time. How you use
that hypersensitivity very much
influences what emerges over a
long period of time. If you go
to a concert or you just sit
down chat with friends, you're
going to have a certain level of
experience. But if you approach
these hours in a contemplative
manner, if you approach them as
an opportunity to go deep within
your consciousness, totally
internalized, isolating yourself
from the world, a journey
begins. It's a journey that has
many levels, because as we
confront all the things that a
hyper sensitive mind throws up
to us to confront, and it
usually starts with all the
fears, all the things we're
ashamed of, all the things we're
unhappy about, those are the
early confrontations that lead
to the healing process. But if
you keep that up, it keeps going
deeper and deeper and deeper. If
you navigate this, this journey
carefully, I always recorded my
sessions within 24 hours, and
that's really important, because
the more careful you are in
recording your session and
pondering them, the clearer, the
deeper your next session is
likely to be. So there's a
circle of learning that's
involved. So for 20 years, I
kept up this systematic
practice, and then I waited. I
stopped it. I went from 79 to 99
and then I didn't write LSD in
the universe, I didn't publish
it until 20 years later. In 2019
I spent many years analyzing my
experiences, pondering them,
trying to sort them out, before
I was ready to really publicly
release this hidden side of my
life. My students never learned
about my psychedelic work. I
kept a firewall between my
public life and my private life
in this regard, and it's only
after I retired from the
university that I've really been
willing to go public on this
side of my life. Amazing.
Andrew Holecek: Even there,
there's so much to talk about.
Let me just if I might ping one
question for you. Just briefly,
I am a musician. My first degree
is actually in classical piano,
and so just briefly, why? Why
music? What was the role of
music and how did it help you?
How did you choose it? I don't
want to spend a ton of time on
this. Yeah, but, I am
interested, where did that
inspiration come from, and how
did, how did it end up
supporting your journey? There's
early
Chris Bache: research done on
how music influences psychedelic
sessions. I have references to
that, to the those sources in my
work based. Basically it creates
a field and an ambiance that
supports you, letting go of your
current physical reality,
relaxing and yielding to this up
rushing of material that comes
from the unconscious. There are
about five stages in a
psychedelic session as the
energy is building, as it's
peaking, and as you're coming
down, it's hours, you know, it's
eight hours of the day, and you
have to choose music to support
each stage of that process. So
the music would be very
aggressive and very long,
chordal sequences with powerful
crescendos in the early stages,
long, expansive passages in the
middle stages, gradually
tapering off into quieter and
quieter and judgment music at
the end. After of after only a
year or so, I basically stopped
using classical music, which is
more commonly used. I shifted to
using a lot of indigenous music
because I found it to be more
powerfully evocative. It helped
me go into let go of my
conventional reality and enter
into unusual reality.
Andrew Holecek: Well, that's
really interesting, Chris,
because in the inner yogas of
tantric Buddhism, which I know
you're a student of the
Vajrayana. Yeah, as you know,
the subtle body is actually the
kind of frequency or the domain
that is literally quite in
resonance with sound. And so
when we're actually touched by
music, it's really our subtle
body that is touched. And this
is really interesting to me,
because when you talk about this
journey, which in one way, and
I'll be curious to see if this
resonates with you, I really
appreciated your frequent
allusions to the work of Carl
Jung, and I don't remember you
saying this overtly, but the
process of individuation, how it
is that bringing the unconscious
processes into the light of
conscious awareness is what, in
fact, constitutes one vector of
awakening. And so the reason
this is interesting to me is
that the subtle body is also
connected to the unconscious
mind, and so in a certain way.
And let me see if this is
landing with you. When you're
working with this type of music,
it's almost as if you're
creating a tuning for
Invitational harmonic in
external auditory mechanisms or
mediums that therefore could
perhaps evoke correlative inner
qualities that help you, in
fact, bring these processes into
the Light of Consciousness. Is
it fair to say something like
that?
Chris Bache: I think that's
fair. And, you know, basically,
I think that's a good
description. The subtle body is
very actively involved in the
psychedelic process when you
open up into deeper states of
consciousness, I learned that
deeper states of consciousness
are higher levels of energy, and
so it places enormous demands on
your physical body, but
particularly their subtle energy
body. And so it's very the
subtle energy body is very much
involved. It's a very you're
moving into highly stimulated
states, which are not simply
psychologically stimulating, but
they're energetically subtle,
energetically stimulating and
physically stimulating. Yeah,
that really
Andrew Holecek: makes so much
sense to me. But I want to put
an exclamation point, and return
to something that you intimated
that you also ping on later in
your book, connected to this
kind of amplification, using
these agents as means to
heighten awareness and
amplifying the mind. And what
you said at the end really
struck me, because, in fact, I
was a student of chugya Trungpa
Rinpoche, a statement that I
always took from him to be
pejorative negative, that LSD is
super Samsara. I originally
heard that as a negative, your
twist on it was fantastically
alchemical or tantric, because
now you put a positive spin on
it, that in a very beautiful
way, the super Samsara gives you
the opportunity to bring these
unconscious processes into the
light of awareness. And
therefore, I think the word you
use is confront, even
confrontation, the word you
could say inner jihad, right to
wrestle with these inner
dimensions as a way, again, in
the alchemical or tantric
spirit, to transform these super
Samsara into nirvana through
proper relationship. Is that? Is
that one way to talk about what
you experienced as well?
Chris Bache: It is I want to, I
want to tag two items there. The
first one, again, it all depends
on how you meet this super
Samsara. Samsara is very
addictive. It's very
distracting, it's very alluring.
And if you increase the your
sensitivity to Samsara, it can
take you on a journey that just
will just distract you and lead
you, and it really doesn't take
you anywhere. Accept through
into more Samsara. But if you
use this opportunity in a true
contemplative fashion to look
deeply at the Samsara that's
there, then you you find that
you the Samsara will fall apart.
You, when really take the
samsaric tendencies to their
roots, and when you take them to
their roots, they become
uprooted, and you begin to move
into deeper levels, deeper
levels of Samsara, but then
eventually into the levels that
go beyond Samsara, into extra
Samsara levels of reality, into
the Bardo, but then eventually
into extra Samsara levels of
reality. Now I want to the
second point I want to mention
is people use psychedelics for
many different purposes, some
for recreation, some to hyper
stimulate creativity. But three
basic purposes are therapeutic
healing, which is the dominant
way that people are using
psychedelics today in the
psychedelic Renaissance, to heal
the wounds of life, of the
personal psyche, second for
spiritual realization to
accelerate one's awakening, to
accelerate the one's awareness
of Nirvana, or entering into the
condition of nirvana. And this
is why I had started. This is
what got me started, like many
people in the late 70s, into the
psychedelic work, but
eventually, very quickly,
really, that agenda fell away in
my practice, partly because of
the very powerful protocol that
I adopted. Personal
enlightenment fell away as not a
significant part of my journey,
it came back around in the end,
and it was always there, but it
wasn't the primary modality,
collective awakening became very
important that is working on
behalf of the human family. The
Bodhisattva vow, in a sense,
came through very strongly. But
eventually my work settled into
a third agenda, which I would
call cosmological exploration.
The what my work became was a
long journey into what I think
of as the consciousness of the
universe, or the consciousness
of the creative intelligence
that's behind the universe and
within the universe, and you
don't need to explore all those
deep pathways in order to awaken
spiritually. You don't need to
go into archetype of reality.
You don't need to go back to the
birth of the universe in order
to awaken to the truth of your
essential nature, as the
Buddhist would say, or to your
Christ consciousness, as the
Christians would say. And so I
wanted to differentiate
cosmological exploration from
the project of spiritual
awakening, because if we hold
cosmological exploration to the
measures or criteria of success
of spiritual awakening, I think
we're going to miss the mark of
what's actually taking place in
the journey.
Andrew Holecek: Oh my gosh,
Chris boy, you're going to the
deep end of the pool. Yeah. Wow.
So let's unpack this, because I
think this is really
interesting. This is super
important, in my opinion,
because it begs a number of
questions. One, is the
relationship between, excuse me,
the individual and the
collective, the individual and
the cosmos. And therefore, deep,
as a scholar of religion and
philosophy, deep questions about
the nature of mind and reality
that I guess, to paraphrase it,
there's so many ways to get into
this, but 111, question that
comes to mind is, is it, in
fact, the mind that's in the
universe or the universe that's
in the mind? In other words,
what exactly is the relationship
between the individual and the
cosmic? And is, in fact, part of
what I hear is a dissonance,
potential. Dissonance, for me,
is a, is a subtle cosmological
dualism that there therefore
seems to intimate a difference
between the individual and the
cosmic, that there's still some
sense of separation implied
there. So maybe help me
understand that tease that apart
for me, because if I noticed in
one of your footnotes, you talk
that if you were to pin yourself
into a corner philosophically,
you would, you would define
yourself as a monist. And so how
does monism play into this if,
in fact, you're intimating a
subtle dualism?
Chris Bache: It's only a
functional dualism which all
monist traditions recognize. Fun
at Quora. I'm a monist at heart.
And this comes this not a
philosophical position, it's an
experiential position.
The deeper one goes into one's
own consciousness eventually
come to that point where, where
let. Let me, let me back up and
start again. Contemporary
thought, scientific thought,
tends to see the physical world
as the only world that exists.
And they tend to see the
physical world as operating by
mechanistic processes, that
there is not consciousness in
atomic in chemical processes,
and that consciousness somehow
pops into existence at some
point in the evolutionary
process. Now there are lots of
philosophical reasons for
challenging the adequacy of that
understanding of consciousness,
and I align with those
philosophers who are
panpsychists who believe that
consciousness, or the what you
might think of as or
consciousness, a core origin,
consciousness is present in
physical reality or energetic
reality from the very start, and
that conscious consciousness
isn't added later, but
consciousness is part of the
emerging universe from the Big
Bang forward. So that just mark
that okay experientially, when
one, when one shatters one's
personal mind, when when one
reaches the limits where your
personal history can no longer
contain what's happening in your
mind. And when you've excavated
through the various levels of
your personal unconscious, one
drops into a larger field of
consciousness. Part of that one
of the part of the field you
drop into is the field of your
species mind. And here's the
common ground with Carl Jung the
collective psyche. But if you
keep working and dropping and
dropping and dropping you deep,
it drop into deeper and deeper,
larger and larger levels of
consciousness until eventually
you're in very familiar, very
territory that's very familiar
to the mystics. When they are
talking about God consciousness
are talking about all as one.
The experience over and over
again, is that the entire
universe, both its physical
manifestation and it's the mind
that underlies this
manifestation is fundamentally a
single organism, and that all
life takes place within this
single singularity, and all life
is a manifestation of an
emergence of this singularity in
diversity. And when we first
began to discover this
underlying reality, what I would
call the mother universe that
underlies the daughter universe
of the physical world during the
Axial Age, you know, about three
to 5000 years ago, it was so
what we encountered, where we
began to get, have the the
meditation techniques, or the
psychedelic techniques in the
early Hindu Soma, to Drop into
this reality. It was so
intoxicating and so ecstasy
filled, that we developed an
interpretation of life that said
that the purpose, the purpose of
life was to get back to that,
that there is nothing worth
holding on to in physical
reality. There is nothing worth
holding on to in individuality,
what you really want to do is
take the drop and put it back
into the ocean. You want to
dissolve ego and end up in back
into the oneness. And I
understand that, but I think
it's a fundamentally flawed
cosmology. Now that we're
beginning to understand how old
the universe, how big it is, how
intelligent it is, how how long
it's been working to bring
forward the more evolved forms
of life that it has to think
that after 13 point 7 billion
years of evolution, when just a
Few 1000 years ago, we've become
self conscious enough to be able
to penetrate our individual
consciousness and discover this
underlying cosmic, cosmic
consciousness, which holds the
entire universe, just when we
discover that, then we want to
dissolve and disappear out of
existence altogether, home.
Makes no sense. I don't think
that's and what I've learned, or
what I've been taught in my
sessions, is that the universe
wants to support individuality,
not the prism, not not the
individuality that's imprisoned
within solitary, egoic
awareness, but a robust
individuality of what we might
call the soul, which is open and
porous and in constant exchange
with the larger rhythms of life.
This is the both and position
that when one awaken
spiritually, one literally
becomes more. More of an
individual than you were before
you awakened, you know. So
there's a, so there is a, I
think that when we go deep, we
not only discover the oneness,
and we discover that that
oneness is the essence of our
individual being. Classic Atman
is Brahman. The essence of the
individual is the essence of the
totality. But now we discover
that Brahman delights in
manifesting Atman and in growing
Atman, and in Atman waking up to
its own true nature, and then
that waking up is just a stage
in a larger evolutionary process
of empowerment so that we
literally learn to become more
and more and more of a conscious
synthesis of individuality and
spiritual totality.
Andrew Holecek: Oh, Chris, oh my
gosh. I can hardly contain
myself here. What I mean? Talk
about diamonds from heaven. I
mean, this is your journey.
You're not Johnny Appleseed.
You're You're Johnny diamond.
See, your life is throwing
diamonds. But let me just maybe
this is an issue of semantics
and the nuance of talking. Yeah,
what a challenge when you start
talking about Non-duality,
nature of mind and reality using
dualistic mechanisms, you're
headed into trouble. So but help
me understand a couple things
when, when you talk about the
universe, wants to support and
there are other intimations in
your in your book, that I found
really compelling, how it is
that you felt from day one, that
there was a larger intelligence
that was guiding your journey,
that you felt held by the
beloved. And remind me to come
back to this, because I want to
share a personal story about my
own retreat time where this,
this came into real dissonance
with me as a practicing
Buddhist, because, as you know,
on the Buddhist tradition, their
biggest, one of the biggest
teachings, is on emptiness, non
theism and that sort of thing.
And so I'm wrestling a little
bit with reconciling things like
non theism and emptiness with
what you're talking about. So to
be a little more articulate
about this, let's be point a
little bit more paint point
blank. From my end, how do you
reconcile man theism, with this
notion of Universal
Intelligence, which almost seems
to intimate a creator principle,
a God, if we dare say, because
you almost seem to be implying
that there is a divine trans
human intelligence, God,
whatever term you want to pen to
it, that somehow is, in fact,
your beloved that is holding
you, guiding you and nurturing
you. How do you reconcile that
with the teachings on emptiness
and non theism?
Chris Bache: Yeah, it's really
not difficult when you when you
move into it. So let's focus on
the Buddhist teaching of anata,
no self, emptiness of self.
Shunyata trans, which can also
be trans, translated
transparency. I think I really
endorse the Buddhist position of
its radical agnosticism. I think
it's an anti theism. So
basically, it's a critique that
says every theism which is being
proposed or has been proposed
has structural flaws to it that
it so the concept of God, the
concept of theism is critiqued
as being inadequate, and in its
place, Buddhism proposes a pure
process understanding of
reality, that everything is
dynamic, everything is
constantly changing. Everything
is fluid. Everything is in
process. There is no thing which
holds its existence by itself.
You only exist in the interplay
of the whole ocean of causality,
of karmic forces, cosmic, down
to species, down to individual.
It's all an open system. And
when you when you wake up to
your essential nature, you
don't. You don't wake up to a
separate thing. You wake up to a
fluid process, and you breathe.
Now, the fluid process of
existence, I take that to heart,
and that resonates with my
experience, in that every I
experienced myself as constantly
being guided and instructed and
tutored in my psychedelic
sessions. But the nature of that
consciousness that held me and
broke me down and and opened me
and then broke me down some
more, the nature of that
consciousness never revealed
itself. As a being, as a person,
as a personality, and the very
structure of what it was that I
was engaging kept expanding and
changing. Now in psychedelic
states, you don't learn, or you
learn by becoming what it is
that you're trying to learn
about. You don't take the ego
there and have an experience of
something. You literally shatter
and you dissolve and become
this. So my experience was that
when I began to become aware of
this, this other that was
holding me and guiding me, and I
began to ask it, who are you?
What are you? I experienced a
death which then dissolved me
into a deeper level of reality
where I discovered that I was
this was myself. It was a deeper
level of quote, myself, not my
personal self, capital M. And
this repeated itself over and
over and over for hours on this
one particular session, until
eventually it brought me into
the realization that it's an
endless progression. It's it's a
seamless consciousness within
this vast consciousness. We are
an individual consciousness
confronting an infinite
consciousness. How we experience
ourselves at the moment of
contact, as we dissolve into it,
influence what arises out of
this infinite consciousness. And
that's that awareness, that this
consciousness that I was
engaging and discovered myself
to be part of was truly infinite
and open ended, and that I
reached a point 15 years into
the journey where I discovered I
would never reach the end of it.
It was an infinite progression.
No matter how many years I did
this work, there was always more
to discover. So that means, and
that, to me, resonates very
deeply with the Buddhist
position on its critique of
theism, its critique of gods
that have physical forms of the
critique of gods that are come
out of human history and that
are we can understand to be
partial approximations, attempts
to understand something which
are partially adequate and
radically inadequate at the same
time. You know so when you move
beyond individual consciousness
and move into the collective
psyche and begin to engage some
of the dynamics of the
collective psyche. Part of what
you engage are all the stories
that we've been telling
ourselves for 10s of 1000s of
years, all the values that have
been involved in these stories,
which have been reinforcing
themselves on all these cultural
traditions. And there comes a
point where you die out of the
collective psyche, just as
earlier you had died out of your
personal psyche. And when you
die out of the collective
psyche, you move into a states
of awareness which are trans
species, which are go far beyond
the entire human history. And at
that point, you're moving into
states of awareness that are
radically, radically beyond and
clear than any states of
consciousness that take place
within the collective psyche.
And you just you realize that
all the stories of our religions
are part of the collective
psyche story, and that there are
the realities far, far, far
beyond any of those realities.
And I think that Buddhism is
pointing to that phenomena. When
it says it's fundamentally
agnostic, it says you shouldn't
restrict yourself to any
limiting belief about God.
However, you can experience the
reality that we're pointing to.
We can experience this reality,
but our understanding of it will
always be partial and
fragmented.
Andrew Holecek: Oh, my goodness.
So geez, every one of these
little snippets brought off for
a couple hours on this. Yeah,
there are a couple of things
here that really stood out for
me, Chris and again, there's,
there's, these are really seed
syllables for massive arenas of
for conversation. But one is, is
what you talk about so
beautifully in your book. And I
have not read living classroom
yet, but I literally just got it
in the mail, and that is this
radical, revolutionary new
pedagogical approach, which you
talk about, and I love it. This,
this transition from kind of
Newtonian, atomistic pedagogy,
individuality, separate from
others, to kind of a quantum
entangled pedagogy where using
that mixing metaphor is the
connective tissue of
consciousness that you're
really. So you're learning by
becoming I mean, what a
fantastic thing to say, which,
by the way, has resonance in
both the Hindu and Buddhist
traditions through what my
language is the Gnostic
pedagogical approach of hearing,
contemplating, meditating, which
is ingest, digest, metabolize,
until the teachings actually are
purified, filtered from
conceptual defilements into full
somatic empowerment, embodiment,
and there that's where true
knowing comes from. And so I
love that aspect of your
journey, that that it introduces
a type of pedagogy that is
completely resonant with the
classic wisdom traditions. You
experience this through your
journey, I also want to come
back to and this is key to me,
and this was a really, really
big experience for me when I did
my three year retreat where I
experienced what you're
referring to for the first time
in my life, and I wrestled with
it, Chris, because it really at
that time, it wasn't dissonance
with my obviously limited
understanding of emptiness and
non theism, where I did feel I
was being held and loved by
something bigger than me. And
this really created a rut for
me, because it was like, Hey,
wait a second. I thought there
was no externality. I thought it
was all solipsist. You know,
it's not solipsistic, but it's
just mind only. So how, how can
there be an external agency
without capitulating to the god
principle? And so what I want to
share with you, that, again,
your book was such an
inspiration for me, is that, in
a very real way, when I was
doing these guru yogas and
devotional practices properly,
my mind broke. I died to a
limited self sense I had, you
know, we can come back to this
in a little bit. There's just
tremendous hardship and pain
before that breakthrough
occurred, and then the minute
that happened, I felt this
complete container, mandala,
holding environment of love and,
dare I say, and this is in
quotations, an external agency
that was, in fact, holding me.
And then what became
unbelievably interesting to me,
Chris was, in a certain way, in
the third year of my retreat, I
lost something. I lost some of
these initial qualities. And so
it first, it was like, Wait a
second, I Where did my magical
nature of mine go and, and I
was, I really entered a kind of
a dark night of the soul within
my three year retreat. And a
lama came in and said something
that just floored me, that it
was a female Lama that said the
dakinis can bestow awakening,
and they can take it away. And,
and I said,
Unknown: What? What
Andrew Holecek: like that was
like, you know, it was like a
big Bong just hit my head. But
it was so true, it felt like
somehow it had been taken away.
And it took me decades, Chris,
to finally understand the really
brutal, painful, powerful lesson
that was developing in my
retreat. And you mentioned this
a little bit in the very last
chapter of your book, which I
thought was just absolutely
genius, that I was getting stuck
in a kind of almost spiritual
bypassing, or Transcendentalism,
in the negative sense, that I
was dissolving into these
completely formless realms where
I became the universe. And I
realized, on one level, when
this agency, for lack of a
better term, took it away the
and this is my thought bubble,
probably akin to some of the
thought bubbles that entered
you. It was like the command
was, you will find me in form,
or you will not find me at all.
In other words, it was almost as
if don't get stuck on this
formless stuff. Don't get stuck
in the transcendental aspect.
Come back to the earth. Come
back to the imminent, come back
into body. And that turned out
to be one of the most radically
challenging. And eventually,
over 20 years of trying to
incorporate that revelatory
experiences of the retreat was
that, no, it's not about this
ascent into this fundamental
Godhead. That's just half the
journey. The other half, the
evolutionary half, is taking
that and bringing it riveting,
it molding it back into the
earth. And so I want to pause
just to share that story with
you, because when you share that
in your book, it was like, Oh my
gosh, this is exactly resonant
with what happened in my own
experience. And so I want to
return to, if you don't mind,
help me further understand, and
this will help many of my
listeners, who are Buddhists,
who really work in the realm of
non theism and emptiness, this
so called agency, the beloved,
that, in fact, can embrace, that
we can call on, that we can work
with, that we really are not
alone. We can take refuge in
these greater forces to help us
along our path. So sorry for the
long winded interjection, but I
want to because I appreciate
very powerful my own experience,
not just a theoretical thing.
This is a big deal in my own
practice life.
Chris Bache: Yeah, you know,
maybe it's a footnote to my.
Earlier comment to bridge into
this new wing. I think Sri
Aurobindo critique of Buddhism
is correct in that he he
criticizes Buddhism for not
sufficiently confronting the
fact of existence, the the
extraordinary power and majesty
of existence in in rejecting
anything static and anything in
form, in its agnosticism, in its
anti theism. And it's I'm not
taught teaching all of that as
well and good. But he says, We
have to come to Terence with the
fact of the magnitude and the
genius and the majesty of the
universe of which we are part.
Now Buddhism may say, well,
thank you very much. We don't
need that. What we really need
is freedom from our suffering.
I'll take the freedom from
suffering, and I'm not going to
engage in the metaphysical quote
speculation and our bend those
responses. It's not an either
or, and it's a certain kind of a
capitulation to not confront
some of the magnitude of the
breath of life. And I think that
now to move more towards what
you were describing, I mean
when we have these
breakthroughs, when we do the
work and we go through the
purification processes, and we
face our shortcomings, and we
let go, and we let go, and we
immerse ourselves deeper and
deeper, and then when we have
these melting experiences,
where, as you say, we are
embraced, we are held by orders
of of genius and orders of love
beyond anything we had ever
experienced before. And one can
go deeper into that, there's
there's, I've learned that
there's so many levels of
oneness. And there's even levels
of of of the void, of the
fertile void, though that seems
like a contradiction. There are
levels of that, and you can go
deeper and deeper into that. And
it feels initially like an
external or an other because it
wasn't there before, or we
didn't experience it before, but
we do now, and it's it clearly
is not inside of us. It feels
outside of us because it's
holding us. But the more sorry
I'm having something peeping off
back here, it's okay. It's all
good. The more you go back and
forth into that condition and
back out again and into it and
press it, of course, the more
you realize that you're just
waking up to your own nature.
You're awake because your nature
and this universal nature is the
same nature that our essential
nature is this vast expanse,
this love that floods us from
outside is actually a love which
is welling up also from with
inside. The challenges is
stabilizing those insights and
bringing them into our daily
experience. Now I think this is
a this is a challenge of all
spiritual practice. Of course,
we go on these long retreats, we
get into subtle, subtle
territories. We come back to the
honking horns, and it's just
it's so difficult to hold on and
to integrate day to day. And
this is particularly the case, I
think, in psychedelic practice,
whether you're using
psychedelics as a spiritual
practice, or whether you're
using psychedelics, as I did, as
a measure aiming at cosmological
exploration. Because in my
experience, in what I did, I
think I pushed myself far, far
deeper into the consciousness of
the universe than I could ever,
ever internalize and stabilize
in this lifetime. And I came to
realize during my time, after I
came off the mountain, after I
stopped my work when I was
beginning to kind of just come
off the mountain, come away from
that long period of practice
that I had, I had created an
imbalance, an unwitting
imbalance. I thought that
because I had integrated each
session thoroughly and carefully
and conscientiously, that I
could step back from my sessions
and I could take all these
blessings with me. And I learned
that I had basically leaned so
heavily into Transcendence that
I had sort of lost my foothold
in imminence. And I knew from my
experience. Experience is that
the entire universe was the body
of divine are the body of this
infinite consciousness. I knew
that I was never outside of
divine reality, inside physical
reality, but I could not hold
that awareness. Yet inside
physical reality, I know that
there are beings who do the
Great Beings are always one's
guides in these things. But I
had, it's kind of like you, I
think what, what I was kind of
kicked off of the path, kicked
off of the mountain by the
sessions themselves. I did not
know I was ending them. They
were being ended. But there came
I had these last sessions, which
basically let me know that it
was time to end. And one of the
things I learned in the process
of ending is that I had to not
expand my consciousness. I had
to not alter my consciousness in
any way if the states of being
that I had experienced in my
sessions were ever going to come
and awaken fully inside my
historical existence. So I had
to sit with the shell of my
historical existence if I was
ever going to fully integrate
these vast bliss, domains of
ecstatic presence. And I think,
I think I did go farther than
was good for me, and I have been
in a completely different but
equally important process since
I stopped my sessions, the way
the sessions put it, or the way
my meditation put it is, there
is the dying of discovering, and
then the dying of keeping. And I
had done the dying of discovery,
but now I had to do the dying of
keeping, and that's a different
process. Wow.
Andrew Holecek: I mean, you're
stopping my mind with every one
of these, so many things here,
but a couple things, whoa. So
much about this is mind bending.
It's really mental yoga,
stretching almost to the
breaking point. And so a couple
questions here is, and I wrestle
with this. I mean, your the
integrity of your being, Chris,
your presence, the clarity of
your writing, the elegance of
your scholasticism, your
academic predispositions and the
like, I have to say, have been
incredibly important for me to
substantiate the veracity of
your journey. And I see it with
the mobility of simply the way
you're presenting yourself. It's
like this is the real deal. The
real deal, but it is such a mind
stretch. And so a couple of
things along this beautiful
challenge of stretching into the
notion of, I love your
nomenclature here, psychedelic
practice. I've never heard that
before. So talk to us a little
bit about this revolutionary
notion Greek, you know, the
skids have been greased by
Michael Pollan, James Kingsland,
Stan Grof, these amazing
predecessors, the shoulders upon
which you now stand where you
can now silently but radically
proclaim the validity of
Entheogen, psychedelics as path.
So talk a little bit more about
the practice of psychedelics,
how to work. This is a path. And
then to come back to before I
forget, parenthetically, the the
importance of integration and
the danger of disintegration. In
other words, were you ever
afraid of going insane, that you
were stretched beyond your
capacities to contain, and
instead of stretching, you snap.
So again, there's two big
noodles thrown there. The first
noodles, yeah, the first and I
think in many ways, probably the
most important, is talk to us
about psychedelics as practice
and path, and then to come back,
maybe a little bit about the
process of integration versus
disintegration, sanity versus
insanity.
Chris Bache: Yeah. Well, you
know, in different interviews
that I've done, I make the point
that I've never tripped. People
say, you've done 73 trips. I
say, No, I've never tripped.
I've done sessions. These are
therapeutically focused
sessions. But actually, I'm in
my own mind, I think of the
Japanese term sashin. The sashin
is a meditation retreat. It's a
period of time set aside for
spiritual, intense spiritual
practice. So when I talk about
LSD sessions, I could be talking
about LSD sashin. It is a period
of time set aside for
therapeutic work, for spiritual
work, for cosmological work. And
there are certain just as in a
sashin that. Your daily right?
Life changes. You change your
schedule, you change your eating
you change your sleeping
patterns, you change your
rhythm. In order to focus and
intensify this practice, just as
you did when you did your three
year retreat, everything changes
around this long period of
sustained introspection. The
same is true in the psychedelic
process. The critical the
underbelly of using psychedelics
as part of a practice of
transformation, an organized
practice of transformation. The
underbelly is that it's
temporary. You only have these
states for a few hours at a
time, and even if you use them
diligently, you still only have
them for a few hours of a time
at a time, which is really the
major reason why I stopped. It
became too painful for me to
keep coming back from these
states, until eventually, I made
a deal with my beloved, my name
for this intelligence, whatever
it is, that it would not bring
me back into these dimensions
again until I could stay it
became It was just too painful
to come and go. But before you
get to that point, you can do a
lot of cleaning, you can you do
a lot of healing, and you would,
you can do a lot of good for
other people in that. What
happened in my work, after about
two and a half years, when I
went through this, what Stan
calls the perinatal process. And
all you go through this,
reliving your birth, confronting
all the fears of death,
confronting the fundamental
existential crisis of whether
there is any meaning in
existence, eventually going to a
complete shattering of your
individual egoic reality. I
thought, Oh, that's great. I've
gone through an ego death. It
was a shattering experience.
Things are going to open up now
go into clean sailing, not what
happened. What happens that
everything cranked up all over
again. The suffering got worse,
and it expanded for two years of
practice into larger and larger
levels, 1000s, hundreds of 1000s
of people, 1000s and 1000s of
years, I had entered the hell
realms. And at first I thought
this is like a deeper level of
ego death. But eventually I came
to understand that, no, this was
not about me at all. This was
not about fundamentally, my
personal transformation, on my
personal awakening, or even my
personal healing. This was about
trying to heal some aspect of
the collective psyche, that
there is an organizational
structure, a consciousness, that
that is our species
consciousness, and all the
wounds of history that are left
unresolved are not only left
unresolved at an individual soul
level, but they are left
unresolved at the species level.
So all the wars we fought, all
the terrible things we've done
to each other, all the trauma,
to the extent that that trauma
is not healed, it it resides as
unfinished business within the
collective psyche. And every
spiritual practitioner who goes
deeply enough in whatever
methodology they're using is
given, often an invitation, if
they choose to exercise it, to
lift some of that suffering, not
out of their personal life, but
to lift some of that suffering
out of the collective psyche,
and for reasons that I think are
sole choice that became a large
part of my work. And I think
there's nothing really special
here. I mean, this is what any
mother who sees a child
suffering is going to do if she
can do something to try to help
that child suffering, to
alleviate it. Any father worth
his salt is going to try to help
a suffering child, if we are
given the opportunity, we're
going to try to help other
people who are in pain. This is
just the normal workings of
life. So to me,
in fact, it became a mystery to
me why the collective suffering
stopped, why I wasn't allowed to
stay in there anymore, when
clearly there's continuing
collective suffering in the
human psyche. Why was I taken
into deeper levels beyond that,
levels which are very difficult,
very challenging, but they were
not involved with collective
pain. I'm losing the second.
Andrew Holecek: Part of your
question that you would ask,
yeah, no, happy, happy. To throw
it back up, because there's and
there's so much richness coming
out that's returning to this
notion of we circumambulated
this but haven't really
directed. Talked about if the
place of fear and well of
integration versus
disintegration, did you ever
actually fear, especially coming
back to the so called real world
for your sanity? I mean, did you
ever feel you're going to become
so unhinged? Because let me just
say this very briefly, Chris,
one of the things that was
profoundly resonant with with
your work, and this is what just
blew me away, this kind of on
one level I've come to see
psychedelics is a type of
Tantra. And by this, what I mean
is, and this has been a radical
change in my more conservative
nature, being more
traditionalist and paying homage
again. There's tremendous genius
to the power of tradition. But
there are also some near
enemies, ossification,
redefining even the tradition
itself losing tributaries of new
information and growth. And so I
used to be really somewhat
disdainful of these kind of
psychedelic approaches. Is
chemical mysticism in the
pejorative sense, these kind of
cheap fixes. But I've really
changed my tune in that I now
see them as a type of Tantra. By
that, what I mean is that in
Tantra, body is as important as
mind. And now we're talking
about body, very subtle body.
We're talking about chemical
body. We're talking about body
at the level of neuro chemistry,
basically. And so I think again,
within the context of
psychedelics as practice and
path, it actually can fit in an
expanded rubric of Tantra, where
body, in this case, chemistry,
is as important as the mind that
is evoked. And this kind of
neuro pharma, phenologic, neuro
phenomenological way to use the
neuro end to bring about these
phenomenal states. And so with
that in mind, yeah, the question
was the role of fear, fear and
integration versus
disintegration, and how that
relates to your ability to
contain this information
Chris Bache: you I had, I did
come into places to go through A
Death-Rebirth cycle is always an
ordeal at one level or another.
It always involves a surrender
to the unknown. It always
involves yielding to a certain
fear that's holding your system
locked in place. And there were
places where at advanced stages
of the game that I truly did
fear for my sanity, or at least
I knew that I was going
someplace that was completely
beyond anything which I could
hold on to. I could not hold on
to sanity as I had known it. And
it was like going over a
waterfall, and you just but once
you go through that, once you go
over that waterfall, and you
experience that death, and you
experience waking up in a new
reality as a new being, a new
kind of being, not only a new
and improved you, but a
different kind of being, where,
for hours at a time, you can
experience the universe as it
experiences itself completely
beyond any human right frame of
reference once you experience
it. That is the nature of the
cycle. And this is one of the
great gifts that I got from Stan
Grof, was the absolute
conviction that if you let these
experiences take you wherever
they want to take you, even
though you don't understand
them, even though you don't
understand why it's happening
this way, and it's extremely
painful. If you surrender
completely, it will always take
you through a crisis, and it'll
catch you on the other side, and
it will receive you, and there,
there is a blessing waiting for
you on that other side, and for
me, coming back from a session,
it's never I have no trauma from
any of my psychedelic history. I
can listen to the music I used
and even the most horrifying
aspects of the journey, and I
love it. I'm completely
comfortable with it. I can talk
about any of the difficult
portions without any resonating,
any trauma, because when you
take it all the way through, you
complete the cycle. Things get
bad. They get worse. They get
worse. They get very, very bad.
But if you let surrender, it'll
take you through to a
completion, into ecstasy, and
then what you bring back is this
entire cycle. You bring back the
knowledge that things get bad,
but things things get great, and
that's the rhythm of death and
rebirth. That is the spiral of
death and rebirth. Now that
doesn't mean and I thought as
long as that was going on, I
was. Teaches that you know that
I was holding everything in
balance. What I did find,
however, is that other thing we
talked about, you can go so far
into the ecstasy, you can go so
deep into Transcendence that
literally learning how to live
with your memories becomes a
major challenge. So as a
spiritual practice, this
practice is different from
classical spiritual practices,
which are much more emphasizing
kind of holding on to
everything, relatively speaking,
holding on to where you go in
smaller increments. I have an I
have an understanding of how the
universe works, but I don't live
within that reality on a 24/7
basis. The great beings live
basis. So being able to, I'm
speaking out of my memory, and
it's good to have memories of
these realities. I mean, I
really think that changed my
life. But it's one thing to be
speaking out of memory. It's
another thing to be speaking out
of an immediate present, right
here, living experience of this
reality and learning you can
internalize so many profound
memories that it literally
becomes challenging to live with
those memories. They haunt you
for the rest of your life, and
they haunt you in a good way.
They're not. They don't haunt
you in any negative way. You
literally are haunted by the
beauty of the universe, right?
And so you just, you try to live
it and embodiment as best as you
can. Yeah.
Andrew Holecek: Do you think? Do
you think, Chris, one of the
things that really struck me was
what you just paraphrased, and I
have to say, in this part of the
book, I struggled with this part
of this part of the book, when
you were talking about just all
the pain, all the hardship, all
the death, the unbelievably
wrenching section about the
dying children, was I was almost
too much. And so, yeah, I hung
in there, and I'm glad I did, in
a certain way, almost metaphoric
of you're hanging in there. But
is it possible that that perhaps
the what was being invited was
developing a one taste
relationship to both the heaven
and the hell, that there would
in fact, be no preference and no
because that's what they say,
allegedly, the very highest
stages before the 11th Bhumi,
the highest kind of membrane
barrier before awakening, is no
preference whatsoever for
Samsara, nor Nirvana in
discovering the inseparability.
So do you think on one level
that the agency was somehow
eliciting the teaching lesson of
great equanimity, that, in fact,
relate to the agony in the same
way you relate to the ecstasy,
to realize that there's
fundamentally no preference for
either that, that that may have
been what was being suggested
there? Does that resonate with
you.
Chris Bache: I understand the
teaching, and that teaching does
come up and reflect certain
aspects of the journey. I'm not
sure that it reflects this
particular aspect in a in a
satisfying way. I have a
different way of understanding
because you're talking here
about the ocean of what I call
the ocean of suffering. And you
know, one of the things I
describe in the book is insights
that came much later in the
session, that I don't think
everybody has to go into
something like the ocean of
suffering. I don't think
everybody has to go into the
hell realms or spend as long in
the hell realms as I spent
there. I mean, I don't think
people need to be afraid of
going through what I went
through as kind of a necessary
part of any kind of spiritual
journey or cosmological
exploration. I think that this
was something that my chose, my
soul chose to do before I was
born. It manifested so quickly
in my sessions after a couple of
years, and it was such a
tenacious and sustained part of
my journey that I came to
understand that this was
literally a soul's choice. And I
say this without pride at all,
because I think there are many,
many, many beings in the world
today who have made the same
choice. I think we are living in
a critical time in history. We
are living in a time when the
sin. Of the fathers literally
are just pouring out of us. And
I don't I quote The biblical
passage, not to put this all on
men, but that really the
limitations of our up to now
standard, of our evolutionary
standard, are just pouring out
of us because we are being
challenged to move into our next
evolutionary step, not only as
individuals, but as the species
that the creative intelligence
of the universe is trying to
awaken not only individual
spiritual practitioners, but the
game is collective now it's
desperately trying to awaken the
entire human species and the the
hell realms that one are
literally manifesting on Earth
as part of this collective
detoxification process. And I
think there are many beings who
are have taken the Bodhisattva
vow into their life and are
working to alleviate suffering,
collectively, socially,
politically and also psycho
spiritually. Because I think
this century is different than
earlier centuries, because
there's a boiling taking place
as a there's a there's a turning
which is taking place deep
within. And so I assume that I
knew what I was getting into,
and I volunteered for this work,
and I know that this it's a hard
chapter to read, even though I
cut it down to the minimal form,
it's difficult material. And yet
I've had so many people write me
and say, I know exactly what
you're talking about, because
I've been, I've been going
through these experiences for
years, or I went through them
and I didn't understand them.
You've helped me understand them
some. But I think it's, it's not
an unusual experience, once we
understand that what's taking
place here is a collective
dynamic. It's something that we
as an individual may have
started, but the universe uses
our individual initiative to
accomplish something of its
purpose of its agenda, and its
agenda is to heal the human
species in order to clear out
the dross that is holding us
back, to make more room for the
infusion of grace, our energy or
awareness that is coming to
carry humanity through this
crisis that we are coming into.
We literally cannot afford to be
a planet that's run by egos
anymore? Yeah, for sure, we're
just killing the planet. We need
to be a planet that's run by
awakened souls, and by that I
mean beings who have a conscious
awareness of their history, so
that they know that they are not
simply egos, separate private
cells that they have an awakened
soul consciousness where they
know themselves to be spiritual
beings in dynamic relationship
with other spiritual beings,
including non human beings. In
this world, you know, animal
kingdom, and when we wake up in
that way, and we discover how
old we are and how many
generations we've been doing
this, and we discover the
breadth of our human of our
relationships with other beings,
then Naturally, we make
different choices. We make more
inclusive choices. We make
choices for the long term, we
make choices on that serves the
good of all. And right now, I
think we desperately need to be
making choices that are
inclusive and work for the good
of all.
Andrew Holecek: Yeah, that's
really beautiful. With your
permission, and if you don't
want to go here, that's fine. I
want to turn again. I have to
contain both my enthusiasm and
the energy of like, Oh my gosh.
We need to talk about that. We
need to talk about that. So I'm
letting so much slide that it's
fantastic. But with your kind
permission, I want to turn to
this issue of the the scientific
and academic elephant in the
room. How do we know if
anything, any of this is
actually true? How do we know
issues of replica bill,
replicability? I mean, how do we
know if, if what you're seeing
is idiosyncratic to your own
biochemistry, that this and
again, in the best sense of the
word, not pejorative, this is
your trip. Yeah. And how do we
know that if seven, if 1000
other people did exactly what
you did, that they could even
come close to replicating your
insights? Or would they, in
fact, have their own particular,
biological, historical,
phenomenological, whatever
matrix? Context whereby they
would see and write a different
journey, a different book,
through 20 years of exploration.
So the issue here is the problem
of proof and universality. What
would happen if 1000 people did
exactly what you did and they
came up with 1000 different
visions? I mean, how certain are
you that what you're
experiencing is actually true,
or simply your enculturation,
your your own unique
biochemistry and all the
histories that bring about the
narrative that you're sharing
with us. So are you okay? Okay,
going in this direction?
Chris Bache: Absolutely, that's
a really important question. I
mean, that's like a foundational
question, because if it, if this
is only echoes from my own
personal psyche, or even echoes
from the collective psyche, then
it has a certain kind of
epistemic value, but it doesn't
really have sufficient epistemic
value that we that warrants our
attention. And I discussed this
all the way back in dark night,
early dawn, in the first
chapter, where I'm outlining
what it this psychedelic
philosophy, and there's a
section there called the
epistemic warrant of psychedelic
experience, where I flesh out
this question and look at what
the issues are involved In this,
in questioning whether these
experiences truly do have
epistemic value. So that's I
just point there. Also Ken ring
and I have had a dialog about
this. Ken is good friend,
wonderful researcher near death.
Episode, I used his books for
years in my classes. He
challenged me on the same
questions, and we did a dialog.
Eventually we published it in
I'm blanking on where it is. I
should have this at the tip of
my tongue, it's online. Yeah,
it's online. It's quite the
essay. Is our deep psychedelic
experiences trustable? Yeah, and
if it were just my experiences,
that would be one thing. But
here's, I think, the great value
of Stan Grof work, where Stan
Grof has collected psychedelic
experiences from hundreds, if
not 1000s of people over
decades, and he's integrated
them into a certain model of
what happens at different stages
of the journey. My experiences
fit squarely within the broader
phenomenological discussion of
experiences that he has already
outlined. And so I think that he
provides, in a sense, a broad
epistemic warrant for look,
taking seriously my maybe a
little unusually intense, or
maybe a little unusually deep my
experiences. But there's not too
much new here. When you look at
the full breadth of experiences
that he's reported in his many,
many books, culminating in his
great master work, the way of
the psychonaut. So there's a
deep, you know, overlap. There
another point, I think I'm
thinking of Michael sabhm, who
was a cardiologist in the early
days of the near death episode
movement, and he was very upset
that people were talking about
coming back from a cardiac
arrest and talking about
spiritual realities. He didn't
believe in any of that stuff,
and he was going to
systematically disprove it. And
he eventually wrote a book in
which he came to the conclusion
this stuff is real, and he
differentiate between what he
calls the local event and the
transcendent event that when
somebody has is in surgery or
has a cardiac arrest, they get
out of that they have a
sensation of getting out of
their body, and they can
experience what's going on in
the local arena, the surgical
theater, the waiting room down
the hall, the hospital, what's
going On in the parking lot
outside, and then they go into
the light, and they leave
physical reality, and they go
into a transcendental reality.
He says, We can't evaluate the
transcendent experience that
they have, but we can evaluate
the accuracy of their local
experience, and that's what he
tries to do whether what they
think they experience locally
is, in fact, verified,
verifiable in that world. And he
provided evidence that in fact
it was. Now that doesn't prove
that the transcendent experience
is true, but it certainly
increases the credibility that
if it's the local experience is
true, the Transcendence
experiences gets a little bit
more little boost of
credibility. The same thing
happens in psychedelic
experiences. Many psychedelic
experiences are such that they
can be verified information
about the conditions of birth or
circumstances of birth, the
things that people learn that
they really. We can reasonably
exclude the possibility that
they had learned through natural
means, and yet, it turns out
that these things can be
validated. That plays here. The
other part, though, is, I think,
cross validation, other people
having similar experience,
Andrew Holecek: communal
confirmation, exactly now,
Chris Bache: what we find is
this, when people start working
with psychedelics, if you took
100 people from 100 different
backgrounds, different socio
cultural backgrounds, different
trainings and whatnot, they
would have very different
experiences, because
psychedelics, or LSD, is an
amplifier. It doesn't take you
to a particular experience that
amplifies your mind. And because
we have different histories, we
come in contact with different
experiences. However, Stan
reports that when people go
through the perinatal
Death-Rebirth process, our
experiences get very, very
concentrated and very
standardized, we begin to deal
with issues which are not
idiosyncratic, but are
universal, fundamental
existential issues, and that
when people navigate the
Death-Rebirth experience, every
person that he has experienced
who goes through that process
comes back with a an
understanding of spiritual
reality, which is fundamentally
compatible with each other, that
there is a spiritual world that
was waiting for us and receives
us from then it's a matter of
evaluating our individual
explorations of that spiritual
world. Now, what I did in my
first in my first book on
psychedelics, near dark night,
early dawn, I put together three
areas of inquiry, psychedelic
research, near death episode
research and out of body
research, particularly the work
of Robert Monroe, founder of the
Monroe Institute of Applied
Science, author of three books
exploring the out of body state.
And I asked whether these
cosmology is that emerge from
these separate bodies of
exploration, out of body
research, near death episode
research, psychedelic research,
are their cosmological visions
diverging, or are they
converging? And once you look at
them carefully, they are
converging. They are clearly
converging. So that's addressing
the question Are, are these
experiences trustworthy? Now, in
my dialog with Ken ring, I
present other reasons why I
think they're trustworthy, and
that is for every time I had my
own cultural expectations
fulfilled, because I'm educated
in world religions, I'm educated
in comparative spirituality, I
have an understanding of certain
of these things, but for every
time I've had them confirmed,
I've also had more experiences
that that shatter my
expectations. I learned things I
was not expecting. I learned an
understanding of reincarnation,
how reincarnation works, and
where it's taking us that I was
not expecting at all. I wasn't
expecting anything about the
birth of the future human. There
was nothing about my
conditioning, which led me to
think that humanity was coming
into this crossroads. There were
so many things that I was shown
so consistently that were far
and beyond anything that I had
personally expected, that I
think one can reasonably
conclude that this is a
confrontation with truly an
independent reality. And I mean
independent, I have to qualify
that, but a reality that it was
not simply echoing back to me,
my own expectations. And if you
study the work of other people
who push deeply into these
conditions, into these states, I
think we find a fundamental
convergence, which doesn't mean
we're seeing the exact same
thing. But the issue is, do our
do our visions overlap? Are they
coherent with each other? Do
they overlap? Now, clearly we're
only at the very early stages of
this inquiry. What's important
is not any one person's
experience. What's important is
when we get, if we were to be
able to get a standardized
protocol, take 100 people, 1000
people with some type of
standardized protocol, with
very, very different
backgrounds, and put them
through the same regimen of
internal, introspective work,
then we get all of their
testimony, all of their
experiences, put them all on the
table, and begin to look at,
what is it that's consistent and
what is idiosyncratic? That's
where, where we're going. We're
just are not there yet. We're
only at the very early stages.
So I have no doubt that some of
the things may be somewhat
idiosyncratic to me. But. I
think that when we get to that
point where we have hundreds of
people putting their testimony
forward, we're going to find
much more consistency and
overlap than we find divergence.
Andrew Holecek: Oh, my goodness.
So so so many things here as
well. What a beautiful answer.
Crystal really the difference
between correspondence
epistemology and coherence.
Epistemology, I mean, the truth
is born of coherence is the type
of knowing that you're alluding
to here. But this begs the
question of aspirations around
this. And so pardon the tongue
in cheek reference here. But I
was this came to me out of who
knows where, where you know,
where do you see yourself in 20
years? Do you see yourself and
again? If you don't want to go
here, fine, but how do you see
yourself? Are you a shaman for
our age? Do you see yourself?
And this is where the play on
Word comes in, not establishing
the church of LDS, but the
church of LSD, right? So do you
see yourself? Not the Latter Day
Saints, but you know LSD. So do
you see yourself? Do you see
yourself? And I think you
understand the heart of my
question, founding a church
where, in fact, you know you
have a place where you can, you
now can create, as a visionary,
as a revolutionary, a holding
environment, a mandala container
that can allow future
Psychonauts to actually embrace
this as path, because otherwise,
where is this going to go? Are
you just a unique and really
interesting blip, or is are you
portending the possibility of
really creating a tradition of
Psychonauts using rigorous to
whatever extent they can,
methodologies, frameworks? I
think you see where I'm coming
from here. You know what's next
in terms of people say, somebody
comes to you and says, Chris,
I'm so blown away by your book.
I want to take psychedelics as a
practice. I want to create this
as a path. What do I do? Where
do I go?
Chris Bache: Well, the first
thing I tell that person always
is, please, don't do what I did.
Do it gently. Be gentler. Be
more careful. I think I'm a
symptom of a cultural pivot that
we're making. I don't think I'm
important, and as we make this
cultural pivot, I think I will
just sort of disappear under the
wave of history as a somewhat
early explorer. But I think we
are making a pivot that's going
to include and is embracing the
value of psychedelics now, right
now, you know, we basically did
about 25 years of this work, and
then in 1970 6970, it was all
made illegal. Then we went into
this long dry period until 2014
when Scientific American
published an editorial basically
on the front page of that saying
that it's time to let scientists
determine, not politicians
determine whether psychedelics
have therapeutic value. So right
now, there's this tremendous
Renaissance taking place.
Universities all over the world
are studying psychedelics, are
establishing centers for
studying psychedelics. A
tremendous explosion. We're
starting where we started back
in the 1950s exploring these
potentials for healing the
personal psyche. We're looking
at post traumatic stress,
healing addiction, healing death
anxiety, healing depression.
We're really focused on using
these substances in therapeutic
applications and under control
scientific conditions. And this
is, and that's perfectly where
we ought to be. We need to now
that we've started this inquiry
again, we need to be very
rigorous, establish the
protocols, do the documentation,
look at the brain wave pictures,
so on and so forth. Sooner or
later, however, we're going to
discover the same thing we
discovered far back, and I'm not
talking about the popular 60s
psychedelic movement, though
that too. But the serious
researchers, the Stan Grof and
that early generations Ralph
Meister, that generation of
researchers, discovered that
these substances have
philosophical value, not just
psychotherapeutic value. They
give us entire insights into the
structure of the deep psyche.
They can even give us insights
into the structure of the
cosmos, into the structure of
the cosmology of the mind. And
if we take PhDs who have people
who have PhDs in physics and
astronomer they can. Literally
come back with deeper insights
into the realities that they
are, that they are educated to
understand. I often have wished
that I had PhDs in astronomy and
physics, because then I would be
able to understand so much more
than I was able to understand
given the background that I had
in humanities. We're making this
pivot, I think that just as
psychotherapists are creating
all sorts of creative protocols
for exploiting the therapeutic
potential of these substances,
it's only going to be a matter
of time before we develop
philosophical protocols which
for systematically exploring
these states of consciousness,
going into them in a rigorous
manner, coming back, recording
them, evaluating them, looking
at our experiences in the in a
social context for social
validation, or asking that
question, embodying putting our
experiences in the context of
other bodies of knowledge
looking at how these experiences
correlate to quantum physics,
for example, or correlate to
super string theory. I think
this is, this is not me. I'm
going to be gone 20 years. Hell,
I won't be around in 20 years. I
don't think I'll be around
nearly that long. I'll be gone
and and actually and two, I
should say it took me a long
time to even be willing to share
these experiences, because I
know how upsetting or
controversial they are. I
literally thought of writing the
book and letting it be published
post human, yeah, exactly,
because I didn't want to deal
with the fall out of it. And I
think what happened with
Andrew Holecek: Wolfgang Pauli
in his conversations with Carl
Jung, right? He didn't want any
of that revealed until after he
died. But anyway, I'm sorry. I
didn't mean to
Chris Bache: cut, yeah, and I
just, I thought, but you know,
the mother told me, said, No,
you can't do that. She said, she
said this, we need all oars in
the water. She said, You didn't
give yourself these visions. We
gave you those visions, and they
were never given to you for your
private edification. You were
holding these visions in trust,
and that she wanted me to share
them, not because it's not
important that they're my
visions. She wanted me to share
them because they would support
other people in their spiritual
practice, other people in their
social work, to help us through
this very, very intense time of
history that we're coming into,
all hands on deck. And so I did
the book, and I don't have any I
don't have any agenda. I think
what's what's clear is that
there is a social pivot taking
place, and that's what's
important as we move forward
collectively, the work, which is
being done in graduate programs
and medical schools all over the
country. That's what's
important. I think I'm a little
bit ahead of the curve in terms
of the philosophical discovery
only because of the very, very
intense methodology that I used.
But I don't think I'm really
that far ahead of the curve.
There is a professor from
Southern Methodist University
called Bill Barnard, who's
written two fantastic books, one
on William James and one on
Henri Bergson, a fine academic,
Bill Barnard and he's publishing
a book from Columbia University
Press this year called liquid
light, Which basically is a
philosopher's reflections on his
extended experiences with
Ayahuasca and living with the
Sante Daime community in Brazil.
Beautiful book, magnificent
book, and symptomatic one more
academic who's willing to go
public on their psychedelic
experiences and not simply
recording them and saying all
this is, you know what's
important, but evaluating them
critically, digesting them and
offering them as part of a
ongoing historical discussion.
So we're making this pivot.
It's, it's happening,
Andrew Holecek: and it's, it's
radically brave. Chris, I want
to acknowledge your bravery on
this. And again, this is a
stretch for for me, because I'm
being introduced, over the last
couple of years to how
conservative I am. In some
levels, I always thought myself
as this liberal, far out kind of
guy, but I realized, in my own
way, I have my, I wouldn't say,
blind spots, but natures of
being conservative that that
really know, being challenged
stretched open and going, Wow,
this is fantastic. And one of
these is the just the generous
courage of writing a book like
this, because you know this from
the traditional admonitions, He
who knows does not speak, He who
speaks does not know. And so
here you are. You're speaking
all over the place, and I used
to really question it. And then,
you know. The beautiful book by
me. Je Rinpoche, if you haven't
read it, in love with the world
amongst journey through the
Bardo life and death. It's an
amazing journey of his intimate
sharing that is profoundly
inspiring. Your book. Vi, in
certain sense, violates the code
of secrecy, but I think we're
living in unusual times that
require unusual slash extreme
measures. And so I, for one,
really applaud your courage that
you are you are stretching the
boundaries in so many levels, in
terms of pedagogy, radical
innovations and path and also
courage and sharing. And so you
were about to say something, I
want to return to what you're
about to say, but I really
deeply thank you for that,
because the other tradition, to
Kuhn Rinpoche said sharing
experiences inappropriately, and
that's the key, is like being in
a dark cave with a candle and
giving your candle away, you're
left in the dark. Opportunity is
transformed into obstacle. And
so I this is both an applause
for what you're doing and
perhaps a commentary elicited
from you in terms of inviting
more and more of the sharing so
that people can realize there is
a chorus of sanity coming out.
Yeah, radical, innovative,
innovative ways of learning.
Chris Bache: So yeah, I had to
really face resistance around
that too, because Buddhism,
traditionally, you don't talk
about your experiences. You
know, you really don't talk. It
can become an encumbrance on you
to talk about your experiences.
But you know, I'm a teacher. I
love to teach. I was designed to
teach. I'm a yacker. I I love
to, yeah, you know, I just,
that's what I love to do. And as
I said at the in that coming off
the mountain chapter, it wasn't
simply the imbalance of toward
Transcendence which made me sick
coming off the mountain. It was
the silence that I had to live
with, because, as a philosopher
of religion, I had had the most
powerful philosophical
experiences of my life, and I
wasn't allowed to talk about
them. I wasn't allowed to share
with them. I wasn't allowed to
do my job, which and to do my
job as an academic, because of
our phobia, our laws around
psychedelics and that holding
that information literally makes
you sick inside. You know I
wasn't allowed to be who I truly
am, and writing the book was
part of my own self healing, and
beginning to speak about it is
part of my own self healing. And
at the same time, having said
that, I have no agenda
whatsoever. I I'm not. I have no
I'm not trying to persuade
anybody. I don't have an ax to
grind. I've got nothing to sell.
I'm I'm an old man. You know,
I'm 72 years old. The end of the
diving board is getting close.
Thank goodness. This being that
I am is so ephemeral, is so
short lived. I have no
attachment to it, and certainly
no attachment of using it as a
model of anything. But I love to
teach, and I hope that the
experiences will be useful to
other people, even if they never
take any psychedelics
whatsoever. I hope that the
vision of the universe and the
vision of the intelligence of
the universe will resonate
deeply with the people's inner
experiences and their cognitive
experiences as science becomes
more aggressive in pushing its
own boundaries, but I hope it
will speak to people, whether or
not they ever take any
psychedelics, because I think we
are at a pivot point. We are
just we're coming out of this
terrible period of history where
we believe that there's no
intelligence to the universe,
that it's all an accident, that
it's all a mechanistic rule of
the genetic dice, and there's no
real intelligence to the
existential circumstances that
we confront. And I think this is
being exploded, and we're waking
up and suddenly we're it's like
a veil is being lifted. We're
waking up to a world in which
reincarnation is a fundamental
fact of life. It's a fact of
nature. We're waking up to to
truly an emergent intelligence
in the universe, which
everywhere we look, whether it's
in the solar system, in
galaxies, in the genetic code.
Everywhere we look, we are
seeing orders and orders and
orders of intelligence. And this
is simply accelerating that
immersion into that
intelligence, and that opens up
a whole new I think this is a
pivot point that we're coming
into in. And you know, it
couldn't happen a minute too
soon, because we are about to go
extinct if we don't change.
Andrew Holecek: It really
reminds me, Chris, of what the
ecology scientists talk about is
punctuated equilibrium. Things,
simmer, simmer, simmer, simmer,
simmer, and then they sudden,
flip some certain way. It's like
what you said so beautifully in
the book that gestation takes a
long time. Birth happens
quickly. And so when I look at
the 50,000 foot view, what I'm
seeing here is exactly what
you're intimating, that that
correlative, like the Taoist
say, correlative with the dark,
is the emergence of light. And
in direct proportion to the
insanity, are voices of sanity
coming in. And so if we can
relate, it's like they say in
Tantra, hell is paradise, that
the greater the obstacle, the
greater the opportunity. And
voices like yours and others
that are actually coming up in
this ocean of tremendous dark
edge talk about the Kali Yuga
really lend credibility to this
CO emergent principle that if we
simply look properly, voices
like yours and others, where
you're just part of a chorus of
sanity coming up, just a chorus,
and if we see that, then we then
we can. It's all about right
view, isn't it? Like the Buddha
say that if we simply have the
right view, that the greater the
obstacle, the greater the
opportunity, then what you're
talking about is adding to that
kind of view, and so I don't
want to draw too much of your
time. I could talk to you for
the rest of this day, but with
your permission, there's just a
few more things that, oh my
gosh, I have to ask you sure one
is in this is a little bit, I
mean, it's philosophical, but
it's interesting for most
people. And I think this is for
you as well. When, when we say,
oh, that's just theoretical,
that's philosophical, well, it
may be so simply because it's
not your experience yet, but
when it becomes your experience,
it's no longer theory, it's no
longer philosophy, it's your
reality. And so one of the
things that you talk about that
that again, challenges both
Hindu and Buddhist approaches to
teleology, purpose on one level,
as you know, the Tibetans talk
about Leela. The world is just
play. The Tibetans talk about
Rolpa, just this divine play and
dance without directionality,
without purpose, and so is it
simply a matter of stepping out
of binary modes of thinking that
is either that or the other and
switching to more. What do they
call it? Dioletheism. This the
ability to hold different views
concurrently. I think Jung
talked about this as well. So
talk to us a little bit about
the emerging human which implies
purpose, teleology ends the
Omega point. I mean, does that
fit into your both your
experience and your
understanding of what you went
through?
Chris Bache: You know, I think
when some of the great masters
talk about life is leela, life
is play. Creation is Leela. It's
a dance. I don't think they're
saying, of course, in any
frivolous way, but I think what
they're saying is not
necessarily that life doesn't
have an intelligence that is
expressing itself in purposeful
activity, but they're saying
that life isn't generated out of
compulsion, life is not
generated out of necessity, that
life comes out of the fullness
of being. It comes out of the
excess of being. It doesn't come
out of a deficit of being. And
that there's an exuberant
quality to life, and we express
this exuberant quality in this
metaphor of a dance, because
dance is not compelled. We dance
out of joy. We dance out of an
excess. We don't dance out of
necessity. I think the I think
when I you know, the theme of
the future human, of the
emergence of the future human,
was a completely unexpected
theme in my work, and it was one
of the most consistent themes of
the work, and it became the
context within which everything
else took place. And it
eventually became the context in
which I understood my entire
incarnation to be taking place.
It started in the 23rd session,
and at the last time I
encountered it was in the 70th
session. It was a consistent
thing, and it is. And here I
would just suspend any theistic
notions of mechanistic intention
or purposeful intent or
manipulative intent. I don't
think in those categories, I
would hold onto an emergent
understanding of a cosmology
that there is an innate quality
which is. Emerging, we go
through these punctuated
equilibriums, this these crisis
points and that there is a a
genius at work in this which I
don't begin to understand. The
you know how this works. What I
will report is that in my
sessions, when I dissolved into
this larger intelligence, which
existentially, I was part of,
but cosmologically, was much
larger than anything I could
relate to personally. It was It
told me a story over and over
again, and it laid it out
systematically, layer by layer,
without contradiction over years
that humanity was coming to a
turning point. Humanity was
approaching a critical time in
its evolutionary journey, a true
before and after time that
there, that the karma of
millennia was kind of rushing
into this valley. It's like
multiple rivers pouring into a
canyon. There's nowhere for us
to go except up. This is a
critical time and that, and it
is a time in some way foreseen
by the great seers of history,
by the great saints, by the
great spiritual geniuses of
history, the great incarnations,
the great prophets, the great
awakened ones that they that
they have seen this kind of
coming forward. It's a vision
which is shared by indigenous
peoples that we are coming into
this time and then 55 sessions,
15 years or so into the work.
Now I have to back a bit, time
became very porous to me in my
work. I mean, I was taken beyond
linear time, multiple times, in
many different modalities, into
what I call deep time. Deep time
is not eternity. It's not it's
not timelessness. It's
experiencing different spans of
time from within a different
frame of reference. And I was
taken into deep time, and I was
taken into it, not as Chris
Bache, because Chris Bache had
been dissolved long before, and
I had been dissolved into the
human unconscious, into the
human species mind. And I don't
know whether it was because of
the work that I had given in the
ocean of suffering, whatever it
was I was taken into the future
and experienced what I saw, what
I experienced as the death and
rebirth of humanity, asked the
human species a cataclysmic
period of history in which
humanity was literally just
broken down. We lost control. We
were we were put through a
crushing historical process
where all the all the
assumptions of the past broke
down. We were literally brought
to our knees. We were reduced in
the end to the challenge of mere
survival. It just we were
stripped down. It was a terribly
excruciating experience, but
when it was at its worst, when
it was at its peak, it was like
a hurricane that passes over a
Pacific Island, suddenly, I
began to experience it. Things
were beginning to get better.
Things were beginning we there
were many, many people had died,
but many survived, and the storm
began to pass. We began to pick
ourselves up. We began to
reconnect, and as we did, when
we did, we discovered that we
had been changed. This crisis
had changed us at our core. We
began to enact a living
intelligence, an aliveness, that
we had discovered in the worst
of this crisis. It was like this
crisis opened up our hearts and
made us a more compassionate
species, and it opened up our
mind, making us a more
intelligent species, able to
integrate and access information
from the intelligence of the
universe itself. As we began to
reconnect with each other, we
began there was a snowballing
effect, so that just as there
had been a breaking down and a
breaking down and a breaking
down, there was an acceleration
of creativity, an acceleration
of the actualization of values
that we had discovered in the
worst of this crisis, where
everything felt new, everything
there was a new set of values, a
new set of ideas, a new
political reality emerged, a new
social reality emerged. Later, I
was given more instructions on
the mech, some of the mechanisms
that are involved, and
instructions and teachings on
that. This is a shift which is
taking place at the center of
the collective psyche without
going into too many layers of
the discussion. Now this is not
simply a shift in the political
arena or the social arena or
economic arena. It is a shift in
the core substructure of the
human psyche, a shift in the
architecture of the collective
psyche, and we've been just as
we collect all our experiences
over many incarnations at the
soul level. The human species
has been collecting and
integrating its experiences at
the collective level, at the
unconscious, collective psyche
level. And what's happening now
is that we are pivoted. We're
poised to make a pivot in the
collective psyche, and that
after we make this pivot, all
human beings born will be
operating within the context of
a literally, of a different
collective psyche. And I think
we see the prototype of this
psyche in Christ, in Buddha, in
Muhammad, in these awakened
beings who we have been trying
to emulate for generations and
generations, beings with
expanded hearts, with expanded
compassion, with expanded deeper
insights into the universe. They
speak differently. They don't
work the way ordinary people
work. They are different kinds
of being, and I think we are
becoming a different kind of
being, at least. That's the
consistent message that comes
through my work over and over
again.
Andrew Holecek: It's literally
breathtaking. Chris, a few with
your confirmation, I have to
bring you back at some point,
because we haven't, I wouldn't
say we haven't gotten to the
goodies. Oh my gosh, it's been
so rich. Your chapter on the
diamond Luminosity blew my socks
off. Your chapter on coming from
down from the mountain was
brought me to tears. I have to
bring you back to talk about
that, because I don't want to
dilute the impact of what you're
saying by trying to do a shotgun
of I mean, how do you distill 20
years of unbelievable insight to
even two hours of conversation?
And so to whatever extent I have
been able to, I wanted to
concentrate on a couple heart
essence points. Add a little
water to them so we could
understand them without
capitulating to my near frenetic
predisposition to like, oh my
gosh, I have to talk to him
about this, right?
Chris Bache: We'd be going,
you're doing a great job. You're
hitting really important topics.
Andrew Holecek: We'd be going at
this my point, but I wanted
there's a couple of things
before we close for today that I
want to return to, that that I
think are somewhat important, at
least they are to me. And two
things here. One is, your
journey seems to imply a type of
attainment. In other words,
you're alluding to extraordinary
states. And I'm not contesting
that at all, but I'm wondering
if the languaging, the branding,
so some of the things that
occurred to me, using somewhat
marketing methods is one thing
that needs to happen is this
whole thing needs to be
rebranded, this whole LSD thing,
the branding thing is really so
contaminated with histories that
we need to rebrand it as
entheogenic practice or
whatever. But the other thing
that needs perhaps to be
rebranded. And this is just me.
I'm curious how this lands with
you. Is there seems to be this
intimation that you have a left
conventional reality on what
level you have and attain the
state that are extraordinary?
But is it, in fact, Chris, just
as viable, if not more so, to
say that this is the
extraordinary state. In other
words, this is the non ordinary
state, Samsara, and that what
you're actually doing in your
journey is, is, this is a
narrative that keeps coming over
and over. I loved it, the
narrative of opening, receiving,
surrendering, and maybe for next
time, not only opening the mind,
but just as much. Again, in
tantric languaging, the
unbelievable importance of
opening the body and so as a
consequence of opening. And you
mentioned this so many times, I
was curious how often you said
this, dropping. You open, you
drop. So it's not a journey of
ascent, so much as it is a
waking down into really. What
are ordinary states that that
when you relax properly and have
the capacity to be so open, what
you're talking about is
completely ordinary that you're
not really going anywhere.
You're simply relaxing deeply
into the right here and now. And
so the reason I say this, Chris
is because one thing that they I
think could be a little bit
intimidating for people, is, Oh,
my. Gosh, I can never do that. I
could never attain that that's
so far removed. I think if, if
you look at it in this different
way, and I'm curious, if this
lands with you, it empowers the
immediacy of what you're talking
about, that that fundamentally,
this is the nature of the mind,
this is the nature of the human
and even trans human condition.
And so talk to us a little bit
about the, the the almost the
false note, the false notion of
path. Because even the notion of
path needs to be rebranded here,
because that implies you need to
go somewhere else. And in the
very striving you actually
ironically leave what you're
trying to attain. Yeah, no, the
whole notion of like you attain
enlightenment, that's actually
an oxymoron. You cannot attain
enlightenment. There are
mutually exclusive terms, so a
lot of noodles against the wall,
but I think important ones,
because it also ties into the
last thing I wanted to say here
is you also use the phrase a
number of times of coming and
going. In other words, you enter
the state. You left it, you
entered it, you left it. That
also means a return to some kind
of source. So I'm wondering
about the relationship here
again. I know I'm tossing a lot
out the relationship between
source and essence, and the
relationship of all this to
recognition. That is, in fact,
recognition not the central
message here that if you simply
open your mind and heart,
irrespective of the means,
meditative, pharmacological or
whatever, if you simply open and
recognize everything that seems
to be intimated here is, oh,
geez, I need to do this 20 year
journey to attain this.
Provisionally, maybe yes, but
absolutely no, it's right here
right now. You just need to open
your eyes, divine eyes, and it's
been here all along.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I absolutely
agree with you, in fact. Well,
let me back up, and there's a
lot there. I'm sorry, yeah, in
the early stages of the journey,
there is a subjective sense as
one moves into psychic level
reality and subtle level
reality, there is a subjective
sense of opening becoming
larger, opening and becoming
larger. And that's why I think
psychedelics were named mind
opening. It is a sensation of
opening the mind, late in the
journey, later at a more
advanced stage, when I was
working at what Stan would call
causal level reality. Yeah, we
can as well. Yeah, everything
reversed. I had the experience
that my mind, everything was
converging. I was in very, very
large states of consciousness,
very, very high energy. But
instead of going deeper into
those states, all everything was
converging back to right here,
right now. My my sessions were
getting harder to describe
because they they were so taking
place inside ordinary reality. I
wasn't being taken outside.
Everything was converging, and I
began to think, Oh, my God, have
we really misclassified what
these substances are. They're
not mind openers, they're mind
concentrators, absolutely. And I
think what happens is, at
different levels of reality, the
subjective experience changes
from opening to a concentration,
or it may be the case that the
consciousness orchestrating My
experience was bringing me back
into what would more be
recognized as a more classical
kind of spiritual awakening. But
the core is that it's really
simply the case a sashin is you
turn your mind and you focused
on the present, you eliminate
the outside, and you go right
here, right now. And when you do
that, this purification process
happens, of course, but where
you end up at the end is simply
where you were in the beginning,
but with fewer distortions. Yes,
Elliot, yeah. And you're just
cleaning, you're cleaning the
makyo, you're cleaning the
distortions. But there's no
place to go. There's no place
else to go to, except where you
already are, and there's nothing
to become except what you
already are and always have
been. You don't you know that
reality, which doesn't begin, it
doesn't end. There's no turning
on, there's no turning off.
There is only the relaxing into
what has always been right here,
right now. And I think that's
that is true on at least it was
true in my experience in the
psychedelic path, I don't think
anything that I'm describing is
original. I think everything
that I've described in the book
can be found in the spiritual
literature of the mystical
traditions, the contemplative
traditions. The cosmology that
emerges in psychedelic research
is not a new cosmology. It's an
old cosmology. It's it's only
new in the context of its
emergence, and it leaves you, I
say, you know, in somewhere in
the end stages of the book, like
the only thing which is of value
to me in the psychedelic work is
purification, purification and
just purification, and it
because it brings us into a more
intimate experience of what
already is. And by some silly
nonsense, we keep ourselves out
of the joy of this deep and
profound reality that is living
in us, that is us that is
expressing itself. So I
absolutely agree with you. I uh,
yeah, it's yeah, it's just
purifying. That's all.
Andrew Holecek: And again, the
not that this brings validity to
what you're saying, other than
the validity to my world, is we
come and learn and understand
things in terms of other things,
yeah, technological knowing and
so what brought such deep, deep
resonance was, wow, here's an
amazing individual who's taken
an entirely new path that is so
resonant with my path, and
again, completely aware of the
hubris of saying my Path
betokens the truth, and
therefore yours is true because
it relates to mine, right?
Subtle self aggrandizement there
is actually not so subtle,
right? I think your stuff is
true because it resonates with
my trip, totally aware of that,
yeah. But with that said,
there's so many resonances the
notion of purification as you
know you're and this is what the
question I wanted to ask you,
how, as we start to close up for
today, one of the chapters or
sections that really spoke to
me, of course, somewhat
previewed by what I just said
was your interjection of the
path of Vajrayana, that and how
that is now perhaps create,
creating a, again, a holding
environment to support augment
transition in more and this you
understand, hopefully, the
question in more Organic means
more phenomenological versus
neurological means, so called
traditional methods. And so as
we start to wrap up for today,
because I want to give people
something to take home, like,
how can they use this work with
this? And I have one follow up
there, but what has been the
role, and continues to be the
role of both meditation and the
Vajrayana to augment, support,
enhance, stabilize what you've
gone through.
Chris Bache: Well, one of the
gifts that came out of my
psychedelic experiences was a
deepened appreciation of the
power and effectiveness of
classic spiritual contemplative
practices, and including the
Vajrayana practices, by becoming
sort of temporarily more aware,
I was able to appreciate more
deeply how these practices were
affecting my body and how they
were affecting my mind, even
though, and they also helped me
manage some of the challenges
that I was running into,
because, remember, I wasn't
doing this work, or I didn't end
up doing this work for the
purpose of spiritual awakening,
though that was always there in
the background. But I was doing
it to explore the universe as a
philosopher hungry to explore
the nature of reality. But the
Vajrayana practices helped me
manage the excess of energy that
was having was being flowing
through my body by giving it an
intermediate place to live and
breathe that was like in between
my physical existence and my
psychedelic existence, there was
This Vajrayana practice space
that, of course, taught me that
these pop these practices, are
much more powerful than I had
appreciated, or I might have
appreciated just from working
with them, from my ordinary
time, space consciousness, I
also came to appreciate that
these practices are empowered by
the Morphic field. Which have
been generated by 1000s and
1000s of beings doing these
practices for hundreds and
hundreds of years. The power of
transmission the lung when a
practice is given, it's not just
to maintain the formal purity
the practice, but there truly is
an energetic transmission, and
the power of this practice draws
upon the cumulative power that
is set in motion by 1000s of
beings using these practices
over many, many years. Now, I
don't know whether to describe
myself as a Vajrayana
practitioner today, because
while I do practice and I do
meditate. The focus of my
practice is different. In some
ways. The focus of my practice
is actually speaking. There is a
way in which when I speak about
these things, I remember them,
when I remember them, they
become actualized within me.
When they become actualized
within me, my mind shifts, my
body shifts. Everything shifts
inside of me. And so actually
for me, this wonderful
discussion that we've been
having, and I really, really
appreciate the deep, engaged
quality of the questions you've
been asking me and where you've
been taking us. For me, this is
like a spiritual practice. For
me, your your questions give me
the opportunity to open in ways
that I wouldn't ordinary. I
wouldn't be open in today
otherwise, in that context, as
part of my ongoing effort to
simply to be useful to the
universe. I practice. I do my
practices, but I don't practice
with the intention of trying to
accomplish something beautiful,
and I don't practice with the
intention of changing what's
going to happen to me when I
die. Now it may be arrogant to
say this, but I just report that
I have a sense of what's going
to open to me when I die,
because I've been there. I've
been there, different ways, been
there, done that, and the
universe has has made promises
to me, and I don't think the
promises are false. I think
they're just very matter of
fact, and so I don't practice in
order to change what's going to
happen to me when I die. I
practice to change how I am
right now, and to try to be of
more use to people right now. So
to kind of declare my system to
clear my system to remember,
yeah, and I use my psychedelic
memories in my Vajrayana
practice. You know, in Vajrayana
there's the Samaya sattva and
the chinana sattva, the being of
practice which attracts the
being of reality. And so we do
these visualizations and
exercises and mudras in order to
create something which is an
approximation of an eternal
principle, by virtue of which we
draw that principle into our
being. Well, I use my memories
as Samaya sattva in the creation
of Samaya sattva in order to
open the channels to the Jnana
sattva of these principles in
reality. And that, to me, is
just, this is a this is a
natural process. So I do the
Vajrayana practices, but I do
them with my own particular kind
of twist. And understandably,
it's hard to find a teacher who
is comfortable with somebody
who's owns a psychedelic history
the way I own mine.
Andrew Holecek: Yeah, and maybe,
maybe that needs to change and
adapt. I mean, and who are we to
say that? Talk about the
arrogance of that. Because, as
you know, Chris and I'm so glad
to hear you say this, there
actually have been in the wisdom
traditions admonitions, a
warning against originality.
That's very interesting to me,
that originality is somewhat
suspicious. And I find that a
very interesting statement. On
one level, yes, it abides by the
elegance, the beauty of the
tradition, and on one level, the
sort of irreducibility,
irreducibility of the awakened
mind that's already been
discovered. And I think if it's
related to properly, that can
prevent rogue and. Uh, science
and the like. But on another
level, if we don't evolve, we're
going to go extinct. If we don't
bring we meaning the wisdom
traditions as a representative
of if we don't bring new
tributaries of upaya, skillful
means, cultural adaptations to
perennial traditions, then I
think it's not going to be
applicable to the modern age,
and it's just going to be
relegated to the dusty
disciplines in dust bins, in old
stole stale churches. But just a
couple of things here before we
close, because I don't want to
take more advantage of your
time. We started with this
notion, or I did with this
notion of hyper objects, top
issues, topics, phenomena that
are so big it's hard to wrap
one's mind around that. You
know, I always say stretching is
good for growth. This has been a
journey of a mental yoga, yeah,
and I'm wondering if Is it too
ostentatious to talk about. And
I so appreciate your your
humility, your modesty, but
there's also tremendous power
that you're releasing, that you
are a shaman to, that you were
expressing, and I so appreciate
I've never really related to
this is is also speaking as
practice. Dialog is practice,
engaging in what we're doing
here is path that's really
beautiful. But would you say, or
is it fair to say that you're
also pointing towards and this
connects to your book, the
living classroom, hyper
pedagogy? Are you, in fact,
intimating a possibility for
accelerated forms of learning?
And I resonate with this deeply,
because when I explore what I
call the nocturnal meditations,
Dream Yoga and the like, one of
the reasons I'm so passionate
about these practices is because
they are a revolution in
pedagogy. It's a way to use the
mind and the nocturnal arena to
really accelerate learning,
because you're working with
these foundational dimensions
and so is it fair to say, based
on what your experience, that
what you're also pointing to are
possibilities for hyper
pedagogical approaches where we
can, in fact, accelerate our
evolution, if it's held within
the right view, within the right
set and setting, within the
right container, that we can
really ramp things up in a
healthy way, with a boat, again,
with a Bodhisattva ideal, and
the motivations and all the
parameters of safety and
security, because the faster you
go, this isn't the essence of
the Vajrayana. It's a jet versus
a car. Jets can crash. Cars are
safer, but they're slower. Is
that a fair thing to say that if
we relate to this properly, what
you're also pointing out here is
not only just hyper objects, but
hyper pedagogical approaches.
Chris Bache: I think so, yeah,
you know, in the living
classroom, I don't mention
psychedelics at all. I wanted
this book to be about fields of
consciousness and the effects of
fields on learning and the
accelerating effect of focused
intentionality and energetic
transmission that takes place in
the classroom or in any group
context. And I don't talk about
psychedelics at all. But the
backstory to that book is this,
I was doing my private
psychedelic so called Private
psychedelic practice. I was
opening up into the ocean of
suffering. I was going into
these very, very deep collective
states of consciousness and
eventually into deeper, you
know, Transcendence, states of
consciousness. I never talked to
my students about it, but I
found that my students began to
be impacted by my work in very
precise ways. When I was going
through certain thresholds. They
began to go through certain
spiritual thresholds. And it
began to happen when I was
lecturing, nothing to do with
psychedelics, just lecturing on
world religions, just something,
and I would be looking for some
example to use to make a point.
And I experienced a door open in
the back of my mind the way it
first happened, and this little
piece of paper slipped into I
read the piece of paper, and it
was an idea of something to use,
and I tried it, and when I tried
it, all of a sudden, the energy
in the room shifted, and
everything became more animated,
and I began to work consciously
with these kind of subtle
suggestions that would pop into
my mind from seemingly nowhere.
And then few years down the
road, students started to come
to me, and they said at the end
of class, you know, it's strange
that you said what you said
today, or gave this example,
because this is exactly what
happened to me this week, or
this is exactly what happened to
my mother. And at first I
dismissed it, and I thought,
okay, but it kept happening, and
it kept happening, and the deep.
My psychedelic practice went. It
began to happen more, but it
also began to touch deeper areas
of their life. It was as if
their soul was slipping messages
to my soul, which was slipping
it to me, leading me to say
things that were giving them
information or touching very
intimate places in their life
that I had no way of personally
knowing about, experiences that
places that they needed healing
or information that they needed
to take the next step in their
learning, and this was became
such a characteristic part of my
teaching, so many people were
being moved in ways that were
beyond my conscious intention
and even beyond my awareness
when it was happening. And a
pivot point came when I I looked
at my class one day and while I
was lecturing, and I looked up
and I saw a half dozen, 10
people in the room with very
quietly tears rolling down their
face, and I realize I've got to
understand what's happening. I
really have to understand this.
And that's the entire book
living classroom was downloaded
in 10 minutes in one session,
the title just dropped right in.
And I had been wrestling with
this idea, but it gave me all
the information I need to
understand two basic points, but
all of the both of them hinge
around the fundamental reality
that consciousness has an atomic
quality, a separate quality, and
it has a quantum quality. So
there is individual awareness.
And individual awareness is
true. They don't know what I
know. They're here to get what I
know. We give a test, and I can
test whether they have it, you
know, that kind of stuff, but
there's a quantum reality, that
my individual experience is
grounded in a quantum in an
expansive field of
consciousness, and they are
grounded in this expansive field
of consciousness, and that
activates potentials, which are
entirely natural. It's like
throwing a stone into the war
into a lake, and the ripples
spread out. When one person does
deep clarifying work, it
triggers clarification in the
consciousness of people that
they have karma connection to.
It's a simple, simple natural
phenomenon. So I think what I
eventually wrote down and
clarified was, what would it be
like if we taught consciously in
a Transpersonal pedagogy, or in
an integral pedagogy, or in a
pedagogy that recognize the the
innate interconnectivity of
consciousness, which doesn't
mean that we abandon the
individual strategies that we
know and work so well, but we
incorporate using strategies of
focused intentionality, of of
conscious of conscious
engagement that goes beyond
classical teaching, so that, for
example, you know Chud as a
Vajrayana practice. It's a
purification practice. And I
learned Chud and I was doing ch
for my spiritual practice. I
began before class even began,
when I would get a roster of the
students for my class, I would
start incorporating this roster
in my ch practice. I would
literally pray for my students
using this particular vehicle. I
would pray for them, and I pray
for them through the entire
course, for their well being.
Not I don't try to. It's not my
job to think I know what's right
for them, or what they should be
doing, or anything like that. I
simply pray for their well
being. I think the more we kind
of activate these latent
potentials in groups, the more
we accelerate learning. And I
found it's not only the there's
not only a collective field in
the room, but there is a class
field. But even deeper than that
is the course field, that there
is a learning and empowerment
that takes place over years, so
that the students you have the
individual mind situated within
a class mind, situated within a
course mind. This is an
absolutely once you see it, once
you understand it, you begin to
recognize it happening in all
sorts of different contexts, in
different places. So if there is
a hyper object, the hyper object
is simply the connective tissue
of mind. It's that we are at
all. Always, always inherently
connected, and we simply become
conscious of that and become
responsible to it, yeah, in
whatever we're doing,
Andrew Holecek: yeah. And again,
it's back to that narrative of
making unconscious processes
processes and making unconscious
processes conscious. Because if
you can do that, then you can
increase levels of
communication, elicitation,
evocative whatever, to then,
then really heighten that what
is, what is already again, it's
already there. So why not take
advantage of it? Why not engage
it? Why not make it, bring it
into conscious awareness, pay
allegiance to it, surrender to
it, and therefore enhance it,
accelerate it in and of itself.
And so Chris, I want to pay
homage to your time. I just a
few last things, the famous last
words, wait a second, it'll be
midnight.
Chris Bache: Wait Chris, this is
fun.
Andrew Holecek: I mean, I
literally, I could talk to you
for the entire day. But to wrap
it up for now, people are what
you're releasing here is a
Pandora's box of both wisdom and
potential neurosis. And by this,
what I mean is I wonder if you
worry about what you've released
here, because here's a little
bit of where I want to close
with this is I can definitely
hear or imagine listeners going,
this is for me. I This is my
path. I want to do this. And
they may see this as a quick
fix, as a lazy man's approach.
And of course, your book shows
this is not for the feeble
minded or the feeble hearted.
You have to this is jihad. This
is inner Dharma combat. You have
to really go to work here. So
what would you say, like Dharma
surgeons General's warning,
these teachings are hazardous to
your egoic health, right? So I
want to throw a little bit of a
caveat to listeners who go, oh
heck, I don't need to go into
retreat. I don't need to do a
three year retreat. I can just
pop these pills and I'm going to
attain these states. And I knew
there was a quick silver bullet,
this is it. So you understand,
it's a slightly extreme
rendering of this, but people
glom onto these sorts of things,
and they're gonna run into them,
run with them with wrong
motivation, with wrong intent.
So talk to us as we close here
several things. And this also
ties into my experience. I have
not done this yet, but I've
talked to people who've done
Ayahuasca retreats in Costa
Rica. They go down there. They
have these mind blowing
experiences over four or five
planned medicine trips, and then
they leave, and then they tell
me, I know these people. They
go, it was great, but I don't
feel supported. They don't
follow up with me. I'm left
completely to my own devices. I
am like, what do I do with that?
Yeah. So as we close for today,
again, lots of noodles, because
this topic is just so rich. Talk
to us about like, if someone
came to you, would you act as an
advisor? Or are there advisors
they can be drawn to? Do you
take responsibility for this
Pandora's box of wisdom that
you're releasing? What are the
shadow sides of doing this
without proper sentence setting.
And so I know trying to close,
but I can't help myself. I think
this is important. We have to
throw some caveats out there for
those who may be thinking that,
ah, this is the long awaited
spiritual silver bullet. I'll
just pop these things and I'm
good to go.
Chris Bache: Yeah, boy, no
silver bullet there. There are
no shortcuts. In this one, I've
learned there are no shortcuts.
There are intensifications of
practice, but there's no getting
around the fundamental laws of
spiritual reality. You know that
there's just no getting around
them? And the early idea that
psychedelics represented an easy
path. It just turned out to be
facile and not true. In fact, my
concern is just the opposite. My
concern is that if you use these
substances even conscientiously,
they are, they can be so intense
that it's too demanding a path.
It's just too demanding. You
have to really, really be wise
in the in the handling of it.
I'm I was very concerned in
sharing this material, because
it would break my heart if
someone were to read my book and
then jump into some type of use
of psychedelics and injure
themselves. And it's easy to
injure yourselves, because you
you open, you can open so
deeply, so quickly that you
really can't handle everything
that comes at you. And you can,
you can disrupt a healthy psyche
in ways that can be permanently
crippling, and it would. Break
my heart if somebody did that,
and I did a lot of practice, a
spiritual practice around that
particular issue. What we're
learning is that breaking
through, breaking the boundaries
of the personal psyche, going
into deeper states of
consciousness, is really not
that difficult. It's really not
that hard. We're beginning to
see more and more attention
being given to integration, the
requirements of integration,
what constitutes a healthy
practice. And I offer myself as
an example of someone whose
practice was not entirely
healthy, I would think I went
too deep, and it's caused me
years of kind of, I won't say,
distress, but years of having to
manage
uh, the joy that I had temporary
that I knew on a temporary
basis. So and in it, one of the
reasons I left the suffering I
you know, I didn't blunt the
suffering. In the book, there
were people who were advising me
don't put that in, because
people are not going to get
scared. They're not going to
understand it. One of the
reasons I put it in just because
it was true and I promise to
give it an accurate account, but
I put it in partly because I
wanted people to be able to
understand how this stuff works,
how understands it. They are
amplifiers. Amplifiers brings up
our garbage. It brings up our
trash. We have to confront that
garbage, confront that trash.
But even when we do that and do
that well, we still have to
manage the wisdom of
integration. There is a book
that was just published this
past year in England. It's inner
tradition press psychedelics and
psychotherapy. And the focus of
this book is really on
integration. And I have an essay
in there with other people. My
essay is called the challenge of
integrating an extreme
psychedelic journey, not simply
in a psychedelic session, but an
extreme psychedelic journey. I
think we need more essays like
that. We mean more discussions
about what is good, what does
healthy psychedelic practice
look like? What are the symptoms
of imbalance in psychedelic
practice? What is the symptom of
too much people chasing new
experiences before they've
integrated the experiences that
they've had. I've seen many
students suffering. They've
literally fried themselves.
Their energy feels very fried.
They've gone back to the well
too many times. They've plugged
into the universe at too high a
level. And they haven't stayed
grounded. They feel kind of
crispy. They have paid a price,
and some people truly have paid
a price of dysphoria and various
types of imbalance,
psychological imbalance from
entering into these states. So
the problem is, you see that our
culture doesn't have a wisdom in
the use of psychedelics. Some
indigenous cultures do the
shamanic cultures do have that
wisdom. We have to learn from
them how to use these practices
wisely. Right now, we're using
these practices within a
therapeutic arena, and we are
drawing upon our therapeutic
wisdom of how to integrate these
healing practices well. But as
we go deeper, we have to go
beyond therapeutic wisdom. We
have to go into shamanic wisdom.
We have to go into the sage
tradition wisdoms, to really
learn how to integrate these
practices. Well, having deep
experiences, it turns out, is
not that difficult, and it's not
necessarily very beneficial. It
doesn't have a long lasting
effect. Juliana, of Norwich,
English mystic, had one. She was
on her death bed. She was dying.
She had a Near-Death Experience.
She had an experience of the
love of Christ, and she had an
experience of the feminine God.
She spent the rest of her life
meditating on it, and she
unpacked one experience in her
book, the revelations of divine
love. It takes years to unpack
the full potential that's
unleashed in even one
experience. So it would there.
We have a lot to learn.
Hopefully, we will be wiser in
this century with psychedelics
than we were in the last
century. In the 1960s where we
did a lot of psychedelics, we
had a lot of experiences, a lot
of. Breakthroughs, lot of cap,
some casualties, not as many as
popular press would have us
believe. But did we change
people's lives profoundly and
permanently? Some Yes, but not
as many as we thought. Would we
would? I think we need to really
be wise and grounded in our
reappropriation of psychedelics.
Do you worry about what
Andrew Holecek: you've released?
I mean, one thing that comes to
mind here is, I spent a lot of
time in the Himalayas. I've
tracked above Everest base camp.
I've seen a lot of high altitude
sickness. And so on one level,
that's what this is like. It's
like I've seen this where, when
you're climbing to Everest,
you've got to spend two days in
Namche Bazaar, for instance, at
12,000 feet to acclimatize. And
the people that don't, that
don't acclimatize and go up,
they're the ones that get high
altitude cerebral or pulmonary
edema and run into very serious
problems. And then the way they
have to cure it, as you know,
you get headache, you stop, you
go back down. You retreat to an
altitude where the symptoms were
not there, and then you slowly
work your way up, otherwise the
high altitude sickness, your
lust for the summit, will kill
you. So do you sometimes worry,
Chris, about again, what you
release? Because on one level,
this ties in so beautifully, I
think, to what we said, but I
said at the outset, because
that's why it's beautiful.
Because I said, is, this is a
form of Tantra, and it's
interesting, is, I just wrote an
article for tart, is the West
ready for tantra? And as a form
of Tantra, as you know, there
are practices that are
prescription strength, TUMO,
dark retreat. There are
practices that are does not
designed for public consumption
because they're too powerful.
You're dealing with
thermonuclear power as it's
embodied in your subtle body.
And so what you're talking about
here is the danger of what's
called salon practice, inner
yoga practice where the
condensed impact of your entire
cosmic history is ensconced in
your body and subtle body. And
so when you're doing something
like this, as the danger with
doing inner yogas, and this is
what your book screamed out to
me. Said, Oh my gosh, Chris is
doing inner yoga here, and this
is why, not only is he opening
his mind, he's opening his body.
And as the channels winds,
chakras are open and released,
whoa, if you can't ride that
wind, you're going to be blown
away by that wind. And so I see
this as a absolutely confluent
with these prescription strength
tantric practices, yeah, if I'm
not done with the proper
motivation, proper set in
setting, really intelligently,
they're not going to light you
up, they're going to burn you
up. And so again, lots of things
being thrown out there. But I
think this is really important,
especially in the impatient
West, where people, people are
going to go shit, I'm just gonna
run with this.
Unknown: Yeah, do
Andrew Holecek: you worry about
you worry about what you
Chris Bache: there, so to speak,
or worry about it. I made, first
of all that I do worry about it.
It's, I'm glad we're talking
about it. I hope I get
opportunities to talk more about
it. It needs to be discussed,
the relationship between this
high potency psychedelic as a
spiritual practice, but also as
a initial initiatory practice,
and the practices that you're
talking about as initiatory
practices, they can burn you up.
I got rather well singed. And,
you know, had to manage them.
Have had to manage them. The
other side of it is the mother
asked me. She said, You know, we
did not give you these visions
for you. We gave them for the
people. She said, Let them see
me through your eyes. Just, just
let me see. Let them see me
through your eyes, as you have
seen me. And it's like, I am not
important. What's important is
what was shown me, and I hope
that by sharing that cleanly and
honestly, it will help people in
their own spiritual development.
That is my fundamental
conviction, my fundamental
motivation as a philosopher. I
trust my students to deal with
the information that I make
available to them, even when it
jars their system, even when it
upsets their agricultural
worldview. I work with them to
make sure that they don't get
pushed too hard, that they
integrate them. This is
something. It's a. Little
different. This isn't a way I've
said something. I've not said it
in motion. It's happening all
around me. I'm simply one voice
which is part of a psychedelic
revolution. It's just one voice
trying to bring some clarity on
one certain set of issues. I
should also mention that I made
a choice a long time ago, not to
function as a therapist, not to
function as a clinician, but to
function as an explorer. I do
not work with other people. I do
not work as a therapist. I do
not take people in psychedelic
sessions. I don't do that work.
That's a different set of
skills. It requires training
that I don't have. I work with
people who are training to be
those people, and there are lots
and lots of places where people
are training to work as
psychedelic elders and as
psychedelic therapists, and I'm
in conversations with some of
these training groups. I'll be
doing one this coming weekend,
in fact. But I've made a choice
to really work as an explorer
and to bring a report back and
to support other people who are
working as clinicians, who are
really trying to help people use
this material wisely. Now, as I
said, I think right now we're
learning the wisdom in the
therapeutic context. We still
have to learn that wisdom,
incorporate that wisdom into the
shamanic the shamanic wisdom,
and to integrate the wisdom that
comes from the sage tradition
different levels of depth, I
just trust that we will find
that wisdom. I hope there are
not casualties or not too many
casualties along the way in that
process. I do worry about it. I
trust. I just in the end, I have
to trust that we will find the
wisdom to do this. Now, my sense
is we're going there. No matter
what psychedelics are here,
they're not going away. They
didn't go away during the 40
years of prohibition. They're
not going away. Now what we need
to do is accelerate and deepen
our understanding of how to what
they are, how they work, and how
to work with them. Well, what
they do and don't give us. And
in my book, I've really tried to
emphasize the underbelly of
psychedelics, that they are
temporary, that my chapter on
methodology is the path of
temporary immersion. That's not
the same as the path of
contemplative immersion. You
really have to work with those
limitations and understand them,
to work with them safely, and
they are powerful. And I really
mean it. I don't recommend that
people work with high doses of
LSD as consistently and
methodically as I did. I
wouldn't do it that way again, I
would be gentler with myself. I
would open up smaller windows,
gentler substances, lower doses,
precisely because of the
challenge of sustaining the
impact how these experiences
impact you, not only in the days
immediately following your
session, but in the years
following your session.
Andrew Holecek: Yeah, you know,
so interesting, Chris, you
talked earlier about and this is
a wonderful definition of
translation of Shunyata.
Emptiness is translucency,
transparency and one on one
level, you are the exemplar of
that transparency. There's no
difference between the inner and
outer with you, and to me, it's
really quite beautiful to see.
And I also have to share a
little bit of the magic that I'm
feeling, even in the
conversation itself, that and I
hope my listeners take this in
the right way. Some of these
questions are not coming from
me. I can tell when I'm asking a
question. But I can also tell
when these questions are coming
from me, and so this next one
did not come from Me, and I hope
it's okay to ask this in
relationship to the beloved, to
the mother. Do you ever feel? Do
you ever feel that you were
brought into this world on
behalf of the mother, to act as
her child, Luminosity, to act as
that voice. I mean, do you ever
look at your trajectory as
actually being a kind of Avatar
of the mother itself that you
were brought to again, this idea
of purpose and divine purpose
and teleology. Does that? Does
that speak to you around this?
Or do you feel this is a little
bit more sort of serendipitous?
I mean, another way you could
say this in my languaging is to
what degree is karma predispose
you towards this? But more
specifically, using your
languaging, do. You think the
beloved sent her child into this
world, right? Well, we're
getting really Christian here,
man, right? Yeah, tongue in
cheek aside, I think you hope
you see where I'm coming from.
Chris Bache: I think that before
I answer the specific, I want to
answer the general. I think that
many of us at first, I believe
that we all knew what we were
getting into before we
incarnated. We have choices to
make, and we choose our
incarnation. Now, we may not
choose it, if we're if we're
kindergarteners, we don't let
them choose their curriculum,
but by the time you're in high
school and college and graduate
school, you're choosing your
curriculum. And I think this,
this is true about reincarnation
too. We choose our incarnation.
We choose the form of it. We
choose the timing of it. We
choose the place of it. We knew
at a time when we knew more than
we know now what we're getting
into. We said yes to the options
that of this incarnation. So I
think this is the lives that we
are living are, for the most
part, for the vast majority, I
think, are chosen lives, okay?
And I think this is true for me,
and I don't think, I certainly
don't think I'm an, you know, an
Ishtar for the for the mother.
But I have always considered
myself in service of the mother.
I'm in it's in my astrological
chart. It's in my constitutional
chart. I I wanted to be, you
know, my first vocation in life
was to be a priest. I woke up
when I woke up at five or six
years old, I wanted to be a
priest, and I was raised
Catholic, and that's how it
expressed itself. But that fell
away. But the desire to serve,
the desire to know and to serve,
was always there, as it is for
many of us. And so I also
learned along the way, not in my
psychedelic work, but actually
in some hypnotic work I was
doing in past life therapy work
that I have history with
psychedelics. I have Native
American history with
psychedelics. It's what made me
comfortable with this mode of
spiritual practice. So I believe
that I was born to do what I
did. And that's, that's not
inflationary, that's just,
that's just very simple this,
this is what I did, what came
naturally to him, and it's no
big deal. It's just what is I
love to teach. Just so happened
that it took a little bit of a
twist, and I'll add one other
little, small piece, there's
been great benefit to me in this
in that I also learned that I
have had a number of lives where
I paid a price for speaking I
was tortured and killed for
speaking out, and so I was
internalized. I brought that
resistance in this lifetime, and
it's not been easy. From the
first time I wrote on
reincarnation. I had to overcome
great resistance, but what I
found was that by overcoming
that resistance and speaking the
truth as best as I could
understand it, it always worked
out well. It always I was always
richly rewarded for the process.
So there's been so learning for
me in rising to the challenge of
doing this. It's not been easy
to write about psychedelics in
our particular culture, but
look, the friendships that it's
given me, the context that it's
given me the opportunities to be
with people, has been very
rewarding. And I think, I think
there are a lot, lots and lots
and lots of people who are like
me, like yourself, who have
deep, deep spiritual hunger,
spiritual drive. And they they
do it, and as they get into it.
They're not holding this just
for themselves. They are truly
Bodhisattvas. They're doing this
practice for everybody. First
thing you do in a practice
awaken bodhicitta, and the last
thing you do in your practice is
you distribute the merit. You
know, this is, this is just the
nature of reality. This is just
the very simple process of
waking up to the true condition,
which is a shared existence that
we all, that we all embody.
Andrew Holecek: Yeah,
breathtaking, breathtaking.
Chris, really. How can people
learn more about you? Again, I'm
going to probably going to say
one more thing, and we're going
to be here till midnight. But
how can people learn more about
you? What are you currently
working on? How can we support
you? Part of, part of what we
do, my aspiration is cross
pollination. Is bringing,
bringing this core. Of sanity so
that we can increase
connectivity, enhance the
connective tissue, strengthen it
and into whatever degree
possible at whatever levels of
reality, overt or covert,
support each other. So how can
my community learn more about
you, support you and your
journey, and what are you
currently working on that we can
look
Chris Bache: forward to? Yeah,
well, it's very kind of you to
ask that I just finished
teaching a seven week course at
the shift network, which is
basically a seven week course
built around LSD in the mind of
the universe. And that course is
now it's available, and people
can get that course and download
it, and there's an hour lecture
followed by half an hour of Q
and A and, you know, there's
material there, and there's also
readings there that they can go
into. I have a website, Chris
bache.com, it's unfinished, but
it's there. And if you want to
get access to some of my talks
or some of the things I've
written, they're there. I don't
do a bulletin. I in right now,
still absorbing the feedback
from the course I did with the
shift network. I probably will
do some more teaching with them.
I will probably be having
conversations like we're having
now, for people who want to have
the kind of conversations that
flow out of critical psychedelic
practice and with a spiritual
twist to it. I look forward when
covid allows us to gather
together in groups to do
retreats. I happen to live
outside of Asheville, where
there are lots of retreat
centers around here, and I hope
that there'll come a time when
people can gather, we can gather
physically for long, weekend or
week long retreats where we can
just enter into the discussion
more deeply. I don't have any
immediate plans for that. I'm
just, I live kind of in a
responsorial mode. You wanted to
have a conversation. I'm
delighted to have this
conversation, but I just thought
of wait until things come to me,
and we'll take it
Andrew Holecek: from there.
Beautiful, beautiful. Well,
Chris, I just like with your
book, you're I'm left with just
this perfume, this this sense of
awe and wonder. It really the
magic and mystery of the entire
affair, the the surrender to
some whatever you want to pen
hyper object them, and
necessarily not a silly word,
but a shrink wrap word for the
ineffability, the elegance, the
beauty, the magic of this world
and your your presence really
embodies to me, and that's why
so much I wanted to do this, not
just merely audit, audit with
audit, auditory means, but also
visual means. Is you're doing
something right. You're doing
something right, and your mere
presence conveys the kind of
authenticity, if I may be so
presumptuous, of what you've
done and what you've elected to
be as your path. And we are the
beneficiaries of your the
diamonds that you're throwing
across this planet. And so on
behalf of my community, really,
thank you for taking time out of
your busy life to spend some
time with us, and I'm just left
somewhat breathless. Breath
taking the insights that you
shared is really, truly, deeply
inspiring. And I don't pivot
these words out lightly. It's
really mind bending, mind
blowing. And what a tremendous
gift your courage in your beauty
has brought to this world so
deep, deep. Thanks, my friend,
until Until next time
Chris Bache: I really touched
Andrew, thank you very much, and
thank you for your work. Thank
you for the goodness that you're
spreading, for the for the ideas
that you're seeding. And it's
really been an honor to be in
conversation with you today.
Andrew Holecek: Thank you. My
words, and maybe we can do it
again in this dimension or
another. So all the best, until
next time, my friend sounds
good. Okay. Much Love you.