Roger Walsh: Roger, welcome to
today's episode of deep
transformation, self, society,
spirit. I'm Roger Walsh, and our
co host is the distinguished
John Dupuy and guest today is
the truly remarkable Chris
Bache, who is a internationally
known professor of Philosophy
and Religious Studies, an
author, an award winning teacher
and an internationally known
speaker, usually in these
dialogs, John Knight tries to
stay in the background. But the
topic of today is so remarkable,
the experiences described so
literally out of this world,
that I want to just give a take
a moment to give a context for
the discussion, compared to the
world's many cultures, Western
culture is unusual in a variety
of ways. In fact, researchers
have recently described this as
weird, W, i, e, r, d, Western,
industrialized, educated, rich
and democratic, and so much
research has been done on
Westerners, that it was assumed
that our characteristics were
pretty much common to the
world's cultures. But now we're
beginning to see that that's not
true, and that other cultures
have their own richnesses and
gifts a wide variety. One very
important distinction between
traditional Western culture and
most of the world's cultures is
in their attitude and use of
altered states of consciousness.
The anthropologist rica bush and
on discovered in her world world
survey that over 90% of the
world's cultures have
institutionalized altered states
of consciousness, meaning that
they use a variety of practices
to induce specific states of
consciousness and then mine them
for the information and wisdom
they use and look they and
venerate states such as dreams,
hypnosis, a trance of various
kind and states induced by
meditation, contemplation, yoga,
asceticism, a wide variety, and
these cultures, anthropologists
now call Police polyphasic,
meaning that they draw the
understanding of reality from
many phases of consciousness. By
contrast, Western culture is
pretty unique in having been
until very recently, a
monophasic culture, in that we
draw our understanding of
ourselves in the world almost
entirely from the usual waking
state and kind of look down on
other states as inferior or
deluded or distorted in various
ways. But that's begun to
change, and it began to change
in the 60s, of course, with an
introduction of psychedelics to
the culture, which was soon
followed by an influx of Asian
practices, meditation, yoga,
contemplations, and after that,
by the rediscovery and rebirth
of Western contemplative
practices, so that now we have
in the West a wide variety of
practices for inducing altered
states. And the West is
undergoing a dramatic and very
important but often unrecognized
transformation from a monophasic
culture to a polyphasic culture,
one in which we are now
beginning to appreciate and
research and draw our
understanding of ourselves and
Reality from multiple states of
consciousness, one of the most
potent and remarkable ways of
inducing all the states is with
psychedelics. That's what
started our own Western cultures
transformation, and it's now the
subject of a lot of solid
research at places like one of
the leaders is John Hopkins
University, where scientists and
clinical clinicians are
discovering that psychedelics
have, just as the original
research in the 60s and 70s
found a wide variety of
therapeutic applications and and
perhaps most surprising, very
profound spiritual applications,
the capacity for inducing
profound openings to radically
altered states in which which
profound vistas and
understandings of ourselves and
re. Howard has become available.
That, of course, is not new to
the rest of the world, but this
is new to Western research, and
the findings are quite
remarkable. So we're very
fortunate in having with us a
man who has devoted his life to
the research of these curious
chemicals, and has done it both
through academic research and
comparative cultural analysis,
but also through a remarkably
intense, long, lasting,
carefully analyzed and
documented systematic
exploration of the use of these
chemicals themselves, his
experiences are nothing less
than extra ordinary, and have
far, far reaching implications
for our understanding of the
fundamental nature of reality in
ourselves. He did this in as a
systematic investigation into
the fundamental nature of
reality, and he was able to
reflect on his first hand
observations with the eye of a
trained researcher, philosopher,
theologian. And then he pulled
together cross cultural,
historical and religious
evidence to bring to bear on his
own investigations that so these
are some of the remarkable
things our guest, Chris Bache
has explored. I mentioned that
he was a prolific author, and
His books include dark night,
early dawn, subtitle steps to a
deep ecology of mind. He's also
taught about and written about
education and as an award
winning educator himself, and
his book is titled The living
classroom. And most recently, he
wrote the literally mind
boggling book LSD in the mind of
the universe, in which he
detailed his exploration of
psychedelics and the insights
they opened for him. So that's a
long introduction, but it felt
important to give a context for
these very remarkable
experiences that Chris will be
gifting us with in sharing his
his insights over the many years
of deep, systematic exploration.
I've just spent the weekend
going back to the book. I read
it a couple of years ago in
manuscript form, and was
impressed enough to write a
review for it, and I've been
spending the weekend with it,
and once again, I feel like I've
had my worldview expanded
multiple times and my
understanding of myself and
reality challenged multiple
times, all in very valuable
ways. So Chris, that's a long
introduction, but it's truly a
delight and an honor to be with
you today, and thank you so much
for being with us.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Roger.
It's a very warm introduction,
and I'm just delighted to be
here with you and John today.
It's a pleasure.
Roger Walsh: Well, there are
many places we can we can go
with this, and hopefully we
will, but Roger,
John Dupuy: allow me to give my
little two cents, please. Yes.
Last week, Roger asked me, Would
you like to have Christopher
Bache on? I was like, seriously,
yes, and I had one week, or less
than a week, so immediately, I
ordered the book and I got the
audio version. Thank God, and
that's what that's kept me
through the weekend. But I just
want to put out there, your book
dark night, early dawn, was one
of the more important books for
me, personally, that I've ever
read. So when your name came up
again, the possibility to have
this conversation. Now, I'll
tell you what I I can't remember
all the specifics, but after 20
years, it's been a while when I
first read it, I had a
stabilized understanding of
Non-duality based on my
explorations and journeys and
vision questing and fasting and
prayers and meditation and all
that. And I kind of got it, but
the way you expressed it,
something in that book just
consolidated it, and it has been
accessible to me in a stable
form ever since then. So that's
that's a tremendous gift. So
this, this book that I have been
listening to is unlike anything
that I've experienced, and it is
either you're absolutely sane or
you're completely insane. I my
experiences along these lines,
says this really stinks of deep
truth, and I. Also the very
human, the very humble way that
you present, and self revelatory
what's going on in your personal
life and how you did it and
everything is, is somebody with
an open mind, I think, is, is
just ends up trusting you, just,
I'm in the hands of somebody I
can listen to. And then from
there, it goes on to it's very
big. This may be a bringing
together of everything we've
been working on in our
generation, but in a new,
holistic, religious, scientific,
everything vision that that
transforms us from a reality
where a lot of us are killing
ourselves or live in deep
depression to an absolutely
1,000% changed view of reality.
And I'm not using that as
hyperbole, at least I'm not
trying to it's that big. It's
that radical. Is that that pay
attention to this.
Chris Bache: Thank you. Your
description, John touches me
very deeply, and it really
touches me that something I've
written has influenced your
experience of Non-duality that
just really touches me. Thank
you,
Roger Walsh: beautiful, yeah,
Chris, of course. I think
everyone will want to know what
motivated you to begin this
extraordinary quest. And maybe
you can just say, say a little
bit about water, the nature of
what you actually did to induce
these remarkable experiences and
what motivated you to begin?
Chris Bache: Well, all my life,
I've had a just a deep passion
to understand our universe. I
mean, I was in the seminary,
starting in high school training
to be a Catholic priest. Left
that went on to get a degree in
theology from Notre Dame and
then Cambridge and brown, I
finished Brown in philosophy of
religion, but an absolute,
convinced agnostic with strong
atheistic inclinations, but the
passion to understand what's
real. Why is there so much
suffering in the world? Is there
an intelligence in existence was
still there, still pushing me in
all of my studies now, I had
finished my dissertation. I was
looking for where to go next,
and I encountered Stan Grof
book, realms of the human
unconscious, that extraordinary
book that just turned my life
around and one reading, he
convinced me that LSD, or
psychedelics, could be used
safely, if you use them in a pro
with proper precautions to
explore the deep structure of
one's consciousness. And some of
his anecdotes also indicated
more than one's own personal
unconscious that one could reach
out deeper to explore deeper
fabric of consciousness. And I
quickly realized the
philosophical significance, not
just psychological significance,
of his work. So I realized that
people in my profession,
philosophy of religion, my
discipline, would soon the ones
making the most important
contribution to the field would
be people writing out of an
experiential basis, not just an
intellectual basis. To do that,
you have to have not just a few
experiences, but you have to
undergo systematic training in
the discipline. So that's what I
did. It was 1979 when I began
what became a 20 year journey, I
worked for four years, I stopped
for six years for reasons that I
give in the book, and then I
resumed for 10 years. But
overall, over 20 years, I did 73
high dose LSD sessions following
Stan's protocol, and this is a
regimen that I wouldn't
recommend, I really don't
recommend. Today, with
hindsight, I realized that I
really pushed myself harder than
was sometimes wise, but I use a
lot of precautions. I took, did
all of the classic training for
and precautions for doing fully
internalized sessions with a
sitter. My sitter was a clinical
psychologist whom I was married
to at the time, Carol and using
very carefully selected
evocative music, basically, let
me mention, I worked with high
doses of LSD initially, because
I was still thinking in terms of
a model of individual awakening
or individual healing. And I was
thinking I knew that karma,
according to the eastern models,
it was finite karma, and
basically I wanted to accelerate
my own. Spiritual development,
and I thought that if I could
sustain the intensity of the
confrontation, I could basically
bite off bigger bites of karma
in each session if I worked with
high doses rather than melt it
more slowly with low doses. And
it was simply a matter of
efficiency. It was hard to hit
time for these sessions in a
dual career marriage, and I just
thought I would work a little
harder, more aggressively. And
that turned out that was based
on a completely false set of
assumptions. I found that in my
work, within a few years, I was
entering into domains that were
far, far beyond anything that
made sense in terms of an
individual model of
transformation. I began to
understand that my sessions had
been had catalyzed something
that was aimed at nothing less
than some type of healing or
transformation of the human
species as a whole. So working
with very, very high doses,
since, since existence is
unified from the very start,
working with high doses that
hyper amplifies consciousness,
activates it only it changes not
only how deep you go, but it
changes how wide you are when
you go there. So it activates a
larger field of consciousness,
which then triggers the the
cycles of death and rebirth that
workings with psychedelics
therapeutically does. So I did
this for 20 years, and I
finished in 1999 and then I
digested those experiences for
another 20 years this. This a
very challenging undertaking. It
took a long time to connect all
the dots and to absorb them, and
it took me five years to write
the book. Yeah, yeah, it's a
lot. Yeah. I was thinking I
would be much more comfortable
writing this book posthumously,
holding it and releasing it
posthumously, because it is so
exposing in the sense of your
most intimate relationship with
the divine. But the mother told
me no, there's no time for that
kind of indulgence. The word it
was needed, and it would mesh,
it would support other people in
their work and our times that
we're going into. Historically,
we all hands on deck. You know,
all hands on deck needed to come
forward now,
Roger Walsh: beautiful and and
it really does feel that this
work you did, and really was
work of exploration with these
psychedelics and the writing of
the book, really is was done out
of a very large motive And and
as you said, it was, it was
work. I was struck by just the,
you know, our culture has this
very naive media view of
psychedelics as being done for,
you know, getting high and
having a good time. And, yes,
that can happen. But, and you
had some extraordinary ecstatic
experiences. But you also went
through the hell realms, not
once, but multiple times. And as
you describe having to open to
levels of not only your own
suffering, but collective
suffering, the history of human
cruelty, et cetera, et cetera. I
mean, this was extraordinary. I
just found myself bowing to the
courage you had to bring to this
time after time after time, and
yet you always seem to find that
ultimately, there was a value in
the suffering. I wonder if you
could say what kept you going
and what kind of value found
there.
Chris Bache: Well, this was the
great gift that Stan gave me in
his work. He taught me to trust
the process, and that was
affirmed in my own experience.
And my experience was, if you
completely trust the process and
let your session take you where
it wants to take you, it may get
worse and worse. You may enter
experiences that are completely
inscrutable, that completely
horrifying. You don't understand
why you're going here or what
sense it makes. But if you
surrender to it completely, this
will come eventually to a
culmination, and you'll be taken
through a Death-Rebirth cycle.
You some part of you will die,
will slough off. You'll be taken
into a transition. And through
this transition, you will awaken
in a different reality, into a
different level of reality. And
for the remainder of that
session, you will. Experience,
teaching our experiences within
a completely ecstatic framework.
So there is the purification
side of a session and the
ecstatic side of a session. So
what you internalize at the end
of the day is not just the
suffering, but the entire cycle
that suffering reaches a peak.
There is a culmination, there is
a breakthrough, and then there's
joy and ecstasy and communion,
and then integration at the end,
it's the balance of the joy and
the ecstasy of insight with the
purification process that makes
it manageable. If I had to go
through all the suffering for
years. Without that ecstatic
teaching, I would not have been
able to do it as it was. It was
difficult when I was going
through the ocean of suffering,
which was in the third and
fourth years of the work, fifth,
fifth year of the work, the
morning of a session, was
difficult because I had a sense
of what I was getting into,
where it was going, but I don't
think it's any more difficult
than a soldier on the eve of a
battle or a mother on the eve of
labor. You know if it's
especially if it's your second
or third birth, you know what
you're getting into. You know
it's going to be a hard day. You
Gird your loins and you prepare
for it. And in for my case, I
don't think what I did was any
more exotic than someone who
wants to climb Mount Everest or
someone who wants to go to the
North Pole. Personally, I don't
know why anybody in their right
mind would want to climb Mount
Everest, you know, but you but I
do understand the explorers
mentality. I wanted to see, I
wanted to understand, I wanted
to know. And no matter how deep
I went, I found that there was
always more that I could be
shown, that would be shown me.
John Dupuy: Did you feel you
were being held or guided in
some in some sense, taken care
of in
Chris Bache: this journey and
every step along the way, when I
would go through this
consciousness was waiting for
me, and I might not understand
the logic of the sequence of the
pairing of things for years. In
fact, there are certain things
that I only began to understand
when I wrote the book, but as I
went through, I had a basic
structure enough to know that
there was a logic to this
process, and I always felt met.
I felt met and engaged,
sometimes very consciously,
where I would ask questions and
it would orchestrate my
experience. But always, there
was an intelligence, meeting me,
taking me, educating me,
breaking me down, beating me
down to dust, taking me further,
taking me back, over and over
again until I understood
something, and then it would
take me deeper. And there was a
systematic progression to this
process. I found that this
systematic progression was
really important, because
there's so many levels of
consciousness that it can take
you into but when you enter a
new level of consciousness, it's
very disorienting. It just
cognitively is confusing you,
and this manifests by not being
able to remember everything that
happened to you. You just don't
have a framework in your mind to
hold it. But if you go back to
it again and again and again,
and you're systematic and
rigorous, and you record
carefully, your system will
acclimate, and you will learn
how to stay conscious in
dimensions of reality that
previously had swallowed you and
I actually began in Time to
realize that this deeper
consciousness was titrating the
experiences of Transcendence,
giving me time to absorb and
acclimate, even though sometimes
I wanted to run on it kept me
and fed me in small steps so
that I could retain and hold
what it had been Giving me.
Because the purpose I found was
not simply to transcend and
experience some form of ecstasy.
The purpose was to bring that
ecstasy back into your time
space consciousness. And first,
hold on to it, remember it, and
then secondly, digest it and let
it seep into your bones as
deeply as possible.
John Dupuy: And you talked about
in the book is how you framed,
or you became to understand that
the hell realms, suffering
realms that you would have to
visit were for your benefit and
they were for purification. Mm.
Or that they were getting you
prepared for the revelation.
Chris Bache: Yeah, there. It's
complicated. I mean, it took me
about two and a half years to go
through what Stan Grof calls the
perinatal dimension of
consciousness, the perinatal
level where the purifications
are very intense, and the
physical purification and
emotional purifications, which
eventually end, and for me,
ended an ego death, you know,
like just being shattered, my
entire physical identity being
turned inside out. And then the
ocean of suffering began. And in
the beginning, I thought this
was a deeper form of personal
suffering. It was a deeper form
of ego death, but eventually,
and this is why I wrote Dark
Matter Lee dawn at core, to
answer this question, to solve
the riddle, why did the
suffering get as large as it
did? And the conclusion I came
to is that it really wasn't
aimed at my personal
transformation at all. It was
aimed at healing the human
species, that the human psyche
in an aggregate form, at the
collective unconscious, there
are wounds which humanity has
still not healed, the things
that we've done to each other in
war, the terrible disasters that
all the suffering that human
beings have accumulated, not all
of it, has been healed, and that
there are vast tracks of the
collective psyche where this
suffering still festers. And I
think every spiritual tradition
recognizes that in deep
spiritual practice, you have an
opportunity. You don't have to
do it, but an invitation is
sometimes extended, that if you
are willing to take on some of
that suffering, literally, just
to become aware of it, it can
move through you and resolve
itself, just like our personal
suffering enters into our
awareness, moves through us and
resolves itself. And so for two
years, I did the ocean of
suffering work, and it wasn't
really until about halfway
through that that I began to
understand that this wasn't for
me. It was for my family. It was
for the human family, and only
later did I begin to understand
the historical circumstances of
our times that made the healing
of the human family, the healing
of our past, so important in
order to clear the foundation,
so to speak, to allow an
imminent transformation to take
place in history.
John Dupuy: And I'm sure that
gave you, you mentioned girding
your lines up, that gave you
that warrior or soldierly
perspective, it's not just about
you, Chris, you know, to do this
thing that was way beyond, way
beyond any human capacity to
survive, I would believe, just,
just on its own, but To keep
coming back and not and it
shifts from being an individual
quest to
Chris Bache: everybody and
everything. And it may be the
case that this, it's largely a
function of my choice to work
with these very, very high doses
that blow you so deeply into the
deep structure of reality. But I
think one of the things I
learned it made this may not
open for everybody. Everybody
may not enter these domains. One
of the things I learned over the
course of my journey is that
this was a task which my soul
took on before I was born. So
this was part of my karmic
choice to do this work so it
wasn't forced upon me and it
wasn't a tragedy. It was simply
part of my life's work, and the
universe more than rewarded me
for this phase of the work,
because following the ocean of
suffering, it took me places in
the ocean of suffering, and
afterwards it more than amply
paid me, or repaid me for taking
this work on. As always happens,
whenever you do anything for
others, the universe has no
choice but to get give back to
you. That's because the universe
acts out of oneness. So if we do
something for others, it always
comes back to you in one form or
another,
Roger Walsh: beautiful and in a
sense. Sounds as though this
shift you went through from the
assumption with which you
entered this work, that you were
doing it for your own
understanding, Revelation,
transformation, and yet you were
forced, almost against your
inclinations, to see this in a
larger context, that you were in
some way, some mysterious way,
both opening to and allowing
yourself to be an instrument for
the transformation of collective
consciousness. And I can
certainly understand that was
challenging, because it's a very
different it's a different world
view. It's a very different set
of assumptions about the nature
of ourselves and reality that
even makes that recognition
possible. And I can certainly
understand what a shift that
was. Would you like to say more
about that?
Chris Bache: My first concern
was that, at first it sounded
like ego gone amok. I mean, it
sounded like ego inflation. And
so I really had to sit with that
for a long time, because my
experiences were telling me that
was not what was happening, but
the larger challenges, as you
said, Roger, this is a very
different worldview in the
classic individual patient
model, you the individual is
having experiences. So you the
individual has Transpersonal
experiences, and the individual
is always kind of at the center
of the circle. But in this
model, my individual existence
was completely secondary to this
dynamic, and so it becomes not a
matter of my being being central
to what's happening. I got the
system, I got something started,
but I dissolve completely into
pre existing fields of
consciousness. And these fields
of consciousness are, what are
the dynamic force having these
experiences? So it manifests not
only in the ocean of suffering,
but it manifests later, when I
was going into archetypal
reality and causal oneness.
Reality, it's hard to describe,
but in many ways, in many
experiences, I was like Chris
Bache was like a bit player, not
like there is something going
on. This is so challenging that
the in the book, I have an
appendix, which, in the appendix
is what dies and is reborn. When
you experience so many deaths
and rebirths, it becomes a
cognitive question, what is it
that's actually dying? It feels
personal and you experience it.
Is it just ego dying over and
over again? And the answers that
I offer at that in that part, I
know, push very, very far. I
mean, because on the one hand,
it's ego, and then it becomes
species ego, and then it becomes
something I call the shamanic
persona. But in the end, what is
dying, I think, is literally
some aspect of cosmic
consciousness, or some dimension
of cosmic reality, is softening
and surrendering and opening up
to a still deeper dimension of
cosmic consciousness. And this
deeper dimension of cosmic
consciousness pours its
blessings into me at the very
bottom. But it's not primarily
into me. It pours it into the
deeper dimension of cosmic
consciousness itself. And I know
those are very hard concepts to
entertain, and it's a it's a
very different way of thinking,
and it's tentative my
description, but something along
that order, I think, is required
to understand when you explode
consciousness this radically.
And again, I don't think it's
wise for people to explode
consciousness this radically, I
would work with lower doses. I'd
work with Psilocybin, gentler
substances, if I were doing it
over again. Here, we have to
appreciate that LSD in this
quantity, when it's contained,
when it's intensified in a
therapeutic modality, you
basically just shatter your
consciousness and dissolve it
far beyond physical limits, and
you spend hours dissolved into
some stratum of the universe
and. And then you congeal and
consolidate it. And then you
shatter, leaving your historical
existence radically behind and
dissolve into into some fabric,
some stratosphere, of
consciousness. And you live
there for a while. It lives. You
are it part of it as it lives.
And then you congeal and bring
it back and hold it beautiful.
Roger Walsh: I'd love, I'd love
to tease out several things you
said, but, but I do want to ask
a very specific question, that
is, you've referred on several
occasions to the very high doses
of LSD used. So might you just
tell us what doses you did use?
Chris Bache: Yeah, I aim to be
working at 600 micrograms, but
because I wasn't using a
pharmaceutical, identified dose,
I would say 500 to 600
micrograms to be safe, but it
was not less than five.
Roger Walsh: There's a lot of
LSD, yes, put mildly, and I want
to, I want to tea, tease out
your description of this very
remarkable phenomena, that of
the Death-Rebirth experiences,
which is found as a as a and
recognized as a very important
experience, and a literal birth
experience, Psych, spiritual
birth experience across the
world, spiritual traditions.
It's deliberately sought in
traditions such as Shamanism,
and yet you describe it in not
an entirely new way, but a
radically expanded way, as a
repetitive process of dying to
one identity and limitation
after another, after another,
after another, reconstituting a
new, new, more porous, expanded
identity, and then having to
offer that into into the whole
and let me just see check my
Understanding of Death-Rebirth
against yours. And have you?
Have you respond, from your
enlarged perspective, to me, it
seems that what actually dies,
what we confuse ourselves to be,
and what actually dies and
Death-Rebirth experience is our
self representation. We mistake
a self image or a self concept
or a self narrative for our true
self, and what needs to die is
that representation. So it dies,
we find ourselves opened to a
much larger perspective and
possibility, both of both of our
own identity and of the nature
of reality. But for some reason,
I tended to think, until hearing
you just now, I tended to think
of for psychological reasons,
psychodynamic, habitual patterns
re establish themselves, and
another self representation
forms. But you're putting this
in a larger, more cosmic or
ontological perspective,
suggesting that an even deeper
understanding of the of the
Death-Rebirth would be that one
that as part of the cosmic play,
the leela, the the the formation
of the universe by the two
cosmic beings that you describe
in one place in your book, that
that separation is built into
the game, the cosmic game, as
Stan Grof would call it. And
what I'm understanding you to
say is that identity is
reconstituted in a rebirth
process because of the very
nature of the of the universe
and consciousness that
consciousness separates so as to
play again. Am I understanding
you correctly?
Chris Bache: I think your
description of ego death is spot
on. What dies is what is
consumed. Is our self
representation, what we have,
our sense of identity that we've
amassed from our physical
experience and our time space
existence, our time space
experience. And I also want to
mention that every every
medicine has a certain range. It
has a certain, you know,
signature, and it has a sort of
power and of range. Psilocybin
has a certain depth of range
that even if you repeat it many
times, it will reach you, take
you into the upper register. But
still, there is a upper
register. Ayahuasca has a range,
and maybe I think of it as a
deeper upper register. Salvia
divinorum has a range, ketamine
and five Meo, DMT, all of these
substances have ranges. Now one
of the things, and LSD has a
range, and of course, then we
start looking at doses and how
doses affect the range. Now, I
tend to experience Psilocybin as
a very body grounded type of
psychedelic experience, very
much tuned to my emotional body,
it opens up a range, but it's
it's it's it stays, in a sense,
within the parameters. It
stretches, but does not shatter
as aggressively as LSD does the
parameters of individual
identity, but it can dissolve
them, soften them, and open this
up, in my experience in working
with high doses of LSD, is that
all of these things happen, but
because of the particular
intensity of this substance and
its lack of history,
anthropologically, it's
therefore it doesn't have the
fields associated with it that
Psilocybin and Mescaline or
Peyote have associated with it.
It tends to shatter our time
space identity, and throw us in
a level of experience that lies
beyond that reality in a
spiritual reality. But if we, if
we go back to that place again
and again, our experience there
begins to congeal, and we
develop an alternative identity
persona. I call it the shamanic
persona. It is an identity which
is comprised of all of my
experiences at that level of
Transpersonal reality. And it's
kind of super ordinate to my
individual egoic identity. But
it's stable. If my experiences
have been well managed, it's
stable. So that when I go into a
psychedelic space, and I
transition away from time and
space and I I enter into a
familiar sense of self at a
certain level of spiritual
reality. But if and I acclimate
there, I learn how to stay
conscious there. I i learn the
ropes, and then I but if I keep
pushing the edge, if I if the if
the chemical is strong enough,
and if the intent is focused
enough, eventually, in my
experience, you come to the
ceiling, and at that ceiling,
there is a cost that's exacted.
Another round of death takes
place. But what's dying is not
the ego. What's dying is that
shamanic persona or that second
identity, because that second
identity is a holder of a
certain level of Transpersonal
experience. And if you want to
go deeper, you don't need to,
but if you want to go deeper,
you've got to die at that lower
shamanic level. And so the
shamanic identity dies, and you
transition into yet another
level of reality in which the
whole workings of the universe
is different, different rules,
different phenomena exist,
different bandwidth, so to
speak. And you must acclimate to
that level of reality. Every
step deeper into the universe is
a step into a higher level of
energy. I can over. And you to
acclimate at a particular level
of reality, you must acclimate
to the energy. And that's some
of the very, very intense
cleansing that continues to take
place, 3040, 50 sessions in is
because you're, you're you're
learning how to stabilize
consciousness is extremely high
levels of Energy. That just
takes a long time. So, so what
eventually came out of all of
this is appreciate is an
understanding that death and
rebirth is stage specific, that
there are many levels of the
universe, and if you
systematically push through
those levels, there are a. Gates
that you come to, so to speak,
and at each gate, there is a
sacrifice asked now at the end,
eventually, once you've died so
many times, death becomes a
meaningless concept, because you
always learn that you're always
going to be reborn. Some essence
of our identity will continue.
The Phoenix always rises.
Eventually, the concept, or the
concept of death, as an
interpretation of what's
happening, yielded to a concept
of purification. I learned that
all dying is, in fact,
purification. It's just that
when purification reaches so
deep, it's destructuring
whatever self representation or
whatever reality representation
you're operating within, it
becomes purification unto death.
It's actually dissolving the
structures within which you are
holding reality and death. So
it's it's death, but it's a
fluid death. It's a purification
process.
John Dupuy: So, so Chris
following up what Roger asked
about what dies? Well, what
doesn't die?
Unknown: Yeah. Ah.
John Dupuy: Because in your
book, you talk a lot about
reincarnation has been being a
given in in the universe as it
was revealed to you, this
universe, multiverse, whatever
this mysterium tremendum is that
you've brought back to us to
talk about, so what doesn't die?
Chris Bache: Well, I think when
we go deep, we realize that
everything is dying constantly.
Everything is dying and living
and dying and living constantly.
There. There are no stable
things which are not dying in
this universe. And to see that
clearly of is, of course, is is
considered a great
accomplishment to really
understand that everything is
temporary, everything is
transition, everything is
moving. Everything is fluid,
holding on. You know, people
have asked me, What is it dies.
And you know, there is, what I
will say is, there is, there is
always continuity of memory. If
you do your if you organize your
session, well, there is
continuity of recall. So
therefore there is continuity of
memory. You might say that
memory doesn't die, but I don't
really think that's the best way
to describe it. I think memory
is shattered and reconstitutes
into it. I don't know of I don't
know what doesn't die, but
here's, here's something
John Dupuy: is being purified,
right? What is that? What is
that that's being purified?
Chris Bache: Well, I'd go
farther and say, I think that in
this process that life gives
birth to individuality, not an
ego, not a self, but life is
giving birth to an
individuality, and the nature
that individuality matures and
deepens as the soul matures and
deepens, and as one's spiritual
experiences deepen, my
understanding, I mean the
Vedanta traditions and many
spiritual traditions basically
believe that the individual is
an illusion, and the goal is to
shatter the illusion and to
dissolve irretrievably into the
oneness of all existence. I
understand that cosmology, but I
think it's a mistake, and it
doesn't jive with my experience.
My experience the universe is is
very intensely interested in
birthing an individuality and in
aging that individuality and
refining that individuality and
maturing it so that in the end,
we die, but we die in order to
grow up, and we die again in
order to grow up. In the end,
this is what I call the birth of
the diamond soul, that
reincarnation basically is aging
us stage by stage, level by
level, helping us grow and to
become more than we were, more
than we were. But sooner or
later, we reach a point where
all of our former lives and all
of the history, all the
experiences and wisdom and
mistakes we've made, all of it
comes together into an
integrated singularity. And as
I've experienced that
singularity, when I experienced
that happen in my sessions,
there was an absolute. I was
catapulted into a state of
awareness beyond anything I.
Experienced up to that point in
time. I was an individual, but I
was an individual in pure
Shunyata emptiness, condition,
transparent, open to all
existence. I was individual, but
within a boundless existence,
but I had my full memory intact,
and I think that this is where
the universe or the Divine is
taking all human beings, that
individuality is not the
problem, separation is the
problem. Ego, boundedness is the
problem. Individuality is not
the problem. Individuality is
the great beauty. It's one of
the great gifts that the Creator
is giving us the opportunity to
be an individual.
Roger Walsh: Chris, can you draw
a distinction there between the
individual, individuality and
separation? Let me see if I'm
understanding individuality
gives a sense of the recognition
of of I can't come up with
another word that into being
individual, but separation
usually is but, but the
individual can be so there can
be a sense of individuality
within the recognition of one's
innate connection with
dependence on an ultimate unity
with the all, or the pure
consciousness. Is that? How you
would distinguish from
separation where there is a
forgetting of the connection to
the greater whole?
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think when
Buddhism teaches Shunyata and
when it teaches anata no self,
they are not they're basically
defining a type of self
experience where this we
experience ourselves cut off
from other selves, we experience
ourselves as cut off and away
from the universe itself. When
that self dies, one experiences
an individuality which is porous
to others, and that is we live
in compassion, and we experience
an individuality which is in
communion with surrounding
layers and layers of
consciousness, so that there is
a spiritual openness and an
openness of compassion to other
beings. We are still an
individual, but we are an
individual that's situated
within the boundaryless
condition
Roger Walsh: and so and it
sounds as though I may take me a
little moment to unravel this,
but it sounds as though you're
saying there's a value In that
individuality. And I'm reminded
of Ramakrishna, a great Indian
mystic who was just
extraordinarily fluid in his
ability to roam through
different realizations and
states. And he described being
lost in unity, but but then
longing for separation so that
he could worship and relate to
the mother, so there were both
sides there, and I hear
something similar here. There
are some traditions you pointed
to, Advaita Vedanta, for
example, where the where the
self is regarded as an illusion,
the fundamental reality is our
inseparability, or is rather the
Non-duality of existence. And
yet it sounds like you're
pointing to out of your own and
here's the beauty of it, it came
out of your own experience. You
were aware of all these
traditions, these ontologies,
cosmology, metaphysics. And yet
out of your own experience, it
feels like you came to the sense
that there is a beauty and
perfection in the individuality
in and of itself. Is that
correct
Chris Bache: it is? It is, and
let me frame it this way, before
the before time and space
existed, before the physical
universe existed, when
everything was in the pure,
fertile void condition when
whatever you want to call the
absolute made a choice to
manifest physical existence. The
physical universe is the only
thing strong enough, I think, to
shatter the the oneness. Of the
absolute, into pieces that then
can become individually awakened
to what it is within the body of
the Divine. So the the great
gift of the physical universe,
or one of the great gifts. Of
the physical universe is
literally the density that
causes the oneness of the Divine
to shatter into pieces, so that
those pieces can become
operational as Divine within the
body of the Divine, and in that
context, individuality, I think,
is one of the great gifts of
creation. It's one of the great
gifts of of the universe. And I
don't think the creator wants to
destroy that individuality.
After billions and billions of
years of getting us to this
point, finally, when we wake up
and become conscious and we can
drop our conscious down to
source and understand and
identify that part of us which
is universal, which is oneness
with all the universal, with
what is alive. I don't think the
intention is then to simply say,
Okay, let's destroy that. I
think we're growing, and I think
we're going to be growing for
billions and billions and
billions of years more. We are
just getting started in this
process of waking up to the to
the vast expanse of existence.
And yet we're waking up in a way
in which we become lovers of it.
We become servants of it. We
become a fractal embodiment of
it. All these different
metaphors for describing this
mystery of the dance. Let me
John Dupuy: just say that I've
seen the same thing, and you
expressed it much more
eloquently. And I feel like I'm
a yellow belt, you know, I'm
talking to a 10th Don or
something like that. But yeah,
that somehow, in in the awe, the
preciousness of the individual
that is that infinitely more
precious, at the same time, it's
a yes, and it's this and that,
and it's working itself out, and
that's come through very clearly
for me at times. And I had to
rethink a lot of my ideas about
psychology, given that and feels
deeply human at a good at a deep
level. And also, let me say what
you were, what you were
describing, is your experience,
at some point, self awakens,
okay? Dink, that just opens.
That's just Jesus said a man
must be born again. Well, what
happens when you're born? You're
just little helpless infant.
You're not good for anything but
being precious. And that's the
beginning of the journey. And
then it seems that you're
talking about a Christ like or a
Bodhisattva. Responsibility. At
a certain point we have to take
on responsibility, not just for
own awaking, our own mistakes,
our own suffering, but for for
the all, for the collective. And
that adds, I guess, the word is,
a nobility to the task that
otherwise would just be very
narcissistic, if you will, and
just very, you know, chasing
your tail, but, but that, that
understanding, that quality that
you express at a deep, deep
level is, I Think, is essential,
and because we have the
archetype of Jesus, of a human
being whom an individual who was
crucified and murdered in this
most horrible way almost
imaginable, who then goes down
into the underworld and blah
blah, but comes back still, him
barely recognizable. Some of his
disciples didn't. But at some
level, a transformed level that
has kept the rest of us running
in his, you know, his path for a
couple of 1000 years. But that's
a story of the individual that's
contained within our western our
western treasure chest of wisdom
stories.
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah. It is a
story of divine incarnation come
to fruition. And I think that
story has archetypal
ramifications that are much
larger than the Christology that
was developed to under to
interpret it, which ended up
making Jesus into a unique being
when really he's a prototype,
Unknown: beautiful, nice,
Roger Walsh: and that that seems
to be a major division that
occurs in each of the great
religions, and probably other
many others as well, and perhaps
reflecting different different
developmental, psychological
developmental stages on the
people who make the
interpretation the the the
founder is either elevated to
unique status which the rest of
us can only approximate at best,
or is recognized as an exemplar
and. You called a prototype of
the capacities and potentials
latent within us. Seems a very
important distinction you point
Chris Bache: to the I want to
mention that, as you said, John,
when you begin to experientially
tap into that in us, which is
universal, then eventually all
aspects of your life heats to to
come in alignment with that. And
that's why love is is you know,
deep you know, not arrows, but
agape, love and compassion,
social justice, fairness,
naturally arises as one.
Spiritual practice deepens
because you have discovered this
hybrid nature within yourself.
You are individually awake and
awake to a universal bond, a
universal level of reality that
becomes an expression simply of
your true nature. It's just
spontaneous. And I also want to
mention that I don't think you
have you certainly don't have to
go where I went in order to
spiritually awaken, even if you
wanted to use psychedelics or
spiritual awakening. To me,
there's three uses that I'd
separate, using of psychedelics
for healing, using of
psychedelics to spiritually
awakening. And then a third,
which is what my journey became,
a cosmological exploration. If I
wanted to use psychedelics for
simply spiritual awakening, I
would recommend a protocol
working with very low doses,
because it's about dissolving
the ego, and you got to get
after where the ego lives in the
world, and that's closer to
time, space realities. You do
not need to shatter time to
become spiritually awakened. You
don't need to enter archetype or
reality. You don't need to go
back to the beginning of the
universe to become genuinely
enthusiastically spiritually
awakened. What I started kind of
aiming at spiritual awakening,
but the method was so powerful
it shoved me in a way past that,
or through that into a deeper,
into a different agenda. And I'm
entirely sympathetic to
spiritual teachers who would
say, you know, your time would
be better spent cultivating on
abiding the abiding presence of
the transparent condition, then
learning these, going on this
quest to learn how the universe
is put together in these
different levels. And I
understand that critique, and I
I share it to a degree myself. I
wonder sometimes whether I would
have my time would have been
better spent focusing more on
the Enlightenment side of the
things than the cosmic
exploration side. But what
happened in my work is that it
pushed deeper into the
cosmological exploration side.
John Dupuy: Well, you said you
were a philosopher, and you went
with a philosopher's quest into
this journey, and exactly what
you said, and it's exactly what
you did, so there's no flip
flopping there,
Roger Walsh: and you did it with
a very specific aspiration and
intention. Chris, I recall that
you said before each session you
would affect you effectively
offer yourself as an instrument
for the highest good of all,
very similar to the Bodhisattva
aspiration, or even reminded me
of Jesus statement, not my will,
but thine. It really felt like a
an offer, an unrestricted
offering of yourself as an
instrument for for acquiring
whatever wisdom you could was
opened to you, or you were
gifted or graced with in order
to be an instrument of
transmission to others. And it
feels like your prayer was
answered very clearly. And you
talked about, well, you know,
could have been as valuable to
to just do spiritual practice.
And perhaps, perhaps that's
true, but, and it's kind of
like, let 1000 spiritual flowers
bloom. You can't. You gave us a
new kind of flower, and we are
benefiting from it. And who
knows how many people, other
other people will benefit from
it. So wonderful that you did
what you did, and beautiful that
you did it with that aspiration
and prayer. It feels like your
prayer was answered.
John Dupuy: Yeah. Chris, how do
you what do you do these days?
I. Mean to keep yourself, man,
you went on the journey like you
know, just remarkable, and you
came back and you mentioned that
you're teaching. Do you have a
way of staying awake to
everything that you were gifted,
everything that you were shown,
or do you find in the
transmission and the teaching
that that's what keeps you still
crisp base in this limited
reality, but at the same time,
in touch with and transmitting
what you learned on the other
side, if you will?
Chris Bache: You know, there's a
question I ask in the book, what
is the value of true but
temporary knowledge? And I don't
doubt that any of the experience
that I had on my journeys was
true, and I also know it was
temporary, and it I cannot live
in those places that the places
where I've been, I can't the
idea of bringing them back and
integrating them as a stable
state is that it may be true for
certain levels of experience,
but some of the deeper
experiences not possible, at
least not in, not in my present
level of psycho spiritual
development. I know that there
are great beings who can, who
are masters of these domains,
and always they are the they are
my guiding light. But I know
that Chris's abilities are not
cannot stabilize these states of
consciousness in my present
life, I use those experiences in
order to I use them in my
meditation practice. I use them
in my vara practice. They are,
they are the Samaya sattva that
opens me to the Jnana sattva. So
they are the being of practice.
It opens me to the being of
reality of these things. But I
also have a certain a lot of my
time these days is spent
grounding, just being grounded,
staying grounded, living in
touch with the Earth, because I
spent so many years out in the
far reaches of the cosmos that
it's good to be in touch with
the earth and grounding on the
earth. But most of all, I'm a
teacher. I mean, I just, I love
to find things and to share
them. And during all the years
when I was doing this work, I
could not really share them. I
really could not share them
directly in my classes. Now, the
first time I shared them was in
dark night, early dawn, where I
addressed experiences that had
come up in the first half of my
journey up to about the halfway
point in LSD, in the mind of the
universe, or what I prefer to
call it, the name that it had
for me in all the years I wrote
it, diamonds from heaven. That's
I shared the whole extent of the
journey. But to me, the most
important part of it all is the
chapter on the birth of the
future human and the final
vision. What was because the
work was so little focused on me
and so much focused on the human
family, it seemed it just became
natural that, and I guess this
is by some larger cosmic design,
the story that kept being
pounded into me and I kept it
kept being shown over and over
again, was the human story,
where humanity is in its
evolution, what we are coming
to, the pivot point that we are
coming in into in history, the
absolute shift, which is taking
place at an archetypal level, at
really, at the plate tectonics
of the art of the collective
psyche, that we're coming to a
tipping point where a tipping
point that will change the
condition of the human psyche at
the collective level, not just
an aggregate number of
individuals, but there is a
shift taking place underneath
us, at the collective psychic
level that is going to market a
before and after in human
history. This was shown me again
and again, and then years later,
I was taken, I was dissolved
into the human species. I mean,
I just dissolved without
remainder, and then was taken
into the death and rebirth of.
Humanity, not in any details,
not given details of when,
exactly when, where or how, but
that humanity was going to go
through an epic, an era when it
would completely lose control.
All the assumed, all the
assumptions of life were going
to be stripped away. We were
going to go through a crushing
ordeal as a species, an ordeal
that would be so terrible for
time we would think that this is
the end. We're going extinct as
a species on this planet. But in
my visionary experience, we come
through this, we survive and we
are absolutely changed in the
process. When we come through
this crisis, this long crisis,
we have reached. We reached.
Have reached something inside
ourselves. We have cracked open
our heart, we have cracked open
our mind. The humanity that
emerges from the historical
period is a changed humanity. It
is a deeper humanity. It is a
more open and a more mature
humanity. One of the ways
putting together different
things from my sessions, I've
come to believe that this crisis
that we're coming through with,
a global systems crisis driven
by a series of ecological crisis
just tremendous converging
forces that we are increasingly
aware of these days. But this is
a crisis of consciousness. We
literally cannot afford to try
to run this planet any longer as
a at from the egoic level of
consciousness, the the ego is
separated, and it leads to a
divided world. And I think
what's happening is we're the
soul is coming forward in
history. I mentioned the diamond
soul. I think we are literally
growing up into our full soul
being, and that we are coming to
a point where, when we
incarnate, we will never be
tempted to identify just with
this body, but we will know
ourselves to be 100,000 year old
being, and we will know that the
planet that we are leaving is
the planet that we will return
to. We know we have these deep
karmic connections with everyone
around us, and we know that we
are all embedded in the oneness
of the divine consciousness.
This is the magnitude of the of
the transition that we're going
through. And I think that all of
us, in all of our spiritual
practices, are contributing to
this transition. And I think
it's why so many people are
having such very, very intense
yogic practices and meditational
practices and past life therapy
practices, because there's this
is tremendous unloading which is
taking place, which is part of a
collective healing, which is
making way for this awakening of
something new in history.
Roger Walsh: Chris, you gave a
beautiful description of one of
the more well, there's so many
profound openings and insights
you had, but you did have a
profound recognition of the
possible future ahead of us as a
human species, which you just
summarized briefly, and and your
insights are resonant with the
sense that seems to be growing
among many people that we Are
Coming to a time of
extraordinary crisis and
opportunity. I think of that
combination being very well
expressed, perhaps best
expressed by a mutual friend of
ours, Dewayne Elgin, whose many
books on on the transition we as
a as a species, are facing,
really point to current time as
a bottleneck in which there is
we really may face a, if not
civilizational collapse, at
worse than a loss of a lot of
current capacities as a species
and the death of many, many
people. Yet also, he points to
the possibility of this being
could be, if we bring enough
awareness, aspiration, pure
heartedness, to the process, it
could be a kind of collective
rebirth. I'd love to hear you
speak more about how the vision
that seems to be emerging among
a number of people with de this
deep concern about our future
meshes with your the insight you
were given.
Chris Bache: Yeah, new Wayne is
a is a real brother in all of
this, and I've been deeply and
shaped or informed as I've
digested my own experiences by
his math. Methodical, combing
through all the ecological data
and the social data, looking at
our the converging forces in
history, through several of his
books, i I can only speak, or I
should only speak, out of my
visionary experience, because I
have, I have a certain
familiarity second hand through
people, authors like Dwayne and
other writers of our time in
history. But my sense of this is
really informed primarily by my
visionary experience. And so let
me stay just there. And again I
had this took place for me,
these visions took place going
back to 1990 through, 1995 96 so
I was very ecologically
uninformed 25 years ago, when
these took place, I was not
aware of the what's what's
happening culturally and
historically, as I have when I
first had the experience of the
death and rebirth of humanity.
It took me about a year to
recover from that experience,
and I felt like I was, as I say
in the book, I felt like I was
walking around Hiroshima a week
before the bomb was to be
dropped, knowing what was coming
with profound compassion and
deep respect for all Human
beings on the planet, knowing
that they had all volunteered to
participate in this grand
exercise, and at a deep soul
level, that they knew what was
coming, even though, at an egoic
level they may be did not know
what was coming. It took me a
year and a lot of work to
stabilize. And ever since that
time, through the early 90s,
I've held this, this knowing in
my body. I mean, it literally
lives in my body, what's
happening. And then as as I
become more informed by the
historians and by the ecologist
and the environmentalist, and we
really begin to see get a better
hand a grip on global climate
change and whatnot. It meshes,
it seems to mesh very well with
what the inner experience is,
with the variance that there are
some people who are serious
students of the data who believe
that we're not going to make it,
the data is just so strong that
we've already had our shot, and
even though we're living on
borrowed time and we will not
make it through this transition,
we are essentially extinct
already, and all I can say is
that, in my experience, that's
not what happens and and it's
it's not because the crunch
that's coming is not as bad as
we think it's going to be. It's
going to bring us to our
collective needs. It's going to
be worse than we are now, even
envisioning. It's going to just
break us down completely.
Roger Walsh: That's a very
painful and probably very
realistic vision. It sounds
like, at least from what I
understand, the data and and we
come through, we come through,
Chris Bache: we don't come
through, but a new we is born. I
believe that these historical
pressures that are building are
literally a birth. They are
truly giving birth, and that to
the future human. But then the
question is, well, what will
this future human look like,
what is actually being born in
history? What do we mean? Is
this just more of an analogy or
some what do we mean when we say
it's a birth? And the way I
understand this, I go back and I
look at it through
reincarnational lens. I mean,
you know that I believe that
reincarnation is a empirically
demonstrated fact of life. Ian
Stevenson and other scholars
have just demonstrated that
reincarnation is true. My first
book on life cycles was about
reincarnation the when I look at
the universe, I see I see our
planet pulsing in and out of
time and space, reincarnating
beings. I see us century by
Century, millennia by millennia,
beings reincarnating time and
time again in giving birth,
labor is very I mean gestation
is long. The. Labor and birth is
short and intense. I think the
human family has been gestating
the future human for hundreds of
1000s of years, we have been
just dating the future in the
dynamics of reincarnation. The
labor that is taking place, I
think, is a short, intense,
convulsive period. But what we
are giving birth to is already
foreshadowed on once we
understand the dynamics of
reincarnation, what is coming
forward, I think, truly, is the
consciousness which holds all of
our reincarnation experience as
a simultaneous present. This is
a consciousness that we all
contact. If everything goes
well, when we die, when we're
born, we're contracted to small
ego. When we die, we return to
the soul. When we're born, we
contract into another ego. When
we die, we return to the soul
that holds all of our memories,
not fragmented, but integrated
as a single being. If we keep
this up over and over, sooner or
later, the soul awakens inside
human incarnation. I think
that's the being that's being
born in this historical crisis.
Souls will live on this planet
differently than egos live on
this planet. I think all the
great spiritual leaders of the
Axial Age were all
foreshadowing, were giving us
teachings that were helping
bring this about. They were all
teaching us to think deep, to
look deep, to feel deep, and to
to allow the needs of others to
become super ordinate to our own
individual needs, but not
canceling out. They were
inviting us to live old, to live
wide. And I think now, just as
we are trying to become one
planet, ecologically,
politically, the world citizen
is emerging that is being
matched by something is taking
place inside us. So as the world
is trying to become one, we are
trying to become one soul
integrated within ourselves. And
I think we're going to make it
my experience, at least my
visionary experience, is while
nothing is nothing is decided,
nothing is determined,
predetermined. My experience is
that we make it but this is not
the end of the story. Of course,
this is simply the next stage of
human evolution. Human Evolution
is going to continue as long as
the universe is alive. So
whatever we're doing now, it
will be superseded eventually by
yet another stage of in our
development, in our spiritual
development, but this is a
particularly important stage
right now.
Roger Walsh: And Chris you in
one sentence, I think you you
elucidated a very important
point, a kind of pivot point for
this possible rebirth of the
human species. You said, Nothing
is predestined. It's up to us.
So that's a big statement.
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah, it, I
mean, if it's if everything were
predestined, there would be no
point to incarnating, right?
Because if everything had to be
the way it's got to be, then we
wouldn't be learning. And if
we're not learning, there would
be no adventure here. So it is
open ended. We could lose the
planet. We could lose this
opportunity. It's going to
require our very, very best and
our very deepest in order to
come through this changed and
built better.
Roger Walsh: So from that
perspective, then your vision
may not be one of this is the
way it's going to be. But
rather, here is the possibility
to which we can allow, we can
open ourselves.
Chris Bache: You know, yes, and
I have to acknowledge that. I
think this has happened. I think
there are some times when people
who nearly die part of their
life review, they have a life
preview, and sometimes what they
and they see of the future which
does come true, and sometimes
they see a future which they can
change. And I talk about this in
the book Ken rings work heading
toward omega. And so if they're
seeing a future that they can
change, they're seeing a
conditional future. Future, not
an absolute preset future. So I
think what you're saying is
true, that what I'm seeing is a
possible future, maybe even a
probable future, but a possible
future that we still have to
enact. So I say yes to that, and
I have to add a post script.
Some of my experiences have
taken me so far into the future,
into what I call deep time, not
eternity, but into time, but a
different modality of time, have
taken me into the into deep
time, and have given me an
experience of this historical
transition that humanity is
making, not as a future event,
but as a past event, as
something that We have
accomplished. So from that
perspective, from that deep,
cosmological expect perspective,
if I were speaking from that
voice, I would say, we will make
this transition. Nature knows
what it's doing. Nature has not
brought us here unprepared. The
genius of the universe that we
see in DNA and galaxies, the
genius that saturates every
piece of the universe knows what
it's doing when it brings us,
when it to this particular
critical turning point, we will
make it. We will become more
than we have ever been before.
Roger Walsh: Beautiful, may it
be so and and from my own
perspective, which is not having
had your visions, agnostic about
the whether we'll make it or
not, it seems like whatever
perspective we hold, the only
thing to do with our lives is to
do what you did, to offer them
in the service of human well
being and survival. Is that
congruent with your
Chris Bache: absolutely well?
It's going to take all of our,
our very, very best efforts to
move forward and to move forward
deeply and with a deep heart,
with an open mind, absolutely
all, all hands on deck.
Roger Walsh: Beautiful
John Dupuy: Chris, I get, I get
a feeling from you just, you
know, my hit as a man who's
heated the calls in his life.
You went and you became
educated, and you got all that
part squared away in your life,
so that later on, you'd be in a
position much better position to
share what you were called
again, to learn, and you had the
courage to keep it up, my God,
that is a miracle in itself,
over those 73 journeys and that
that you're also at peace with
yourself, because now you're
giving back This vision, you did
this work, and the work
continues in the sharing of it,
and that's a pretty good place
to be.
Chris Bache: Yes, it is a good
place to be. It's always a good
place to be when one comes to a
point in one's life where one
feels that one has done what was
asked to be done, and then the
rest is gravy. And now I'm in
the situation writing the book.
When I finished writing the
book, I knew that I could, I
could die at peace. That was the
closure of the project. Now I'm
in a new phase where I'm trying
to figure out how to make what I
did useful to other people. How
can I serve other people
carrying the knowledge or the
memories that I have? How can I
make it useful to people? And
I'm still figuring that out. I
don't I'm still trying to figure
out how I can be useful to other
people who are on their own
spiritual path, on their own
intellectual path, who are doing
things I can't imagine doing
wonderful things. How can I be
useful to them, to support them
in their process, as we enter
this time in history?
Roger Walsh: Beautiful and it
sounds like that's a question
that's really been with you and
challenging you and I. Want to
put it in a context, it seems
like there are two different
kinds of questions. There are
knowledge questions, is it
raining outside? Look outside?
No. In the question. There are
wisdom questions, which will
seem more like cons are
questions you can ask
repeatedly. Each time you do.
They take you deeper into the
question, deeper into yourself,
deeper into life. And sounds
like this is your your wisdom
question, or your sometimes
called your sacred question, is
now to the forefront in your
life.
Chris Bache: It is, and I know
that when I have the opportunity
to be with like minded spirits,
like minded beings. And we talk
about these things. I know that
something happens inside me,
that my shell is pretty thin
anyway, but something happens
and I get porous. And when I get
porous, a larger knowing flows
through me, works with me. I
become irrelevant, but the
teaching teaches itself in that
way, and that's that's really
why I wrote the living
classroom, because this was
happening in my classroom, I
never, ever was able. I never
talked about my psychedelic work
to my students. I didn't bring
it into the classroom. I built a
firewall between my spiritual
practice and my teaching work.
But I found that the deeper I
went into the consciousness of
the universe. In my spiritual
practice, the more it began to
activate students in my
classroom, the more there was an
unconscious transmission, an
activation taking place, which I
had to learn how to manage and
how to control, not control, but
how to manage in order to keep
everything safe for everybody in
the classroom. So I've learned
how that works. And I've learned
that when you throw a stone into
the lake, it naturally ripples
out entirely. And so everybody,
when we do steep, deep practice,
naturally. People around us are
going to be touched and are
going to be influenced. So I
know that when I when people's
questions take me to reflect
upon life in a way which is
informed by my experiences,
there is a gathering and a
reinforcing that takes place
between their psyches and my
psyche, and together we become
more and there is a transmission
that sometimes happens, and a
healing that sometimes happens
that no one is in control of,
and yet it seems to be the work.
Now, what's happened since the
book has come out, covetous has
shut down personal contact of
that sort, so that I've been in
a period of incubation, and
we're having lots of zoom
meetings, and basically I've
been incubating and trying to
see where this is going, see
where it wants to go. I'm about
to begin a seven week online
course on the book, which will
give us another opportunity to
push this a little bit farther.
How much can we actually give
this transmission online? I
would rather be doing it in
person, but right now, it's an
online world.
John Dupuy: Well, from where I'm
sitting, it feels like it works
Roger Walsh: pretty well. And
Chris, what's the name of the
course, so listeners can find
it.
Chris Bache: Well, it actually
hasn't been given a name yet.
This is on the shift network.
The shift network is producing
it. It's going to be on LSD in
the mind of the universe. But we
haven't settled on a name. It
might it may be called diamonds
from heaven. It may be called a
spiritual journey into the mind
and heart of the universe, but
it'll be on shift network
starting the middle of November,
and it starts November 30.
John Dupuy: Chris, do you find
that people are responding such
as it is, given the times that
we live in are, how's it going?
Are the books selling? Are your
people going, Oh my God. Have
you met any fellow travelers who
maybe had similar, you know,
experiences and note, I mean,
from my experiences, what you're
saying really corresponds and
deepens and fills out the. What
I've learned in my own journey,
in my own life. So how's it
going?
Chris Bache: It's going just as
you say, there's nothing unique
about my experiences. It's just
it's in a it's in a group of all
of our collective experiences
that pushes the boundaries in
certain ways. But I've had many
people write me and say, I you
know you've you've clarified
what my experience has been.
Here's what I've experienced
around this topic. And I've had
many people write and say, I've
never touched psychedelics in my
life, but I've had many
experiences that are completely
in alignment with your
experiences. Let me explain to
you my experience, and it's so
it's clearly, this is, this is a
large pattern that's coming up
within the collective psyche as
a whole, and it's been a joy.
It's a joy to share and then to
enter into conversation with
other journeyers. What's
important is not any one
person's experience. Clearly,
what's important is the in this
case, the psychedelic
experiences are the psychedelic
and spiritual experiences of the
entire human family. When we put
all of our experiences on the
table, then we can sort out
which ones are not essential, or
which ones are idiosyncratic,
and find the ones that are
universal and are more
epistemologically valuable. And
to do that, we have to put all
of our experiences on the table.
So for me, I'm simply putting my
experiences on the table in
dialog with other people as we
all put our experiences on the
table, and then we begin a
conversation of those
experiences. And I think we're
still in the early stages. I
mean, I think the book you
edited Roger of the early
psychedelic elders, you know
that work was putting a certain
generations insights on the
table, and I think it's
beginning again. The tricky part
right now for me, as people
absorb my work is the focus of
the psychedelic Renaissance is
psychedelic therapy, and that's
exactly where it should be,
healing the human psyche,
careful control studies, lots of
brain wave maps, you know, and
all that stuff. And very, very
careful control studies. And to
a certain degree, my work rocks
that boat, because it's, it's
doesn't follow that protocol. It
uses extreme doses, high doses,
it's using a very, very powerful
chemical which doesn't lend
itself to healing as much as
well as MDMA or a Psilocybin.
And so there's a certain
tension, I think, between the
therapeutic focus of the
present, very important work
being done, and in my work, and
yet, there is a huge underground
psychedelic community which is
not waited for a scientific
validation. And this community,
I think is been having a
conversation among itself for
many, many years. And I think my
work is being received very
well. Yeah, in that community,
Roger Walsh: beautiful, yes, and
and you spoke of, you know,
you're still exploring the next
question. You spoke of a period
of some years, I think, 20 years
of assimilating these
experiences. So, so it sounds
like the process, process of
integration, has been very long
and has had its own challenges,
and perhaps that's not a topic
that's given enough attention.
In spiritual circles, there's a
lot of focus on doing the
practices and opening the
particular states of
consciousness and insights, but
but not so much, perhaps, on the
very essential work of
integration, which is an
assimilation of the experiences
or reflection on them, or
recognizing their implications,
dialoguing about them in
community, anything which allows
us to come to a broader
understanding of their
implications and possibilities
and to and and their
implications for how best, how
Now should we live?
Chris Bache: Yes, yes. There is
a book that's just been
published called psychedelics
and psychotherapy that is a
collection really focuses on
this issue of integration. I
have an article in it, very
important. I think that we're
getting past the stage where the
excitement over being able to
break through to these
dimensions of consciousness is
kind of calming down, and we're
beginning to realize that the
real issue is, what do we do
with these experiences? How can
we hold them? How do we
integrate them? How do we
integrate them individually in
small community. And how do we
integrate them intellectually,
so that we shift the paradigm of
the reality that we're living
within that and of course,
psychedelic experiences support
the paradigm of a living
universe, that the universe is
not dead matter, but the entire
universe is alive. It supports
the paradigm of an intelligence,
orders and orders and orders of
intelligence that lie behind and
within physical existence. So
there's so many levels to it,
and I would offer my own
experiences, some of what not to
do. I mean, I'm deadly serious
when I say I think I pushed
myself harder than was wise at
the end, when I was this, the
chapter that was the hardest
chapter in the book to write was
the last chapter coming off the
mountain where I reflect upon
the years after I stopped my
sessions, took me a year just to
write that chapter. I thought I
paid a lot of attention to
integration throughout my work.
I wrote all my sessions down. I
did a lot of spiritual practice
throughout and even though I
couldn't teach this stuff, I had
it in conversation with my
partner at the time, and I
really I paid a lot of attention
to individual integration. I
wrote the living classroom to
reflect tell the story of how I
took care of my students who
were being touched by the work
so social integration. So I
thought that when I stopped
these sessions, I would be able
to step away and I would live
with the bounty of the
extraordinary gifts that I had
been given, and the most
important of which, which
emerged in the last five years
of the work we haven't talked
about yet, but the diamond
Luminosity sessions that those
particular immersions into
Dharmakaya the clear light of
absolute reality. But what I
found was that in the years
following. In five or six years
following my sessions, when I
stopped, I had entered what I
call the deep sadness. It was a
period of withdrawal into a
loneliness from not being able
to return to such ecstatic
experiences of being dissolved
into light, literally just into
light. I knew that I needed to
stop. I had for reasons I
touched. I knew it was important
for me to stop. I had to spend
years absorbing what I had. But
there was such an unfulfilled
longing to return to those
dimensions of reality that I
found I reached a point where I
realized I was just waiting to
die. I was taking care of my
children. I was taking care of
my students. I was not suicidal.
I was living a balanced life,
but in my heart, I was just
waiting to die, and I with more
time, I realized something's
wrong here. This is not the way
this work is supposed to end.
This is not I made a mistake.
Somewhere along the way, I made
a mistake, and I began to
wonder, is it possible to have
too much God? But I knew the
entire physical universe was
God. I knew that the Divine is
everything that exists. So it's
not a matter of having too much
God, because I knew God was I
was living inside God. So what
was the mistake? And eventually
I came to see that the mistake
was not too much divine of the
Divine, but it was too much
Transcendence. There is a
balancing act between
transcending time and space and
being embodied inside time and
space, and there are truths in
each of these realities. And I
had plunged myself so deeply
beyond time and space, so many
times into such intimacy with
that which supports time and
space that I lost my bearings, I
lost my foothold inside time and
space, and I had to, so I made
an absolute decision to ground
myself. Inside time and space,
and to let what I had
experienced in these subtle
states of consciousness, to let
it work its way into me, I had
to literally not alter my
consciousness so that these
states of awareness could enter
into my physical being. Whereas
previously it had entered into
my altered being, now it had, if
it was ever going to enter into
my physical body, I had to sit
still and let it come to me.
Because, as you know, in these
states, nothing in reality
changes. We don't do anything.
We simply wake up to something
that's always been there. It's
always been there. And I reached
a point where I simply had to
sort of be patient and let this
transformation take place. And
so in a sense, on the one hand,
there's nothing more for me to
do, and on another hand, yeah,
there's something more to me for
me to do.
Roger Walsh: Yeah. And you're
talking now about a very
interesting topic. You're
talking about the traps that can
go with this kind of deep work,
and usually we talk about traps
on the spiritual path or with
psychedelics. Similarly, we
usually talk about the earlier
paths, the traps of being
overwhelmed, of fear, of terror,
of acting out certain
psychodynamics of ego inflation,
taking these experiences to be
proof of our unique
Transpersonal nature and
specialness, and yet you're
pointing to some of the traps
that can occur significantly
further along. It sounds like
you're talking about about,
well, you one way of framing
what you just said, this deep
sadness or losses would, of
course, be, and you do this in
your book. I think the in terms
of the dark night of the soul of
St John of the Cross, the the
challenge that comes when we
taste something so
Transcendence, so divine, so
inspiring, and then lose that
contact in a way. And you're
talking about the some of the
traps that can come with the
sheer amount of energy coursing
through one's body and the and
the the possibility of
transmission as a result and and
and of being seduced by those
capacities. So, so this is a
very this is another kind of
gift you're giving us pointing
out, giving us the beginnings of
a map of the more advanced traps
that can come
Chris Bache: the traps that
happen when everything goes
right, deficiency, but when
everything goes right, you can
have too much of a good thing. I
found I didn't know that at the
beginning.
Roger Walsh: Is it too much, or
is it our attitude towards it?
Chris Bache: I think you can
have too much of a good thing in
the sense that I think in every
one lifetime, most of us, we can
only integrate so much and
productively, and I think it's
possible to bite off more than
we can really thoroughly chew.
And sometimes I think I bit off
more than I could, more than was
wise for me to chew. And but
you're all absolutely right.
There are so many pitfalls on
this path, ego inflation,
thinking you're special because
you've had a special experience,
and it's so important to stay
grounded, really grounded,
grounded, grounded, so that all
of these things wash through
you. And my wife was, was very
good at helping me remember,
always, always, what's important
is not what happens on the day
of your session. What's
important is what you can do the
day after your session. It's,
it's that you it is how you live
your life in the world, carrying
the insights that you've had as
best as you can into your
fallible life, and recommitting
yourself to purifying your life
of all of its all of its you
know, messy Garbage, and living
a clean and compassionate and
proper life that that continues
just because you become one with
God, what happens is, I don't
actually these days, I don't
know why anyone would want to
become one with God, because
once you do that, it triggers
enormous purification processes
that don't stop. Up. I mean,
it's just it goes on and on, you
know, it just deepens. Yeah,
there are lots of ways for this
path to go wrong,
Roger Walsh: and yet, there was
something which, in the in the
way you approach this, that
allowed you, I not there were
ways you got caught, but they
weren't the gross ways they
weren't you didn't harm others
you. But there were subtle ways
in which you get you've got
caught, such as the dark night
of the soul, but you always you
worked your way out of it. What
do you what do you attribute
that to?
Chris Bache: I contribute. I
attribute that to good company,
the people I was with my former
wife, Carol. We were married for
24 years. She is the mother of
all my children. She was my
sitter for all my sessions. She
never did a session herself. She
is a very serious varana
practitioner. She has since gone
on to complete her three year
retreat. So she's, she's a lama,
acknowledged as such, and she
was a great help keeping me
grounded during all these years
when I was, you know, going in
and out of the universe. My
teaching, just my children, kept
me grounded. Teaching kept me
grounded, but studying the great
masters, because the more I
studied the great masters, the
more it showed me my own
imperfections. It All. It showed
me what I was not by looking at
their greatness. And so I never,
I could never take myself. They
kept me honest with myself as I
went my students kept me honest
because, you know, I I had to
earn a living teaching at an
open enrollment University, and
I'm walking into a classroom
filled with people, many of them
who don't want to be there, and
I have to kind of trick them,
persuade them to be interested
in some of the things that we're
going to be studying here. It's
hard work. I was not teaching
graduate students. I was
teaching an open enrollment
University for people who are
going to college for the first
time. So it was just good, hard,
honest work that kind of kept me
focused and gave my body and my
mind time to absorb the enormity
of what came forward. But
eventually, eventually, the
second thing I deal with in that
chapter of coming off the
mountain is what I call the
sickness of silence, and that's
the isolation of doing
psychedelics in a psychedelic
phobic society where
psychedelics are illegal, where
you cannot, even if you can
share them in small groups, you
cannot share them
professionally. I'm a teacher,
I'm a public person. I could not
share my experiences psychedelic
I literally had to retire from
my work as a philosopher of
religion before I could begin my
real my deepest work as a
philosopher of religion. That's
the iron. Yeah, that, in fact, I
retired a little early,
precisely to give me enough time
to write this book, to do this
work, and as I began to to be
honest publicly in the writing
of the book, this boy, it took
me a long time. It took me
before I wrote the book. It
literally took me about three
years just to get myself into
the psychological position where
I was willing to let people this
deep into this part of my life,
and the only way I was able to
do that was to truly let go and
remind myself over and over
again these experiences were not
given to me for me. They were
never part of they were never
private. They were never given
to me for me. They were always
given to me to share, to help
the human community as a whole.
So by let taking myself out of
the picture and just sharing
visions without owning them in a
sense, or appropriating them,
they were never private visions
that made it easier for me to
release them and let them, let
them have their impact without
owning that impact myself,
Roger Walsh: and there was so
many experiences which brings up
a. Of another topic, and that is
if we look across the great
religious traditions and, of
course, other traditions as
well, which haven't had such a
major impact, we almost always
find a worldview and
understanding that there is some
final experience towards which
we are working, and we get that
final experience, and then it's,
you know, bliss and roses wasn't
exactly what you found. And
there aren't, it seems like
there was an endless opening
for, always, for the
possibilities that that you open
to, and there aren't, to my
limited knowledge, there aren't
a lot of examples of that. I
think the best, the best in our
own time. Maybe the teacher amid
or Almas is the pen name he
writes under, and his two most
recent books, runaway
realization and the alchemy of
transformation, he he spent
decades with profound study and
a kind of spiritual genius
opening to opening an enormous
number of states. And then he
built up this extraordinary,
sophisticated psycho spiritual
map of the progression of states
and ways of working with them.
And then recently, he stepped
off his own map and said, No,
there's nothing. Yeah, you can
see a progression and there's no
final goal. Every opening is
merely a port. Can be, can be,
merely a portal to another
opening, and it, and he has a
statement in there which
probably only a handful of
people on the planet could make.
He said, Yeah, I've been
enlightened many times, and
every time everyone someone
says, oh, that's the final
experience. But I always find
there's something more, and that
seems your experience.
Chris Bache: It is, I think, and
I think it's, it's particularly
the experience when you use,
mean, this is a path of
temporary immersion, the path of
temporary I mean, all of our
practices are temporary, but
this psychedelic path,
particularly is a temporary
path, and that's the
temporariness is what makes it
tricky. But I like you, I
thought I was doing this path in
order to get to an end state,
that there would be a goal I
know when I would reach it, it
would solve all my issues, or
because people describe as
becoming one with God, or
becoming dissolving into the
meta, cosmic void. And what I
found was that actually I became
one with God or one with mind of
the universe many times. And
there, there are many gradations
or many levels of oneness with
God, and there are even levels
of the primal void. There are
levels of void in the universe.
Eventually, there were many
levels of Homecoming, of
homecoming and peace and reunion
and just relaxing into the the
bliss of return. And when the
diamond Luminosity opened, 15
years into the work, when, when
the diamond Luminosity opened,
and I entered this hyper, hyper
Clear, clear, just unbelievably
clear. Level of awareness. And
in the next four years, I only
in 26 sessions. I only touched
this reality four times, lots of
purification, lots of cleansing,
lots of four times. The second
time I touched it was the 50th
session, and I was as deep into
the universe as I would ever go.
I was far beyond time and space.
I was dissolved completely into
this ecstasy of the pure
Luminosity. And then my visual
field pivoted 90 degrees, and I
saw reality far in the distance,
filled with a light, an even
greater light than the diamond
Luminosity, light, and a ray of
light hit me from that reality,
and it absolutely shattered me,
and took me 10 minutes to
recover from it. And that's when
I that's when it sunk in that
it's an infinite progression.
It. There isn't a matter of
coming to an ending spot. You
stop. You come to an ending stop
when you simply can take it no
longer. You can take the
ecstasy, no longer you can take
the cycle of death and rebirth,
no longer. It's an endless
progression. It's an endless
progression, and that's one of
the reasons I would be gentler
with myself if I were to do it
again, I recommend others. It's
not about reaching an end state.
It's about opening up, letting
all this wisdom in, letting the
beauty in, letting the healing
in, going through the
purification process and
becoming a little more alive, a
little more conscious and in the
dance of life, in the dance of
the universe, but it's not about
reaching any end state.
Roger Walsh: And you you had
that recognition there was
always more and and the always
more required something of you,
it required a another level of
purification, free for each
taste of that, something more.
And you just alluded to what you
called the diamond illumination,
which, in some ways, I mean, I
hesitate to put any, any
differential value on these
things, but in some ways, felt
like one of the most impactful
of all experiences that you had,
and something which left you, as
I recall, you said in the Book
that that for this you would
gladly die so and you relate the
you, what you called the diamond
illumination, to the experiences
described as the culmination
point in in some other
traditions. I just be lovely to
have you expand on on give us a
feel for this realization,
whatever extent you can, of
course, and for how it relates
to the goals of other
traditions.
Chris Bache: Well, as I
understand it, the reality that
I was taken into in those four
sessions is a reality that's
outside of the Bardo it is extra
Samsara reality. It's outside of
time space, and what I call the
echoes of time space, Bardo
reality, what happened in the
first two times I went into this
condition, I was taken deeper
and deeper into it. I had the
encounter with what I call the
absolute light, which showed me
that it's an infinite
progression. Then the next two
times I went into it, this
diamond Luminosity began to
crunch itself deeper and deeper
into my physical being. I wasn't
going out. It was coming in. So
it literally was crunching
itself into my psyche, into my
body. It felt like it was
changing me at a cellular level,
and eventually, at the very end
of my journey, it changed my my
perception had changed, my how I
see things, literally,
physically, how I can see
things, not permanently. It gave
me a temporary experience that I
call diamond vision. I was
seeing 100 1000 times more
sharply, more clearly than I
would have ever seen before. And
at that point, I realized that I
was seeing through the eyes of
the future human. I was seeing
in a way that all humanity will
one day see, that all of our
senses, sight, touch, taste, all
of our senses, are being
elevated and animated to higher
and higher levels, the more
consciousness we can internalize
in our body. So this crunching
into me is actually an
acceleration of something which
is taking place more slowly for
all of us in our reincarnation,
evolutionary reincarnation
process, and that's the message
I got at the end of my sessions,
was that one of the reasons I
had to stop my sessions was the
whole movement now was no longer
going out and into the whole
movement was the that which is
out, coming into me, coming in
deeper, deeper into me. And I
literally had to stop my
sessions in order to let this
process reach its end stage.
Reaches its natural conclusion
when I reflect on. On the
diamond Luminosity condition,
the parallel and I draw
parallels to the spiritual
traditions that I'm familiar
with, the ones that stand out.
Of course, all the spiritual
traditions speak about light.
All of the reincarnational
traditions speak about extra
Samsara, reality, the clearest
description I've I've come
across are in the Buddhist
traditions whose text I know the
best, and their description of
Dharmakaya, the clear light of
absolute reality, the clear
light which is the I
that which is the seed reality
out of which all existence
emerges, that which is the love,
out of which all emotion, all
love emerges, that which is the
pure, distilled power out of
which all energy of Creation
emerges in its absolute,
transcendent, hyper, clear,
clear, clear form, containing
everything within it and nucleus
and yet, something which is
beyond creation itself truly, I
understand why touching that
reality even once undoes
centuries of living in the
shadows of karma. Karmic vision
is always shadowed, and it's
always approximate. It's always
conditioned. But to touch
something which is so profoundly
unconditioned, and then slowly
the task, I think, is to slowly
shape one's life so that one can
live the conditioned existence
in abiding communion with that
which is unconditioned to live
the light in one's physical
manifestation, something I have
just getting started. I have so
much to learn in that process.
I'll never be able to, never be
able to conclude this during
this one lifetime. But my belief
is, what the universe seems to
have promised me, is that when I
die, I will return to that
condition, that there is nothing
I need to do between now and
when I die, to return to that
condition, and if I meet any
obstacles along the way, if
anything arises which would
prevent me from returning to
that essential truth, I have
learned how to dissolve those
obstacles by taking any
obstacles into me until
eventually they dissolve of
their own of their own weight.
Roger Walsh: What a wonderful
vision and and something which
clearly, even as you were
counted now, I could see you
going into your own experience
and being deeply, deeply touched
by it, even now, 2030, years
later. So it's an exquisite
example of the way in which
these experiences touched and
incarnated in and as you and
still have their resonance and
and and impact and transmission,
I felt palpably touched by by
the qualities of qualities that
that you were expressing out of
your in your description, given
out of your direct experience,
which felt partly out of your
direct experience in this moment
and a very exquisite
transmission. And you also spoke
of, once more, of the idea that
these awakenings, the
recognitions of these remarkable
realities, are not the end point
that that there's a that's a
stage. But beyond that is the
integration, the bringing it,
allowing it to incarnate in and
through us. And you pointed to
what you called the diamond
vision, and you mentioned that
the diamond illumination was
most resonant view with the
Tibetan Buddhist tradition. And
interestingly, the Tibetan
Buddhist tradition speaks
further of of a stage beyond
that which it feels like you're
illuminating of of pure
perception or recognition, in
which one's perception is so
transformed by this realization
that. One sees this world not as
some merely mundane material
reality, but as an expression of
that diamond illumination. One
sees sacred beings. One sees it
as what's called a pure a pure
land optimized for awakening,
and expressive of awakening. So
they call it the pure
perception. I'm not telling you
anything you don't know, of
course, but might be not. Might
be interesting for our listeners
to know that your description
not only of the awakening to the
diamond illumination, but its
very effects on you, something
that is recognized and highly
valued in certain traditions.
Yeah, truly,
Chris Bache: there is nothing
unique in any of my journey. In
any it, I'm simply rediscovering
things which many, many people
in many traditions have already
discovered that the technology
may be a little bit different,
but the core understanding of
existence, the core truths, the
core insights, have been with us
for a long, long time, embodied
by Great Beings, passed along
generation by generation by
Great Beings. There's really
nothing. There's nothing unique
in my work.
Roger Walsh: And you you open to
a two experiences that others
have opened to, and you had your
own unique constellation. And
you bring to it something which
is unique, your own gifts as a
philosopher and theologian. So.
So once again, it's the yes and
Chris Bache: something that the
mother told me at the end and
when I was really not sure what
to do with all of this and what
the mother, which for me, you
know, my my naming of the
Absolute, tends to run in the
feminine direction. I see myself
as a servant of the Great
Mother, and I see all physical
existence as the embodiment of
the Great Mother, and the
transcendent divine as more
male, and the embodied Divine is
more female. But what the mother
said was simply let them see me
as you have seen me. That's all
just let me. Let them see me as
you have seen me. They'll know
what to do with it. It will
serve them in ways that you
cannot anticipate. Just let them
see me. And she was very clear.
She said, You know, you didn't
give yourself these visions. You
didn't decide what visions you
were given on any particular day
you were not you did. Had no
control over when you were
broken and when you were
nourished. We did that. None of
this is of your doing. It was
all our doing, and you have no
right to hold on to any of it.
And I think this feeling is a
feeling that spiritual beings,
or people who have given
themselves over to intimacy with
the universe, have always felt
that their practice is not their
own, and the fruition of their
practice is not their own, and
they have no right to hold on to
their fruition of their
practice, because it's in the
very nature of the of the
awareness that the divine serves
all. The Divine is all and in
the end, it's the mother
speaking to her children. It's
the mother's love for all of her
children, and it's the mother's
desire to wake up all of her
children, which is the driving
force of it all.
Roger Walsh: And I was, I was
struck by your description then,
which echoed a theme in the
book, that when you when you
were portraying the
communications you receive from
very profound realms of
consciousness and being that you
did it as did it in the plural,
first person plural, we have
given you these gifts, and I
think it's reminded me very
much, as you pointed out, the
Quran, where Allah speaks as in
as we
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah. And I
don't think, I don't think it's
a plural, like a polytheism,
it's a plural, like, just vast.
I mean, just. Just unable to
wrap our minds around it so
enormous that that it swallows
our capacity to describe or to
concretize, and somehow we
speaks to that more effectively
than I. I think sometimes, no
matter how profound this our if
we were to take the greatest
spiritual geniuses of our
generation, and truly just the
great, great masters of our
generation, and if we could go
forward 500,000 years, or
however many 1000 years, we
would imagine, the great masters
of that generation will be able
to see more, will have deeper
experiences still, because there
is a certain sense in which the
experience of any individual is
kept within, in certain sense,
the capacity of the herd, they
push the edge, but they're
limited by the capacity the
collective psyche. But as the
collective psyche evolves, it
extends the limit of the
individual spiritual genius. So
it's it's an ongoing, ever
unfolding, ever progressive
deepening of this rapport
between the creative
intelligence and we who are the
result of that creative
intelligence.
Roger Walsh: Yes, and, and I'm
going to ask you to I'm going to
ask a question which is going
to, of course, impossible. We
need another few sessions, but,
but has to be asked. And that
is, after all these experiences,
these openings, these gifts and
graces, and ones which had very
dramatic impacts on your
understanding of yourself, why
you were doing this, the nature
of reality, which exploded your
understanding not once, but many
times. And that was one of the
things I found in the book and
even in our dialog now,
recognizing my own limiting
presuppositions such as, yeah,
you know, these chemicals are
good for psychotherapy and
healing on an individual level,
but no, you were forced to the
recognition, kicking and
screaming all the way I would
say, to a larger recognition
that this was potentially about
a healing of collective
consciousness and more and
always more. So obviously, in a
in a reality in which there's
always more, there can be no
definitive map. But how would
you describe to the extent you
can your understanding of the of
the nature reality, how would
would? How would you
characterize or point us towards
your worldview at this time?
Yeah,
Chris Bache: I'll do my best to
answer your question and to not
weep as I do so,
John Dupuy: go ahead and weep if
you need to.
Chris Bache: I see the universe
as a magnificent as the as as
pure genius, as saturated with
genius and saturated with with
the geniuses ambition, the
creative impulse, I see the
birth of stars and the birth of
galaxies and the birth of
planets and the birth of species
and the birth of an intelligent
a self aware species within some
of the planets and a
reincarnating species within
this Planet, all as acts of
profound genius, of just
unspeakable genius and and love,
because it is the sharing of
existence. It is the the
gestating of the conditions that
make infinite progression
possible. I see death and
rebirth. I see reincarnation. I
see the Bardo. I see this vision
that when we die, we don't
simply wink into this we go into
a very specific great, great
gradated series of levels of.
Existence that reflect our
limits and our capacities. I
used to think of the Bardo as
kind of the the the the enemy or
the opposition. It was a cloud
getting in the way. But now I'm
beginning I see it as the
compassionate blanket. It keeps
us safe as we enter into deeper
and deeper communion with the
true power. I will call it the
divine. I don't like to call it
the divine, though I use this
language sometimes, but because
our concepts of the Divine and
of God are so childlike, are so
childish compared to the reality
itself. But to become to touch
that power until we are fully
formed and capable of
withstanding the intensity of
that reunion, it would shatter
us. It would just absolutely
shatter us. We have to be very,
very strong and very congealed
as an individual before we can
touch that reality and stay
conscious and coherent within
the reality, that reality, and
that's just the level of reality
outside the Bardo of this
particular piece of time and
space. So I don't know what lies
beyond the Dharmakaya. I don't
know what lies in the absolute
dimension. But everywhere that I
have journeyed and everywhere I
have seen, there is genius
arising. There is purposeful
intent, not not an easy to
recognize purposeful intent,
sometimes a very, very hard,
complex, subtle, purposeful
intent. But it's there behind
everything. It's there. It's
always there. It's always
pressing for more and uplifting
us all. And in saying what I've
been saying, you know, I'm just
echoing, echoing the teachings
of the great spiritual lineages
of the great teachings. There's
nothing original in what I'm
saying. I'm simply echoing, not
what I've been taught, but I'm
echoing teachings that I have
seen elsewhere, that it's all
alive, It's all
and the depth of love that holds
existence is proportionate to
the depth of the genius that is
orchestrated existence that was
one of the hard things for me to
take in, that the genius I could
see, but the love that's
proportionate to that genius.
I've become much more bhakti in
this process than I had, than I
had ever thought that I would
be. It's just, it's just
impatient patient. Wake Up Now,
wake up in 100,000 years. Wake
up in a million years. It
doesn't really make that much
difference to the Creator,
because it doesn't think in the
short term. She thinks in the
long term. She thinks in the
long term, and she doesn't think
about individuals. She thinks
about all of us. She thinks
about the entire planet, the
entire galaxy, the magnitude of
as far as I've gotten in all of
this work, I've just touched the
edges. Just touch the edges.
Roger Walsh: Thank you so much,
Chris again, that was a true
transmission of the not only the
magnitude and the genius, but of
the heart. Like Words fail,
heart chattering, heart,
boundlessness of love that you
saw. And what is, what is
inspiring Is that is that, yes,
you, you keep saying in true
humility that there's nothing
new in what you saw, but the
fact that you did see it, that
you are reporting your own
experience, that this is direct
phenomenology, not some out of
some text out, but this is what
you found in your direct
experience. And it echoed.
Because the discoveries of the
great saints and sages
throughout human history, and it
also echoes the findings of
other deep explorers, which
which Stan Grof put together in
his book The cosmic game, where
he took the deepest insights of
the 1000 people he'd worked with
and welded them into a
synthesis, a a cosmology, an
ontology, a metaphysics, which
was remarkably similar to some
of the findings, the great
traditions, and I think was most
synchronous, most congruent of
all, with Kashmir Shaivism, the
very profound mysticism of
India. So yes, from one
perspective, we can say, yeah,
you just saw what's been
reported umpteen times. No big
deal. Why'd you waste your time
writing a book? On the other
hand, Thank you, Chris. This is
a new way, the fact that we have
a we have a an integrated report
of these truly trans, egoic,
Transpersonal, trans everything
openings from a different
modality is very affirming of
perennial wisdom and perennial
insights, so nothing is left
out.
John Dupuy: You include the all
somehow. And I was thinking,
it's like this guy's telling me
about the burning bush, and I
smell the smoke beautiful, and
holding on to your humility and
your your your humanity and
coming back and being a human
being, you know, is such a gift,
brother. Thank you so much.
Roger Walsh: Indeed, indeed,
there's, there's one more theme
I want to point bring back, or
actually just point out that's
been underlying so much of what
you've you've said, you've
talked about being guided, being
taken into, being offered, being
graced by an intelligence and
love far Beyond the passes all
understanding and and and what I
take from that is something that
resonates deeply from my own
much more mundane explorations
and from reading great
psychologists and therapists and
other psychedelic explorers. And
that is we live, usually, the
vast majority of humankind lives
at war with their own their own
minds, deeply distrusting of
their own psyches and
themselves. And yet, the deeper
we go, the more we discover what
you discovered, that we can
trust ourselves, that given,
when we open open as fully as we
can, we find that our minds are
not these malevolent cesspools
of pain and trauma and and
malevolence. Yes, there are
those, some of those elements
and bits we have to have to be
willing to face, but there's so
much more and that when treated
well, when treated well, our
minds are self healing, self
actualizing, self correcting,
self transcending, yeah, and
That's that leads to this
profound trust, both in
ourselves and in the greater
reality.
Chris Bache: Yes, absolutely,
you say it very well, self
correcting, self healing. We all
have knots. We're all born with
knots. We bring in garbage from
a previous lifetime, lots of
previous lifetimes, but when we
bring our awareness, when we
bring those knots into
awareness, they open, they untie
themselves. When we bring our
pain into awareness, it heals
itself, itself. It clarifies and
then, as as those shadows
lighter, as lightness, we get
clear and clear and relax them.
Then the genius of our being
shows itself more easily, more
strongly. And then the wonderful
discovery is that there is no
membrane, ultimately, no
absolute membrane between our
individual existence and the
existence of the universe itself
that we just drop right through.
And so the awareness that
bubbles up inside our individual
life and the awareness which is
bubble. Growing up around life
around us in totality and in my
neighbors, and in each other and
in the planet, it's the same
life. It's not a separate life.
So and that's when, you know, I
think when we begin to really
understand existence, then we
can relate to the beauty of the
universe and own it as a
reflection of our beauty,
because if we don't understand
reincarnation and we don't
understand how life works, we're
always going to be estranged
from the magnificence of a
beautiful sunrise and sunset or
the stars at night. But as we
get clearer, everything begins
to become simpler, more
transparent, and that's just as
you say, We're self healing,
self clarifying, self arising.
Roger Walsh: Wow, Chris, you've
given us such an incredible
gift, and I know that you are
very aware that this is not your
gift, and that you're you are
the instrument through which
this gift has come and that's
the aspiration with which you
entered this very intense,
decades long investigation, and
yet, all because of that, this
is an extraordinary transmission
you're offering unique, yes, re
esperannial discoveries, and yet
unique in its own form and time
and the capacity for
contextualizing within the best
of our contemporary knowledge
and understanding of the great
tradition. So it's a priceless,
just a priceless gift. And I
think John bowed to you before I
bow to you. We both, both bow
and and you, you'll let the bow
go through you.
Chris Bache: Gentlemen, I know
enough of each of your work to
know who I'm with here, and I
bow to you deeply because I know
that all of all three of us have
been working these fields for a
long time. All three of us have
been nurtured by the wisdom and
had been contributing to the
wisdom. So I the vow is
returned, brothers, truly, truly
is
Roger Walsh: thank you. And
that's the way it is in in the
spiritual traditions, one vows,
we bow to each other,
recognizing who, who we really
are. Chris, is there anything
you'd like to say that by way of
completion,
Chris Bache: first I'd like to
say thank you. I become more
whole. I become healed and more
whole when I get to speak about
these things, then I get to do
what I was designed to do. And
there are still not that many
places where I get to have the
conversation that you pulled for
me today, that we had together
today. So I want to say thank
you, and I'd like to add as a
footnote. If there were one gift
that I wish I could give people
straight out of my experiences
here, it would be the gift of
letting go of the fear of death,
just letting go of the fear of
death. If you're afraid of
death, you have life turned
upside down. This is where the
hard work is done. This is where
we do the really hard work.
Death is we have so many stupid
ideas about what happens to us
when we die. Death is the great
liberation. Death is even the
partial liberation. Is a great
liberation. Death is joy. Death
is return. Death is to return
again to the arms of the
Beloved. To be born is the
beginning of the hard cycle. To
die is the end of the hard
cycle, the beginning of the easy
part of the cycle.
Roger Walsh: That's that's a
wonderful flip on our
conventional understanding.
Chris, well, I'm just going to
repeat myself. What a gift. But
I want to, I want to close by
mentioning again your books, the
several dark, night, early dawn.
Subtitle steps to a deep ecology
of mind. You wrote about your
teaching experience and how to
how teaching can be a
transmission in the book for
living classroom. And most
recently, the and book we've
been primarily focusing on today
is the extraordinary book,
Ellen. LSD and the mind of the
universe. LSD and the mind of
the universe, and both John and
I, I don't think we can
recommend it highly enough.
We've both been inspired by it.
Chris, it's been a sheer delight
to be able to do this dialog and
these explorations with you.
Thank you so much for on our
behalf, and also on behalf of
all our listeners and all the
people who who you're touching
in so many ways. Deep gratitude.
Thank you so much. Thank you.
This has been deep
transformation, self, society,
spirit, talking with Chris
Bache, you you.