Unknown: Our program tonight was
brought to us by Heather
tishbein. She is a personal
friend of Chris's, and so I'm
going to ask her to introduce
him, Heather.
Heather Tischbein: Thank you,
Daddy. I'm just over flowing
with joy to be able to share my,
not really friendship, but my
acquaintanceship with Chris,
with my ions family. I met Chris
20 years ago through the
Holotropic Breathwork network,
and Stan Grof and I read his
book back then, dark night,
early dawn, Steps to a deep
ecology of the mind, and got to
participate with him in person
in a workshop. So that was 20
years ago, and when his new
book, LSD and the universe of
the mind was advertised on the
shift network with the seven
weeks seminar, I immediately
signed up for that and read the
book and participated in that
seven week program. In the
intervening 20 years, I had a
health crisis and spent a couple
days in in a coma off planet,
which I actually remember that
experience and what Chris
describes as kind of the over
the thematic energy of the mind
of the universe is exactly where
I was and what I experienced
when I was off planet and on
life Support. Chris's work has
had an impact on my life around
understanding who I am as a
human being on planet Earth, as
as both a part and the whole
simultaneously. And I can't even
put into the words the help it's
been in helping me coming
through, really resolving and
appreciating. I know this might
sound weird, but the gift of
early childhood sexual trauma
and but more importantly than
all of this deepening of
understanding has been my felt
experience of genuine comfort
around when in His presence and
and in the in the world view
that he puts forth in this
latest book, I just feel so much
love and comfort for Chris Bache
in the world. So it's with
immense gratitude that I welcome
Chris to my ions family here in
southwest Washington and beyond.
Chris Bache: Well, thank you
very much, Heather, and thank
you everybody for inviting me
here and letting me be spend
this time with you. So let's get
into it. We'll see where we go.
We have this topic we're looking
at today, the birth of the
future human is a huge topic, so
we're going to have to trim it a
little bit and shape it, but
we're going to dig into it. I'd
like to jump into it and see how
far we can actually go into the
center this issue. So first I'm
going to share my screen and
throw this PowerPoint up here.
Okay, all right, and this is
coming through for everybody.
All right. Well, it will come as
no surprise to anyone in this
group. Let me move this down
here, but we are a planet in
crisis. Everybody knows the list
of challenges that we are
currently facing. We are
confronting an escalating
climate crisis, growing droughts
and forest fires, more flooding
and stronger hurricanes. Our
reservoirs are drying up and
water tables are collapsing.
Rising sea levels, research is
now showing us that we have
already baked in by 2050, a 12
foot rise in the oceans, and we
know from projections what that
means in terms of changing club
flood, coast lines and eco
refugees. We are facing the
worst species extinction since
the extinction of the dinosaurs.
We're dealing with fist fished
out oceans. These extreme
economic inequality and unstable
interlocked national economies
and weapons so powerful we dare
not use them. We are, in
essence, world on fire. We are
entering a time of planetary
emergency. Is up here a little
bit. There we go, of planetary
emergency, and it's happening
much faster than we ever thought
it would even 10 years ago.
Umar hot
egg, a British economist, wrote
an essay recently, we're not
going to make it to 2050 in
which he says, quote,
skyrocketing inflation, growing
shortages, runaway temperatures,
killing heat, failing harvest,
shattered systems, continents on
fire and masses turning to
lunacy, theocracy and fascism As
a result, this is the condition
we find ourselves in today. What
I'd like to do is offer a
perspective on these events that
comes from my psychedelic
experiences reported in my book,
LSD, in the mind of the
universe. So first, I'd like to
give a short overview, to give a
context for the visionary
experiences that I'm going to be
sharing with you today. I'm
going to be touching on my
psychedelic work and the book,
LSD in the mind of the universe,
but I'm not going to go into it
in great detail, except for that
portion of the Book having to do
with the birth of the future
human, and you'll get a sense of
it from my initial comments. And
if you'd like to invite me back
for another time, we can spend
the time going into the overview
of the book more deeply. Let's
begin.
Yeah, here we go.
Should have thrown that up
earlier. All right, here we go.
Now. My work derives from Stan
grofs work, and these two books
changed the course of my life. I
finished graduate school in 1978
and read realms of the human
unconscious at that time, and my
life pivoted. I did the work
that I eventually did as a
philosopher, not a psychologist,
not a therapist. I was primarily
trained in philosophy of
religion, and was interested in
the philosophical potential of
psychedelics to explore the deep
structure of consciousness, and
through that, the deep structure
of the universe itself. Now in
his work, Stan differentiates
clearly two different types of
working, psychedelic therapy,
low dose psyche lytic therapy
and high dose psychedelic
therapy. Psychedelic therapy, as
it was practiced at Spring Grove
Hospital in Baltimore was
restricted to three sessions.
Here they were working with
terminally ill cancer patients,
and the focus was to try to
trigger something which
approximated a near death
episode, to help them with death
anxiety. They weren't trying to
heal them. They were trying to
help them with with the anxiety
that arose, arises when it's one
is facing death. So I thought,
Well, okay, if you can do high
dose work three times, you can
do it more than three times. And
what I ended up doing was 73
high dose LSD sessions between
1979 and 1999 and now this is a
very aggressive protocol. It's
not one that I would recommend
today, knowing what I know
today, I would do it
differently, where I starting
over again, but that's just what
I did. I did this work as
systematically and rigorously as
I could. I followed the same
protocol, and this is a
therapeutic focus. I was always
lying down with eye shades, with
a sitter. I use the same
substance, the same dose level,
the same set and setting, same
sitter, same recording process,
even the same location. All of
these variables can influence
one's experiences in
Non-ordinary states. So it was a
very stable position from which
to engage in the dialog with the
universe and communion with the
universe. I saw myself at the
time simply doing an extended
course of psychedelic therapy,
but when I got to the end of
this work and was looking back
over it as a whole, I realized
that there was something
different going on than was
described in the early
literature on psychedelic
therapy. This the protocol may
be the same, but when you
extend. The number of sessions,
as many as I did, it really
unfolds into different
challenges and gives you
different opportunities to
engage the universe. So I gave
my work a different name, and I
call it psychedelic exploration.
The protocol is psychedelic
therapy. All internalized
sessions, all working with
supportive music, so on, so
forth. The difference is the
number of sessions. In my case,
73 sessions. Now let me clarify
further. Just I think it's
important to differentiate,
especially since there are many
different uses of psychedelics,
let me just mention three of
them. The first is the
therapeutic the use of
psychedelics for therapeutic
healing, which is, of course,
our current focus in the
psychedelic Renaissance taking
place. Now. Second to that is
using psychedelics for spiritual
awakening, not quite the same as
therapeutic healing, but
somewhat different. And this is
actually why I initially got
into this work. Was to
accelerate what I thought of as
my individual spiritual
enlightenment, but the protocol
I adopted was so powerful that
it really took me beyond healing
and beyond spiritual awakening
into a process that I would
describe as cosmic, logical
exploration. I did this work to
explore the deep structure of
the cosmos itself. I did this
work as a philosopher. I
wouldn't do it the same way if I
were doing it again, and I do
not advise people to do what I
did. But I came through it. I
survived it reasonably intact.
And now I'd like to share some
of the results from this work. I
kept very careful, detailed
records of my sessions, always
within 24 hours of every
session. And I'd like to give a
little bit of context for the
visions that I'll be sharing.
When you do this work, you go
through a Death-Rebirth process
that everybody is familiar with.
The first one is, is ego death.
And this line here represents
the the horizontal line
represents the line between
physical matter and spiritual
reality are between ordinary
consciousness and Transpersonal
consciousness. And the open line
represents the vast expanse it
opens to us in Non-ordinary
states of consciousness, and the
drop at the bottom of the line
represents our individual egoic
awareness. And that first
circle, that red circle,
represents the Death-Rebirth
process that takes place in
psychedelic work, egoic death
and any spiritual practice where
one is transitioning one opens
one's consciousness beyond our
individual ego into the vast
expanse that lies beyond
individual awareness. Now Ego
Death catches most of the
attention in the literature
today, but what I found in my
work is that if you work
consistently with a very
powerful methodology like I did,
you go through not one death,
but many deaths. As one goes
deeper and deeper into the
universe, one comes to a series
of thresholds, a series of
gateways, where one must go
through yet another death in
order to enter into this deeper
level of existence. And it isn't
simply a repetition of ego
death. It's really different, a
different kind of death that
reflects the different levels of
reality. One is working at Stan.
Differentiation is writing
between psychic levels of
Transpersonal experience, subtle
levels and causal levels. And
I'm going to use that language.
I use that language in my book,
but I don't have any vested
interest in any particular
cosmology or cosmic logical
ladder. It's the principle that
is important that the universe
has many levels, and as one
enters into those levels
systematic, if you do it
systematically, there is a
gradual unfolding level by level
as one goes deeper into the
universe and into these states
of consciousness, at least,
that's how it manifested in my
work. It doesn't necessarily
have to be that way for
everybody, but that's the way it
manifested for me. Now, when I
got to the end of my work and
was beginning to crunch all of
my experiences and beginning to
prepare for the writing that I
did, on the basis of those
experiences, I differentiated
five fundamental levels or
categories of experience, or
levels of kind. Consciousness
that my work unfolded into. The
first was one's personal mind,
one's personal unconscious. The
second is the species mind, or
the collective unconscious. The
third is archetypal mind,
the fourth causal oneness
and the fifth diamond
Luminosity. And let me just very
quickly go through and place the
chapters of my book in that
context. Just to give you a
context for what we're talking
about, there's a chapter on
crossing the boundaries death,
which is basically telling the
story of crossing what Stan Grof
calls the perennial level of
consciousness. It 10 sessions
and two and a half years of work
on the species mind. There is a
chapter called the ocean of
suffering, and a chapter called
deep time in the soul. And it
took me a total of about four
years to get to this point in my
work, and at that point, I
stopped my work for six years
for reasons that I give in the
book, and I resumed it six years
later, and when I did the
purification part of my session,
which was the ocean of
suffering, began exactly where
it had stopped six years
previous. And I won't go into I
can't explain all of this in
detail, but the ocean of
suffering was opening up to vast
territories of collective pain
and anguish, which I first
thought of as a deepening of ego
death, but I later came to
understand that I was tapping
into or that something was
guiding in me, in my sessions,
to tap into the memories of our
collective suffering that our
species still stores in the
collective psyche, anything
which is not integrated at the
end of an individual life gets
stored at the level of the
collective psyche. And the
patient in this work had become
not just me, but the patient had
expanded to become, in some way,
the entire species of my family.
When I resumed my work after the
six year hiatus, the ocean of
suffering began exactly where it
had stopped, but in the ecstatic
portion of my sessions, I
entered a series of initiatory
experiences where I was taken by
the universe and given a series
of cosmic logical initiations.
It was like cosmology, 101,
teaching me how the universe is
organized and structured in
certain ways. Eventually, this
work came to a culmination. I
went through yet another death
and rebirth process and entered
what I came to call archetype of
mind, the greater real in the
chapter, the greater real,
archetypal reality. And here I
talk about the quasi platonic
level of archetypal
consciousness and the quasi Jung
Ian level. And I say quasi
platonic because it was it
affirmed Plato's core insight,
that there was a reality behind
the reality of time and space
which ordered time and space.
But I did not experience
archetypes the way Plato
experienced them. I did not
experience them as eternal ideas
in the mind of an unchanging
God, but I experienced them as
vast, living, dynamic, cosmic,
logical process, processes that
were so large I could not wrap
my mind around them. At the
quasi Jung Ian level, I
experienced repeatedly
dissolving into the species
mind, and I was given repeated
instructions on how the
collective unconscious, or how
the species mind functions as an
integrated whole, that all of
our individual minds are wired
into this vast collective mind,
and our individual psychological
issues and even our physical
diseases are part of the
psychological stresses and
strains and even the diseases of
our entire species, and that our
individual healing directly
contributes, both physically and
psychologically To the healing
of our species. Then this work
culminated, after 18 months,
into yet another death and
rebirth process which took me
into causal oneness, which I
describe in a chapter called a
benediction of blessings, where
I was given a year of extra
ordinary life. Blessings of
oneness, of non dual
consciousness, of Shunyata
dissolving into the meta cosmic
void, experiences of profound
cosmic love. It was truly
totally existentially life,
satisfying time. And then I
entered into the five years, the
last five years of my work, the
diamond Luminosity work,
described in the chapter the
diamond Luminosity here, I
entered beyond the collective
psyche beyond even the oneness
of existence into a super,
rarefied celestial domain of
exquisite diamond light. Now, I
had known light many times up to
this point, but this was a
higher order of light than I had
ever encountered before. All
right, I'll just stop there. And
and then I came into the final
piece of work, the final year of
work, the final vision, which
then led to the last chapter.
Whoop. Let me back up the last
chapter, chapter 12, coming off
the mountain. Now, you see, I've
skipped a chapter here, and
that's the chapter I really want
to focus on today, the birth of
the future human. I really wish
I had written this in a
different order. The order
should be a benediction of
blessings, and then the diamond
Luminosity, and then the birth
of the future human, followed by
the final vision. But, ah, well,
this is the order in which I
wrote it. In the birth of the I
summarize a series of visions,
experiences that I was given
over many years. In the work, I
kind of pulled them all out of
different sessions and
consolidated them into this
particular story, the birth of
the future human. All of those
sessions that are summarized in
this chapter actually began as
far back as the initiation into
the universe, material and so on
and so forth. But I really focus
them the story of her simplicity
in this particular chapter. So
what I'd like to do now is focus
on this theme of the birth of
the future human. And there are
three components, two of them
we're going to focus on today.
The first one is a series of
visions that I call vision of
awakening. It's a series of
visions that I was given between
1991 and 1994 so you can see how
long ago this was. This goes
back over 30 years, visions of
where humanity was in its
evolutionary development. This
was followed by a major session
that I call the Great Awakening
session, which took place in
1995 which was then later
followed by the final vision
that that occurred in the 70th
session, very near the end of my
20 year journey. So what I want
to focus on today is the visions
of awakening and the Great
Awakening. So first, the visions
paper over the course of my work
dropped into my session.
Scattered throughout my sessions
was a series of visions that
kept coming back to this theme
of human evolution. Kept
describing the city a situation
that humanity was entering and a
turning point that humanity was
coming to in its evolutionary
destiny. And I organized these
visions into a series of six
visions, which I give these
names, the visions of divine
love, all humanity, guiding
intelligence, our species as a
single being, collective
purification
and the future human.
So what I'd like to do is just
go back first and read you some
excerpts from these visions. And
I can talk about these visions,
but I think it might be maybe a
deeper way to transmit the
content of these experiences by
actually sort of sharing some of
the visionary material
themselves. And I invite you to
enter into a receptive state.
State, you're welcome to close
your eyes, a receptive state
where you can hear what I'm
going to be sharing with you
from a deeper than simply
rational place in your
consciousness. Now I should tell
you that my sense is what I'm
doing with you is reminding you
of something that you already
know. What's it's not important
that I had these visions. If
these are significant, it's
because of what they tell us
about humanity and what they
tell us about all of us and all
of the work that we are doing as
we incarnate in this generation.
So first divine love in this
session, which dates back to
1991 I was taken back to the
beginning of creation and their
experienced evolution in the
context of a larger cosmic
agenda. Suddenly, I was
overwhelmed by the most
extraordinary cosmic love, a
love unlike anything I had ever
known. To awaken to this love
was to remember a primordial
decision that I had somehow
participated in. In fact, I came
to understand that all of us had
voluntarily chosen to be part of
the evolutionary process of
creation in response to this
divine love, I then experienced
all the suffering that humanity
had endured throughout history
as taking place inside this
love, I realized that all the
suffering inherent in evolution
was noble beyond words, it was
all part of a cosmic plan that
we had entered into voluntarily
along the Way, and even we had
entered into freely, however
unconscious of this fact we had
become along the way, nobility
of great suffering, voluntarily
shouldered in the name of Divine
Love, suffering that would
stretch across millions of
years, suffering that would
become so inscrutable that it
would be used as evidence that
the universe was devoid of
compassion. This was the
nobility of humanity's gift to
the creative intelligence of the
universe. All of the suffering
that humanity had endured and
will endure in the decades
ahead, you're part of a
conscious
there are no victims here.
Second theme of all humanity,
the quote from the session,
the great difficulty I have is
describing the enormity of what
is being birthed. The true focus
of this creative process is not
individuals, but all humanity.
It is actually trying to awaken
the entire species out of the
seething desires of history, out
of the violent conflicts and
scheming of individuals and
nations, there was now driving
forward a new awareness in human
consciousness. Its birth in us
is no less difficult or violent
than the birth of a new
continent. It drives upward from
the floor of our being,
requiring a transposition of
everything that has gone before
in order to make room for its
new organizational patterns.
What is emerging in history is a
consciousness of unprecedented
proportions, the entire human
family, integrated in a unified
field of awareness, the species
reconnected with its fundamental
nature. Our thoughts tuned to
Source consciousness. The scale
of what I was witnessing took my
breath away. The third set of
visions. I saw humanity climbing
out of a steep valley, and just
ahead on the other side of the
mountain was a brilliant, sun
drenched world that was about to
break over us. The timeframe was
enormous, and I should mention,
perhaps it should have mentioned
sooner that time became very
porous in my work. First time
opened up in terms of my
personal life, but then time
opened up in terms of our
species life. I. Planetary life
and the life of the cosmos
itself. So I was regularly taken
into vast, trans temporal
landscapes. After millions of
years of struggle and ascent, we
were poised on the brink of a
sunrise that would forever
change the condition of life on
this planet, all current
structures would quickly become
irrelevant. All truths would
quickly be rendered passe.
Truly, a new epoch was dawning.
The lives of everyone living in
this pivotal time in history
were helping to bring this
global shift about as I
witnessed this scene, I saw
that, though we did not know the
deep future at a personal level,
there was a more encompassing
level of consciousness that
could see it very Clearly. This
was a deeply moving and
clarifying experience,
individually, we humans could
not see what was coming, and so
did not understand why things
are the way they are, yet
isolated from the future the
present makes absolutely no
sense to be ignorant of what is
being built would be to be
fundamentally blind, and our
species is not blind. There is
an intelligence in it, preparing
us, guiding us, an intelligence
that knows the future and is
preparing us for it as
systematically as we prepare our
homes for the changes of
seasons, next our species, as a
single being, I was taken deeper
into the unified field of
existence and experienced the
dynamics of humanity's awakening
as movements being initiated and
orchestrated by a single
integrating intelligence. I
experienced the evolution of our
species at the systematic growth
of a single organism, a unified
being that all of us were part
of the subtlety of the
cooperation of the parts with
the whole was extra ordinary to
experience the incredible
diversity of our species as a
single unified field made many
events clear. New patterns
sprang into view, and the
patterns made transparent sense.
Nothing in our theological or
philosophical systems does
justice to the facts. What I
then saw was that the unified
field of humanity was moving
decisively and precipitously to
become more aware of itself.
Whereas previously it had
existed in an essence, in as an
extended fabric, largely
unconscious of itself. Now it
was waking itself up visually.
This took the form of energy
coming together in Swift,
contractive spasms that created
bright flashes of awareness. I
repeatedly saw extended webs of
energy suddenly contract and
explode in brilliant flashes. In
the past, these flashes had been
swallowed by the inertia of the
collective psyche and had not
endured now, however, the
flashes were beginning to hold
their own and to connect with
each other, with other flashes
occurring around the planet.
The visions address collective
purification, which I think is a
particularly important concept
in order to understand what's
happening in history, in this
century, when an organism is
called on from within to become
more conscious, it must first
cleanse itself of the
psychological byproducts of
living at its lower level of
awareness. It was bring forward
the residue of its past and
purge that residue from its
system in order to lay the
foundation for a more refined
level of operation. Our system,
our species, was doing this in a
wholesale manner and with great
determination, by crystallizing
within itself generations that
embodied our toxic legacy. It
was the coordinated exercise of
the self evolution of the
species as a whole. The poisons
of humanity's past were being
brought to the surface in us,
and by transforming these
poisons in our individual lives,
we were making it possible for
divine awareness to enter more
deeply into future generations.
We had volunteered for this role
for both our personal good and
the collective good. I saw that
this century formed a watershed
into which the karmic streams of
history were flowing, and that
as the process came to fruition,
the future condition of our
species would be beyond anything
that we might project from our
current state of fragmentation.
The present form of humanity is
transitional. As Sri Aurobindo
said, we are cells in a super
organism intent on rapid change
our very constitution, the form
of our species is a stage in a
larger evolutionary journey.
Lastly, the future human. At one
point, I was given a brief
experience of the future human
we are becoming. I was carried
deep into the distant future and
allowed to experience what will
be the abiding state of humanity
at that time, what a magnificent
being. Just touching it filled
me with rapture, calm and sheer
delight. It felt clear, warm and
whole. There was an abiding
sense of oneness that was deeper
than just the feeling of being
interconnected. It was a feeling
of being truly one underneath
the diversity of life, such
expansiveness, such breath of
being. It was spiritually
embodied realization, the
tantric awakening of our entire
species, spirit and matter in
perfect balance. This
penetrating glimpse transfixed
me. Its beauty, grandeur and
simplicity pierced my heart, the
net result of all of these
experiences was to give me a
deep understanding of the
challenge that humanity was
entering, the challenging period
of history that we were ending,
and what was going on underneath
the surface of historical
events. And it focused me on the
question, how can the entire
species be awakened, as I've
seen, what would it actually
take for the whole of humanity
to make this quantum jump in
awareness? I had been shown over
and over again in many different
forms, that this was the project
of history at this point, but
nowhere was I shown how it would
be accomplished.
At this point,
I entered into the diamond
Luminosity work, where about
once a year, once every five
sessions or so, I entered into a
deep state of mystical
absorption into the crystalline
body of the Divine. I had
entered into two such
experiences in the 40th and 45th
sessions, and I was expecting in
the next session, the 55th
session, to enter into the
diamond Luminosity. Again,
instead, that's that's not what
happened. Instead, in 1995 as my
family and I were preparing for
the Christmas holidays, I had
experience of in a session in
that I came to call the Great
Awakening session. I experienced
what I'm going to describe, not
as an individual, but as the
entire species. I had been
dissolved into the collective
unconscious so many times and at
so many different levels, and
all of that seemed to be
preparation for what unfolded
itself in this session. This
session was so deep and so
challenging and so difficult to
navigate that it really took
years for me to assimilate it
fully into my life.
I was dissolved.
Into the collective psyche, and
I experienced what humanity as a
whole would experience in the
decades ahead. So let me share
with you the core scenario
pulled out of this visionary
experience in a field of
relative calm, a small anxiety
began to grow. Slowly, people
were looking up and becoming
alarmed. Humanity was gradually
waking up in alarm to events
that had overtaken it.
Conditions got worse and worse.
People became more and more
frightened as the danger
increased, forcing them to let
go of their assumptions. At
deeper and deeper levels, there
was less and less people for
people to hold on to, fewer
Givens that they could assume,
how they would live, where they
would live, what they would do
for a living, how society was
organized, what could be
possessed. The world as they
knew it was falling away.
Decades were compressed into
minutes, and I felt the people's
fear deepen as they had more, as
they lost more and more of what
they had considered the normal
and necessary structures of
their world, step by step,
events were forcing a rapid
reassessment of everything in
their lives. The events that had
overtaken earth were of such
scope that no one could insulate
themselves from them. The level
of alarm grew in the species
field, until eventually,
everyone was forced into the
melting pot of mere survival. We
were all in this together.
Families were torn apart,
parents from children, their
children and children from each
other. Life as we had known, it
was shattered at the core. We
were reduced to simply trying to
survive. For a time, it looked
as though we would all be
killed. But just when the storm
was at its peak, the worst of it
passed, and the danger slowly
subsided. Though many had died,
many were still alive. As the
survivors began to find each
other, new social units began to
form. Parents and children from
different families joined to
form new types of families
everywhere, new social
institutions sprang into being
that reflected our new reality,
new ways of thinking, new values
that we had discovered within
ourselves during the crisis.
Every aspect of our lives was
marked by new priorities, new
perceptions of the good, new
truths these new social forms
reflected new states of
awareness that seemed to spread
through the survivors like a
positive contagion. These new
social forms then fed back into
the system to elicit still newer
sites, states of awareness in
people and the cycle of
creativity between the
individual and the group
spiraled the entire system was
becoming alive at new levels,
and this aliveness was
expressing itself in previously
impossible ways. It was as if
the Eco crisis had triggered the
myelinization of nerve cells in
our species brain, allowing new
and deeper levels of self
awareness to spring into being
repeatedly. There was the
message, these things will
happen faster than anyone can
anticipate because of the hyper
arousal of the species mind,
1000s of fractal images drove
this lesson home again and again
faster than anyone can
anticipate. The pace of the past
was irrelevant to the pace of
the future and
my visions did not give me any
details about how or when this
would take place, except that we
were entering a profound global
systems crisis that was being
triggered by a series of of
ecological crises around the
planet, and this was of a scale
and a magnitude that was
historically unprecedented. I
was also shown many teachings
that I won't go into now, but
are in dark net, early dawn, and
in LSD, in the mind of the.
Universe. That point that showed
me, gave me insights into the
dynamics of the collective
psyche, that basically, the
suffering that we were entering
into was so widespread and so
profound that it would impact
not just individuals, but it
would actually reach through the
lives of the individuals to
impact the collective
unconscious itself, and it would
drive the collective psyche into
what a scientist might call non
linear conditions. And just as
physical systems, when they are
driven into non linear
conditions, can do remarkable
things, seemingly impossible
things. Likewise, the human
psyche, the collective psyche,
when driven into non linear
conditions, hyper aroused by the
suffering of its people. In that
condition, it was capable of
doing previously impossible
things. In this respect, the
suffering that we are entering
into, and it's certainly not
punishment, and it's not a sign
of failure, but it's actually
instrumental in helping us let
go of the past and let go of our
narrow, petty, egoic history and
enter into A deeper communion
with the creative process of the
universe. Now this brings me to
the next question of, what form
will the future human take?
Because I think we are going
through a transformation which
is so deep, it's not simply a
civilizational turning point,
and it's not simply a
destruction and rebirth of our
economy and our industrial
culture to a greener planet and
a greener culture and a greener
body politic. It is a
transformation which is actually
reaching deep into the
fundamental substructure of the
human psyche. The crisis we are
entering is a crisis of
consciousness. In that respect,
it's an evolutionary
consciousness, because we can no
longer afford the luxury of a
planet which is being run by
egos with this sense of separate
private our separate private
existences, even well
intentioned egos, we need to
grow into a deeper, more mature
sense of self for this planet,
in my Understanding, my context
for understanding the future
human is reincarnation. Now, my
first book life cycles was about
reincarnation. I considered an
absolutely fundamental concept,
and I think it's a concept which
we have ample empirical evidence
to document. I think that the
issue of reincarnation has, over
the last 50 years, moved from a
speculative theological table to
an empirical psychological
table. I think Ian Stevenson and
other researchers have given us
a vast quantity of evidence that
should convince any clear
thinking, critical person that
reincarnation is a fact of life.
But in the course of my
sessions, I was given an
understanding of reincarnation
that seemed to go beyond the way
that idea is presented in the
Eastern and even Western
mystical traditions,
classically, reincarnation is
presented as a an individual
form of individual evolution,
where we make choices, we
inherit the consequences of
those choices. We grow
incrementally, step by step,
becoming more compassionate,
more respectful, more
intelligent over long, long
periods and 1000s of lifetimes,
but eventually mature into a
spiritual awakening. We come
into a spiritual awakening where
we make contact with we resume a
deep experience of our inner,
divine nature, and at that
point, we can leave time and
space. The Hindu term for this
experience was moksha, escape,
escape, not only from ego, but
escape from time and space
itself. In Buddhism, Nirvana is
followed at death by the deeper
state of pari Nirvana, final
Nirvana, which is carrying on
beyond a type of enlightenment
that goes beyond physical
existence. All of the cosmology
of the last 5000 years, and both
Western and Eastern traditions,
have been basically what I would
call up and out cosmology, the
goal. Goal is to achieve some
type of fundamental transition,
either salvation or
enlightenment, so that when you
die, you can leave time and
space behind. But that leaves,
of course, unanswered the
question, what is the purpose of
space and time to begin with?
What does creative intelligence,
when, before the creative
intelligence manifested space
and time. What? What was it
thinking? Why did it do so? What
is the purpose of space, time
itself, the understanding of
reincarnation and the experience
of reincarnation that developed
in my sessions basically
outlined a different trajectory.
There was one particular session
where and I had done, I had done
past life therapy, and I was
familiar with the number of my
previous lives, and I had worked
in healing them, and I had
written life cycles 20 years
before, but I came into a
session where suddenly all my
former lives began to come into
me and to begin to wrap
themselves around me. It was
like wrapping a filament of
white light around a kite spool,
until eventually all of those
lives fused into one, and when
they fused into one, a brilliant
diamond light exploded from my
chest, and I was catapulted into
a state of consciousness far
beyond anything that I had ever
experienced before. Up to that
time, I was both an individual,
but I was an individual within a
frame of within a context and a
frame of consciousness beyond
anything that I had ever known
previously. And I came to call
this the birth of the diamond
soul. And I think this is the
fundamental trajectory of human
evolution that we have been
incarnating for 1000s and 1000s
and hundreds of 1000s of years.
We and in this evolutionary
process, we have been growing
and growing and growing, and we
are coming to a point where the
next step in our evolutionary
development is not simply taking
one more evolutionary step in
this long evolutionary
progression. But actually is a a
fusion, a coming into an
integrating, first healing and
then integrating all of our
former lives into a single
consciousness, a consciousness
that we can call the soul, the
consciousness. I think we return
to soul consciousness after we
die, after incarnation, we
expand into the soul. We
contract into egoic awareness.
We expand into the soul. We
contract. And if we keep this up
over and over again, 1000s and
1000s of years, eventually,
sooner or later, the soul, the
large consciousness that holds
all of our experience, awakens
inside time and space. And when
the soul awakens inside time and
space, heaven is born on earth,
and there is no felt need to go
elsewhere. I think all of the up
and out cosmiclogies are
basically incomplete.
Cosmiclogies That made sense in
the time in the context in which
they were born, but I think they
are an incomplete vision of what
the project of existence is
young souls become old souls.
Old Souls eventually become
complete souls, and that's what
I think of as the birth of the
diamond soul. Now many people
have had these visions. They
have had this understanding.
They use different words to
describe it. Some people talk
about Homo noeticus, homo
luminous, homo spiritualis. But
there are so many people who
have this deep intuition that we
are on the cusp of a major
transition in the human story.
And I think this transition is
literally the birth of the
diamond soul inside history. And
this is taking place not just
for individuals, not just with
individuals, but it's taking
place for the entire species. We
are in the process of giving
birth to a new species on this
planet, and the nature of this
species is implicit in the
history that we have, that we
bring to this event in order to
solve the crisis that we are
entering into in history, we. We
desperately need to grow up as a
species. In this context, from a
reincarnational perspective,
growing up means owning and
integrating the larger
consciousness that has been
gestating within us for 1000s of
years, owning it, seeing the
world through its eyes, and
letting its accumulated wisdom
shape our choices. The soul
lives in history differently
than the ego. The soul knows
that its relationship with this
planet extends beyond the limits
of its present life. It knows
that the earth we leave behind
is that the is the earth we will
inherit in our next incarnation.
It knows this, and it acts
accordingly. So to summarize,
the core vision that came
through my sessions, humanity, I
think, is coming into a time of
profound transformation, a time
of planetary compression and
accelerated development, a deep
shift in the collective
unconsciousness of our species
is taking place, a shift in the
archetypal blueprint of
humanity, a shift that's taking
place Literally, kind of in the
it's a plate tectonic shift in
the collective psyche. And one
way of describing this is a it
is a profound awakening into the
truth of oneness, but not an
awakening that dissolves the
individual, but awakening that
liberates the individual into a
deeper and higher sense of
participation in not only the
human community, but also into
the Celestial community. For
there to be a great awakening
like this, there must first take
place a great death, and this
death is all about purification.
It's all about letting go,
healing and letting go of all
the terrible things that we've
done to each other, for all the
attitudes that have divided
oneness, and all the the hatreds
and the animosities and the
racism and the genderism and the
speciesism that has clouded the
earlier stages of human
evolution. We must surrender our
smallness, the ego's constant
self, cherishing with all of its
divisions between people, races,
religions, classes, nations and
even species, I believe we are
entering the dark, a dark night
of our collective soul, a time
of emptying, a time of intense
anguish, of progressive loss of
control and systematic
breakdown, a Time of global
purification unto death that
will last generations. But
through this hard labor, we will
give birth to something extra
ordinary, more than just a new
civilization. What is emerging
is nothing less than a new order
of human being through the
global systems crisis, our
planet is giving birth to the
future human, a higher form of
humanity, the diamond soul, is
being born in history, and we
are All part of this
transformation. Thank you very
much.
Yeah, okay, I'll stop this year
now. Yeah, wow,
Unknown: that was amazing,
Chris, thank you so much. I
mean, I personally know the
truth of what you're saying from
my own intuitions and my own
brief experiences. Yeah, well,
thank you so much. So let's open
it up. Let's take a take a
minute to breathe, I guess, and
then let's open it to questions
and conversation. Yeah,
and if you'd like to start just
unmute and speak,
Chris Bache: yeah, I really do
see myself just reminding you of
things you already know, things
you knew before you incarnated.
My sense is that everybody
chooses, every one of us has
chosen to incarnate voluntarily,
that we chose the incarnation
that we are now in knowing
beforehand what we are getting
into. We may have forgotten once
we incarnate, but we knew before
we were born, and we will
remember. When we die, it's that
we are all carefully placed in
order to participate in this
collective transformation.
Beautiful, Chris, this whoops.
Jonai: This is Janae, and I this
is absolutely beautiful. And I
kept thinking all the way
through, what do I do with what
I just learned in terms of
science and the new DNA testing
that's been done, epigenetics,
the fact that we have the same
genome as the what's called
inadequate and anatomically
modern humans back in the
200,000 period time and What,
and what I'm coming to is that
this is all. This is all when it
when it actually comes out. I
mean, most people don't even
know about it yet, but when it
actually comes out, it's
preparing us. It's preparing
it's giving us what we have
right now, and it's giving us
the opportunity to move on from
there. That's kind of the way I
look at it. And I the one thing
I kept thinking all the way
through, how long is this going
to take? And you answered it in
the end, it's going to go
through several generations, or
maybe many generations. But this
is where we this is where we
jump off and fly and move.
Chris Bache: And, you know, I
don't have any visionary
experience of how long or the
how or the details I wasn't
given that kind of detail. So
for that, I have to go to the
experts like everybody else. I
have to go to the scientists who
are really plotting the
escalating climate crisis that
we are entering in the social
sciences who are looking at the
broader social and political
ramifications of these crises.
But my sense is that the 21st
Century is pivotal. I mean by by
2020, by 2050, well, first, let
me recommend, and you notice
that I haven't talked about,
what can we do? How do we
respond to this crisis? How do
we participate in it? And we can
talk about that. But one of the
people who has thought
extensively about this and
written about it beautifully is
Dwayne Elgin, and his latest
book, his most recent book is
his book choosing Earth, and
he's a social activist. He's an
evolutionary thinker and a
futurist, and his wife has
created a film based on the book
called facing adversity,
choosing Earth. And it's both.
He's Dwayne is giving away the
book and his wife is giving away
the film. You can find, you can
get a PDF from Amazon on the
book, and you can find the film
online in the in the book Dwayne
outlines what science is say,
telling us about the next five
decades, you know, and each of
those decades, the crisis
deepens precipitously, and we
are now in the decade of the the
great on the falling the falling
apart, beginning of a sense of
falling apart. Institutional
value systems are falling apart.
This will continue to accelerate
into the great unraveling. I'm
sorry. Let me back the great
unraveling followed by the
falling apart, followed by the
deep crash. By the time we get
to 2050 we're going to be
looking at a deeply, profoundly
different world than we are now.
And so my sense is that this
this crisis of near extinction.
And because we are looking at,
you know, when you really look
at the people who are looking at
the numbers and how many
billions of human beings are
going to likely to be dying as
we run into shortfall of
harvest, and so on and so forth,
we are looking at a near
extinction event, and extinction
is a tremendous accelerator of
evolution. So my sense is, if we
don't make it this transition in
this century or close to this
century, we very well might not
make it at all. So I do expect
it to take several generations,
but I do expect the 21st Century
to be focal in this transition.
Thank you.
Thank you. Jean, I see that you
have your hand up.
You're on mute. Jean, i. Me
Jean Fox: there. Sorry about
that. There you go. Yeah, I
mentioned in the chat that in
2007 I met a Chandler who who
wrote about this and in a lot of
detail, and he gives it, gives
all, gives it for free. We'll
share his information for free.
It's not for profit, but it's
just that it's, it's nature
cleansing itself in preparing us
for the next step. And we're all
we're always stuck in our minds,
but what we need to do is be
present with each other, says
the in the who's ever going to
be left through all these
processes? We just have to show
up for each other and solve the
problems and moment by moment,
because all we have is each
moment. And if we're stuck in
our minds and isolating from
each other, in our houses, in
our jobs, we're not going to be
there to support each other.
Look what's happened in Kentucky
or any of these places where
there's a disaster, we're in the
middle of a disaster. In the
disaster isn't it's not time for
planning, it's time for doing.
So we have to really just, when
somebody needs something, do it
for them. Help what, whatever we
can do to help each other,
because it's hard, yeah, yeah.
Chris Bache: We have to become
the human being that the world
needs right now, both on an
internal level, we have to face
our shadow. We have to heal our
shadow. We have to become more
whole within our souls, but also
on a political level, on a
social level, I think there's a
synergy between the world is
trying to become one, to grow
past the nation status, the
nation state idea, it's trying
to become one. And there's a
synergy between our in our soul
is trying to become one. We
carry the history of humanity
inside us, as well as our
society carrying it outside of
us. So as the world is trying to
become one, we are trying to
become one. There's a
synergistic dance between inner
and outer here, and so this are
stepping into this means
stepping into it, and each of us
has a little bit of a different
way of stepping into it, because
we all carry a different karmic
agenda. We all undertook
different responsibilities as we
incarnated. There is both an
internal and an external, a
psychological and a social
dimension to this
transformational process.
Jean Fox: And we are. We are the
Earth. Yeah, of the Earth, we're
so we're tending, tending our
gardens. And this other channel
that I was talking about. His
name is John tettmer, says we're
going back to an agrarian
society, whatever, whatever
humanity is left to be one with
the earth, to be work in harmony
with the earth, and evolve again
from there in A equal, symbiotic
Yeah, instead of raping.
Chris Bache: And in that
context, let me just mention
that some people have asked me,
Why do you focus on human beings
so much and don't talk about
experiences of other species?
And of course, many people who
work with psychedelics in a
shamanic kind of context of many
experiences of with other
species, and that I've had a few
of those experience. But the
main track for me has been
working with the humans, the
collective human psyche. And I
think this is because humanity
is the greatest threat to life
on this planet right now. And if
we can heal the human species,
then all the other species on
the planet will be safe. And
it's not that I don't respect I
don't think they're inferior to
human beings or so on so forth.
They absolutely are just as
precious as human beings are.
But in order to ensure their
well being, we have to heal
humanity.
Jonai: We're the ones that are
destroying them. Yes,
Chris Bache: they were here
first. Yeah.
Unknown: So Regina, you have
your hand up,
Regina: yes. Thank you so much.
I wanted to know how you. Do it
differently, that you would do
it differently. Now I'm just
curious.
Chris Bache: I would vary the
dose level. I would work with
high doses sometimes, but low
doses at other times, I would
also balance LSD with other
psychedelics like Psilocybin or
Ayahuasca. Each of those
psychedelics, all of them, have
in common the amplifying effect
of amplifying the sensitivity of
consciousness, but they do so in
slightly different ways, they
kind of bring out different
aspects of the spectrum of
consciousness. So that LSD tends
to sort of drive towards the
high cosmic logic ceiling.
Psilocybin tends to sort of be
work closer to the emotional
body, closer to the physical
body. Ayahuasca tends to do that
as well and bridge a little bit
step farther and deeper out. So
I would balance high doses
versus low doses, synthetic
psychedelics and organic
psychedelics. And I don't think
there is a fundamental core
difference between synthetic and
organic psychedelics, but I
would just differentiate those
two here. And one of the other
reasons I would do it
differently is because I
thought, when I began this work,
first, I thought this was all
about my personal
transformation. Well, well that
was that went out the window.
It's not about personal
transformation, it's about our
collective transformation. But I
also thought that the goal was
to get to some end state. You
know, people talked about
becoming one with God, or
becoming entering into the
primal void, or somehow reaching
some end condition. And so I
drove hard to reach that end
condition. But the way it worked
is that every time I would get
into what appeared to be a
homecoming state or an
absolutely soul satisfying
existential bliss, by keeping
driving, I would be taken into
yet another level of
consciousness and yet another
level of consciousness, until
eventually, I had one pivotal
experience in my 50th session,
where I was shown that it's an
infinite progression. You'll
never reach the end of it. The
Divine fabric is an infinite
fabric, and that's so one of the
reasons I would, I would do it
differently, is because I'm, I
think the goal is not to reach
some destination or some end
state. The goal is to become
transparent and to let as much
of the of the Divine into our
lives as possible, and to live
in that abiding and to deepen
that abiding communion. So I'm I
was a young man when I did this
work. I'm a little more patient
with the slower methods of
transformation than I was when I
did it. Thank you for that,
because I've been coming to that
realization myself. And it's
like there is no end. It's
forever. It is forever that, in
itself, is very difficult to put
your mind around. It's like,
yeah, yeah.
Regina: So that was, I guess I
would for myself, say that is
the ultimate surrender to be
able to do
Chris Bache: that. Yeah. And
whatever transition we're going
through in this next 100 years,
or whenever, whatever we're
going through, it's not the end
point for the human story,
right? We're going to be on this
planet for millions and millions
of more years if we survive this
potential extinction event. And
so we're going to keep growing.
We're going to go beyond the
diamond soul. We're going to
keep growing and growing and
growing. The creative
intelligence of the universe
does not seem to think in small
scale. It thinks its landscape
is vast. It thinks in galactic
proportions. It thinks in
magnitudes of time, far beyond
what we've even begun to try to
conceptualize in our religious
traditions of the world. I think
science has basically erased the
Blackboard and given us a
completely larger landscape,
which as our experience of this
landscape deepens, we're going
to have a deeper understanding
of the intelligence that
saturates this landscape, in a
way that even science is a hard
time admitting today, but it's
getting there.
Regina: Yeah, just the thing of
impatience alone, just that one
thing alone. Yeah, how different
it would be if we really, truly
were just able to be, yeah.
Unknown: Yeah. That, Victoria,
you have your hand up,
Chris Bache: yeah. Well, you
keep moving around on my screen.
Boy, I just was such a deep
experience. Felt like every cell
in my body was saying yes, and
so I wonder if did two questions
that are personal, so if you'd
be willing to talk about it,
just your ability to really
trust what has your experience
has been and what has been shown
to you, and then how you
incorporate that, I guess, in
the moments of your life, you
know, it's it's like, okay, what
do we do this moment, next
moment, next moment.
No. One of the things, one of
the great gifts I got from Stan
Grof was the understanding that
when you go into these deep,
cathartic, high, amplified
states of consciousness, you're
going to start to go into get
into stormy weather, you're
going to get into hard,
challenging circumstances.
Things are going to unravel on
you, and you're going to have an
instinct to pull back. You know,
this is a bad trip. You just
don't want to be here. This is a
terrible, terrible terrible
thing to happen, but if you are
willing to embrace it, if you
give yourself over to it, if you
let it take you wherever it
wants to take you, even though
you do not understand it at all,
you do not understand what's
happening. You don't understand
the logic of the whole thing.
But if you surrender to it,
it'll take you into a crisis,
which eventually peaks, and then
some part of you will fall away.
You'll you'll go through some
type of death, and then you will
awaken into a different reality,
as a different being with a
different set of capacities in a
deeper level of the universe, so
that you learn to trust the
cycle. It is a cycle process so
that you you open, you engage,
you surrender, and then you are
reborn, and you bring back the
entire cycle of both the trauma
and the ecstatic rebirth. So
that is a that develops a kind
of trust, which you learn by
practicing it. You learn by
doing it. And today, now, as I
have backed away from doing this
work, I mean, I stopped my
intense work in 99 so I've had a
long time to live with those
experiences, which will bring me
to your second question. And as
I've watched the shadows of
history deepen, I have to fall
back on this deep trust. And I
mean, it's I fall back on it
because I don't know how the
universe is going to work out.
What I've just seen tips of I
don't know how it's going to do
it and and my heart reaches out
in compassion to the billions of
people that are on the planet
going through very, very
challenging circumstances. In
the end, you either trust or you
don't trust. I choose to trust
that the creative intelligence
knows what it's doing, that the
creative intelligence that gave
birth to the galaxies and gave
birth to the planetary systems
and gave birth to life on this
planet, and so brought self
awareness into the life on this
planet, it knows what it's
doing. I choose to trust that it
believes that we are ready to
make this transition, and that's
why it has allowed it, or it
supported its emergence. How I
live with these things? Well,
it's not always been easy. I
mean, integrating integrating
individual sessions has always
been easy because I I followed a
strict therapeutic protocol
which maximizes the procedure of
clear contact and clean
integration. And I can't
emphasize this enough if you go
into psychedelics and you're in
a helter shelter environment and
you're kind of, you know, at a
concert, or you're doing the
set, and the other you don't
necessarily have clean contact,
and therefore integration can be
complicated, but if you have
clean contact and and careful
attention to integration,
Recording your experiences,
remembering your experiences,
pondering your experiences,
giving voice to them, giving
poetry to them, giving artistic
representation of them. You can
hold on to more and more your
experiences. However, I found
that I went so deep on my.
Particular journey I went deeper
than I think was probably wise
for me to go. And what became
challenging was not to manage
the pain part of the
experiences. What became
challenging, in the end, was
managing the ecstasy. It took me
so deeply into the divine bliss
and into the ecstatic nature of
transcendent reality. That when
I stopped my sessions, the
physical world just began to
lose its appeal. It began to
lose its luster. It could not
compare to the intensity of that
Rapture. Now I know that there
are great spiritual beings, and
they have always been my
mentors, but there are great
beings who can live consciously
in the physical world and in
this great transcendent bliss at
the same time, and all honor to
the great ones. But in my
personal case, I went deeper
than I was able to sustain the I
was able to remember them. I was
able to record them and hold
them in my memories, but I
wasn't able to live in them.
24/7, and that made living
challenging, and I spent
literally decades after I
stopped my sessions, actively
working to integrate those
sessions into my daily life. And
writing LSD in the mind of the
universe and going public as a
psychedelic professor was
actually part of my integration
process, because one of the
burdens of doing this work was
the secrecy I had to, had to
use, and this secrecy that
allowed me to do the work also
made it difficult for me to
integrate that work, because I'm
a yacker, I'm a talker. I love
to learn and share what I
learned. And here I as a
philosopher, I was cultivating
these very, very profound
experiences, but I wasn't
allowed to talk about them. I
couldn't bring them to my
students. I could not bring them
to my colleagues at the
University. And so beginning to
sort of talk about them, to
systematically integrate them
into into some rhyme and reason
in dark night, early dawn, and
then in LSD, in the mind of the
universe, has been one of the
ways in which I have stabilized
them and integrated them and
made my peace with them, because
with that book, I have become in
the outside world, what I was in
my inner work, and in that there
is great peace, and beyond that,
it's an ongoing process. I don't
think I will complete
integrating this work in this
lifetime. I think what
integration means changes as the
experiences go deeper, what
integration means when you're
working at the personal
unconscious, or even the
collective unconscious, it's
different than when you're going
into radically trans, temporal,
trans, spatial states of
consciousness. So that right
now, I don't think we really
even understand fully what
entering into these states of
consciousness is doing to us. We
are kind of our early enthusiasm
for our ability to enter into
these states, we haven't quite
caught up with ourselves in that
way. So we have a lot of work to
do in the area of integration,
and in that context, I would
mention a book called
psychedelics and psychotherapy,
edited by Maria Papa Spira and
Tim Reed, which is an excellent
book on specifically addressing
the question of integration. And
I have an article in the book.
What was the name of that book,
psychotherapy, psychedelics and
psychotherapy.
And so thank you for that. And
do you find just one last
question, do you find, you know
when the the ego? Do you? Do you
find yourself really being more
aware of what your state is and
each moment and choosing? Or is
it beyond that?
Again, I want to go back to what
I showed in the very the early
slide, the difference between
therapeutic healing, spiritual
awakening and cosmic logical
exploration. Your question is
basically asking, how do these
experiences affect my spiritual
condition, my my psycho
spiritual condition, my
spiritual state, if I were
seeking spiritual. Awakening I
would do, have done a completely
different protocol. I think
working with low doses would be
the approach that you would want
to use if you were really
seeking what the classic state
of enlightenment or you have to
kind of work with where the ego
lives in the world to realize
that kind of abiding
transparency, where you can
enter into a kind of
transparency where you relax
into the present and relax into
the infinity of eternity now,
and relax into the oneness that
holds all things in existence.
Cosmic logical exploration is a
different agenda, and so my
whatever I whatever I can
integrate from those cosmic
logical experiences, what I can
and cannot integrate does not at
the Spiritual Awakening level,
does not really impact the truth
that emerged as in the Cosmic,
logical adventure. As a
philosopher, I wanted to
understand how the universe
worked and the experiences that
the universe gave me as I
pursued those that question are
not experiences that I can
stabilize and integrate. 24/7,
some of them may be, but many of
them I can't. So I do spirit. I
was doing spiritual practice
meditation through all of my
work through all the years, and
continue to do so. And one of
the ways I do spiritual practice
today is to cultivate the
conscious recall of my memories,
not to try to get stuck, not to
be stuck in my past, but because
my memories are my deepest
experience of the universe, and
by cultivating that conscious
recall of those experiences, it
allows me to enter into a state
of transparency where I enter
into something approximating a
version of that intimacy, again,
beautiful. It's it's not an
abiding 24/7 thing for me. It
comes and goes. It's a daily
practice thing.
Thank you so much.
Unknown: Jonah, you have your
hand up again.
Jonai: Yes, you can hear me.
Okay. That kind of leads into my
question or comment when you
say, cultivating the conscious
recall of your experiences. Does
this include past life? Does
this include everything I mean,
past life, this life, whatever
happens to be, come into your
mind when you're doing that
well.
Chris Bache: In my psychedelic
work, I did encounter some
former lives. I also have
encountered former lives. In my
hep meal therapy work that I did
for three years. So but here I'm
specifically focusing on my
psychedelic work. And, you know,
it's it's interesting. I don't
really focus very much on
integrating my former lives. I
think I somehow have done enough
house cleaning that they are
kind of okay. They're kind of
comfortably tucked away. It's
more the cosmic logical the
memory of cosmic logical access
that I cultivate,
I what I am,
is kind of strange, because you
know when, when you look at
people who have deep spiritual
experiences, usually they have
them in the context of a
meditation tradition or
contemplative tradition, and
they can often hold on to the
experiences that they've tapped
into, sometimes, not always, but
often, this approach is
different, and it's why I
emphasize as a methodology
chapter in the book. This is the
path of temporary immersion.
It's not the path of abiding
presence. It's a path of
temporary immersion. You have to
come to terms with the
temporariness of the conditions
that you have entered and use
those hours in order to affect a
long term, abiding change in the
condition of your of your
psyche, but you and you, just
because a person may have had an
extra, ordinarily powerful or
beautiful experience or cosmic
experience, doesn't mean. That
they have necessarily become a
beautiful or powerful or cosmic
being. A lot of people made that
mistake in the early days. We've
learned from that we have to
constantly be remembering these
are temporary experiences.
What's important is what we can
do the day after our session.
Jonai: Right? Right? Everything
is an opportunity, and it's
there to learn in some way. As
the way I look at it, in 1998 I
was just jumping into the nine
gates Mystery School, which
you're familiar with, I'm sure.
And then it all went from there.
I had done some preliminary work
to that, to get ready to do
that. And then, but, but I
wanted to bring up was
reincarnation, which was kind
of, it's kind of, and the new
trajectory that you mentioned in
terms of reincarnation, you said
all of the last all I wrote down
all of past lives fused into
one, and it's kind of, and I've
done a lot of past life stuff. I
mean, from there I went through
into esthetic studies and and
experiential training in ancient
archetypal techniques, ancient
techniques, and all that kind of
wisdom techniques and all that
kind of thing. And I did, I did
a lot of past life. It wasn't it
was because it's karmic issues,
taking an event and going back,
and then there was a forgiveness
process at the end of that. And
it's it changes the energy of
it, and in changing the energy
of that past life experience, so
to speak, it's a story. It makes
a tremendous difference, because
that energy is no longer
affecting us. I mean, it
changes, you know, the emotional
and everything and so and I
didn't. I did quite a bit of
that for myself. I also helped
other people do it. But so it
is. It's accepting whatever has
happened in the past. And if you
need, if something is up and you
need to forgive it, fine, and
you go from there. But then
you're also saying, in this
lifetime, all of that is also a
part of it, and in the future,
the future, and whatever is. And
so you're expanding. And another
thing as I listen to you talk
and think about I'm an avid
reader, and I haven't, I kind of
shut down on that for a while,
but, but I'm back into it now,
because I'm trying to update you
know myself, and so I can learn
from reading your book, from
hearing you talk. I can, I can
somehow not exactly relate to
any kind of a way. I can you
went through all of the
psychedelic part of getting
there, but I I feel an
understanding of what you're
saying, yes, and so I sort of
feel like I've always been a
person who, I likes to learn
from other people's experiences,
right? Because it takes so much
less time than me trying to go
through all those experiences. I
mean, you went through how many
years of this, and here's where
you are, and now you are sharing
this with everybody. So we have
a place to start, yeah, and we
can go from there, yeah. And
that's what I'm counting on. I
started counting backwards on
birthdays when I from 60. I had
read something about 120 years
our bodies should be able to
last. So I thought, okay, 60
years old if I stop counting
backwards and don't get into
this senior thing of aging and
dying and everything and go
backwards. And somebody said,
Well, what if you get to zero?
And I said, Well, I'll just hang
out there for however long it
takes. And so that's another I
mean, that's just not 100 that's
120 and who knows, you know. And
with the with the current, with
our soft technology, as, as Greg
Braden calls it, all of that,
that technology we have in
within us,
Unknown: to to
Jonai: to repair and reflect,
refraction and rejuvenate and
everything. You know, I'm really
focusing on that that's real.
So, yeah, okay,
Unknown: thank you. Johnny, so
Jean, do you did you have
another question? I just
Jean Fox: had one quick
question, if someone were want
to do, do you recommend, Chris,
if you're want to do your own
journeying, guided, or self
guided. So I feel like I've done
some of my own and it's yeah,
sometimes it can be scary by
yourself absolutely so go ahead.
Chris Bache: I really recommend
if you're going to work with
psychedelics, that you work with
somebody. Who really knows the
landscape, who knows the
territory? And now I don't. I
have a particular glitch around
guided experiences, because I
don't the role of a sitter is,
to me, is not to guide a person,
but simply to help keep you safe
and focused while you do your
inner work the universe guides
you. Sit here's role is to keep
you safe, keep you protected,
and help keep you focused. And I
if you're going to amplify
consciousness, I think it's
really important to work with
somebody who is has therapeutic
skills and has knowledge of this
territory, and just to loop back
just a little bit, psychedelics
here are not the issue, not the
primary issue. In fact, the name
of this book, LSD, in the mind
of the universe, was given by
the publisher. That's not what I
call the book. I call the book
is diamonds from heaven because
it's a story of initiation.
Psychedelics are secondary. You
can enter into these states
through any number of different
spiritual technologies,
spiritual techniques and the
visions that I've shared with
you today are they're not unique
to psychedelics. They they have
surfaced in spiritual
traditions, in channeling
traditions, in indigenous
traditions, psychedelics is
simply another technology for
accessing these deep states of
awareness, right? So, and I
would encourage you, please,
anybody, don't do what I do did,
and please be careful if you're
going to work with psychedelics,
be very careful, very
conscientious, because when you
open these doors, you can get in
over your head. And there are
people who open these doors and
walk away traumatized and
scarred for years. Okay, so I
want to be very careful.
Jean Fox: There's so many,
there's, you know, a
psychotherapist. Then there's
lot of different groups, yeah,
but it's hard to discern. It's
very kind of recommendations of
how to find your, you know, even
trusted friend.
Chris Bache: Yeah, things are
changing, of course, as it was
mentioned earlier. You know,
mushrooms are becoming legal in
various places. Hundreds and
1000s of people are being
certified as past as psychedelic
therapists. The future is
opening up in ways we could
never have anticipated 15 years
ago. Thank you. Michael Pollan,
you know, and all of those,
we're entering a new and
exciting era, but we're still in
a transition, because it's
still, you know, it's still in
the gray zone.
Unknown: So thank you. So we're
running out of time, but I'm
going to have two more
questions, Ron. I'm me.
Chris Bache: So I really
appreciate that last question
and your answer, Chris, I think
this is extremely important in
this topic. And I again, I had
said before that I speak from a
different type of experience
than you had. You were doing
science. You were tracking
things very carefully. When I
talked about that, I'd had some
experience with micro dosing
before it was called that. That
was a social thing, but I will
say that my last session and I
did have a few larger dose
sessions that I did my very last
session, I think satisfied me,
because I did a solitary
session, and I was in nature,
and I remember the emotional
place that it took me was very
strong and very poignant. I was.
I had tears of both what I now
know are both joy and grief.
Because I was, I was really
appreciating the oneness of the
magnificent beauty of all of
creation around me, and it's
amazing complexities. And at the
same time, I was having grief,
because I was aware of what
we're doing to our world and who
we are as humans and all of our
failings now at the moment,
because I didn't have a sitter
and I didn't have any science or
good counsel, someone keeping me
safe and keeping me on track
with my experience to make it a
healing experience or a
therapeutic experience. Years, I
thought I was having a bummer,
because I was so emotional, I
didn't know how to cope with
that at the time, and only now
in in looking back, you know, 50
years ago, no 40 years ago,
that, and having this topic
become more public, and being
able to read and and listen to
people like you speak about it,
I could say that I've probably
spent my whole life integrating
that, you know, and so it's it's
been okay, but I want to really
chime in, in a very simple
street wise guy sort of way to
say it. This is not to be done
lightly, and even even with
micro dosing, without, without
having someone be a sitter and a
guide and and doing that, I
would really, I would really
caution it, and then, especially
with the larger doses, I so
appreciate how you went into
detail about your answer to that
last question from, I'm sorry I
forgot your name is a jean. So
thank you, Chris, thank you so
much for all of this. Thank you.
It's, I've, I've really
appreciated it very much.
Unknown: Thank you. Thank you,
Georgina. You get the last
question.
Georgena Eggleston: It's too
Yeah, what is really, really
short is LSD country, indicated
for those people with a
diagnosis of traumatic brain
injury.
Chris Bache: That is a question
that I'm not competent to ask.
It should really be answered by
clinical professional. I would
imagine it would depend upon the
nature of the of the injury. But
really, let me, I won't, let's
yield that to the people
who should answer.
Georgena Eggleston: So the other
question is, is you gave the
quote by the British
professional at the beginning, I
got, certainly the sense of
lack, limitation and fear. And
as we've been talking about the
precipice and what we're going
into, it sounds like those are,
the consciousness, lack,
limitation, fear, here we are.
How can, how from your
experience, what? What do you
say to my interpretation of
that, for all of us going into
this crisis?
Chris Bache: Yeah, you know,
some people said, have said, If
we focus too much on the
negative, we actually will bring
about that negative. We will
think it will bring it into
existence. And I think I
understand that, and I do
understand self generating
realities and so on so forth.
But I don't think that's the
primary danger. Now, the primary
danger is not facing those
realities, and that if we don't
face those realities, we can't
mobilize to address them. If we
don't really understand and face
in a cold, sober fashion how
overextended the we are with
this planet, we will never be
able to bring about a change, a
fundamental change, of our
individual and our social way of
living on the planet. So to me,
I would rather sit with people
who are facing that, who are
engaging the grief of what we
have done to the species on this
planet and to the planet itself,
to work with that issue and take
that all the way down to a
resolution, and then move
forward and through it. And
there are, of course, Joanna
Macy people who are doing this
type of work. I think a great
deal of grief work is needed as
we confront the damage that
we've done, but then we move
into, okay, let's get on top of
this. Let's move forward. Let's
make these changes that are
necessary.
Georgena Eggleston: Thank you.
Unknown: Okay, well, thank you
so much. I'm going to put it
back on the gallery view. So
thank you so much, Chris, this
is amazing and inspiring and
really powerful. Thank you for
your years of work, for all of
us, all of humanity, for Austin
to have this in insight into
what. Were about, and I'm going
to read your book, both of your
books. Which one would you
recommend I read first?
Chris Bache: Oh, I always
recommend that people start.
First of all, you can read LSD
in the mind of the universe.
It's it's a much simpler book to
read than dark night early dawn.
It does not require dark matter
at dawn, dark naturally, Dawn is
pretty academic, muscled, but
LSD in the mind of the universe,
I wrote that to be accessible to
a wide range of people. But
personally, I find, if you don't
know the literature on
reincarnation, I often think
it's best to start with the life
cycles, which is my book on
reincarnation, because
reincarnation is fundamental to
what emerges in LSD, in the mind
of the universe.
Unknown: Okay, thank you so.
Thank you everyone for joining
and for your comments and
questions and thanks again,
Chris, this is wonderful. I
think we might have to have you
back to talk about your book
later on. So thank you so much
again, and thanks everybody, and
we'll see you next time. Thanks
so much Dottie and Heather. Much
love Yes, and thank you again,
Heather for bringing us. Chris,
Chris Bache: thank you so much.
Unknown: Bye, everyone. Thank
you. Thank you so much. Bye.