Chris Bache: In all of my work,
I always felt myself engaging
and being engaged by a larger
consciousness. This
consciousness did not take
concrete form. It never took
personified form. It never took
concretized form, and it
changed, or the qualities of
this consciousness changed the
deeper I went, so that I began
to understand the way I think of
it is the consciousness that we
enter into communion with in
psychedelic states, is an
infinite consciousness that's
capable of generating any number
of different types of
experiences or types of
awareness within us and our mind
acts as a seed catalyst, a seed
crystal that catalyzes a certain
set of experiences from this
infinite consciousness. If you
do this repetitively, over
repeatedly the experiences that
you have and you integrate,
internalize and go through the
various purification processes,
it changes your your
consciousness, and therefore the
consciousness that you take into
the next encounter is a
different consciousness that
catalyzes a deeper set of
experiences from the infinite
potential of consciousness. And
that means that the what you
experience as this guiding
intelligence, the this massive
intelligence that you meet at
different levels is, in a way, a
consciousness that arises at the
intersection between your
individual mind and this
universal Mind. And as you
change, the intersection
changes, so that from my
experience, the consciousness,
which I felt was always guiding
my sessions, was always
invisible to me, but was always
felt. It didn't adopt concrete
form, or very seldom, adopt
concrete form, because the form
would change as the experiences
deepens. So you know that
formless quality is, I think,
something innate to do with the
consciousness itself, and then
in going beyond the collective
level of consciousness, between
beyond the collective psyche and
even beyond human history. When
you're pushing so deep, you're
going beyond Jung's category of
archetypal consciousness, you're
letting you're going beyond
human history altogether, all of
the interpretive frameworks, all
the images, all the concepts
that we associate with our
religious and spiritual history,
they just fall away. Basically,
if several 1000 years or five or
10,000 years of religious
history just fall away, and
you're moving into states of
consciousness that go beyond any
category of gods or deities or
angelic beings. You're in a
completely different world. So,
yes, always guidance, always an
intelligence engaging me, but
formless,
Unknown: yeah, well, I have yet
to get to that level in my
particular journeys, but perhaps
some day, and I'd like to ask
more specifically about sort of
the forms that can appear so.