Tasshin Fogleman: Hi friend,
thanks for joining me. I
Chris Bache: was glad to be
here. Tassim, thank you for the
invitation.
Tasshin Fogleman: Yes, my
pleasure. I've been reading,
I've read three out of four of
your books in the last and last
month or so, and just been
devouring them. So it's been a
real treat to read them, and
I've been very excited to have
this conversation. So just to
begin, yeah, so just to begin,
I'd love to hear you share your
background and really your life
story, anything that you'd like
to share about yourself,
biographically and your story.
Chris Bache: Basically, I made
my living as a university
professor at a modest University
in Northeast Ohio. I'm a
professor of religious studies.
My background is I have a degree
in Notre Dame, in theology from
Notre Dame and New Testament
criticism in Cambridge, and a
PhD in Philosophy of Religion
from Brown and so very
classically educated, raised in
the Deep South, coming from
Mississippi, but when I finished
my graduate training and came to
Youngstown State University,
where I taught for 33 years, I
met the work of Stanislav Grof,
of course, one of the foremost
authorities in the psychedelic
integrating psychedelics into
psychotherapy, and his work was
a turning point in my life. So
at that point, I continued to do
my work, and I've just made my
living week in, week out, year
in, year out in the classroom,
doing the things that professors
do. But in my personal life and
my private life, I began a 20
year journey working with high
doses of LSD in a therapeutic
protocol pioneered by Stan and
other early researchers
exploring the deep structure,
not only of my own
consciousness, but of the
consciousness of the universe
itself. At least that's my
understanding of my best
interpretation of where I went.
So after holding that material
and sitting on it for 20 years,
I did this work for 20 years
between 1979 and 1999 and I sat
on it and crunched it and
digested it for another 20 years
before releasing LSD in the mind
of the universe, the story of
that journey. So basically, I'm
a university professor who's
part of the underground
psychedelic movement in this
country, beautiful.
Tasshin Fogleman: It's been an
incredible journey to learn
about and appreciate you sharing
it. I you know you allude to a
few in a few points to, kind of
who you were before you started
this journey, and your younger
self. And I forget exactly how
you put it, but, but sort of
like, you know, you might not
have expected me to go down this
journey, and I've, sort of, I
got the picture of you as, sort
of like, straight laced and sort
of like analytic. What were you
like at that time before you
started all this well,
Chris Bache: I began my life
seeking to be a Catholic priest.
I was in the seminary in high
school from three years of high
school, and got a degree in
theology from Notre Dame. So I
began a very conventional and at
the same time, by the time I
finished graduate school,
because of all my education that
I had acquired, I became an
atheistically inclined agnostic.
Basically, the study of
philosophy of religion and
science had basically wiped my
theological slate clean, and I
became a pretty hard and fast
agnostic, and that's the way I
began this work, and it was the
LSD work that opened me up to a
broader understanding of
existence. Now, I've been a
meditator all my life, since
college, and I've practiced
within different Buddhist
traditions within the passina
tradition and Zen tradition, and
eventually settling into the
Vajrayana tradition. But that
all came after the psychedelic
work. Well, I started meditating
beforehand, but the evolution to
more specific Buddhist lineages
came after the psychedelic work
had begun. And I've raised, you
know, three kids, been married,
you know, mortgages, standard
kind of affair, you know. And
you know me, look at me. I mean,
I look like an accountant, kind
of I was designed to be an
undercover agent
Tasshin Fogleman: for
psychedelics. Wow, I love that
description. What? What was it
that so captured you about Grof
work when you encountered it?
Chris Bache: Well, I immediately
saw that if what he was saying
was correct, this had enormous
implications. For philosophy,
which was my interest, not just
for healing in clinical
psychology, but here was the
method that allowed us to get
deep, first hand access to
dimensions of consciousness. And
through those dimensions of
consciousness, dimensions of
reality that I had seen
described in many spiritual
bodies of literature, but here
was a protocol that allow people
to be initiated, if only on a
temporary basis, because this is
a path, what I call the path of
temporary immersion, and we have
to be really careful not to
confuse a path of temporary
immersion from what I would call
the bad the path of abiding
presence, more contemplative
meditational path, but it gave
us temporary access to states of
consciousness far beyond our
ordinary egoic awareness and far
beyond space Time awareness to
explore the deep structure of
the universe itself. This has
been a philosopher's dream, in a
way, and particularly in our
culture, which was is
materialist metaphysical
convictions, which has come to
believe that there is nothing in
the universe outside what can be
explained by its material
substrate, that matter is the
only thing that's real. Matter
is the only thing that exists.
And here was a method that was
challenging that assumption gave
us experiences that would be
might be very difficult to
explain in terms of that
materialist hypothesis. So
that's that immediately picked
up my philosopher's ears. I'm
not
Tasshin Fogleman: quite sure how
to ask this question, but when
you decided to go on this
journey, and, you know, were
inspired by Grof and wanted to
adapt his protocol for your own
use, what did what did that look
like, practically for you? What?
What, how did you embark on
that?
Chris Bache: Oh, I, I follow the
very strict protocol, and it's
one of the things I think that
made my work a little unusual
over the years. It came when you
work in a therapeutic protocol,
you are totally isolated from
the world. You don't take
psychedelics and go for a walk
in the woods, or go to a
Grateful Dead concert, or even
stay up talking with friends,
you're totally isolated from the
world. You're protected by a
sitter who manages all the
logistics of your day, handling
the music you're listening to,
carefully curated music with
headphones and eye shades you
basically like in a meditation
retreat. You turn your attention
totally within. And psychedelics
are an amplifier. They amplify
the condition of your
unconscious, and it causes
subtle levels of of your mind
which you might you have to
really reach to be able to have
access to them. It allows those
subtle dimensions of your mind
to come forward, and if you meet
them in a very conscientious,
focused manner, then a cleaning
process begins, a healing
process, a confrontational and
therapeutic engagement process
begins, but you're totally
isolated. So basically, it's an
entire weekend agenda. If I'm
working on Saturday, which I
usually do, I'd start in the
early morning. Would last all
day until after supper time.
You're spending days beforehand
that there's protocols that you
do beforehand, a lot of
preparation of your body, a lot
of preparation of your diet and
of your spiritual practice.
There's certain spiritual
practice I would do before a
session and spiritual practices
I would do after a session
eventually. So it's one very
intense day followed by several
days before and after
preparation. And you know, it's
a several day commitment each
session I did, I chose, after
several medium dose sessions, I
chose to work at very high
levels using psychedelic
therapy, not low dose
psychelytic therapy. This is a
protocol that I don't recommend
today. It's not that I'm against
occasional high doses of LSD,
but this consistent working just
exploding consciousness so
violently or so aggressively is
a protocol that I really don't
encourage today. But I worked at
500 to 600 micrograms for 73
sessions in 20 years, and on
average, it came out to about
five sessions a year. I worked
for four years. I took six year
hiatus, and then I worked in a
very aggressive 10 years. So it
worked out to about five
sessions a year.
Tasshin Fogleman: Can you
explain the difference between
psychedelic and psychedelic?
Psychic protocols?
Chris Bache: Yeah, a psyche
lytic protocol is a low dose
protocol where which stimulates
the unconscious more gently and
allows it sort of peels the
unconscious layer by layer and
so layers of your trauma or
anything you're holding which is
problematic or uncomfortable for
you surfaces in smaller
increments, layer by layer. If
you work with high doses of LSD
in the early years, these were
limited to three sessions. The
the work it's that Stan did at
Spring Grove Hospital in
Baltimore was working with
terminally ill cancer patients
who were dealing with death
anxiety, and what they were
trying to do was to precipitate
a something approximating a
Near-Death Experience, to give
these people who were dying a
bit of a glimpse, a foretaste of
where they were going when they
died. So it's a very powerful, a
much more evocative state.
Instead of processing all the
individual layers of the
personal psyche, it tends to
blow through those and drive
consciousness into a more
radical state of awareness. So
what I did was I thought, well,
if you could do this work safely
three times. You could do it
safely more than three times.
And I was still thinking in the
early years in a personal model.
I was thinking of cleaning my
own consciousness, but cleaning
it in bigger in bigger
exercises. It's kind of like
eating my karma in in fewer and
larger bites. It turns out that
model was completely incorrect,
as I learned by the second or
third year.
Tasshin Fogleman: Did you have a
sense when you're starting out
that this would be a long term
endeavor, that you'd be doing
these journeys many, many times?
Chris Bache: No, I didn't. When
I started it out, I had been
meditating, and I had
encountered the usual blocks
that everybody hits in the early
years of meditation, and I first
thought I would do some this
therapy in order to push through
and clear those blocks in order
to accelerate my personal
awakening. And it turns out that
that was a false model to bring
to it and but once the adventure
started, once I began to break
into these experiences of the
cosmos, then I was hooked. I did
not expect it to be taking up
such a large proportion of my
life. And what I found was, if
you go very deeply into this
work, you're you don't integrate
it around the edges of your
life, and continue to live your
life kind of like an ordinary
life, deep spiritual practice,
as you know all when you commit
to very deep spiritual practice,
it becomes your life. You wrap
your life around your spiritual
practice. And that happened for
me too. I mean, it just this
became a central focus of my
life. Of course, I my students
and my teaching were central
focus. My children and family
and marriage were central focus,
but my psychedelic work became
the core of my deeper
philosophical undertaking.
Tasshin Fogleman: And how did
those aspects of your life
relate to each other and
influence each other? Well?
Chris Bache: Basically, I feel
that my marriage and my teaching
were very grounding. First, I
love being a parent, I love
being a dad, and I love being
married, I love teaching. I just
love being in the classroom. And
I found that those commitments
just kept me grounded when I was
off exploring different
dimensions of reality on the
weekend, when I would come back,
you know, there were dishes to
wash and students to teach. It
was a very grounding way. So
they completely complimented
each other well. It just, you
know, because I mean, any deep
explore, I think, has this
experience, you're going in and
out, you're going back and forth
into these periods of deep
absorption, like a retreat. And
that's really why, I mean, I
never say that I've tripped. I
say I do a session, and it's
kind of like a Zen session, a
period set aside for intense
spiritual practice. A
psychedelic session is really a
psychedelic session. It's a
period set aside for intense
spiritual practice when you go
back and forth over and over
again, in and out of these
states, back into your ordinary
life. It's. Really it's
important to keep them in
balance. And my life was
organized in such a way that it
did keep those two different
sides of my life did stay in
balance with each other and help
each other.
Tasshin Fogleman: And can you
speak to the you make a
distinction between using
psychedelics for therapy and for
spirituality, and for, you know,
the kinds of cosmological
explorations that you ended up
leaning towards. Can you speak
to that distinction?
Chris Bache: Yeah, and that's
something I became more
articulate about as the journey
went on, and particularly as I
came back and began to write up
the entire thing, because I
found that many people who were
beginning to read my work were
trying to understand it within
frameworks that were too small
to understand the project. And
so I differentiate very clearly
now three different projects
that you can do with
psychedelics. You can do others,
of course, but just three one is
therapeutic healing. This is the
primary work of the psychedelic
Renaissance today, working on
healing the wounds of the
personal, unconscious, post
traumatic stress, death anxiety,
depression, alcohol addiction.
This is working at a personal
level, at the early stages.
Different than that is spiritual
awakening. This is basically to
try to awaken spiritually to the
truth of one's inner being, to
experientially have access to
the center of consciousness,
which turns out to be the same
unified reality as the entire
field of consciousness that
underlies all existence. This is
a different project than simply
therapeutic healing. It's it.
This is spiritual healing,
spiritual awakening, you know,
opening up to the to the rich
spiritual underlying fabric of
existence, the exploring of the
universe. Cosmological
exploration is a different
project. Still, cosmological
exploration is not simply
becoming aware or coming tuned
to the spiritual truths of life.
It's exploring beyond those
realities into the deep
structure of existence, going
beyond space, beyond time, going
into deep time, going into deep
space, going into archetype of
reality. You do not have to go
into these dimensions to wake up
or become a fully realized human
being. You do not have to go
into archetype or reality. You
do not have to go to the
beginning of the universe before
the Big Bang and watch creation
emerge out of the great void of
primal existence. This is a very
kind of different agenda, and I
think it's important to keep
apples and oranges separate from
each other. Now, they reinforce
each other. They support each
other in my journey, which
became primarily one of
cosmological exploration. Of
course, there was a great deal
of healing that took place at a
personal level, and there were
episodes of rich spiritual
awakening. But if I were aimed
at just spiritual awakening or
just psychological healing, I
would have organized the
sessions quite differently. But
spiritual, you know,
cosmological exploration is
really kind of like any kind of
demanding extreme sport, kind of
like going climbing Mount
Everest or going to the North
Pole. I don't know why anybody
would want to go to the North
Pole, but it's a very demanding
thing that some people like to
do, exploring the deep
structure. The Kant of the
cosmos is something like that.
It's a very demanding, rigorous
it requires tremendous
safeguards, and it is going in
places that very few people have
gone. And it's not the same as
spiritual awakening.
Tasshin Fogleman: Yeah, on the
one hand, I find the distinction
persuasive, because this really
does characterize your work and
the kinds of discoveries that
you found. And then I think if
you were holding that
distinction as like a purely
separate thing that wouldn't be
aligned with my own experiences
of these things. But it sounds
like you're saying, no, they can
all happen, but it's more like
what you're aiming for or what
your intentions
Chris Bache: are, yeah, and the
overlap.
Tasshin Fogleman: In that case,
how did you structure your
sessions so as to aim in the
direction of cosmological
exploration? And how might
someone structure them if
they're aimed at the other
goals?
Chris Bache: Well, hmm. Yeah, I
didn't first. I didn't
understand a lot of this at the
time when I was doing this work,
I understood it only after I'd
gone a long way down this road
and was looking back and
beginning to understand some of
the choices, the how the choices
I've made an impact of the
trajectory of the work. But
basically, once you decide
you're dosed, that's a
significant decision in this
process. But working with high
doses, you completely surrender
to the process. It's impossible
to try to direct. You can set
all the good intentions you
want, but the states of
consciousness that arise with
high doses of psychedelics,
amplified by very carefully
selected music and
internalization in a Kiva
practice, this sets in motion
processes that are so powerful
you can't control them at all.
You can't direct them, and the
strategy is simply to surrender,
to let to let your consciousness
take you wherever it wants to
take you, to show you whatever
it wants to show you, no matter
how inscrutable at the time, no
matter how painful, no matter
how absurd it may seem at the
time, just let it take you. It's
only after the fact, when you're
putting it all together, that
you may begin to understand some
of the dynamics of the
unfolding. So there's you put it
together after each individual
session, but then over a string
of sessions, I found that there
was a sequential development. So
more or less one session where
one session ended, the next
session would begin, kind of
like keeping a dream journal.
You're just going deeper and
deeper, and you may not
understand what's happening
until multiple sessions down the
road, and then when you look
back, you understand that
there's a continuity of
development that is taking place
across these different sessions.
So it's not a matter of aiming
the intention beyond the dose
and setting. It's really a
matter of complete surrender and
then figuring out after the fact
what has happened.
Tasshin Fogleman: What is the
word Kiva that used
Chris Bache: Kiva, you know, in
in the Native American
Southwestern tradition, when
they would do sacred ceremonies
with Peyote or with sacraments,
there's a Kiva as a hole in the
ground, you know, with a ladder
coming down, and you sit deep in
this hole in The ground around
the fire ladder is pulled up,
you stay in there, isolated all
night long, doing ceremony,
until the next morning, when
it's over and the ladder is
brought down. So it's I use it
as a metaphor of what a good
psychedelic session is like.
You're totally isolated from the
world. You don't get up and move
around, you don't talk a lot,
you don't engage with the
outside world. You're totally
isolated that way. You know that
whatever you're confronting is
coming from within yourself. Are
coming through yourself. It's
not You're not being triggered
by outside stimuli.
Tasshin Fogleman: Thank you for
explaining, helpful. Yeah,
there's a question on my mind
about your work, and in
particular, you know, it's
almost as if you're presenting
cosmological findings, and I
find them very persuasive,
personally, and, you know,
consistent with my own
explorations. And at the same
time, I there's a kind of
question of, like, why would
someone take these findings
seriously as some kind of, you
know, not just like an adventure
that you had or an inner
experience, but as something
that really says something about
the nature of reality? Yeah?
Chris Bache: Yeah. Good
question. And of course, the
critical question, how do we
know this is more than just? Why
isn't it just some kind of
echoes of my personal
unconscious, or echoes off the
collective unconscious, and not
something that really goes
beyond those canyon walls? And
here we have to get down there.
A couple of things. First are,
are the experiences replicable?
Do these experiences show up in
the psychedelic sessions of
other people? If it were just me
saying these things or
describing these levels of
reality, then that, if there's
just a one off, then it may be,
just as you say. It could be,
you know, just a personal kind
of indulgence, but these the
cosmology that emerges in
psychedelic states. First of
all, it's echoed in the work of
other psychedelicists, if they
you, if they're using a method
and a substance that has
sufficient power to break
through the same number of
layers. Basically there is a
convergence of experience that
emerges at these very deep
levels, so that when I'm
describing my experiences, other
psychedelic journeyers recognize
them. They recognize them as
reflecting their own experience
as well. What's important in
this context is to put all of
our experiences on the table
together, not just one person,
but everybody's experiences, and
by comparing all of our
experiences in the context of
the methodology that each of us
use to realize these
experiences, then we get a
better understanding of of what
is idiosyncratic and what is
common ground in that context.
My work, I think, is largely
comfortable within the common
ground that Grof has outlined as
he has integrated Hundreds 1000s
of psychedelic sessions from
hundreds of people through time.
But also, what emerges in a
psychedelic cosmology is not
unique to psychedelics
themselves, but it is the same
cosmology that emerges in deep
mystical traditions. In deep
spiritual traditions, the
contemplative traditions, there
are nuances of interpretation,
of course, and there are as
different mystical traditions
have different interpretive
canvases to articulate their
experiences. But if you do a
phenomenological analysis, if
you look at the lineages of
witnessing that come out of
world, mystical cultures, and
you compare them to what emerges
in psychedelic cosmology, they
fundamentally are the same
cosmology. So that, in that
sense, there's nothing unique in
what I'm saying, the only thing
that's unique is this particular
method of gaining access to
these dimensions of reality.
Tasshin Fogleman: Yeah, I think
the method is certainly unique,
and there, at least for me, some
of the findings that you share
feel novel or things that I
hadn't encountered previously. I
mean, in particular, the
emphasis on reincarnation as a
kind of process akin to
evolution and development in a
certain way. I mean, there are
similar things that I'd heard
elsewhere, but, but connecting
it to evolution in particular
feels feels novel. And then, you
know, other things as well, but
then that felt new. So you said
earlier that, you know, about
two or three years into this
process, that you started to
have a new understanding of the
work that you're doing, and it
was less about your own
personal, you know, blocks and
unblocking yourself. What was
that discovery and what did you
learn as that transitioned?
Chris Bache: Well, for the first
two and a half years, I was
plunged into a level of
consciousness that's at the very
bottom of the personal psyche.
It's a dimension that Stan calls
the perinatal level of
consciousness. It's it's at the
interface of the limits of
physical consciousness and the
beginning of spiritual
consciousness. So that,
typically, people relive their
own birth. They relive their
their fear of death. Birth and
death are the revolving door of
life. You know, we get here by
being born. We leave time and
space by dying. In order for
consciousness to expand beyond
time space reality, one has to
confront all that conditioning
in our psyche which tells us
that we are a time space self,
that I am my egoic physical
body, mind, awareness. And none
of us, from that perspective,
are really sure what happens to
us when we die. And many of us
believe there's nothing that
happens to us when we die. Death
is a cessation of all existence.
And we have all sorts of fears
surrounding death, and anxiety
surrounding death. And
basically, in the confrontation
with these perinatal dynamics,
one engages all those fears that
the universe is ultimately
meaningless, that the universe
completely destroys all of our
attempts to do something of
value, do something of enduring,
that something in our life will
endure. And one often re
experiences, one birth in the
same time. But eventually, if
you keep at it, this process
culminates in a in a particular
kind of existential crisis,
often called ego death. And your
your physical identity is
shattered. It's just absolutely
shattered, and then you
transition into a deeper level
of spiritual reality that lies
beyond the parameters of your
physical consciousness. Now. Is
very common in mystical
traditions. Mystical traditions
talk about the death of self,
Shunyata, emptiness of self.
Anata, no self. It's very common
in spiritual traditions, as well
as psychedelic traditions. It's
what happened next that really
kind of shifted my perspective.
I was expecting after going
through ego death, that I would
then have unfettered access into
a spiritual reality. But what
happened was the entire
purification process began again
at a different at a deeper
level, I began to get drawn into
exercises of vast collective
suffering, tremendous pain and
suffering, physical ordeals. It
was like being swallowed by
Dante's Inferno. And this went
on session after session for two
years, deeper and deeper into
these vast landscapes of
horrific pain and brutality and
suffering far beyond anything I
mean, my life has never touched
anything like that. It's never
known anything like that. And
this was a real puzzle for me,
because for a long time I
thought maybe this represented a
deeper ego death. But in time, I
eventually came to the
conclusion that no, this was not
about healing or cleansing my
personal psyche, that somehow in
my sessions, a shift had taken
place, and the focus had become
the healing of the entire human
species, that somehow I was
tapping into festering fields of
pain which were being held
within the collective
unconscious of our entire
species, that just as we
individually hold on to our
memories and experiences and
some of them are problematic,
the entire human species holds
on to the experiences of all of
its children, all of humanity.
And some of those experiences
are very, very traumatic, the
war, the experiences of war, the
experiences of drought, the
experiences of violence against
each other, these aggregate
within the collective psyche,
and they burden the collective
psyche, just as our individual
trauma burdens our personal
psyche. And that somehow at this
point in my sessions, I had been
kind of given the opportunity
and volunteered to cooperate
with this process where the by
making these vast tracks of pain
conscious, there was some way in
which these were being lifted
out of the collective psyche,
just as when you encounter
personal trauma in your personal
psyche and you confront it, it's
lifts that trauma out of your
personal system. And it was
after going through this for two
years that eventually there was
a crescendo of this process, a
huge healing process, which then
threw me into a yet still deeper
level of consciousness, and
that's when I began to really
understand that there are cycles
of death and rebirth in this
work, and that the cycles deepen
and change as the level of
consciousness that you are
working on deepens. So the first
level of healing and cleansing
was taking place at the
perinatal, our personal level of
consciousness. The second level
of healing was taking place at
the collective level of
consciousness. And then there
were levels of consciousness
that I went to that were even
deeper. But this cycle of death
and rebirth, purification and
transformation, is a cycle that
repeats itself multiple times,
if you keep going deeper into
the great expanse,
Tasshin Fogleman: what words
would you use to describe the
levels that you went to, beyond
personal and collective?
Chris Bache: When I was looking
back over the whole of my
journey, I basically divided it
into five broad overlapping
categories, working at the level
of personal mind, working at the
level of the collective mind,
then moving into archetypal
reality beyond beyond even the
collective psyche, and then the
level of causal reality, or the
one mind, where the entire
universe moves us one. And then
beyond that, entering, for the
last five years of my work, what
I came to call the diamond
Luminosity, an exceptionally.
Clear, hyper, hyper, clear
expression of pure light, which,
when I looked for religious
correlations, or spiritual
traditions correlations in
Buddhism, I think this is what
they call Dharmakaya, the clear
light of absolute reality out of
which existence springs. So
those five levels, personal
mind, collective mind,
archetypal mind, the one mind
and diamond Luminosity,
Tasshin Fogleman: I'd like to
return to that. Maybe one of the
themes in your work is, I think,
giving a really persuasive case
for reincarnation. And you know,
I was already, I already sort of
believed in reincarnation for my
own explorations, but it's a
really, really solid case that
you make for it, I think. And
you wrote a book, life cycles
about it, and then later on, in
your most recent book, LSD, in
the mind of the universe, you're
like, oh, there were some things
that I think I didn't quite get
to in that book. And I wonder if
you could describe your current
understanding of reincarnation.
Chris Bache: Well, as a
philosopher, I think
reincarnation is a fundamental
and important concept to
examine, because philosophical
traditions diverge. If you
believe that there is no
reincarnation, and if you
believe there is reincarnation,
you end up with two different
understandings of reality. So
one of the early things I did in
my academic career was really
look seriously at the question,
is there empirical evidence?
What's the state of empirical
evidence for reincarnation? Now,
50 years ago, this evidence what
did not exist, but today it
does. I think we have ample
empirical evidence that
reincarnation is a simple fact
of life. And the primary work
here comes from Ian Stevenson's
work studying young children
around the world who have
spontaneous, detailed memories
of their previous lifetime. And
the opportunity we have verified
these memories, and we have
separated out and really re
eliminated the possibility that
they could have acquired these
memories through natural means.
So for that and for evidence
from past life therapy that is a
strong philosophical case can be
made for reincarnation being a
simple fact of life. It doesn't
mean we understand how it takes
place. We don't understand the
physics of it. We may even have
a very incomplete understanding
of the project of it, what the
purpose of it is, and I
personally think that the
classic Eastern interpretation
of reincarnation I've come to
see is incomplete. It's a first
approximation, but it's not the
complete story. But because of
this available evidence, the
first book I wrote was on
reincarnation, which presented
the evidence and then asked,
okay, so, What? What? So, what
if reincarnation is a fact of
life? What does this tell us
about the way the universe
works? The classic story, and
the story that I used in telling
that story, the classic story of
reincarnation, is a story of the
individual soul or individual
consciousness, making choices,
inheriting the consequences of
those choices, which out of
which, they then make new
choices. So there is a learning
cycle between choosing and
inheriting, choosing inheriting,
and this takes place within a
lifetime, and it takes place
across multiple lifetimes, but
it's the story of the individual
soul into becoming individually
more spiritually mature, more
capable, more compassionate,
more talented, so on and so
forth. In there. It's an
individual story. What I found
in my psychedelic work when I
began to open up into the
collective psyche, and deep
within the collective fields of
consciousness, is that in
addition to this individual
story, there was a collective
story that the entire human
species, and some fundamental
ways, operates as a single
organism, There is an
intelligence that's operating
within the entire species, and
that all of our individual
incarnations were profoundly and
subtly integrated into the
integration of this group,
species of this group, and that
there was a way in which the
intelligence of the species was
manifesting itself in certain
patterns of detoxification,
purification, breakthrough that
were happening collectively. So
it wasn't just individual
choices driving it all, but
there were also collective
choices and a collective
intelligence driving the entire
process. Yes, I also was given a
came into a series of
experiences that gave me a
different understanding of where
reincarnation is taking
humanity. Because the classic
Eastern vision is that
reincarnation evolves you to a
certain point until you have a
core breakthrough. The Hindus
called it moksha, escape, where
we escape ego, but we also
escape Samsara. We escape
physical existence. So the basic
vision here is, you achieve
moksha, or you achieve nirvana,
and then when you die, you
achieve parin Nirvana, final
nirvana. But the goal is to
achieve some type of spiritual
fruition, which then allows you
to graduate from space time and
to rest in some spiritual
paradise off planet, whether
it's the Muslim garden or the
Christian heaven or the Buddha
pure land. It's some off planet
paradise. But that, of course,
leaves unanswered what is the
purpose of time and space? Which
was okay, as long as we were
thinking that time and space had
only been around for a few 1000
years, but now that we
understand that we're talking
billions and billions of years
of evolution of time and space.
It doesn't seem to really be a
very satisfying account that to
say that after all these
millions of years, billions of
years and millions of years of
evolution of Homo sapiens, it's
all the work that has gone into
learning how to walk upright and
use and become a tool user. And
about 5000 years ago, we became
conscious of this deep common
ground of the psyche that as
soon as we begin to become
conscious of this underlying,
encompassing Buddha nature, our
essential nature, as soon as we
become aware, then we leave. The
goal is just to leave. And what
happened in my sessions was
something quite different, at a
pivotal session, and I'd done
past life therapy before. I
mean, not in the psychedelic
work, but, you know,
hypnotherapy I was familiar with
a dozen or so had worked with
healing and integrating a dozen
or so of my former lives. But in
this session, my former lives
started coming into me. They
were coming into me, and it was
like wrapping filaments of white
light around a kite spool more
and more consciousness, more and
more lives were coming into me.
They had been healed. They were
coming into and they reached a
point where they fused all of
these individual lives fused
into one life. And when they
fused, I was there was an
explosion of diamond light from
my chest, and I was catapulted
into a state of awareness that
was beyond anything I had known
up to that point in time. I was
an individual, but I was an
individual beyond any frame of
reference that I had previously
known. And this I came to
understand as the birth of the
diamond soul. I language it
other people give it different
words, but it's basically the
guy idea here is that
reincarnation doesn't just grow
us individually, layer by layer,
class by class, you know,
challenge by challenge, but
there comes a time when our
entire history is aggregated and
integrates into a single
consciousness, and at that
point, that single consciousness
becomes one's working identity.
So basically, what's happening
is the soul is becoming born
inside history and by soul. I
think there are ways of
understanding the soul that are
completely compatible with the
Buddhist teaching on anata and
no self, because this is not an
egoic soul. It's not a soul of
boundaries, it's not a soul of
of that's inherently self
centered in its appetites. But
once the soul emerges there,
it's a tremendous breath of
intellect, Breath of compassion
and a deep communion with the
spiritual forces of the
universe. And so the goal of
reincarnation is not simply to
evolve us to the point where we
become spiritually awake and
leave but the goal is to evolve
us to the point where truly we
become a the next iteration of
human evolution, we become a
species of incarnate souls, so
that we are never tempted to
take our private ego as our true
identity. But we know ourselves
to be of this time traveler. We
know ourselves to be de. Deeper
than that, and we know we have
kinship relations with so many
1000s of people, and we have
kinship relationship with the
earth. We know that the Earth
that we leave will be the earth
will inherit in our next
incarnation. Souls live on Earth
differently than egos do, and I
think that's the I think that's
the pivot we're in the process
of making now, and I understand
four or 5000 years ago, in the
Axial Age, when we first began
to make discoveries of this
spiritual reality, the spiritual
reality, which is so much more
satisfying than time, space
reality, it would develop an up
and out cosmology, the theology,
which says the purpose is to go
home. We don't believe belong
here. This is our fallen
condition. We don't want to stay
here. We want to go back to
where we came from. I understand
that, but I think it's an
incomplete understanding of the
deeper project of creation. The
project of creation is to awake
and bring heaven to earth, to
live the Buddha world here
inside our physical existence.
Tasshin Fogleman: What do you
feel in so, you know, so in my
own life, I've been really moved
by Buddhism and inspired by
Buddhism and certainly other
traditions as well. And I find
what you're saying compelling
that, you know, there, there was
an incomplete truth to the
teachings offered in the Axial
Age where there's there's wisdom
to them and and benefit, and yet
it's also incomplete. And I
wonder how you would describe
the relationship of the
perspectives that you hold now
in to the teachings that we may
have received from the past, and
perhaps Buddhism in particular.
Chris Bache: Well, once again, I
want to emphasize that the work
I did is a path of temporary
immersion. Temporary immersion
does not easily or
conventionally lead to permanent
shifts in awareness, you have to
do a lot of spiritual practice
before any of the things that we
experience in the temporary
condition, the psychedelic,
amplified condition, can become
our ordinary daily
consciousness. And so the great
masters of the spiritual
traditions and the great masters
of the Buddhist tradition have
always been my heroes, and their
teachings have always been my
guiding light in terms of how to
engage the psychedelic states in
a responsible manner, how to
invest in them in a way which
leads can be converted into, or
leads to long term
transformations of one's
baseline consciousness on this
earth. So first, truly,
genuinely, all honor to the
Great Beings of these
traditions. And at the same
time, we know that there is
patriarchy, for example, in the
Buddhist traditions and Buddhism
has had to clear itself of its
patriarchy, just as other
religious traditions have. I
think there are other
limitations. There is a kind of
anti physical, a disparagement
of the physical body, which is a
subtle disparagement of nature,
which itself is becoming aware
of and is having to transcend. I
think there are elements within
Buddhism that have a deep
appreciation of the joy of
living the Buddha nature, and
sees that the Buddha nature is
intended to be lived within time
and space, that Samsara truly is
Nirvana, when understood
completely, Nirvana does not
require an abandonment of
Samsara, but actually is
coherent with Samsara, and yet
they're the mainstream sources
of Buddhism. For the popular
people, still have kind of an up
and out cosmology, working in
Christianity too. You achieve
salvation, and then you escape
to go to heaven. So I think, as
an historian, is simply a matter
of, you know, understanding the
historical context within which
these great masters were
working, and which helped them
and hindered them in some ways,
from the, you know, the full
expression, giving full
expression of their spiritual
realization. And yet, in, in.
And even if you're working
spiritually within an incomplete
cosmology, the levels of
spiritual realization which can
be achieved is just
extraordinary. What great
masters can do, the great
mahasiddhis of the lineages can
do, is just extraordinary and
deserving of all respect. So in
criticizing the cosmology within
which some of them operate,
that's not to criticize the
level of spiritual realization
that they have achieved, nor I
want to emphasize again, to have
had unusually deep spiritual
experiences in a psychedelic
state is not to have stabilized
those experiences any meaningful
way in one's ordinary
consciousness. There is still a
great deal of work to do before
those states of awareness can
become abiding in any serious
sense. So I always want to
qualify the insights that emerge
in psychedelic work,
Tasshin Fogleman: yes, yes, and
certainly for myself, this is a
question that comes from a place
of deep respect. I mean,
Buddhism is, is like, like my
home in a certain way, so, but I
appreciate the clarifications
that you add to it. And I
wonder, you know, you spoke
earlier about your own spiritual
practice and the different
traditions that you've been
exposed to, and it seems like
you found sort of a home in
Vajrayana Buddhism is that?
Chris Bache: Is that right? It
is, and it's a kind of a
modified Vajrayana, because I
was doing kind of intense
Vajrayana practice for a number
of years, and I've modified it
from my own psychedelic
experiences, because I've come
To understand that I have it's
not that I've realized the
states that I encountered in my
deep psychedelic work, but I
have an understanding and
experience of those levels of
reality. They live inside me as
memories. They are active
memories. And so I've developed
forms of Vajrayana practice.
I've expanded them by actively
integrating those memories into
the realization protocols. So
for example, you know, in
classic Vajrayana practice, we
distinguish between the Samaya
Safa and the Jnana sattva. The
Samaya Sava is the being of
construct. It's the being we
formulate through our mantras,
through our visualizations and
using of tankas and exercises to
create some approximation of
pure goodness, pure insight,
which then attracts the
jananissa for the reality, the
cosmic reality. So we we make
our visualization pure in order
to open a channel between the
cosmic reality, which then we
invite to pour His blessings
into us. Well, in a way, I use
my psychedelic memories as part
of constructing my Samaya Safa.
To me, the living memory of the
diamond Luminosity is a more
effective spiritual vehicle of
practice than the beautiful
tankers that attempt to give
some type of physical expression
of the sublime perfection. Okay,
so I modify it in that way. I
also have a sense, because I've
died so many times, and because
I've gone where I will go when I
die physically, I've gone into
that domain so many times. I
feel a deep comfortableness with
it, and I feel a familiarity
with that domain. And I think
this changes one's practice,
because we're told over and over
again, we practice in order to
prepare for the moment of death,
because the moment of death is
the great potential, has great
potential for accelerating our
evolution. And I agree with
that, and I tried to live that
in my psychedelic practice has
been done in a way to prepare me
for the moment of death, and the
net result of it is that I feel
very comfortable with death, and
I feel very comfortable with
being able to navigate what
comes after death, because I
feel like I've already
encountered it in many ways.
Tasshin Fogleman: Mm. What do
you think it was about Adriana
Buddhism that attracted you and
felt like you could
metaphorically find a find a
home there?
Chris Bache: Well, it was my
first wife, Carol, who was my
sitter in my sessions, a
clinical psychologist herself
who really brought me into
vadrana. I was kind of
esthetics. I was more interested
in the Zen tradition. I really
wasn't interested with all the
bills and candles and incense
and, you know, all the fanfare
that comes with Vajrayana. But
she went there, and I basically
followed her there, and through
her, met the teachers that were
gathering and came through Tara
mandala Buddhist retreat center,
Lama sutra malayonis established
the center in Colorado and began
to study with her and go into
retreats with the Teachers of
that lineage. And so I met their
lineage of awakened beings, and
they made a deep impression on
me. If my karma had been such as
to introduce me to the great
awakened beings of the Zen
lineage, then, you know, I could
have gone there just as easily.
But it was just the opportunity
to meet these beings, to receive
teachings from them that made a
large impression on me.
Tasshin Fogleman: And coming
back to your explorations, use
the phrase deep time. Can you
say what you mean by that? Yeah,
I
Chris Bache: when I first began
to enter the ocean of suffering,
when I made the transition
outside of egoic after ego
death, and I went into these
episodes of collective anguish
when I came every session is
divided into sort of two halves.
There's a purification half
followed by an ecstatic half. So
you go through the purification
half, and if you submit to it,
it comes to a crescendo, a
breakthrough, and then you're
spun into a Transpersonal of
section of teachings, and
ecstatic in teachings and next
and so on so forth. So when I
was being, when I was thrown,
after this very intense
collective purification, I began
to enter into states of
consciousness that were
extremely novel and
unprecedented for me, and I
came, I first called it whole
time, and I came to call it deep
time. I began to have
experiences of my entire life
start to finish as a completed
toll. It was like every time
moment in my life was in a tree.
Was a tree, and I experienced
the whole of my life as a single
tree. I experienced my old age,
my middle age. I experienced the
themes of my life as
simultaneously present. This was
such a dramatic expansion of my
cognitive frame of reference
that after the session, I
couldn't hold on to it. It
disappeared. I forgot it. I
couldn't hold it. But I found
that with repetition, going back
into that state again and again,
and it was I was always taken
into the same reality for a
year, for seven sessions, by
returning to it and working very
diligently to stabilize your
state of consciousness there. I
learned how to hold on to it. I
learned to remember it. I
learned how to become
cognitively competent in deep
time. And what I've came to
believe was that there, there
are really many multiple
modalities of time operating
within the universe. Later,
after this period when I went
still deeper in my work, going
in toward archetypal reality, I
experienced larger swaths of
time than just my personal life.
The first was my personal life
about maybe 100 years. But then
I began to experience whole
time, or deep time, in terms of
100,000 year increments, and
maybe even larger later. And
basically, not only was my sense
of time expanding, but who the
being was, who was having those
experiences was expanding. So
it's not simply like you take a
disembodied ego and have an
experience of Transpersonal
reality, which you then bring
back, but literally, your ego is
shattered and you dissolve. Into
a deeper level of consciousness.
And it is that deeper level of
consciousness that opens up into
these deeper levels of time and
then instill deeper you
literally become a different
being than simply a discarnate
egoic presence. You become a
different being for hours and
hours at a time. So you're
dissolved into the fabric of
existence and dissolved into the
fabric of existence, you
sometimes have experiences of
how existence itself experiences
time. Now, there are some trends
in physics today that are
hypothesizing that just as super
String Theory hypothesizes
multiple dimensions of existence
beyond time and space, that some
of these dimensions of existence
that physics is conceptualizing
involve different modalities of
time, I don't know what the
relationship is exactly between
that and what my experiences is,
but my experience is that as you
go to the edges of space time,
you enter into different
modalities of time, and
different sets of insights
emerge in these different
modalities of time. Now I
understand how absurd this
sounds to my academic colleagues
and my scientific colleagues,
who generally tend to think that
the entire universe works within
linear time. There is an arrow
of time. Tachyons may move
backwards in time, but basically
the universe moves forward in
time, and it's an absolute
limit. I think the very best of
the edge of quantum thinking
goes beyond that. And certainly
my psychological, my psycho
spiritual experiences go beyond
that. Time became very porous in
my work, as did all my
boundaries in the work.
Tasshin Fogleman: I imagine,
it's difficult to put into
words, but is there anything
more that you can say about what
the experience of that is like,
like, either with your own
personal life, seeing the whole
of it at once, or the larger
scales?
Chris Bache: Well, first, once
you acclimate to it, it's not
confusing at all. It's clear,
very, very clear. It's it's
simply a different way of
relating to time. Insights
emerge out of the fabric, out of
an extended fabric of time, for
example, at the personal level,
when I experienced my my life as
a completed whole, naturally, I
understood the deep structure of
my life better than I had
before. I understood some of the
themes of my life. I understood
how things that I had been
concerned with and the recurring
issues of my philosophical
inquiry in my personal life,
that those issues were deeply
etched in life and would be
consuming me for the entirety of
my life. I could, I could see
and feel my future. You don't. I
didn't see all the details. It's
not like seeing all the details
of your life, but it is as
though all your time moments
congeal, to give you a deep
reading of what the substance of
your life is about. Likewise,
when you dissolve into the human
species, and you dissolve into a
large swath of time on the order
of hundreds of 1000s of years
you have, there are insights
that arise in that context about
the developmental stages of
human evolution. So I began to
have experiences, not just to my
personal future, but of
humanity's future. And I know
again, I know this sounds
arrogant and like ego run amok,
but it's the most natural thing
in the world that when you
dissolve into the condition of
the full species mind, and you
dissolve into deep time
simultaneously, it's just
natural that some of the
developmental future, what is
from our present, the future of
this species comes into view.
But when you experience that,
you don't experience it as
something yet to be. You
experience it as something that
already has been. And both of
those are held simultaneously.
It is yet to be, and it's also
something that has been so it
has a certainty about it, and I
don't know how to to work out or
reconcile all of these things
with free will and any number of
different questions. But there
is just a there's a breadth of
understanding that opens. So
that not only did I begin to
understand better what my
personal life was about, but I
began to understand the time in
history that humanity has
entered, that it's coming into a
developmental crisis. It's
coming into an evolutionary
pivot point, and some of the
characteristics of that crisis
and the characteristics of a
breakthrough, which I think is
coming, these all emerge, or
these all become possible by
shedding just the limitations of
linear time as we conventionally
know it, and going into deeper
dimension of time. I was
Tasshin Fogleman: definitely
thinking about free will just
now, and I it makes sense that
it would be difficult to address
that on a large scale
philosophically. I mean, it's a
long, long debate, but I wonder
what sensibilities these
experiences gave you about your
own life and free will and
choices, and you know, sort of
having a sense of your whole
life, did, did you feel sort of
like you're fated to make
certain choices, or that you had
free Will in it, or how did that
impact you personally?
Chris Bache: Yeah, free will is
a tricky topic, isn't it, and
much of our popular discussion
of it, I find just not very
satisfying to skim the surface.
Advocates of Free Will over tend
to understate the level of
conditioning that qualifies our
freedom. And people who believe
that the determinism of our
conditioning is so profound that
we may feel like we're free, but
if you examine it really
carefully, you find out that
your conditions are so highly
conditioned, your choices are so
highly conditioned that there
really isn't free will there. I
find a lot of that discussion
just not very satisfying on
either front
Unknown: to me, one
Chris Bache: of the themes that
has come through repeatedly in
my work is that we do, we do
have free will. It's a
conditioned free will, but we
have within those conditions the
opportunity to make choices. If
we didn't have the opportunity
to make choices, we wouldn't be
truly learning. There really
wouldn't be an adventure of
learning. If when we incarnate,
we were simply just inheriting a
predetermined fate, then we're
just basically going through the
process of mechanical
actualization, and it wouldn't
be a genuine learning exercise
if you can't make mistakes, if
you can't truly come to
crosswords and roads and say,
Well, I'm going to go either A
or B. Which one should I do? And
that's a true choice, a genuine
choice, which has learning
ramifications, then we wouldn't
be it wouldn't be an adventure
in learning. And I don't think,
I think the universe wants us to
learn it. List the messages that
I get is that freedom is an
absolutely important quality.
Now it's always relative at
early stages. Is very little
freedom when grass grows, it
doesn't have a lot of freedom in
terms of how to respond to
photosynthesis and so on, so
forth. But the more our
consciousness develops, the more
choice enters into the picture.
The more individuated
consciousness becomes, the more
the cycle of learning becomes
more important. And still, our
choice is conditioned. But the
conditioning gets lighter and
lighter, the sense of freedom
being able to make clear choices
emerges, but to make free
choices, to make clear choices,
require certain self conscious
practice of stepping out of the
conditioning of our mind. And of
course, the meditation
traditions are well aware of
this. Because when we quiet the
mind, what we become very aware
of is all the multiple voices
that are going on inside us and
all the layers of conditioning
that are conditioning our moment
to moment awareness. And we have
to patiently strip those away.
We have to let them exhaust
themselves, and as we do, that
clarity of unconditioned
consciousness begins to Dawn
within our awareness, right? And
that becomes that is such a
novel experience and so distinct
from conditioned. Consciousness,
that it becomes the very highly
desirable state to cultivate to
enter our true nature, our
unconditioned nature. I think
these insights replicate
themselves in psychedelic work
as well, that what one
encounters that in psychedelic
work is conditioning. You're
throwing off layer and layer and
layer and layer of conditioning,
purifying, purifying. It's like
all one long ndrew, all one long
practice of purification to
uncover what is already there,
but something which has been
covered over by that
conditioning. Now in
cosmological exploration, you
are going beyond what is simply
uncovering what is already
there, but that still remains
part of the one of the core
dynamics is letting go of the
conditioning to have a deeper
experience of the clarity that's
present in the immediate
conditions of one's awakened
mind.
Tasshin Fogleman: Can you say
more about the sort of visions
that you had for humanity's
future and the time that we're
in?
Chris Bache: This was one of the
great surprises for me in there,
because I never expected
anything like this to emerge in
my work. I thought this was
about personal transformation,
or even personal enlightenment,
or something like that. I never
imagined that the evolution of
the species would become such a
dominant theme in my work. What
happened was going all the way
back to about halfway through
the work, back into the early
early 90s. Starting in 1991 I
began to have a series of
visions. They were just dropped
into my sessions, a series of
visions that humanity was coming
to a turning point. This was a
true before and after point in
history. This was we were
entering a time of intense
purification, that we were
basically purifying the human
psyche of the sins of our
father, so to speak, purifying
ourselves, lifting the
conditioning of the past in
order to make us more receptive
to and capable of internalizing,
spiritual infusion, spiritual
insights and power that was
coming into us, becoming made
available to us at This time in
history. So there was a
tremendous sense of rebirth
coming. And all of this was
contextualized within an initial
experience of experiencing
creation in terms of love, that
that the act of creation, the
Big Bang is not simply a
generative acts of power or an
act of intelligence, but it
actually is an act of love, that
creation is itself an act of
love, of cosmic love, and
therefore that all the suffering
which is, which takes place, has
taken place since the Big Bang.
All the suffering in the human
story in particular, all that
suffering takes place in the
context of love. This is not
something which is being done to
us. It's not something which we
are guilty we are in any way
guilty about. This is all part
of a creative process that we
entered into voluntarily. We
entered into by choice. And it
is hard. It's very difficult,
but it is a Noble gift that we
are giving to the creative
process to participate in the
evolution of this species at
such an early and barbaric time
in its life that we do these
terrible things to each other.
But all of this was coming to a
crescendo, a moment in history
where we would pivot into a
higher order, a higher order of
spiritual awareness, a higher
order of psycho spiritual
realization. So this went on for
years, and eventually I
cataloged these in the book in a
section that I call the visions
of awakening six core visions,
and that the creative
intelligence was trying not just
to awaken individuals, but it
was trying to awaken the entire
species, but it gave me no
insight into how it was going to
pull this off. I had no idea how
it could possibly achieve this
type of breakthrough in human
evolution. And then in 1995 Of
right before Christmas in 1995 I
had a session in which I was
taken deep into deep time. I was
dissolved into the species so
there was no more Chris Bache, I
just dissolved completely into
the species and taken into deep
time and experienced the death
and rebirth of humanity in a
transtemporal context. So I
experienced a time in history of
increasing destabilization of
two of chaos and tumultuous
unraveling. The systems of life
were being unraveled. There
seemed to be wave after wave of
ecological crises that
eventually triggered a global
systems crisis, a period of
breakdown of structures at
deeper and deeper levels, an
unraveling of life. We were
losing control of life. We were,
it wasn't. We couldn't, kind of
fix our way out of this. This
was a profound shattering of
life as we had known it. At the
core
Unknown: and in the
Chris Bache: midst of this, at
the point where it looked like
we were all going to die, it was
as if a storm passed over the
island like a hurricane passing
over a Pacific Island. And the
winds began to subside. The
metaphorical winds began to
subside. And the worst of the
crisis past, and we began to
pick ourselves up off our knees.
And as we picked ourselves up
off our knees and began to
rebuild and reconnect and put
together life. On the other side
of this crisis, we were we found
that we were different beings.
We were not the same as we had
been when we went into this
crisis. There's something that
happens in this multi
generational crisis, and I don't
have beyond what I've said. I
don't have any details of when,
where or how. It wasn't that
kind of experience. It was the
fact that humanity was coming
into a profound crisis at a
global level, a global systems
crisis, that something about
this transformation would break
through the deep layers of
conditioning of the human heart,
would tear away all the self
centered behaviors, not only of
individuals, but of our culture,
would just break us down. And
when we moved through this
crisis, we discovered values
inside our being. We discovered
new values, new insights, new
ways of being in the world, new
ways of being with each other.
This wasn't simply the birth of
an ecologically responsible
civilization. It wasn't simply a
cultural rebirth, but it
literally represented a shift in
the core structure of the human
psyche. This was a shift in the
plate tectonics of the
collective psyche that, anyway,
that was the vision of it. And I
think that the if, in my
experience, does I examine what
the nature of this future human
is? What is this future human
that's so much more than the
present human is? What is it?
And I think it is the emergence
of the diamond soul and history.
I think that we have been
growing the diamond soul,
gestating the diamond soul for
incarnation after incarnation
for 10s of 1000s of years,
hundreds of 1000s of years. But
the birth of the diamond soul in
history is a relatively short,
traumatic, convulsive period.
Gestation is long. Birth is
short. I think we are entering a
time in history where we can no
longer afford the luxury of a
planet run by egos, even well
intentioned egos. We have to
grow up. We have to grow into a
deeper, our deeper spiritual
identity. And that deeper
spiritual identity is the
diamond stole, or the soul, or
however you want to language
this, we need to grow up. And I
think that we have entered this
crisis, this beginning, the
very, very early stages of an
unraveling of life as we have
known it, and we are going into
a future. And I think it's
really important to have a
vision. That's why, at the end
of the book, I really focus on
the visions that I was given of
the future human. Because if we
don't have an understanding of
what's going on, if we don't
have a vision of what nature is
in the process of producing,
then the pain will be so intense
we could survive. Come to
despair and some terrible
apocalyptic interpretation that
would be very counter our
survival, and I think we need to
have a deep understanding where
nature is taking us.
Tasshin Fogleman: How does this
phrase that use diamond soul
relate to the diamond Luminosity
that you began to experience in
your own sessions. Is it the
same thing or something
different?
Chris Bache: I think it's a
variation of the same thing, the
diamond Luminosity I
experienced, I believe, to be a
level of reality in the cosmos.
I mean, in Buddhist terminology,
I would describe it as an extra
samsaric reality, which means
it's beyond cyclic existence,
which means it's beyond the
Bardo. There are many, many,
many layers of the Bardo.
There's the low animal hell
realms, there's the high deity
realms, but the diamond
Luminosity is beyond all of
those. And there is a clear
sensation, a phenomenological
difference between experiencing
the high deity realms and then
moving into the diamond
Luminosity realms, which is
beyond all deities, beyond
archetypes, beyond any of this
dimension. Now, when the soul
congealed in my being and the
diamond Luminosity, the soul
exploded from my chest. It had
that same quality of light as
the diamond Luminosity, but a
slightly lower intensity of that
light. Now let me back up. We
experience light many times in
the psychedelic journey. It's
very common. When you go through
ego death, you enter light. You
encounter when you enter
collective dimensions, you
experience dimensions of light.
I had known light many times the
diamond Luminosity is not simply
using a fancy metaphor to
describe this light. I learned
that there are many degrees of
light. There are many dimensions
of light, and the diamond
Luminosity is an exceptionally
pure, exceptionally clear
dimension of light. I think the
diamond soul, as an assay light
being is a manifestation of this
quality of light inside
individuated existence. So it's,
on the one hand, it's the same,
and on the other hand, it's a
variation on the same. I
wouldn't want to say it's
necessarily identical, but it
seems to be very, very close. I
will say that when I entered the
diamond Luminosity work over
five years, basically, I only
entered what I call the diamond
Luminosity four times, and I
entered it about once a year for
four years. So I would do it
very intense purification for
session after session, I would
tap into the diamond Luminosity.
Then I would be brought back for
another year, very, very intense
purification before being
brought back into the diamond
Luminosity again. So it wasn't
like accessing it easily and
ever once gained access, I only
touched that reality four times
in its total purity,
Tasshin Fogleman: from the way
you're describing I'm getting a
sense of almost like, you know,
the scientific name for humanity
currently is, like Homo sapiens,
and almost like a different kind
of humanity. Like, I don't know
the Latin term for Diamond, but
like diamond human, or something
like that is, is that consistent
with what you're saying?
Chris Bache: It is, people give
it different names. Some people
call it Homo noeticus, a knowing
humanity, homo spiritualis. Some
people call it homo luminance, a
light humanity. I think many of
us have this intuition that
humanity is going into a next
iteration. You know, there was a
time about 100,000 years ago
where the size of our brain
basically increased 50% I mean,
in a very short period of time,
suddenly we were dealing with a
much larger brain. Nature
triggered it decided to give us
a bigger brain that we came in
with larger equipment, something
like that is happening now. We
are cooperating with an
evolutionary process, but we are
we are not driving the process.
Nature is driving this process.
Nature is bringing us into this
new condition. And we have many
people have this intuition. Many
indigenous cultures have this
intuition of this time of global
crisis followed by breakthrough,
and there's no absolute
certainty you know that we will
survive birth. Is the dangerous
time. Not all fetuses survive
the birth process. So it's not
like this is a foregone
conclusion, but so many beings
have had this intuition, and
they they bring different names
for describing this future
human. Hmm,
Tasshin Fogleman: there's a term
that you borrow from Grof of
COEX systems, and then you
describe meta Coex systems. And
I think a lot of what you're
talking about seems related to
that. I wonder if you could
verbally describe what those are
and and explain those a little
bit.
Chris Bache: What Stan found is
that the psyche organizes its
experiences. It organizes its
memories in terms of clusters,
thematically integrated
clusters, so that it if it takes
all of our experiences of
abandonment, and all of those
experiences that we've had
around abandonment form one
tight experiential cluster,
which he calls a Coex system, or
a system of condensed
experience. Carl Jung called it
a complex we could have,
experiences around anger,
experiences around fear,
experiences around unrequited
love that they basically it's
kind of like reading a novel,
taking all the emotions that
take place in the novel,
highlighting with different
colors, cutting up the novel and
taking all the green in one ball
and all The yellow and another
ball and all the red and another
ball. That when we encounter a
problem in the psyche, we don't
simply encounter one form of
that problem. We encounter a
cluster of experiences that date
back, sometimes all the way into
our birth experience, and
sometimes including former
lives. But we when we melt this
problem, we melt it in layers.
We first we melt the outside
layers, the less problematic
until we eventually get to the
very, very core. What was the
seed problem? Which may date
from this lifetime, may date
from birth, may date from a
former lifetime, and we dissolve
this cluster, this COIC system.
Now my experience has been that
the same is true for the
collective psyche, that the mind
of the universe and the mind of
our species stores its history
in these massive thematic
clusters. So all the trauma
associated with war, all the
trauma of drought and dying in
the plains, all the trauma of
male female violence, all these
patterns of violence and pain
and suffering, fear of death,
that these don't exist as free
floating private existences,
private memories within the
Bardo of our individual souls,
but the collective psyche
aggregates its history into
these massive collective
structures that I call metacoic
systems. So you have co
existence within the personal
psyche and metacoag systems
within the collective psyche. I
think when I was moved into the
ocean of suffering, what was
happening was my system was
engaging metacoic systems within
the collective psyche, and
making some small contribution
to removing those clusters from
the collective psyche, not all
of them, certainly not any of
one all the way down. This is a
work of generations and all
spiritual traditions, the saints
and sages and contemplatives
have the same experience. They
all tap into levels of suffering
which are not personal, which go
deeper. And that's why
bodhichitta, manifesting the
will to save all sentient beings
is the only appropriate
motivation for doing spiritual
practice. Because you quickly
realize that this is a game
that's not a personal game, it's
not a private game. We're in
this together. It's a collective
evolutionary process. So for me,
that engages medical systems.
What?
Tasshin Fogleman: What is this
species aiming at, as you
understand
Chris Bache: it, oh, I think we
are. We are, I don't know that
we can really identify aiming
at, but we are constantly
growing. We are, if anything, we
are aiming at growing. Because
if we. Think that if we identify
what we're growing to what we're
really doing is only identifying
the next stage of our
evolutionary growing, but if we
just look around, it's taken us
13 point 7 billion years to get
to here. And assuming we survive
this crisis, we're going to be
at it for millions and billions
of years more so whatever this
crisis is that humanity is
coming into and growing beyond,
to grow beyond ego, to grow
beyond the narrow confines of
our self centered self clinging,
to go into a larger sense of our
being and presence in the
universe and communion with the
universe. This is just the next
phase, and we will have more
thresholds and more challenges
that will take us into yet
another phase. So if I step back
from all of that and I say, what
is happening here? What is the
project? I think the project is
to grow and become more than we
were before. It's a process
description, it's not a it's not
a content description, it's a
process description, just to
grow and become more than we
were, to be more capable. Now, I
think another aspect of this,
just on the short term, all the
spiritual teachings teach us
that the essence of the
individual is the same as the
essence of the totality. Atman
is Brahman. We are made of the
stuff of the Divine if we speak
of it in divine languages. Or
our Buddha nature, our awakened
nature, is the same as the
Buddha nature of all living
things, of all things. So when
one awakens to one's essential
nature, you're awakening to the
love and the compassion and the
power that created the universe,
that manifests the universe. And
that there are many stages to
this process, but first there is
the joy of awakening to that,
but then there is the process of
learning how to actualize that,
so that one's life becomes a
conscious manifestation of the
power of our essential nature
manifesting in the physical
world. And I don't, I really
don't want to reduce this to
such simplistic philosophies
like you become like what you
love and and as you think is
what becomes your destiny, but
something basically that
recognizes that the experience,
what the experiences that come
at us in the outer world are in
some core way of reflection of
what is coming out of us at a
deep psycho spiritual level. And
that once you understand that
there is this feedback process
between what we are putting out
and what is coming back to us,
and you take responsibility for
that process, then you begin to
consciously manifest your chosen
destiny, rather than inherit a
destiny which has been created
by your unconscious process. So
that we are becoming at this
stage, I think conscious
creators of our own destiny, we
wake up and we become we're
basically learning how to become
creators, because our nature is
the creative principle. Our
Nature is the same as the nature
which manifested the entire
physical universe. So what we're
learning how to do is first
discover and then actualize, and
then participate consciously in
creation, inside time and space,
what we do with that, where we
take that as a species? You
know, just imagine what we can
do a species operating out of
that kind of consciousness.
Tasshin Fogleman: Yeah, I'm
getting the sense, you know,
coming back to the question I
asked earlier about, like, what
is maybe incomplete about
Buddhism or other earlier
teachings. And, you know, there
the sensibility that I at least
received was like, you know,
existence is a cycle of birth
and death that is, in some ways,
sort of like hellish, and you
should just escape. And that's
the goal is to escape and get
out. And from what I'm hearing
from you, it's almost as if both
on individual and collective
levels, the aim isn't to escape,
but to learn and grow and evolve
and have incompre increased
complexity and nuance and
understanding of oneself and the
universe, and really to manifest
that rather than just like
getting out or eradicating this
or something like that.
Chris Bache: Yeah. Yeah, yes, I
think so. And in the end, once
we make this transition, we
understand that what we have
escaped is not time and space,
but we've escaped a certain
mental consciousness associated
a constricted consciousness
that's associated with our
living inside time and space,
but when that bubble pops, when
we have truly escaped that small
world, we experience time and
space completely differently. We
experience time and space as the
Buddha world, as the Buddha
nature.
Tasshin Fogleman: If you don't
mind me asking, what is your
everyday consciousness like now
after all of these experiences
and explorations?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, I wish
I could tell you that I'm a
fully enlightened being, and I
just cruise in the cosmic planes
all the time, but that's not the
case, integrating in my
integrating these experiences is
a lifelong undertaking, in fact,
and the more I'm thinking about
it in the 20 years after I
stopped this work, the more I
appreciate just how Large the
integration process is even to
the point that I really, I don't
really think we know how
entering these deep levels of
reality is is influencing us as
human beings. I think we're just
scratching the surface if we're
working in therapeutic work, and
if we're bringing out issues
from the personal unconscious,
then we have a model for how to
integrate those experiences. If
we go deeper and have spiritual
experiences of the intelligence
that runs through all of life,
we have spiritual models for how
we might integrate those
experiences. But when we go
really, really deep, when we go
beyond space and time, when we
enter deep, dissolve into the
luminous body of creation, how
are those experiences being
integrated in us? Then in the
end, I don't think you can
integrate the infinite into the
finite The only thing you can do
is integrate your finite
existence into infinity. And
that brings us back to the nuts
and bolts of spiritual practice.
You must remove from your being
everything which keeps smaller
than the reality that you are
seeking to enter into and that's
a that's a lifelong undertaking.
I used to think that maybe by
the end of my lifetime, maybe I
would have succeeded in
integrating all of these
experiences. Now I think that
that's too optimistic. I think
this work changed not only my
present lifetime, but it changed
the trajectory of my entire
soul's evolution. I also want to
say that I've kind of come to
the conclusion that I pushed
myself harder and farther on
this work than was really
probably wise for me. I think
that it is possible to go too
deep in one lifetime. And it's
not that the suffering is
problematic. It's not that the
pain that's inherent in
purifying it there's very, very
deep levels is problematic. It's
the joy. It's the ecstasy. It's
being dissolved, the ecstasy of
being dissolved into unspeakable
beauty and intelligence, which
can make your physical existence
kind of feel dried up like not
worth living. And I think I have
suffered from that after
stopping my work, I've really
had to make conscious choices
and lifestyle choices, how to
manage the memories that now
live within me in a way that I
don't think it's necessarily
it's not something I don't
recommend to people. It's a very
demanding process, and I don't
think I needed to do it this
way. If I were starting it over
again, I would be gentler. I
would have gentler ambitions and
a gentler take more care of this
precious body mind.
Tasshin Fogleman: What would
that look like, practically? To
be gentler,
Chris Bache: I think it would
mean fewer high dose sessions.
It would mean, if you're working
with psychedelics, it would mean
integrating, working with a
substance like LSD, which tends
to push the high cosmological
ceiling with substances like
Psilocybin or Ayahuasca, which
tend to be more body grounded,
kind of staying. Closer to the
emotional, textured body. Of
course, it always means
integrating your intermittent
psychedelic work with daily
spiritual practice. The more
I've moved in this direction,
the more I've come to understand
that the daily spiritual
practice is absolutely essential
in order to handle the enormous
swings of energy and insight
that open to you in your
psychedelic work, but I would
just be I would be gentler. I
mean, one of the reasons I
pushed as hard as I did is
because I had adopted what I
learned to be as a false model.
I had adopted a vision that said
the purpose of this work was to
reach a particular state, you
know, to reach the condition of
awakened state, or to reach, to
reach home, to go home, to reach
heaven, to reach to dissolve
into the into the body of God,
to dissolve into the meta,
cosmic void. And what I found
was that there are many degrees
of oneness, and there are many
degrees even of the void. And no
matter how deep I went, I
discovered that there were
dimensions beyond even those
dimensions. And the key came for
me in the 50th session, when I
was in the diamond Luminosity, I
was as deep in the diamond
Luminosity as I would ever go.
And right in the middle of that
existence, my field opened up,
and I saw reality far, far into
the distance that was filled
with a light that was even a
greater form of light than the
diamond Luminosity. And a beam
of flight came and hit me and
absolutely shattered my mind.
And that's when I realized it's
an infinite progression. You
never the idea of getting to the
end of it is just a false idea.
It's underestimates the breadth
of what we're dealing with. So
once I I understood that is not
about getting to a particular
condition or a particular state
that made me more patient, or
makes me more patients with you,
open up, you bring as much of
that reality into your life as
you can, and then you you crunch
it, you sit on it, you you
integrate it into your daily
life. And so I be gentler and
have more modest expectations.
I'm more patient with our human
psycho spiritual evolution than
I was when I was a young man.
Tasshin Fogleman: What would you
recommend to someone embarking
on a similar journey if they
were inspired by your work,
Chris Bache: don't do it,
please. Honestly, I mean, don't
do it the way I did it. I'm and,
you know, I get lots of letters
from people who have said, I've
never done psychedelics, but I
know what you're speaking about.
I've been doing a meditation for
empty of years, and I've had
these kinds of experiences. And
so we know that psychedelics are
not unique to these experiences
at all, but my recommendation
is, go slow. Always work within
a therapeutic modality. Pay a
lot of attention to your set and
setting, not only on the day of
your sessions, but when you do
this work, everyone around you
is impacted, your family
members, your friends. I found
that my students were being
drawn into my psychedelic
practice, and that I wrote the
living classroom basically to
describe, quite to my surprise,
how what I had thought of as a
purely private spiritual
practice was actually
registering and impacting the
lives of My students who are
taking my courses in this time,
and that this is a natural a
natural event that consciousness
is like water in a lake. You
throw in a rock and the ripples
naturally spread out, that this
is true spiritual practice as
well. It's just natural that
people would be touched by those
experiences. So I would be
gentler. Again. I don't know why
somebody would want to go to the
North Pole, but it's not a
recreational undertaking. It's a
serious, lifelong commitment,
and I think it's much wiser
simply to explore closer to home
in ways that keeps the journey
more focused on the nuts and
bolts of one's daily life. So I
have more respect for using
psychedelics as therapy and a
spiritual awakening, and it's a
relatively rare individual who
has the circumstances and the
Constitution to go this as deep
as I did into it, and I want to
there are dangers, right? If you
open up under less than ideal
circumstances, if you open up in
circumstances. Which you are
mixing it up with other people,
or at dance raves, you can open
up prematurely, you and you can
failure. You can have failure to
close you can hurt yourself. You
can really hurt yourself in ways
that does long term damage and
may take you years to recover.
So I I want to emphasize that
this is not an end run around
traditional spirituality. It's
not a and it's not an easy path.
It's a tricky path, and it is a
potentially dangerous path, and
you have to be very cautious
when you are working with mind
amplifiers.
Tasshin Fogleman: I imagine the
kind of person drawn to doing
the work that you did wouldn't
take your advice to not do it.
They might take your advice to
be gentler, but I imagine they
would be sort of bullish about
it and be like, I'm going to do
it anyway.
Chris Bache: Well, you know, one
of the things I hope is that by
seeing what I learned, by seeing
the description of the universe
that I was able to bring back
and share with other people, I
hope that that would answer or
satisfy a certain existential
longing to know these things so
that they don't have to go
there. You know that they that
they can be more comfortable
living within a more textured,
or more inwardly, closer to
Earth, textured form of
spiritual practice that they
don't, you don't, you know, when
people went to the moon, it
satisfied so many of us who have
had that longing, but who will
never make the trip just to see
their pictures and see what it
was like. And I think it's
something can be like that with
spiritual practice too. Yeah.
Tasshin Fogleman: Oh, that's a
good metaphor for it. I think
that certainly describes my own
experience reading your book.
And I'm grateful for sort of the
oh, I don't remember what they
call it, but the picture of the
earth that they took from the
moon, it's as if you took that
kind of a picture for us, and
it's a really beautiful one,
Earth rise. I think maybe it's
called Earth rise, yeah, I'm
curious, what do you make of,
you know, at this time, there's
sort of a larger contemporary
Renaissance, you might say, in
psychedelics. What do you make
of that movement, and what's
happening there? More broadly,
Chris Bache: I think it's very
exciting, and I think it's about
time. I'm very glad that we're
going back in the direction of
integrating psychedelics into
our culture. Right now, the
psychedelic Renaissance is
focused on therapeutic healing.
It's by demonstrating the
clinical effectiveness of these
amplifying substances, that we
are opening the door to these
substances in our culture by
demonstrating that they help us
deal with Post Traumatic Stress,
depression or alcohol addiction
or death anxiety, by healing us
of the wounds of life. We are
demonstrating that these
substances have therapeutic
value and therapeutic efficacy.
And we're also taking pictures
of how the brains behave on
psychedelics, and we're doing
this very carefully control
studies, where we have control
groups versus a testing group,
and so on so forth. This is all
really important. I think it's
it's a very important stage, but
I do see it as only a stage.
What we're going to find is the
same thing we found in the early
decades of the psychedelic
movement, that these this
amplification of the of the
psyche, which allows us to heal
the wounds of the personal
psyche. That same amplification,
when continued, gets us gives us
access to deeper and deeper
dimensions of consciousness.
Now, there is a resistance to
these deeper dimensions right
now, because of our metaphysical
commitment to materialism, right
our course, you know, pre
quantum commitment is to believe
that only things which are
physical are real. And
therefore, when someone is
having an experience of
something which goes beyond
physical reality, we call the
substances that open up these
experiences hallucinogens,
because the hallucination is
something which is not real,
right? It feels real, but it's
not real. But I think what
better understood these
substances are mind amplifiers.
They are psychedelics, mind
openers. And this, once we
consolidate and provide
sufficient evidence for the
healing potential of these
substances, we will then begin
to harness the deeper
manifesting potential of these
substances, or their
philosophical potential. I think
psychedelics represent an
enormous philosophical
revolution, because they allow
those of us to or kind of have
modest. Capacities to have
temporary access to whose states
of awareness and states of
reality that lie far beyond
space time, awareness that has
profound metaphysical
implications, profound
philosophical implications we
can have access. I mean, a
mystical experience does not a
mystic make, and that's what
basically paraphrasing Huston
Smith, and that's true, but a
mystical experience does a
materialist unmake, and I think
it can undo some of the
metaphysical constrictions of
our era and open us up to a
deeper understanding of what's
actually taking place. Once you
dissolve into the intelligence
of the universe, the
intelligence of the mind of the
universe, and into the
compassionate center of the mind
of the universe, it radically
transforms your understanding of
what life is about, what we are
doing here, what the process is
and that has enormous
ramifications, and I think we
will be moving in that
direction, but first we have to
earn the right in a way. We have
to earn that access through
demonstrating its clinical
effect efficacy. I am not a
clinician. I'm not a
psychologist. I was not
primarily interested in healing.
I was trained as a philosopher
of religion, and I simply could
not wait for us to get to this
point in time. If I had waited
for us to get to this point in
time, I would have missed the
opportunity of a lifetime. So I
did the work I did underground,
undercover, privately, quietly.
I wish I didn't have to. I wish
I could have done it publicly. I
wish I could have been in public
discussion during all this time.
But I did it with the belief, as
the early researchers did, that
there would come a time when we
would reclaim these sacraments,
and that we would begin to
systematically harness their
deeper potential. And I think
that's where we're going. There
is a movement among the
pharmaceutical industry that
wants to make money off these
substances, to try to strip the
magic out of the mushrooms, you
know, to basically extract
substances which come from the
psychedelic substances, but do
not induce some of the more
exotic or demanding states of
consciousness that these
substances do in their natural
state. So that they can give us
a pill which you can take every
day, and they can sell us every
day. And because psychedelics,
you can't make money on
psychedelics because you don't
use enough of them. You know,
you only use them
intermittently, and the healing
effect is so powerful that you
don't need to take them every
day, right? The pharmaceutical
industry wants to make money off
of them, and I think that's a
danger, and that's where we have
to really watch that. I also
think the medicalization of
psychedelics is also a danger.
It's understandable that it's
important for the scientists to
maintain research in these early
years, but I think entering into
these states of consciousness is
a human right, and I don't think
it belongs. It doesn't belong
under the governance of the
medical community only. I think
we're going to come into a point
where we recognize that there is
a broader community of
specialists who are skilled in
navigating these landscapes, who
are not necessarily MDS and
PhDs.
Tasshin Fogleman: You know, in
the movement, there's various
organizations that have formed
to be structured around what you
call, sort of the therapeutic
use of psychedelics. And I
wonder if in the future, there
might be institutions structured
around the more philosophical or
cosmological explorations of the
kind that you did, what you
imagine those might look like.
Chris Bache: I think it's just a
matter of time. I think there
will be, in the near future,
there will be clinics,
institutional settings,
hopefully deep in nature,
settings where people who want
to explore the deeper dimensions
of their consciousness can go
and do so under careful
supervision. They can do so
safely. There is backup, but
they can do it in a non clinical
or non medical set of
expectations. It's kind of like
the transition from taking birth
out of the hospitals into
turning it over to the midwives,
where you have medical care
nearby if you need it. But birth
is not a medical procedure.
Birth is an entirely natural
procedure. Procedure, likewise,
opening up into deep levels of
your online and the mind of the
universe is not a medical
procedure, even if medical
medicine can be very helpful in
the early stages. So I would
anticipate that there will be
organizations. There will be
structures, places where you can
go to work with sacred
medicines, various psychedelics
in a safe and effective manner,
which go beyond therapeutic
healing is, I think it's just a
matter of time.
Tasshin Fogleman: What kind of
affordances might those
structures need that might be
different from a more like
clinical or medical treatment?
Therapeutic usage.
Chris Bache: Well, first, we
should recognize that humanity
has already been doing this for
1000s of years, that there are
in among the indigenous people,
among the First Nations peoples,
among the in America, among the
indigenous peoples in Brazil or
in South America, they've been
working ceremonially with sacred
substances for hundreds, 1000s
of years. So we we have a great
deal of historical precedent for
how to do this, how to open up
not only individuals, but whole
communities into sacred space
and bring the entire community
back and put them through a
series of exercises so that they
come back, grounded, really
well, grounded into their
physical lives. We're not
reinventing the wheel here. We
really have much to learn from
indigenous people and First
Nations people on how to work
with these substances. Now there
are screening criteria. You
really want to screen people who
are going into these states.
There are some people who really
should not be entering into
these states, either because of
physical health problems that
they're carrying or
psychological problems that
they're carrying. It's just not
a wise procedure to adopt if
you're carrying certain tensions
within your body and mind. So
there is a place for screening.
But the cultures, these
indigenous cultures, they knew
that they screened it, even
though they didn't have MD
screening the process. So it's
simply a matter of building on
what we're doing, incorporating
the collected wisdom from
indigenous cultures and moving
in to create our own unique
forms,
Tasshin Fogleman: coming back to
the sort of vision for humanity
writ large. Do you have any
advice for the coming
generations?
Chris Bache: Well, the first
thing I would say is that I
think we know enough about the
universe through reincarnation.
If you really do your homework
and you really look at the data,
if you look at the data from
near death episode research, if
you look at that of out of body
research, we know enough, just
enough, to know that we choose
our incarnations. Before we were
born, we made an informed choice
of the life that we were being
born into. So at a time when we
knew more than we remember now,
we made the choice to live the
life that we're living now, not
that we could see every detail,
but we the fundamental core
components we could see before
we were born. And that means
that whether or not we have
conscious recall of that choice,
I think we have reasons to be
confident that we are where we
belong as we enter this time in
history that all of us, every
one of us, has volunteered to
participate in this very, very
challenging time. So that's the
first level, is to be kind of
centered in your core and
knowing that you don't have to
run around and you don't have to
go someplace else or do
something else that you were
already planting yourself on a
trajectory that allows you to
participate in this process. And
this process is the process of
the transformation of an entire
culture. It's going there is not
one person or one type of
person, or a healer or therapist
or artist that's going to make
this transition work. It's going
to take all of us. It's going to
take all the skills that
humanity has to make this work.
The real question is, I think,
not, how do we how do we do? How
do we engage this process
meaningfully so we can help us
transform the real question is,
do we have the courage to do,
which we know we can do? What is
at hand? Do we have the courage
to really enter into this
process consciously? Do. And
that means we basically have to
have the courage to become the
future human that we know the
world needs. We need to become
the human that the world needs
in order to survive this crisis.
We need to become more
compassionate. We need to work
to create a culture which is
more egalitarian, more fair,
more just. We need to show
greater respect to the Earth and
to our the animal cousins who
live on this earth with us. We
need to basically become in our
own personal lives what humanity
is trying to forge in our
collective life, more where, and
that means doing inward
practice. It also means doing
outward practice of social
transformation, clearing our own
hearts of anything which keeps
us small and helping clean out
those things in our culture
which keeps our culture small
and focused on values which
you're destroying the earth.
Tasshin Fogleman: Thank you for
sharing that, and also for
answering all my questions and
speaking on so many topics. I
wonder if there's anything else
that you'd like to say or talk
about I you.
Chris Bache: We are coming into
a hard time in history. We're
coming into a time when decade
by decade, things are going to
be getting worse and worse,
there will be tremendous social
anxiety and personal anxiety as
we basically inherit the
consequences of our abuse of the
earth for all the hundreds of
years that we've been Creating
this extractive economy,
Unknown: but I hope
Chris Bache: in everybody's own
individual spiritual practices,
one encounters enough of the
universe to experience the
profound wisdom, the great
intelligence that's behind this
moment of transformation and the
great compassion and love that's
behind this time in our history
that this is not we are not
victims. This is not an
accident. It is a time that
calls for us to become the
heroes that we have the
possibility of being, that we
really nothing less than deep,
deep heroic sacrifice and
actualization is called for. But
the universe will support us.
Every time we make a change to
live to the larger good, the
universe will support us. It
will. It will help us overcome
our shortcomings. This is, this
is the game of life. This is the
great time of our life. In the
end, we don't want to live a
comfortable life so much as we
want to live a life that's
meaningful, and this is going to
give us all an opportunity to
live very meaningful lives.
Tasshin Fogleman: I appreciate
you putting that in perspective
and speaking so clearly about
it. So thank you for that, and
thank you as well for your time
today. It's been a real pleasure
to speak with you.
Chris Bache: Tazim, thank you
for this conversation. Thank you
for the conversations you've
been having with many people,
all focused on helping us know
more and become more that we
have the possibility of
becoming. Thank you.
Tasshin Fogleman: You're so
welcome. It's a it's an honor
and a privilege. So thank you.
Mm.