Andrew Holecek: So welcome
everybody to our ongoing edge of
mind podcast, where I have the
great honor and delight to spend
a little bit more time with this
remarkable thinker, psychonaut,
explorer of the mind and heart,
Christopher Bache, and really
continue to unpack unfold some
of the many aspects of his
remarkable journey that we
introduced in round one of my
conversation. And so I will
reiterate a very brief bio of
Chris, and then we're just going
to jump right in and slowly
venture into hopefully some
rich, deep waters. So
Christopher Bache is a professor
emeritus in the Department of
Philosophy and Religious Studies
at Youngstown State University,
where he taught for 33 years,
fellow at the Institute of
Noetic Sciences. He was also
adjunct faculty at the
California Institute of integral
studies and on the advisory
board for Grof Transpersonal
training and the Grof
Foundation, an award winning
teacher international speaker
who's the author of three books
and lives in Portland. You're
still in Portland, right?
Chris Bache: Actually, we're in
Weaverville, North Carolina now.
Just Oh, okay,
Andrew Holecek: well, I'm glad I
asked Yeah, yeah. So Chris,
thank you again for for taking
time to return and unfold with
me some of the remarkable
implications of your journey. So
at the outset, deep of gratitude
for you.
Chris Bache: It's a pleasure to
be with you today. Andrew, thank
you for the invitation.
Andrew Holecek: Yeah, really, I
deeply appreciate it. And so
what I thought what we could
explore is I was re reading some
of the material, especially the
latter chapters in your journey.
LSD, in the mind, in the
universe, that's mostly what
we're going to be unfolding, but
also conjoined with the living
classroom, because there's
obviously some wonderful
interconnectivity between those
narratives that will be woven
into this. But I thought what we
could we could introduce is a
narrative, of a topic that's
very near and dear to my heart
right now, so much so that I'm
writing one book on it, and
probably two. And I think we
pinged on this just a wee bit in
our first session, but I want to
explore it in a little bit more
detail now, because to me, I
think using your languaging it
this this narrative of openness
and contraction is really, I've,
I've come to see it as kind of
the combustion cycle of the
spiritual path. And so I thought
we could start with that
narrative as a way to, perhaps,
like a, like a fractal,
reiterate the entirety of your
journey within the session
itself. In other words, start a
little bit more with this
narrative and maybe continue to
expand, to open into deeper and
deeper dimensions. As in fact,
your journey, both during the 20
years and after, took you
through as a way to really talk,
both in a kind of philosophical
and also. And the reason I love
these terms somatic sense, I
love the notion of openness and
contraction, because these are
things we can feel. I mean,
they're not just cerebral,
intellectual story lines. These
are things that we can feel in
our body, mind matrix. And so I
would like to dive into that
with you as we perhaps set our
direction towards what I
consider to be the climax of
your book, The diamond
Luminosity. But because that
light is so bright, that space
is so open, that we perhaps can
dilate the aperture of our
awareness, our hearts and minds
a little bit more slowly and
start by by sending a question
in your direction about how
this, your journey, could be
articulated in this expression,
this kind of pulsation. Or the
Hindus talk about it
beautifully, and the tradition
of spanda, the doctrine of
vibration, which I'm starting to
see now, and I'll share some of
my own experiences and insights
of openness, contraction,
openness and then contraction.
So maybe we could start there
and then that, I think will lend
us gradually into wider and
wider and perhaps greater
degrees of openness.
Chris Bache: Okay, you bet
that's good place to start. So
in my understanding, in my
experience, psychedelics, in
general and in particular, LSD,
which was my primary medicine in
this journey, is an amplifier of
consciousness. And so When
consciousness is amplified,
signals which are quiet, get
large, get loud, and you have a
sensation of your becoming aware
of more and more how you meet.
That increase of awareness, how
you engage what emerges is
seminal in the process. If you
engage the shadow consciously,
it. You confront those things
which keep you habitually
contracted and small. You engage
those fears, or whatever it is,
you take them to their source,
to the root. They resolve
themselves, and when they
resolve themselves, your
consciousness is free to open
into more spacious places. Every
time you let go of something
which is holding your
consciousness in a fixed pattern
or holding it small,
particularly initially your your
time space identity, your
historical egoic identity that
tells us who we are. But if you
can let go of that you discover
that there are these dimensions
beyond your time, space
identity, which are even more
truly, really what you are. And
if you keep this going, you go
through multiple layers of
consciousness. There's a point
where you have to let go,
surrender or die, not only to
your individual identity, but to
your identity as a human being.
Per se, there is a deeper sense
of humanity that defines that
holds the limits of your
knowing, and there's a going
even deeper. There's a sense of
time, space, identity. You let
go of your entire existence,
including all your
reincarnational experiences of
time space as a framework for
holding experience. And your
experience flows beyond time and
space, and this is an entirely
natural process, I think thought
of as a broader conjecture. My
understanding of what happens
inside a psychedelic session is
that it basically accelerates
and intensifies what is taking
place in nature all the time. So
when we are born, our
consciousness contracts into our
an individual, egoic time,
space, identity. When we die, we
expand. There's a sense of
expanding back into the souls,
back back into deeper spiritual
awareness. When we're born, we
contract. When we die, we
expand. And so what happens in a
session? It simply accelerates
and intensifies this natural
process which is taking place in
history over a longer period. So
what it allows you to do is to
accelerate that process and to
start by burning off more karma
than one might get around to
otherwise, and that's the same
thing that happens in
meditation, of course, too. Same
dynamic. And it's
Andrew Holecek: interesting,
isn't it? My favorite running
definition of meditation these
days is habituation to openness,
and I find it there's so many
implications of that, Chris,
because I mean parenthetically,
the Buddha we know
etymologically, usually
translated as the awakened one.
But I've also heard renderings
as the opened one. And so the
reason I find this beautiful,
for a number of reasons, is
encountered distinction. We're
the contracted ones. And so by
bringing this, the reason I
think this is so important is
because by bringing this
process, this phenomenology,
into the light of our conscious
awareness, we can better
sensitize ourselves to it in a
more somatic sense. It's against
something. This is something we
can feel. This is not just a
cerebral, intellectual thing. We
can feel this process of
contraction and openness within
our very Soma. And for me, what
I'm curious Chris is two things.
One, how early in your journey
did this become apparent to you?
I mean, how I can't remember all
your sessions with great
specificity, but where did this
narrative become identifiable
for you? How did it help you as
you continue to go further, and
then parenthetically, just so I
don't forget this as well. The
other thing I find around this
narrative that's so helpful that
you were suggesting at the
outset is that we're practicing
this, whether we know it or not,
where we are, either on the path
of practicing habituation to
openness, or if we don't know
it, and most of us don't, by
default, we're practicing
contraction every time we
capitulate to grasping to
beliefs, to a sense of, I mean,
virtually everywhere that is our
default contraction. And so
again, I know I'm throwing a
couple things out there, but I
think this is so foundational
for me that after decades, when
I look back, it's like, oh my
gosh, I can really look with a
new sense of understanding from
this altitude, wow. My whole
journey has been this kind of
pulsation, opening, expanding,
how much of that can I deal then
metabolizing, contracting, so
little bit around that, little
bit more on that.
Chris Bache: Sure it actually
started in the very first
session. My very first session,
I hit an experience where I
could not remember anything
about myself. I could not
remember who I was, what I was,
I couldn't remember what I did
for a living. I could not
remember whether I was a man or
a woman, I was absolutely
jammed. And I looked in 1000
mirrors. I couldn't find any
piece of individual, egoic
identity, and it was, of course,
very jarring, frightening in the
beginning, and then later in the
session, my sense of identity
returned. But it that experience
was really important, because it
told me, at first, it gave me an
insight into the dynamic. It
shook me up, and it showed me a
certain measure of the true
cost, you know, because I had
read about ego death, and I
thought, Oh, good, let's do it,
and I hadn't appreciated, this
is a true death. This is a loss
of your identity. And it
basically taught me to The Art
of Letting Go and the art of
surrender, because if you can't
control your self identity,
identity, and that's about as
basic as it gets. And so later,
when the ante kept increasing, I
knew that the key to navigating
whatever was coming was to
surrender, let it go and it it
stopped me from trying to hold
on to something familiar, hold
on something I could identify
with. And that just then, that
just went on. It escalated from
there, about two and a half
years later, when my individual,
egoic identity was turned inside
out and just crushed, I went
through a collapse of that
smaller state, and they rebirth
into a deeper state, and then
later through after the ocean of
suffering, After spending two
years in that you know,
surrounded by the historical
suffering of humanity and these
unfinished memories, painful
memories, there was a death
process which then catapulted me
into a deeper level of reality,
beyond the collective
unconscious, into archetypal
consciousness. And this pattern
just kept repeating itself so
but it started very early on,
and then, then it's just the
texture of the openness differs,
the context differs, the purity
of it differs. There's a lot of
light, of course, engaging
fields of light, but I found
that light itself also has
gradients, their various kind of
levels of purity of light,
levels of clarity of light. And
so the actual content of
openness is it changes in the
work. But the phenomenon that of
opening into something larger,
something deeper. Now I want to
caution this little bit qualify
it the sensation and the certain
stages of work and what I would
call the psychic and subtle
levels of consciousness. The
sensation often is of getting
larger. And I think this is
characteristic of subtle level
reality, subtle level of states
of consciousness, and then
later, much later, in the
journey, this experience was
just reversed. That is, I was
experiencing huge fields of
light, contracting into the
present and just exploding me
into that, into some different
state of consciousness. But
everything was contracting,
contracting. So I began to
realize that the whole subject,
I even began to wonder whether
we had Miss identified the
nature of psych of psychedelics
by calling them mind openers.
Yeah, I understand. But at
another level, they are Mind
Mind contractors, where you're
contracting deeper and deeper
and deeper into the present,
present, present, present, until
you drop into a very different
experience of that present. So
openness, we just want to be
careful to recognize that
there's a there are different
modalities.
Andrew Holecek: It's a multi
isn't it, Chris, it's a
multivalent term, right? It has,
it has different iterations and
context. And several things come
to mind here. That contraction
into the present moment is very
interesting in the in the
languaging that I'm familiar
with, and you may be familiar
with this too. Pamasambhava
talked about it as the fourth
moment, which one can only
actually access through the
conduit of the present moment.
So what an interesting kind of
juxtaposition and almost clash
of traditional approaches where
I don't want. Level by
contracting in the healthy
sense. And again, this is, I
think, super important, because
in and of itself, contraction is
utterly non problematic. We
couldn't operate in the world
without that aspect of that
pulsation. And so we tend to
clamor towards openness as that
somehow being the ultimate
spiritual thing. I think
provisionally, there's some
truth to that. But if we can't
merge that openness with our
contraction, then contraction
becomes the bad boy, the bad
girl. And we look at it in a
kind of a limited way, but in my
experience, in Padmasambhava,
use this language of the fourth
moment you contract, you
condense into the portal, the it
becomes the portico, into the
timeless beyond, where you come
to the present moment, and then
that blows up, so to speak, into
the fourth moment, which
Transcendence, even the present
moment itself. And I think
that's helpful, because we're
going to start to tread into
waters where languages will
because it's dualistic and
nature becomes problematic. And
as you know, in the Buddhist
tradition, one has to be, or is
invited to be, incredibly
articulate precise, in order to
realize when we use this term
exactly, how are we using it in
what context. And so I think
therefore, it seems like, Well,
wait a second, isn't the whole
thing about opening? Well, yes,
but it's also honoring the
process of contraction, and how
that can lead to this.
Chris Bache: Yeah, you know,
you're mentioning Padma Samba.
It gives me an opportunity to,
once again, emphasize the point
that there are correlations, and
I'm grateful for the
correlations between my
experiences and those recorded
by the Great Beings. The Padma
Samba was of the world, the
great contemplatives. But this
path that I was on is not that
contemplative path. It's a path
of temporary immersion. So when
I'm describing things, it always
has to be understood that this
is a temporary experience, which
then to unpack the spiritual
potential of that temporary
experience. You know, we can
have that conversation, but
it's, it's not the same as when
you come into these experiences
using what you might think of as
the slow bake method of
sustained contemplation, you
know. So I just always want to
be careful to keep apples and
oranges separate, and because so
many people good point, they
think, Oh, I've had a tremendous
revelatory enlightenment
experience. And that's, you
know, it says, well, good for
you, but, but that's, it's,
that's a temporary experience
Andrew Holecek: that is
unbelievably important. I mean,
how does the saying go? An
enlightened experience does not
make one an enlightened being. I
mean, that's, as you know,
that's a difference in Tibet
language, in between experience
and realization by definition.
Yeah, experience always has a
beginning and an end, yeah. And
in order to mature that, and
that's very interesting, because
that that's a large part of the
path where I think a lot of
people really get tripped up. I
speak from my own experience,
you have these tremendous
metanoias, these openings. You
think you're enlightened. And
then what do you do? You grasp
after that, and you just replace
a chain made of lead with one
made of gold. And so yeah,
therefore understanding that
there's, there's the path,
quality of of continuing that.
And so just to reinstate a
couple things when you're
talking about deeper states,
just to make sure I'm
understanding you, Chris, it
seems to me that you're also
saying a deeper state is, is
somewhat synonymous with, with a
more open state that is, you're
waking in, you're also expanding
and then, and then, perhaps, as
you pointed out, that that it
then points or directs to us how
it is that we're constructing
this self sense, moment to
moment. This is the other thing
I think, that is incredibly
important, that we tend and I'm
speaking from like confessional
thing, we tend to think that the
ego structure, the self sense,
is this monolithic, reified
entity. And this is where we can
learn a lot from our scientific
brothers and sisters in science,
physics and neuroscience, it's a
process. It's not a product. The
self sense is constantly being
constructed. And therefore, when
you go through this type of de
construction, or demolition
derby, by immediate implication,
you can see through the process
of demolition, the process of
construction, and therefore, how
we are responsible for the way
we contract and we do so largely
for purposes of protection, fear
and the like. But is that? Is
that a fair representation of
what you discovered?
Chris Bache: It is, it's, it's a
fair representation, and it's a
way, it's a description which
fits better, in some ways, the
early stages of the work, where
you are still kind of working at
insights which help you
understand your individual way
of being in the world. And then,
you know, I describe my work
fundamentally. Play as a work in
cosmological exploration, where
not only do you leave your
individual ego behind, you know,
at least temporarily and you
leave, but you leave deeper and
deeper levels behind, at least
in my experience, and are given
the opportunity to explore how
the universe constructs its
reality, how archetypal reality
structures time and space
reality, how oneness manifests
in the diversity of all physical
of all life forms, of all
atomic, Nuclear, quantum life
forms, how the pure void of
emptiness is that mysterious,
fertile essence which is giving
birth to time and space. I mean
the vast, you know, the vastness
of time and space, moment by
moment, minute by minute. So it
is, you know, very useful to
understand your personal way of
contracting, the personal way of
you, know, sustaining your
smallness. But for me, I mean,
not trained as a philosopher, I
wanted to understand the larger
spectrum of reality, and so the
invitation that that was given
to me was just to explore how
time and space is made. And I
wish, I mean, I so often wish I
had a PhD in physics and
astrophysics. I mean, I could
have understood so much more of
what I was being shown. But you
know, always, the universe can
only communicate to you
successfully, that which you
have the capacity to understand.
Andrew Holecek: Yes, exactly.
Oh, that's what a fantastic
statement, Chris. Because to me,
it's like, and this is what you
suggest towards the end of your
book, when you were wrestling,
struggling, working with this
process of integration, how, in
a very real way, you using this
particular mechanism, dis
integrated, opened, open, open,
open. And then And then, really,
in my language, in here, using
frameworks that we're both
familiar with, that this notion
of in the Indic Traditions, this
pedagogical approach, I think we
might have hit it last session
of of hearing, contemplating,
meditating, my language and
ingest, digest, metabolize, and
what, the way I read your
experience, that I think is
really worth talking about, is
that you you open to such an
extent, and I can speak a little
bit from my own experience, that
then the issue became one of
digestion and metabolism. And
the reason I mentioned this,
that I think has tremendous
applicability, is that
sometimes, when we look at
things like psychosis, and you
were treading sometimes that
thin membrane between
Transcendence in psychosis, the
loss of self sense, that the the
issue of integration, bringing
that in in a certain way, and
pardon my kind of play on
languaging here is that
psychosis can be, in fact, a
type of eating disorder that you
actually open to such an extent
that then you actually don't
have the capacity, you don't
have the infrastructure, the
wherewithal to digest and
metabolize. And then, instead of
opening body mind. You blow body
mind, and sense of reference is
then completely so decimated
that that is one way to perhaps
talk about the whole psychotic
aspect and the risk, perhaps
some of the perils of doing this
type of deep diving.
Chris Bache: I understand and
you're certainly right that
doing this type of work does
carry certain risks and has to
be approached cautiously and
with careful support structures
in place and careful self
monitoring and so on so forth. I
don't think, and I do understand
the relationship between
psychosis and Transcendence, and
I think it was at Huston Smith
who said a mystic is someone who
learns how to swim in the
waters, in the vast waters, and
a psychotic drown.
Andrew Holecek: That is like
actually, Lang, already Lang,
yeah,
Chris Bache: in my case, I
understand the psychotic looking
qualities of loss of self that,
but I would not ever I would not
describe my experiences walking
that particular edge. And if I
had gotten into a situation
where I felt I was at that edge,
I would have changed course. I
would have done something
differently. My experience was
that by working in a very
carefully clinical type,
modality and opening
systematically. The universe
really opened me systematically,
in a way beyond my calculation.
But it opened me very, very
carefully, and so it peeled me
carefully, and it broke me open,
layer by layer by layer, if it
had. Pulted me, you know,
beyond, beyond beyond so
quickly, then I could have had
problems integration. But in my
experience, I always opened and
I always congealed comfortably
and carefully. And if I had not
congealed comfortably and
carefully, then I would have
been given pause, because that's
a symptom of something really
going wrong. So it's not the
depth of loss of self which
marks the psychotic episode. I
think it also has to do with a
kind of confusion, but I
absolutely agree you have to
walk these waters very
carefully. I seem to have a kind
of a natural constitution. I
mean, you know, I started this
work. I never came from any
traumatized background, just the
ordinary, you know, pains of
growing up and whatnot. But I
had fundamentally, a core,
strong self, and I also had a
capacity, it's in my natal
astrological natal chart, a
capacity to open and an interest
in opening up into the vast
expanse of consciousness and to
contract back. So if you don't
have that natural capacity, or
if you're bringing in disruptive
trauma or other qualities in
your person, then very much this
work may not be for you. You
know, it's a
Andrew Holecek: little bit like
Jack Engler famously said, and I
think it's appropriate
statement, you have to be
someone before you can be no
one. That's right there. I think
that cannot be overstated, that
there the ego itself,
fundamentally, is non
problematic. It's a
developmental stage. It's just a
form of Arrested Development.
And so if you don't have that
stable self sense, then, in
fact, then instead of dis
differentiating, you dissociate.
And then that's where it becomes
somewhat problematic. Then the
ability to find that identity,
to find some refuge, becomes
really somewhat disconcerting.
But Chris, towards the end of
your book, I want to come back
to this just a little bit,
because my understanding of what
you're sharing towards the end,
like what, what dictated
stopping after the 73rd journey
was, and I found this one of the
most compelling, pardon the pun,
electrifying parts of your book.
Where it was, it was as if your
body, mind matrix, had become so
open. And we talked about this
last time. This is so important.
This kind of tantric work, body
is as important as mine. When
you're opening your mind, you
are opening your body. And as
you open your body, even the
classic inner yogic sense, all
these energies, what they talk
about is the winds come through.
And if those winds aren't
written properly, they can throw
you and so if I understand what
you said towards the end, in a
certain way, your system was
running too hot. You there was
so much energy, so much release
that, again, this is this
returns us to this digestion,
metabolism component. It was
like my cup runneth over. I
have, I have enough experience
here to spend the rest of this
life, or other lives now,
digesting this feast. Yeah, and
so isn't, isn't that a fair way
to recapitulate what you said at
the end, that you stopped the
feast because there was just too
much to eat, so to speak.
Chris Bache: I think, I think
that's a fair description. In my
case, I don't, I think it's not
because I didn't ride the wind
successfully. I think I rode the
wind successfully, but I rode
the winds too long in the sense.
I mean, they were just, they
would stretch me out so so wide
and so deep. And I think this
is, you know, in the early
stages of psychedelic use, both
individually, and I think
culturally, we get excited by
having being able to have
contact with the transcendent
dimensions. And that's so
liberating. And it's so
intellectually, you know,
opening to us to the
intelligence that lives in the
universe, that is the universe,
Unknown: but
Chris Bache: our our tradition
is our theological and even our
contemplative traditions, I
think, tend to accept at the
very highest levels, tend to
underestimate the dimensions of
the Divine, or underestimate the
dimensions of the Universe, so
that leads us to underestimate
how vast the world is that we
can open into. And psychedelics
do give us the capacity, even
when they are used well, and I
hope I use them skillfully and
responsibly, but even when I did
that, it basically opened me so
deeply into such intimacy with
the universe, transcending time,
transcending space, and even
though I contracted back, okay,
the memory or the beauty and.
Memory of the communion was just
so dear and so intense that I
could not, I could not take
return and coming back. I just
couldn't do it anymore.
Andrew Holecek: Yeah, you
couldn't. You couldn't go to the
train station and leave your
lover one more time,
Chris Bache: right? Yeah, yeah.
And I just, just had to stay
here and let her come to me in
whatever form was possible by me
not going into a non ordinary
state, but staying here and
letting and just digesting like
you say, I picked up a lifetime
and more of experiences to
digest.
Andrew Holecek: So let me ask
you this, and I hope it's okay
if we go into, I mean, the book
itself is so intimate, it's so
personal, that I don't think I'm
violating any borders with you.
But if I go into areas where
it's like, yeah, I don't want to
go there, you will not offend
me. But what you said at the end
so much was the end of the book.
I was really moved by this,
because in a certain way, when I
look back over my own life,
Chris, it became more articulate
over the last couple of years.
My entire life has been is a way
learning how to prepare to die.
I mean, I wrote a book by the
very title, and in the most
elegant way, that journey has
actually brought me more fully
into life than I could have
imagined. So my passion for
death is that has actually
brought me more fully into life
than I could have possibly
imagined. And so I have a deep,
deep fascination, interest in
death, dying, thanatology. To
me, really, the whole spiritual
path is death in slow motion,
opening, titrating, opening on
our terms. But will you share at
the end? I thought was so
beautiful, just to expand we
said here that I in a certain
way I couldn't wait to die, that
I couldn't wait to return to my
beloved. But let me, let me ask
you this, how do you think, why?
What do you expect will happen,
and why do you think somehow
you'll be more prepared for her
ultimate embrace with a
dissolution of your body at the
moment of death than you are
now. I mean, are you perhaps
again? I don't know. Kidding
yourself is very open question.
What is the intuition or the
felt scent that says I can't
wait to dissolve into the
embrace of the beloved at the
moment of death? And then why?
Why do you think you'll be able
to handle that any differently
than you can handle it now,
Chris Bache: I don't think I
would handle it differently at
the moment of my final death,
whenever that takes place, then
I could handle it now. I think
if I were to die right now, the
training that I went through in
my psychedelic work, and it is
just as you say, it is a
training to die, and that
training actually becomes a
training in how to live.
Because, you know, there's like
two realities in the world.
There's the domain of light, I
think of it as pure light, and
then there's the green reality,
which is manifest physical
world, which is the world of,
you know, the world that we are
part of, nirmanakaya. So there's
Dharmakaya and nirmanakaya, and
they are interpenetrating. They
are the same reality experienced
in different modalities. And
what we experience as death is
really just a an intersection of
a moment of intersection between
these realities. And as you
awaken, you don't you awaken
into a deeper into the fact of
the constant intersection, the
constant simultaneity of these
realities. So what happens when
we die physically and what
happens when we die spiritually,
are really deeply one in the
same in a way, and I feel like
in my sessions I went through, I
was taken into my own death
process multiple times. I can't
really count how many times I
died, and so I have a sense that
I know the pathway well. I read
the literature about the Bardo
confusions that can distract us
and prevent us from returning
fully to a Dharmakaya when we
die. And I recognize that, and I
have, I feel like I've dealt
with many of those, and I, I may
be wrong, you know, we'll find
out, yeah, find out the final
exam, right? Yeah, but I have a
sense that, to me, death is will
be not only joyful as it is for
everybody, but easy, because I
don't feel a deep clinging to
not only my personal identity,
but I don't feel a deep clinging
to human existence or to time
space. Uh so and you're
absolutely right, all spiritual
practice. And I think of
psychedelic practice as I try to
do it as a spiritual practice,
you know, a session. I call them
sessions, not a period of
spiritual practice. Yeah, they
are preparing you for that
moment of death, and if
everything goes well, you do get
to die before you die. Remember
the word those who die before
they die do not die when they
die. So that what would be
lovely if I could experience
what I think of as full
liberation would be if she came
to me while I was still in my
body, and I got to live in the
death state. Yes, I was alive in
the physical state, but it's so
Andrew Holecek: beautiful, and
this is so important.
Chris Bache: This view
Andrew Holecek: alone can
irrevocably, radically alter our
relationship to the end of life
and transition. And by the way,
we should make a deal with each
other. Chris, when I was reading
your book, I thought of the same
thing, that both the use of the
word psychedelic and death. I
think these are branding issues.
We need to rebrand these terms.
So every time I read
psychedelic, it was like
impressed by this ridiculous
condition button to that word.
And so I'm talking about playing
here, but you should replace
every instance of psychedelic
with Entheogen. I should replace
in my work of death and dying.
I'm really going to actively try
to do this because death is such
a reified ridiculous notion. I'm
going to do my best to every
time I use that word as
mindfulness to speech, replace
it with the word transition,
because otherwise death seems so
final, it's so solid, and it's
like this terrible, monolithic
thing, yeah? But no, it's not,
you know, what did Marie Curie
say? Beautifully. He said,
nothing in life is to be feared.
It is only to be understood,
yeah? And so what we're doing
here is this tremendous
understanding. So I want to talk
a little bit about this, because
this is so important for us.
Chris Bache: Well, let me before
we go in the next let me just
hope respond to something you
said, okay, one of the things
that I write about in the book
in the diamond Luminosity
chapter, is, once you've died so
many times and at so many levels
of consciousness, the very
concept of death loses its
meaning because you Learn you
cannot die. The form you are can
die. Everything about all your
understandings and all your
history can die, but you cannot
die at that point. You know, in
that diamond Luminosity chapter,
when I made my first transition
into the diamond Luminosity, the
name of that chapter I gave that
is the death state. And the song
which I've sung in that chapter,
you know, my, my, if you what we
would usually call the song of
realization, was the death
state, you know. And it the
death state is the awakened
state. It is the it is the
reality state.
Andrew Holecek: Yeah, you're the
very impression. This is exactly
the question I was going to ask
you, that when you went through
these repetitive openings,
releases and deaths, it became
easier. In fact, you became more
familiar with it, right? The
very Tibetan word for meditation
to become familiar with. So it's
only because, again, we don't,
we're not we don't understand
it. We're not familiar with it.
Hence we fear it. And so you die
over and over and over. You
become more familiar with it,
you understand it, you befriend
it, and you go, Oh my gosh. This
is just this natural state of
openness that is only fearful in
reference to the ego structure,
to the form which we're
exclusively identified with,
that we're so afraid of letting
go of. So just, I want to
reinstate this. Yeah, it's just
so important. It becomes easier.
The more frequently you die in
meditation or through these
sessions, or whatever, the more
familiar you get with it until
it becomes like his holiness.
Karmapa said at the moment he's
transitioned in this beautiful
interview, two days before he
died, nothing happens. Nothing
happens to get to that point to
say with utter conviction,
nothing happens. Yeah,
unbelievable,
Chris Bache: yeah, yeah, death
becomes your best friend. Truly.
It becomes your best friend. In
your practice, you're always
looking for your best friend.
Now I just want to qualify again
a little bit, just the unusual
scope, though, the hardest strip
down that I went through in any
of my sessions, the most
extreme, you know destruction of
was in the 70th session, in the
last, what I consider the last
vision I was given in among many
major visions. And so at one
level earlier, and I had gone
through so many deaths, and they
do. Get easier, and you look
forward to them, and you embrace
them, and so on and so forth.
And yet I have to put that
beside this particular phenomena
where the transition was not
easy. I didn't resist it. I gave
into it, but it was really
extreme, and that's because my
session, or the consciousness
guiding my session was taking me
into an extremely radical state
of consciousness that was deeper
into deep time than it had ever
taken me before. It was giving
me one last, culminating series
of teachings that required an
unusually large canvas, and so
it had nothing to do with
personal enlightenment or
personal ego death or something
like that. So once again, we
always have to contextualize all
of our observations in terms of
the level of consciousness that
we're working with but in
general, I think you're
absolutely right. The more you
die, the more comfortable you
get with it, but and, and to be
able to say, as the Karmapa did
nothing, nothing happens, is to
be in a cherished, cherished
state,
Andrew Holecek: isn't it? Yeah.
And if we really understand
that, again, returning to the
narrative, the contraction,
openness, narrative, openness
narrative, if we truly
understand and feel in our in
our heart of hearts, that when
we die, it's the ultimate grand
opening, right, there we go.
It's the grand opening. And if
we understand that these are
little miniature openings, we
become more familiar with those
in our meditation state. I mean,
how much of the path is letting
go of identification to thought
the body to exclusive
identification with form. It is
absolutely death in slow motion,
and therefore towards the end of
life, then we really actually
have, like you said, it's a
complete reversal of our normal
fear. Now we actually have
something to look forward to,
instead of going into the Bardos
looking through the rear view
mirror. That's what makes
everything so painful. We
actually now have something to
look forward to is the big
unwind. The big unwind, yeah,
the final exhalation, the final
openness, which is absolutely
fundamentally ecstatic. It's
this release into the into the
blood. And so this is so
important, and I love your
languaging here of the return to
the Beloved. Because if we have
this again in a heart of hearts,
if we know that we are going to
return to the embrace of the
Beloved, you're going to return
to your lover at the moment to
death and be held in this
ultimate holding environment. Oh
my goodness, does that change
our relationship to the end of
life? I am going to return to
the embrace of the cosmic
mother. Wow, these are then you
die as a sinner with a smile on
your face, instead of kicking
and screaming and making a
really difficult transition. So
this cannot, in my opinion, be
overstated, because this will
radically change the way we
relate to old age sickness. As I
look down and this apparatus has
served me pretty well for
decades, is starting to crumble.
Yeah, instead of Oh crap, it's
oh wow, yeah. It's like,
whatever,
Chris Bache: yeah. It's the one
wonderful joy and mercy of life
that they it can't stop you from
dying. You know, it's like, the
older you get, every you get one
foot closer to joy and ecstasy
and the whole attempt to, you
know, cryogenics, to not die and
to freeze the body, that's just
sort of so sad. I mean, it's
just so terribly sad. And it's
not, you know, yeah, it's such
that's why, you know, I taught
near death episode research for
years in my courses, along with
reincarnation research and other
things. And over and over and
over again when students, when I
went with students through this
wonderful literature, and they
watched how those people's lives
were totally changed. Their
relationship to death was
totally changed by their
temporary experience of what's
on the other side of death, and
having experienced the beloved
in their own form of the beloved
that had an experience of
softening permanently their own
fear of death and changing their
expectations. So this is, you
know, this death research is
really, really a powerful psycho
spiritual work.
Andrew Holecek: I couldn't agree
more, the work of Greyson and
Eben Alexander and others who
come back with these really
remarkable stories. And I think
this also is worth reinstating
that I believe it's like, I've
never had an official n de, but
I've had what I call meditative
and the ease. And to me, it's
like you don't have to have
these over and over for them to
change your life. You just need
one. And it's because, and I
wonder if this resonates with
you, it's because they're so
true. There's. So real that it
just takes one to completely
change the texture of your life.
And this is, as you know, they
are using these agents now to
remove fear of death for people
who are just terrified, one
session, one session will
completely open you to the point
where all fear of death is done
and over with. That's no small
Chris Bache: as you say it.
People say, Well, how do you
know what you whether what you
experienced was real? Maybe it
was just a complicated
hallucination or self fulfilling
prophecy, and it's like, no, you
know what reality feels like,
and this is more real than the
physical real. It is a hyper
reality. It's just, it's
objectivity is unmistakable,
yeah, and you don't have to, you
don't can't quibble with it.
Don't need to argue with it.
Don't need to question it's
just, it's obviously true,
Andrew Holecek: exactly, and
then really, again, come back
and come back to the contraction
thing. It is, in fact, egos,
inability to digest, metabolize
that that then contracts against
it and fights against it is a
type of reducing valve. I love
Huxley. What Huxley said, the
brain reducing valve that. And
on one level, we need it,
because it's like you said, we
don't have the capacity to be
developmentally that open. And
so we, on one level, we need
this type of reduction in order
to survive. But really, I would
argue that's what constitutes
growth. Is reducing the reducing
valve continuing to open until
we can actually become this
ultimate openness in this and in
that sense, become the cosmos
itself. And so this ties into
what we're talking about last
time that. And I love what you
said about this, that in order
to become, I don't remember your
exact terms, but something like,
in order to become one with the
universe, we first need to
become one with the self. And
you could say they're the same,
right? Can you say a little bit
more about that? How that was,
yeah, kind of played out in your
own experience, because I think
again, this is where we go and
we die, right? We become nothing
simultaneously. We become
everything.
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, the
experience was to become one
with all of existence. You know,
we would say, to become one with
God, to become one with the
universe, to become one with
one. We can't do that if we're
not one within ourselves, if we
have unintegrated pieces of
shadow or ego fragments or
untouchable wounds or bruises.
So when you when you move into
intimacy with life, life life
itself brings these unintegrated
pieces to the surface, so you
can make your peace with them,
and so you can reabsorb them, so
you can be become whole and
coherent within your own being.
Because how could you become one
with life if you're not one with
yourself. And so it's not, you
know, just these things develop
synergistically. The deeper your
experience of oneness with life,
the deeper your experience of
oneness with yourself, until
they're stopped, until these
divisions, just they disappear
inside of yourself. And I think
one of the wonderful qualities
we appreciate about awakened
beings is there, is there
integrity? Is there oneness,
their sense of deep relaxation
within themselves, which is a
outgrowth of their intimacy with
life itself?
Andrew Holecek: Yeah, and isn't
that? Isn't that fantastic, the
way it yet again, this
reiterates the process of
reiteration itself, that by
learning to, in fact, embrace
ourselves, and again, talk about
practical my tree, loving
kindness, learning to, in a
Certain Way, unite, befriend
every aspect of our usually
disenfranchised spectrum of our
being, all the parts that we
reject that we then throw into
the unconscious mind that keeps
a large part of the unconscious
mind going. And so therefore, to
me, Chris, it's like when we
understand the divine nature of
reality, which includes the
divine nature of the the entire
spectrum of my being, then what,
without this framework, would be
considered the shadow elements,
the thing, the parts of
ourselves that we don't want to
embrace, that we that, therefore
we spend our lives on a certain
very sophisticated avoidance
strategy. If we understand
through this view, say, Yes,
befriend every aspect of your
own being. I mean, again, like
with death, this radically
changes the way we relate to the
unwanted, so called aspects of
our own spectrum. We're being
right here and right now. We
learn how to open, open and say
yes to whatever takes place, and
then that type of integration, I
love, this. The interjection of
the integrity we feel people
then leads to fundamental
integration with the so called
outside world altogether.
Chris Bache: Yeah, and one of
the, one of the last pieces, of
course, well recognized in the
spiritual traditions, is the
importance of giving up private
enlightenment, you know, because
that's just spiritual shadow, so
that the more you know,
everything you do for others is
part of is your awakening, and
everything you do for yourself,
including trying to become
enlightened, it gets in your
way.
Andrew Holecek: Yeah, yeah,
yeah. This and again, this
brings the social nexus of the
path into play, which I love,
what you write about in your
book that we tend to think and I
think provisionally So, if we
look at the term Hinata in its
kind of pedagogical approach,
there's a lot to be said about
start at home, start where you
are, clean up with your stuff.
But the near, but the near enemy
of that is then you become a
little bit myopic, little bit
near sighted. And for me, I say
this with as part of my path. I
mean, on one level, I'm the
happiest when I'm down in my
study, writing, being my nerd
and on retreat. But then, like I
did my long retreat, by design,
with others, you can't wake up
without others, and therefore
then others become your path,
the we aspect, the social,
cultural aspect. I think this is
incredibly important. I speak
from my own experience, because
otherwise, then the solitary
path, the solitary realizing
path, can become a real trap
that that again, in the
narrative of opening, opening,
we then work with the people
that press our buttons. We've
installed those buttons, so
that's interesting. But
bringing, bringing, you know, I
hit a little run in this morning
with the guy who cuts my lawn,
and I paid very close attention
to that. I said, Oh, first of
all, I capitulated to my habit
patterns. It was like, Oh crap.
There was that again. And then
as I stepped away for a second,
I said, Oh my gosh, that was
Padmasambhava teaching me about
patience and so to me, as I come
out, and I come out in my really
long three year retreat, my
aspiration now is to enter
lifetime retreat with this view
that all these annoying again,
that's just my projection, all
these annoying aspects of my
reality now, those are my path.
And I love this because there's
tremendous power in tradition.
And path is it's traditionally
put forth. But there's also
colossal enemies, and one of
these is just that is that you I
can only do this one all the
atmospheric conditions are right
in my own life, right? And as
the world is going to crap right
now, I think this becomes a
little bit more helpful for us
to bring this kind of view to so
called unwanted experiences, so
that we can bring those onto our
own path, realizing that they
are our path. Yeah, yep. So
anyway, it's like you're
interviewing me. I need to back
up a little bit. I get so
excited I can't help myself.
With your permission, Chris, I
want to transition into what,
again, I thought was just such a
dazzling section in your book.
Let's talk a little bit more, if
you would, about the the light,
the diamond Luminosity you
mentioned several times early
on, this, this phenomena of
light, this is, to me, among the
most profound aspects of the
whole shebang. And so if you can
maybe walk us through your
exploration of this light and
how it worked with you on the
path to introduce you to, I
think, is this, this fundamental
kind of matrix of reality?
Chris Bache: Well, this
transition took place 15 years
into my work. So I had already
gone through ego death. I'd gone
through the ocean of suffering,
of collective suffering. I had
navigated through archetypal
reality, both the sort of
Platonic archetypes and the
tissue of our of our species
mind, the tissue of the human
psyche, and then had been taken
into this year of incredible
blessings, of of experiences of
oneness, of Shunyata, emptiness,
of self, cosmic love, primal
void. You know, I felt
profoundly existentially
complete. I mean, I I felt like
I had been asked to give
something in the ocean of
suffering, work, and I gave it,
and the universe had just
rewarded me with just a cascade
of blessings that left me
feeling profoundly existentially
complete. I mean, I had been
given a deep experience of and a
new understanding of
reincarnation that transcended
classical, you know, Easter. And
understandings of reincarnation.
I had been taken into the birth
of the diamond soul. I had been
given many visionary experiences
of where humanity was going in
the future human. And I reviewed
these things, just to sort of
give a context. And along the
way, I had experienced light
many times in different
modalities in different forms.
And then in the I came into a
time when I went through yet one
more very, very intense death
process, which took an entire
session, and then the next
session I began immediately and
trust transported into the
fruition portion of the session
in which I was taken into this
light that was beyond any light
that I had experienced before. I
dissolved into a Luminosity that
was absolutely spell binding and
intoxicating. And in my notes, I
called it the death state,
because it I entered it in a
form of dying, which was an
ultimate form of dying. It a key
point. I was surrounded by a
swirling circle, a disc that
contained all the moments of my
life and I would fall from the
center into this circle and
touch one of some aspect of my
life. And I would instantly die
into the state of Luminosity,
and then be brought back to the
center and fall in a different
direction, touching another
different set of experiences.
And as soon as I did, I would
instantly be taken into this
death state. And this went over
and over, happened over and
over, until eventually there was
no going and coming. There was
just a permanent abiding, or at
least a session abiding, in this
transcendent Luminosity, the
death state, I would say
ecstasy. And it's true, but it's
it's a different than earlier
forms of ecstasy. It just the
most striking characteristic of
it, for me, was its clarity,
clarity, clarity, clarity. I
mean, it was the context within
which all thinking and all
feeling took place. But in
itself, it was hyper, hyper,
hyper, hyper clear,
breathtakingly clear. Just took
my breath away, and I understood
the teachings that even just
touching something like this for
one second dissolves 1000s of
years of wandering around in the
shadows of Samsara, it, and I,
as I came to understand it, this
was what I understood to be
extra samsaric reality, and a
particularly intense version of
extra samsaric reality. At first
I thought of it in terms of
sambhagaya because of the
extreme bliss of it. But as I
really went back to the sources
and studied them more carefully,
I came to associate it with
Dharmakaya, the clear light of
absolute reality. The next
session, when I went back, of
course, all I wanted to do was
get back into this condition. I
had no interest in exploring the
other dimensions that I had gone
into, but I did, wasn't taken
back into this experience, and I
wasn't taken back for another
year and five more sessions,
very intense purification, very
intense kind of cleansing and
healing, other things going on.
And it was after a year that I
went into the diamond Luminosity
for the second time. And this is
what happened over the next
several years, that it would
take about a year of very, very
intense work, and then I would
die awake and again into the
diamond Luminosity. The second
time I went into the diamond
Luminosity was the deepest
experience of it that I had any
time in any of my sessions. And
it was in that deep immersion
that I had my cosmological
vision completely reversed and
turned upside down. I had the
experience of a reality of Light
Beyond the diamond Luminosity,
light I award my field pivoted.
I saw reality Far, Far in the
distance that was just
exquisitely beautiful light. A
ray of light hit me, and it
completely shattered me. And I
called it the absolute light.
You know? It was a light beyond
even diamond Luminosity and. In
that one second, I understood
that it's an infinite
progression, and I had to give
up completely the idea of ever
coming to some type of end
state, because always, my
spiritual tradition had taught
me there were end states. That's
why I was doing this work, to
reach home, or to become one
with God or to become, you know,
one with the universe and some
fundamental, you know, dissolve
into the meta, cosmic void. And
I began to realize that with
that instant, I realized, no,
it's an infinite progression,
and death will keep coming back
as long as you keep pushing,
because you never going to reach
the end of it. At that point in
the next time I went into the
depths, into the diamond
Luminosity, and the fourth and
final time I went into the
diamond Luminosity, I wasn't
going deeper into the diamond
Luminosity, but the diamond
Luminosity was crunching itself
more deeply into my being, and
all the lessons were shifting
and pivoting around that it was
dissolving the structure of my
body. I mean, I could feel it
crunching itself into my
cellular makeup and very, very
intense physical detoxification,
purification processes. And then
this eventually culminated in
the fourth session into the in
the experience of giving me an
initiation into the Buddha
nature, into the pure nature of
mind, and I began to understand
that that magnificent reality,
which has no beginning, it has
no end. It always is, always has
been. We never have stepped out
of that. We never step into it.
It is the it is the abiding
foundation of all existence that
is, in a sense, the embodied
diamond Luminosity. It is, it is
the closest I've come to to
experiencing what diamond
Luminosity is like in the body.
My other experiences of diamond
Luminosity, or diamond
Luminosity as they exist as an
extra physical reality, an extra
Samsara reality. But this was an
experience of pure light as the
foundation of my very physical
existence. Okay, that was the
last time I experienced the
diamond Luminosity. From there,
I went through a couple of
experiences, then the final
vision in the 70th session, and
then basically the consciousness
guiding my work wrapped it up,
gave me a last set of
instructions and sent me on my
way. Oh, I
Andrew Holecek: just want to
take want to take 15 seconds to
pause and just digest that a
little bit.
Chris Bache: I understand. I've
been digesting it for 20
Andrew Holecek: years, because
the the ineffable enormity of
it, it, this, this, it's a
wonderful is you're sharing this
with me, Chris. And by the way,
thank you so much for trusting
to do that. I find this very
interesting dance between kind
of the mythopoetic aspect of my
being and rendering just bathing
in the artistry of what you
shared versus Okay, formulating
whatever in terms of my
references. And so I mean, on
one level, I almost hesitate to
say anything, because what can
one say without just kind of
literally watering it down,
distorting it but with your
understanding, Chris of of
Buddhist nomenclature, because I
remember in your book, you also
shared somewhat interesting
synchronicity, that when the
diamond Luminosity was
introduced to you in this way,
literally almost same same day
kind of thing, the Vajrayana
then became part of your journey
and your path. And so using that
languaging is very interesting
for me. When you say these
things. I find it very, very
interesting, humbling
exploration of my referencing in
will, capacity or lack thereof,
to understand it okay, like, for
instance, oh, that sounds like
the Dharma talk. Oh, that sounds
like the Dharma Datu. And I
really hesitate to say that,
because on one level, you, I
think you understand it, shrink
wraps the enormity of what
you're saying into these names.
But on another level, we can sit
here in silence. Or we can do
the best we can with language to
talk about something that
transcends language and so we do
with we can. Yeah. So with that
said, Would you, would you,
would you resonate with your
understanding of the Buddhist
tradition and descriptions of
someone analogous states clear
light mind. Is that another
quality that comes in that could
say this, you use the term
diamond Luminosity. Interesting
Vajrayana is the diamond path.
But using, and again, without
any violation of your own
personal experience, are there
other Tibetan languaging or
Buddhist terms that would relate
to what you experienced that you
could say that really sounds
like the Dharma data you've used
Dharmakaya before. But again,
I'm trying to simply relate,
using my reference structures,
to what you're sharing.
Chris Bache: Yes, there are, I
mean, clear light mind, to me,
is maybe closer to the nature of
mind in term that quality in
this is I still, I still am
digesting, I'm still trying to
appreciate some of the
differences between the diamond
Luminosity as an extra samsaric
reality, and Then the diamond
Luminosity as at the foundation
of nirmanakaya existence. So
there certainly are many
correlations and and again, all
honor to the Great Beings who
have explored these dimensions
much more deeply than I've been
able to so I mean, always,
always humble student, truly
humble student of the great
teachers. In this respect, I put
the names as best as I can to
clarify or to qualify, but
you're right. I mean, it's
tricky because you can this can
get shrink wrapped, and that
just stops the mystery and just
lets the mind back in where it
really doesn't belong. So let me
just give this a step into a
little different framework. The
universe is 13 point 7 billion
years old. Our planet it's about
four and a half billion years
old. When we plot the the
evolving structure of Homo you
know, we go through home,
erectus, Homo sapiens, you know,
the various stages we got, the
big brain, the 50% increase in
our brain, about 100,000 years
ago, self awareness begins to
emerge. You know, along the way
and about three to 5000 years
ago, we began to develop the
technology, the spiritual
technology, that allows us to
concentrate our mind and bring
us down into that part of our
being where we are not of the
private self, but we touch the
life of the world. We touch that
which is universal. And there's
this tremendous aha, this
awakened sense, and we've
applied all sorts of names to
that experience of our true
nature, our essential nature.
Now, what whatever this is, and
I think you and I have a pretty
good sense of what that
experience is, what this is. It
is the tip of the iceberg of the
unfolding, the intentional,
exquisite unfolding of this
trans, extraordinary
consciousness that we might call
divinity, or maybe not want to
call it divinity, this unfolding
which has been gestating in
creation for 13 point 7 billion
years, and that's only in this
big bang. We don't know how many
other expansions and
contractions of earlier
universes precede this
particular Big Bang explosion?
We don't know. I mentioned this
just to underscore the enormity,
the profoundness of the reality
within which awakening takes
place, and the reality within
which even deeper and deeper and
deeper awakenings take place, as
have been recognized by our
spiritual traditions, our
spiritual additions are only
345, 1000 years old, and that's
a lot of time for an incarnating
soul to penetrate into the
deeper texture of existence. But
if we were to go forward in time
100,000 years, and that's a wink
of cosmic time, but if we went
forward 100,000 years, surely,
reasonably, we would expect our
great. Great spiritual teachers
to be having deeper experiences
of the universe than our best
spiritual teachers today are
capable of having, because it's
it's an ongoing developmental
process of exploring the deep
mystery. So on the one hand, I
want to honor and affirm the
categories and description.
Descriptions of the beings who
have lived up to this point in
time, and I place my experiences
at their feet, and I I seek
their guidance and understanding
what has taken place. But just
as the absolute light came from
a reality far beyond whatever
the diamond Luminosity is.
Likewise, evolution is
continuing. Evolution is
developing, and we are nowhere
near even 10% of human
development. And so I would
expect and almost demand that we
expect deeper and deeper and
deeper capacities for spiritual
experience to continue to
emerge. So on the one hand, we
want to use the categories to to
help us hold on, to illumine,
understand. On the other hand,
we don't want to shrink wrap
them. We want to stay open. And
staying open in this way, I
think, is to stay open into is
to stay open to a deeper
intimacy with the beloved, to
stay open to the light that is
the light that gives birth to
the world, second by second.
Andrew Holecek: That's really
that's exquisite. And what comes
to mind again is this wonderful
kind of fundamental archetypal
narrative of openness, where on
one level, the invitation here
is an ideological openness that
we can very easily, again, the
near enemy of tradition, like
you, I have tremendous, oh, my
goodness, tremendous allegiance,
respect for tradition. But if
tradition isn't you, I think you
understand this in the best
sense of the word. Isn't
modernized without being edited
and distorted, then it can
become ossified. You can reify
even the tradition, and then we
become closed around our
ideologies and belief systems.
And so what I hear you saying
that I really appreciate is this
idol ideological openness.
Let's, let's keep even open to
that. But Chris, if I might a
question of clarity, and then a
few other things when you, when
you use the word extra Samsara
that that is not a term that's
in my common vocabulary. What
What do you mean when you talk
about the light as extra do you
mean post trans Samsara? What do
you mean by extra
Chris Bache: Samsara? I mean
beyond the Bardo, beyond all the
layers of the Bardo, beyond all
Samsara, at a place where the
patterns of cyclic existence
have been eclipsed. My sense of
it is that in between, you know
the physical reality and the
rhythms of physical reality.
When we die, we enter into
various patterns of Bardo
reality, various spiritual
states, but eventually that says
many, many, many layers, 1000s
of layers, but one can go beyond
that in what is the nature of
reality that's beyond the Bardo
existence? Yeah, the Buddha
refused to describe it very
wisely, right? Says, you know,
just experience it for yourself.
And you know, and my sense is
that outside of that, what
happens in the upper Bardo and
it the light gets brighter and
brighter and brighter until you
move into a world which is all
light, it's just all light, and
the quality of Light is is it's
different because it's trans
Bardo and all individualized
existence, and here I have to be
careful, because I for one, do
not see individuality as the
energy enemy of Spiritual
Awakening, because when we
stabilize deep, deep spiritual
awakening. Our individuality is
limit, liberated, not
extinguished. So I don't want to
say that in the domain of extra
Samsara Luminosity, there is no
individuality, but it is an
extraordinarily translucent or
an extraordinarily transparent
individuality.
Andrew Holecek: Yeah, I'm going
to make it a practice to just
pause and work with my usually
incredibly habituated reflex to
fill the space after you make
these i. Amazing statements,
because I want to rest in the
somatic impact of what you're
sharing and not capitulate to my
usual intellectual contractive
predispositions, which I don't
think pay respect and honor to
what we're trying to discuss
here. But let me ask you this,
Chris, so when this is very
interesting, I mean, there's so
many very profound principles
being explored and even
challenged here. So I'm
wondering how what you're
sharing with this. And I was, I
was probably as surprised when I
read this as you were when you
experienced it, the the
dissolution of the so called
omega point, that there isn't
some final destination. And I'm
wondering how you might
reconcile or balance what you
experience as this endless
evolutionary unfolding with
things, so to speak, quote,
unquote, like the changeless
nature. And the reason I
mentioned this is one way that
I've played with this, and
again, wonderful to be open
challenged along these fronts,
is that on one level, emptiness,
in this case, emptiness is
Dharmakaya. Emptiness doesn't
evolve. Form evolves. And so I'm
wondering how that lands with
you. When, when the Buddhist
tradition talks about Buddha,
nature is changeless nature. How
can something change and evolve
that doesn't have form? That's
the an oxymoron. Form evolves,
not emptiness. So how does that
land with you? How do you again?
It's like, oh, they we're
getting down to the razor's edge
of everything here. So how do
you is that a dissonance with
you? Or where? How do you play
with that?
Chris Bache: It's, I don't feel
it as a dissonance, and it is a
deep mystery, which I don't
pretend to fathom in any
profound, you know way. So I'll
just share a few bits and pieces
on those occasions when I have
relaxed into, fallen into, been
drawn into the unchanging
condition, the unchanging
reality, the reality within
which everything arises and
passes away and it itself is not
impacted at all. It is, it
appears to be, the fertile
empty, the fertile void. I want
to hold back emptiness there,
the fertile void from within
which all existence springs.
Now, if we then step into the
existence that springs from
within this cosmic, fertile,
emptiness or void, what's
happening. And we just look at
the big bang, and we look at the
magnificent story of the the
explosion of energy and the
congealing into matter and the
formation of galaxies and the
formation of solar systems and
Sun Life, and then emergence of
life and the emergence of self
and then self awareness, and so
on and so forth. Clearly,
existence seems to be going
somewhere, and it seems to just
delight in in the in form and
the unfolding and
complexification and making self
aware and awakening and and
empowering and the the
empowering of the soul, as our
former life memories become
conscious and we wake up to our
100,000 Year identity, not just
our 100 Year identity. So form
is going somewhere, and that
which is driving form is going
somewhere, and it's it's just
the magnificent creativity of
the universe. And that's why you
know the mind of the universe,
because I didn't want to call it
God, and that's why I got to
ever really comfortable with the
word Entheogen, because that has
Theos and our understandings of
God are so limited, so I yield
into the cosmologist language of
the universe, because we measure
the universe in light years 6
million million miles, and it's
billions of light years across
that bag that huge. And yet,
when we right now, as we become
self conscious as this, you
know, complex biped, and we drop
our awareness down to the center
of our self, what we find is
this magnificent reality which
feels to be a. Unchanging, and
yet it seems to be at the center
of everything which is changing
beautiful. So it seems to be
clearly kind of a both. And so
the Divinity, if we use the word
divinity for it, the divinity
which delights in existence has,
at least, and I don't know
whether this is ultimately true,
because we may just be
scratching the surface even now,
but it's nature, that infinite
nature, that it seems to be at
some level, unchanging at the
center perpetual change, and
that's kind of the best I can do
about it.
Andrew Holecek: I think it's
fantastic, and it's again,
completely revelatory of
conceptual frameworks, just
because concept can't relate to
the seeming paradox. It doesn't
mean reality doesn't abide by
those paradoxes, right? It's
only a parrot. It's only a
paradox to the conceptual mind.
Chris Bache: It has no problem,
exactly, exactly.
Andrew Holecek: It's only when
we try to shrink wrap it that we
enter into the world of paradox
and irony. On one level, to me,
this is beautiful, because this
is, in fact, one of the ways
that I've come to register this
marvelous dissonance. Isn't the
right word. But when, when
duality tries to open and wrap
itself around Non-duality,
which, of course, they cannot
do. One characteristic of that
is, in fact, this irony,
paradox, things that, like the
Niels Bohr, I love what he
introduced the notion of
complementarity. You know, the
phenomena can be, it's not
either or it's and they can be
both light and particle, we you
can be both. Chris Bache and the
cosmos, who says you can't be
both? If Aristotle says we can't
be both. You know, we live in
his we live in his world. And so
one other really important thing
for me here, Chris is there does
seem to be we talked, I believe,
very briefly about this last
time, I want to return to it,
because this is important to me
in terms of path quality. In
fact, very notion of path on one
level, there seems to be a
suggestion in your languaging,
in in what you're sharing here,
what you shared in your book,
this quality of return. I want
to return to the beloved. I want
to return to the light, longing
to return. And perhaps this also
lies in with this whole notion
of paradox, but I'm also
wondering how we can play with
that, with what, to me, seems
the more immediate aspect of
this is a large part I mentioned
this because this is a big part
of my current path is is really
decimating the notion of path
itself. That how fair is it, in
fact, to say the issue of return
is a provisional approach
description, and then perhaps a
more absolute approach would be
around recognition that you're
not you don't really need to
return to anything. The issue is
recognition and self liberation.
So does that somehow speak to
you when, when you reference
longing to return to the mother,
to the beloved, to the clear
light that, again, denotes the
subtle dualism I have to return,
versus No, I just need to remove
the cataracts of confusion, open
the aperture of my heart and
mind, and there the light the
mother is right in front of me
right now.
Chris Bache: Yeah, absolutely. I
think that's a fair observation.
Return implies absence, and the
nature of union dissolves
absence, and so it dissolves the
category of return, and it
encourages a different set of
categories, because it's like
the eternal here, the eternal
now. It's just here all the
time. And so I think that's
absolutely true, that it's a, it
is. It fits at one level, but
then it dissolves itself at a
deeper level. Now, having said
that again, I want to
contextualize this within my
particular journey, which is not
the same as the journey of
spiritual awakening. So the
journey of spiritual awakening
is this art and craft of
awakening into a releasing. All
the constrictions of the present
self, so that we can live in a
state of an abiding
transparency, or Shunyata, to
life as it flows through us like
wind blowing through the trees,
and we simply we rest in the
abiding present of the universe
as it continues to unfold.
Cosmological exploration is
different. It's kind of like
getting into a rocket ship and
going into a different at a
different solar system in the
galaxy, maybe even going into a
different galaxy all together
and and that is pushing the the
capacity of experience, pushing
the limits of awareness, so that
the condition of remembering
reaches beyond even The nature
of mind. It's not about simply
if, if I were had been seeking
only to awaken into the abiding
present, I would have adopted a
completely different strategy. I
think, I think Myron stole
Roth's recommendation of working
with very, very low doses of LSD
in meditation practice would be
a better strategy. But the the
strategy I used, working with
very, very high doses of LSD,
pushes consciousness so far
beyond enlightenment and and I
say that humbly trying not to
confuse the categories, not like
I'm enlightened and I'm more
than enlightened, not like that
at all, but it's going beyond
the state of the abiding
condition of emptiness into the
unchanging reality underneath.
It's going deeper into physical
reality, deeper into
consciousness. Reality. Where
does consciousness come from?
What are the prototypes that
inform the very structure of
time and space, the prototypes
that inform the nature of of
archetypal consciousness within
the human psyche. What are the
very forms that that are giving
birth to time and space? What is
the light that gave birth to the
world, not just the gave birth
to our moment to moment exotics,
but the light that gave birth to
the universe from that
condition, there is a sense of
return, entering that condition
and then coming back from that
condition. And that's why I
think what you say is absolutely
true within a spiritual context,
as we usually mean, spiritual
return is an oxymoron. It's
better to use other categories.
But from within a context of
cosmic exploration, maybe
there's a place, because I
personally cannot imagine how I
could personally, maybe other
beings could and can, and God
bless them, but I cannot imagine
how I could personally live in
some of the places that I have
touched. And so I can only visit
them as a as a visitor, as a
sojourner. And so I come back
and I try to bring back as much
as I can. I try to cultivate
whatever I can of that condition
in my daily life. But I know
that the vast majority of that
reality I will never be able to
bring back in this lifetime,
maybe 100 lifetimes from now,
maybe so I don't know, but I
will never be able to. And
therefore, in that context,
return has a certain ring of
truth to it.
Andrew Holecek: Wow, with again,
several things that come to mind
here. And again, I You're a
philosopher. It's interesting.
This is very compelling term for
me. I think in many instances,
things become philosophy because
they haven't become direct
experience yet. So then we use
that slight pejorative thing,
that's philosophy. And so what
you're sharing here is, is
really quite something. And I
wouldn't say this is, is, this
is simply to discuss it. I
almost said the word challenge
it, but that's not the right
word to discuss this, that what
comes to mind. And so educate
me. Teach me are again, I'm
completely admissive of my
frameworks, because I honestly,
unless I sit here in silence, I
don't have a choice. In fact,
silence is the language of God.
All else is poor translation.
I'm a poor translator, but I'm
doing. Best. So when you
something that that rubs me, and
I love the rub, because that's
what creates the pearl. How do
you reconcile? Teach me when you
talk about this, this
difference, and this is
foundational for you, but it
does challenge me when you talk
about, in fact, the difference
between the individual versus
the cosmic. Because let's, let's
take, for instance, the
reference point that does speak
to me, Chris, that that I'm
finding some refuge in here that
maybe is limited of Advaita
Vedanta, for instance, that how
do you reconcile the duality
that's inherent in your
statement that separates
individual from cosmological
because if, in fact, you're
saying that that deal still does
imply a duality. And so for me,
I I'm wrestling, playing,
dancing with this idealistic
I'm, you know, in Buddhism, as
you know, chitta, Mantra, yoga,
Chara, the world is heart, mind,
spirit. There you're what you're
saying here seems to intimate,
still some other cosmological
versus individual. And so how do
you work play with that in terms
of the what you were talking
about earlier, reconcile that
with oneness. Now, because on
one level, I seem to hear a
monism for you, but now you're
talking about dual aspect
monism. Again, I feel like I
think you understand it. On one
level, it's like, oh, please no,
don't become a philosopher. Here
I am talking about such
beautiful stuff, and here I am
dual aspect, monism. Oh, please
just go away. But I want to
understand this a little bit
more, so that when I leave this,
I'm not merely left with a
wonderful which is probably the
best, this wonderful
transmission from your
experience. But how do you play
with that? Is there, in fact, an
inherent cosmological dualism
when you say individual versus
cosmic versus a modernism that
you seem to suggest throughout
your journey.
Chris Bache: I don't see any
dualism in it. And if there is a
dualism, it's not of my making.
It's of the universe's making.
The universe begins as one in
some fundamental core, you know,
pre BIG BANG, instant Big Bang,
it begins as one and it
manifests diversity. I didn't
choose that. You didn't choose
this. We didn't choose it. The
Universe chose to manifest
diversity. We are part of that
diversity, and the universe
chose to empower in its process
of self emergence, it chose to
empower life to become self
aware and self empowering. So
read, the soul grows and grows
and grows. The soul is that
consciousness which holds the
awareness experience of all of
our lifetimes, multiple
lifetimes. So we're expanding.
We're growing and growing and
growing. We didn't choose that.
We didn't make ourselves we are
discovering a world that was
designed before we even billions
of years before we even showed
up on the scene. So we show up
in the scene, and we begin to
try to make sense of it, and we
begin to try to understand these
things. And one thing is very
clear, that there is a part, and
there is the whole. There are
many, many parts, and there is,
there is the whole. And when we
when our spiritual experience
deepens, we have experiences of
the whole. And at the same time
we experience ourselves as a
part. And how do we reconcile
those? I think we reconcile them
with a deep understanding of
emptiness Shunyata and emptiness
here is simply emptiness of
self, that when we open to the
wholeness of life, it's
immediately obvious that there
is no separate self. We are part
of life. We are an abiding part
of life. We are a bubble in the
ocean. We are part of the
process. That's why, to me,
oneness and emptiness are two
different sides of the same
coin. It's simply the experience
that I'm living and breathing
every molecule of my being,
every thought of my being, every
consciousness, every soul,
everything I am, is part of the
manifestation of the universe. I
am the universe in that respect,
and yet I'm obviously just a
little bitty part, a little
bitty planet, a little bitty
solar system, in a galaxy within
multiple building 2 trillion
galaxies. So we are part, and we
are we. Our Nature is the diet,
is the totality of the whole. In
that respect, there is no
duality, except the duality
which is forced upon us by the
conditions of life. But there's
no ontological duality. There's
a functional duality. De but I
don't even like to use
philosophical categories and
metaphysical categories, because
that traps us within human
thought. In the history of human
thought, and the history of
human thought, particularly in
the western philosophical
tradition, is so constrained it
is not rooted in deep
experience. It's rooted in
sensory experience and highly
intellectually refined sensory
experience, which is why I
think, of course, when we turn
the to the contemplative
traditions, different
philosophical insights emerge,
or different insights emerge
because it's a deeper
experience. And I think that's
the significance of psychedelics
for the West as a philosopher,
they not only give us new
clinical categories and clinical
insights and opportunities to
heal the personal psyche, but as
a philosopher, they open up the
entire world of cosmic
experience. And so as we try to
digest those experiences and
articulate them and understand
them. It allows us to draw from
a deeper set of experiences,
which allows us to basically
entertain a deeper set of ideas.
So I had a training as
philosophy of religion. I might
point to that only to
differentiate myself from the
good psychologists who are
working in clinical context. But
I don't speak like a
philosopher, do I? And I don't
do the things that philosophers
do, and they would disown me in
a minute. They are. They do
disown me, you know? So to me,
there's no duality. There's a
functional duality, which is
basically just a bubble on the
ocean of time and existence
Andrew Holecek: that that's an
incredible response to basically
a very subtle, thorny issue. One
one question Chris from the very
outset, is when you had the
experience of the diamond,
Luminosity, post session, post
meditation. Where does that
light go? What is the
relationship of that light to
the phenomenal display of the
world and appearance? Does the
world emerge from that light. Is
the world an expression of that
light, or both? So, so you, you
seem to, not seem you, you
entered return to a Luminosity
state, and when you, so to
speak, came down, came out of
it, this world appeared. What is
the relationship of the
discovery of that light to the
perhaps covering up, or that's
my languaging. Where does that
light go? How is it what is its
relationship to appearance?
Chris Bache: Yeah, good
question, which I'm not
competent to answer, but I take
some pointers from science and
some pointers from my
experience, the light doesn't go
anywhere. Of course, the light
is always there. We gain access
to it for a period of time, but
we withdraw from the light into
Plato, would say, the world of
shadows. But to me, that
denigrates the beauty, the
magnificence of physical
reality. Scientists tell us that
all the world is made of
molecules. Molecules are made
out of atoms. Atoms are made out
of subatomic particles.
Ultimately, we get down to
quarks. In the end, matter is
made out of light. Yeah,
correct. So if the scientists
are telling us that matter is
made out of light, and if we go
into our mind and drop into the
deepest levels of our mind, and
we encounter light. It's like,
well, you know, there's that
this is such a synergy there. So
my understanding is that the
light of doesn't disappear. The
light is manifesting the
physical world. The light is
manifesting as the physical
world. That means, when we
really sit with the whole trying
to hold it all together, we get
to experience the physical world
as the manifestation of the
Unified being, of being which is
light it manifests. And
everywhere we touch the world,
we find genius in the creation
of solar systems and how stars
live and die, and in DNA and in
ecosystems. Everywhere we're
touching the world, we find
layers and layers and layers of
genius. And if we keep digging
down deep enough, we fall into
quantum reality, you know, dark
energy, dark matter, light. They
call it dark energy, dark
matter, but it really should be
light energy, light matter. You
know, light, light, light. So if
I live, if I get depressed, and
I live in a state of sadness, or
I live in, live in a state of.
That disconnection, then that's
only that's only my own mind
throwing up shadows of illusion.
But when I'm clear, when I
return to clarity, I see the
world as a miracle. Yeah,
manifestation. And I love that
the Prophet Muhammad said that
the only miracle he would cite
for the truth of what he was
teaching was the miracle of the
universe.
Andrew Holecek: And isn't it
worth again? I'm sure you know
this, but perhaps it's worth
just reinstating that when you
say, I experience it, perhaps it
experiences itself right there
on one level. Yes, we use that
languaging. But even then, it's
almost it's, it is impossible to
talk about this without
stumbling into this. It's, it's
this, as you know, reflexive
awareness of the light itself.
And so, yeah, I'm wondering,
Chris, is it, is it fair to say
that then, I mean, this is so
integral to the whole thing,
it's literally enveloped in the
term enlightenment. This is a
and so I of all the teachings,
both in physics, cosmology and
spirituality, the ones that
captivate me the most, that that
I find the most ineffably
profound are, in fact, these
teachings of Luminosity, which
inseparable from emptiness. Is
emptiness slash Luminosity, is
it? Is it fair to say that that
what we know is our self sense
when we condense and contract
from the Unity I'm using my
language in here. Please correct
me if I'm wrong, from the unity
of that formless light back into
reified form in the worlds that
that arises from that
contraction, that that that's a
process of dissociation, that on
one level, we we again, again,
the narrative of openness, when
we completely open, die to
reality, it reveals itself in
this undifferentiated, ineffable
unity of of light, and that when
we can condense, reincarnate,
back into form the minute we do
that the world appears as self
another, and we simply lose
memory. We lose the recollection
of this, this fundamental
expression of the beloved as as
this body of infinite Luminosity
and emptiness.
Chris Bache: I think there is a
sad way of doing that, and then
there's a happy way of doing
that, or so maybe there's a
pathological way, but then
there's an entirely healthy way,
and imagine it this way. I mean,
let's use God language
temporarily, just because it's
kind of handy if, if we were to
become one with God for an hour.
And if God is the essence and
totality of all life forms, then
we would be becoming one with
all life forms. And just imagine
the nearby life forms in your
neighborhood that that would
involve becoming one with all
the Beatles and ants and grasses
and seeds and cockroaches, I
mean all the human beings and
all their manifest forms.
There's so many layers and
layers and layers and layers of
life. So when we say about,
well, we're becoming one with
God, we don't really mean, oh,
my God. We became one with the
billions and billions of ants
that are, you know, right in my
neighborhood. But in fact, if
God is one, if all life is one
in God, then that's what
involves. So what happens, I
think, is that we do become one
with one. We kind of reconnect
to the one. But the happy way is
that when we come back, I don't
come back into being an ant, I
don't come back into being a
toad or bird, I come back into
being Chris, a human being, and
there is a happy and healthy way
in which I come back into this
individual life form which
recognizes that its essence is
the same as the essence of those
ants and birds and toads. No
better, no different. It's more
complicated, but the essence is
the same. There is that profound
kinship with all of existence. I
happen to be a human bubble.
They are other kinds of bubbles.
Together, we make up the unified
existence of the totality. Let's
sing in celebration. We work
together. We didn't choose it.
We didn't create it. We are
awakening up within it. It is
the design of a deeper
intelligence, a deeper
organization that's that's
manifesting itself in joyful
diversity. We we. We can enjoy
the diversity. We can
acknowledge it and be
comfortable within it, and I
don't think there's anything
pathological about it. In fact,
there's an ecstatic joy in
celebrating being a human being
in the in the now, if we exalt
our humanness at the expense of
other life forms, and we're
willing for them to go extinct
in order to allow us to buy a
bigger you know, bigger and
better and whatnot. Of course,
there's a steep, deep pathology
there. But when it's truly
liberated, our our individuality
is recognized as a gift, just an
extraordinary gift, and a
responsibility. We have to
handle that responsibility in
order to protect the well being
of all the life forms that we
are part of, that that are
around us. Then the de the sense
of our common ground, the sense
of the common ground out of
which all life emerges, I think,
deepens and deepens and deepens
and so I don't really this is,
again, a sort of eco psychology
and eco spirituality. We can't
really awaken as a as a separate
self, without simultaneously
awakening as an earth self, an
earth being.
Andrew Holecek: Yeah, that's
that's fantastic. And and talk
about applicability. Sometimes
it's easy to think that these
are kind of elite, treasured,
sterile, Ivory Tower spiritual
experiences, but really these,
there's nothing more practical,
more applicable. This. This is
the farthest from being
philosophy, this is the most
radical transformation in view
from which activism, whatever
you want to call it, enlightened
activity, extraordinarily
practical, applicable behaviors
and actions arise spontaneously
from this. And I think this also
cannot be overstated, because,
to me, my big bug these days,
if, if what we're discussing
here is can't be of benefit to
what's happening in the world,
it's irrelevant. And this is far
from irrelevant. This is, this
is absolutely foundational for
this is right view. It is
ultimate basis. You from this,
from this foundation,
spontaneously, without thought,
arises the activity that is is
appropriate for this day and age
and so Chris as we well, let me
ask you this, when I, when I
hear you, you talking about
these experiences. These are,
these are types of Samadhi
states. You're you're entering
into particular absorption
states, like when you're bathing
in the light, you become the
light. That's a type of that's a
luminous Samadhi. Why does it
end? Why? Why? Why does post
meditation, post session still
take place? Why? Why not abide
in that light eternally? What
brings what's what brings you
back in? It seems, on one level,
it's involuntary, right? So, in
a certain way, we're talking
about rebirth processes. What is
the rebirth process? Involuntary
due to the unpurified habitual
patterns that still bring us
back because of their karmic
power. Why? Why does the Samadhi
and Yeah,
Chris Bache: well, once again,
there are some beings for whom
their Samadhi does not end. But
even those beings experience a
movement in and out. You know,
they live at different levels at
different seconds of every hour.
I would say my Samadhi ends
because I'm not. I'm a being who
cannot sustain those levels of
purity or those levels of
clarity in my current condition.
So the habits of consciousness
reassert themselves, the habits
of my embodiment reassert
themselves, and I once again, am
kind of looking at the world
through the levels of awareness
that I can manage in my embodied
existence. But in a sense, there
is a again, we spirit. Is the
goal spiritual awakening, or is
the goal cosmological
exploration? If the goal is
spiritual awakening, then there
is a way in which we can
realistically aim to enter into
a kind of Samadhi which is
abiding and allows us to live
with a profound sense of freedom
within the context of life. If
the if the experience. Mental
trajectory is cosmological
exploration. Then the burden of
that at least as in this path
that I practice, and I'm just,
let's just stay there and not
talk about the comparative other
paths. The burden of that
discovery is that it's
temporary. The burden is that
it's a Samadhi state, or maybe
even Samadhi is not the right
word for it, to go beyond, to
experience the future, to
experience the future of
humanity in a realistic, graphic
sense, to experience the purpose
of time, space, existence, and a
profound expansion of time that
allows you to span millions and
millions of years of history and
understand and absorb it, to
take it in. I mean, I don't how
could one possibly live in that
condition and have breakfast,
really? So that's just no if you
want to understand those things,
here's a way of doing it, but
then you have to, you have to
come back, and now you have to
live in my 72 year old self, and
I have to cut the grass, and I
have to do my things, and that's
okay, because if, if you do it
well, there is a happy way of
coming back, yeah, and
integrating and recognizing the
limits of what you experienced.
It's a temporary condition. No
big deal not to make too much of
it, learning more as I go. You
know, just so there's a there's
a healthy way, and then there
were all sorts of unhealthy ways
of doing it, but hopefully
healthy way it is. There is an
abiding calm and trust, an
abiding trust in the wisdom of
the universe, in its self,
emergent glory, yeah,
Andrew Holecek: would it be fair
to say, Chris, therefore that, I
mean, I hear rebirth,
reincarnation. We're basically
talking about this fundamental
process. Is it fair to say that
rebirth really takes place in
two dimensions of experience,
the degree of openness we can
tolerate, in other words, what
what they're there by, can bring
the end of and this is important
term for me that differentiates
my understanding of Buddhism
from other traditions. What ends
the process of involuntary
rebirth is, in fact, the ability
to coming back to this central
narrative of openness, to open,
open, open, open, open to such a
new degree. We're so familiar
with it, we're so comfortable
with it that fundamentally, when
that state is revealed at the
moment of death, we we abide in
and as that fundamental
openness, and then when we do
return, as you know, we do so
out of love, manifestation of
compassion, of chuku phenomena,
voluntarily embodying our
wisdom, not involuntarily
embodying our confusion. And at
that point, it's not that
rebirth ends, involuntary
rebirth ends. And just like you
said, done, the play Leo rolper
continues, infinitely out of
love and compassion in the
service of others. Is that a
fair way to share or express
your understanding of this?
Again, I'm trying to dance
around the dissolution of the
Omega point, right, that this is
the final goal. But on one
level, yeah, on one level, it is
the final goal for self, the
cessation of that self, but then
it's just the beginning of this
endless voluntary display of
wisdom and compassion.
Chris Bache: I think it's a very
fair description. I think what
ends is the involuntary nature
of reincarnation. And we
transition into voluntary
incarnation, and with that
comes, I mean, and I think we,
our future incarnations are not
the same as our past
incarnations in this respect.
And the way I've language this,
the way it was shown me in the
sessions, is that long term or
short term. I mean, in long
term, however, it manifests
itself intermittently. I think
in the end, we all become tool.
We all become voluntarily
incarnate, the human when the
entire planet is populated by
self, consciously incarnated
beings, humanity. Will have
transitioned to a new level of
its evolutionary trajectory. And
the way this was presented to me
in the sessions was the re the
birth of the diamond soul. So
all my former lives at one
point, started coming into me,
coming into me. And when they
hit, they hit a critical mass,
and they fused into one. And
when they fused into one, this
diamond light blew out of my
chest and catapulted me into a
deep, deep, deep state of
consciousness that was
individualized. It was
individual consciousness, but it
was individuality actualized in
a way that I had no previous
experience of, and I think that
that's where humanity is going.
All of us are incarnating every
generation. Billions and
billions of people are
incarnating, incarnating over
and over again, over and over
again. Sooner or later, the
entire species not only becomes
awakened, but the entire species
gives birth to this deeper
spiritual awareness which has
been gestating inside it all of
this time, all these hundreds
and hundreds and 1000s of
lifetimes, until we awaken into
our deeper awareness, which is
not just the awareness of
enlightenment, to the awareness
of awakening, but it's the
awareness of our history. It's
the awareness of our
relationship to the universe.
It's a deeper intimacy with the
intelligence of the universe,
the deeper intimacy with all
life forms on this planet. This
is When soul consciousness, and
I don't mean soul in a anti
Buddhist way, but in a way
that's compatible with Shunyata
emptiness, but soul
consciousness awakens, so that
we awaken to the being that we
are in the community of beings
as they are on a planet at this
particular stage of its
evolutionary development with
billions of years ahead of us,
and so I think we're just
beginning to see the edges. When
we first encountered
enlightenment to 5000 years ago,
we called it escape moksha. We
escaped Samsara, right? Let me
get out of here. But now we're
beginning to understand now we
want to awaken here and in the
awakening here we humanity makes
a pivot into a new stage of the
evolutionary story, and a not
not just a larger stage, but a
more peaceful stage, peaceful of
heart, non violent, more
compassionate, more insightful,
more creative. That's the kind
of planet that I think we're
giving birth to right now. And
all of our individual spiritual
aspirations and and pure face
purification aspirations and
healing aspirations and justice
aspirations, all of this are all
organically part of this deeper
story. And the deeper story is
that humanity is coming to a
point where it no longer has the
liberty of living at the lower
level of maturity that it's
lived at in the past. We cannot
afford. We can't run a planet
run by egos. We have to grow up.
And when we grow up, we grow up
into this higher form of
spiritual awareness that the
spiritual teachers have been
telling us about for 1000s of
years. But this begins a turning
point in human history. That's
what we're trying to give birth
to, what I call the future.
Human people give all sorts of
different names to it. We can
all feel it in our bones. It's
Maitreya. It's that higher level
of realization that is working
its way to us.
Andrew Holecek: You know, that's
really, really exquisite. And
I'm wondering, if you know, I
understand the languaging, but
I'm wondering if growing down
might be a more appropriate
embodied aspect, because the
growing up is again
fundamentally moksha, escapist,
FedEx my consciousness to a pure
land when it's really waking
down into the majesty, somewhat
nice way to start to close
things up with The integration
of your work, the waking, down,
bringing, metabolizing,
digesting, incorporating,
literally incorporating,
bringing into Soma body. You
know this, this vast
realization. But Chris, if, if
you don't mind me being slight,
devil's advocate here, that's
just for my stance. Sure, I I've
become very interested,
fascinated for some decades with
development, structural
development, not just not just
spiritual. And this is where I
like integral approaches. And so
I take utter, complete delight
in this vision. And make
aspirations that's may it be, so
that we can all become tukus.
But I'm also wondering, again,
wishful thinking, you talk in
your book about these
evolutionary breakthroughs, when
I look at the world and i i see
what's happening, and we can't
even agree as a society to wear
a mask for the benefit of each
other. Why? Why should there be,
at this point something special
that would occur, like a meteor
hitting this earth of sanity,
wisdom and insight that would
shake us from our collective
slumber and bring us to this
collective evolution and
awareness. It doesn't seem to
work that way. Evolution
stumbles and trips along these
very painful, laborious, long
stretches of time. I revel in
what you're saying, but I'm less
optimistic than I used to be,
that I look at this world and I
put my finger up to the winds
that are blowing, and it doesn't
it's not blowing in the right
direction, yeah.
Chris Bache: So be getting
worse. They seem to be going
away, right?
Andrew Holecek: So I'm curious
outside of of your experience,
and that that's ultimate refuge
for you. What else outside of
that, if there is anything else,
gives you the conviction to say
that that we're heading towards
this evolutionary break through
as a species. Can the big
question these days, will we do
it in time? I personally I'm not
so sure. I try to retain my
optimism, yeah, but it's
conjecture on my part, so I'm
curious how that that challenge
slash rub lands with you. The
development doesn't seem to work
this way.
Chris Bache: Yeah, outside of my
visionary experience, I have
nothing to say, I you know, we
all look at the data. We all see
what's going on. We see the
stupidity and insanity around
us. We see a growing eco crises,
series of eco crises. We
anticipate the desertification
of the middle America. We see
fat and famine on the horizons
already started, but penetrating
into middle class experience
slowly, we see the we're told
that the oceans a 12 foot rise
has already baked into the into
reality, unstoppable by 2050 12
feet by 2050 where we can
calculate How many billions of
people will be flooded out of
where they live and where I
mean, we know we're coming into
extremely difficult times. We
see the forces of conservatism.
We see the reactionary,
regressive forces that are
manifesting in politics
internationally. We see a higher
concentrations of wealth into
smaller and smaller numbers of
people, we see very, very
dangerous and forbidding trends.
And so outside of my visionary
experience, I have no certainty
or surety that this is going
someplace good. So the nature of
my experiences, if there and if
there is any, well, the nature
of my experience is that,
starting about around 1992 93 I
started having these consistent
visions coming in completely by
surprise, just as I had not
anticipated that one could
possibly do any type of
therapeutic work and healing
some aspect of the collective
psyche. I had no idea that it
was even possible to consider
having insights into humanity's
evolutionary trajectory. But
now, once I lived with this for
years, I began to understand
that this is a natural thing,
just as we have, as we go deeper
within our personal life, we
have a deeper understanding and
experience of our trajectory of
our personal life. One can go
deep If one lives in service of
the collective, one can have a
deeper and penetrating
understanding of the collective
trajectory. And in that context,
my experience has been
consistent over years and years
and years of psychedelic
experience and visionary
experience, first many years of
basically saying humanity is
coming to a turning point. We're
coming to a before and after.
We're coming into a to a dawn of
something fantastic. We're
coming to a genuine spiritual
awakening that everything that
our spiritual traditions have
been describing for the
individual. Guess what? It's not
an individual thing. It's
collective thing. This is a
call. Collective dynamic, the
forces of the Collective
Unconscious are activated, not
just my personal unconscious.
And then at that critical time
in 1995 when I had the 55th
session, and it and it when I
was expecting to be taken back
into the diamond Luminosity, it
dissolved me into the collective
psyche. It dissolved me into the
collective unconscious. Took me
into deep time, into an expanded
sense of time. And in that
state, I experienced the death
and rebirth of humanity. I
experienced a global systems
crisis that led to billions of
people, billions of people
dying, just a total unraveling
of cultures we have known it, of
civilization as we've known it,
a complete i i experienced our
entire species losing control of
its story, losing control of its
life on this Planet, just being
put under enormous, terribly
crushing pressure of death and
destruction. And it looked for a
time, it felt for a time as
this, this was an extinction
event, that we were really going
extinct as a species. But that,
and I was given no details. I
wasn't giving a timeline. It
wasn't given anything, given the
experience of the species going
through a Death Event on this
planet, all of us together, and
then I experienced that the
storm began to pass. The storm
began to subside, and those of
us who are still alive picked
themselves up and began to
rebuild, and what we were was
different than what we had been
before and what we be, what
began to happen was a
synergistic of conscious
Creativity, a synergistic of
compounded freedom, a synergy of
compounding insight, a new set
of values, a new set of
understandings, a new set of
capacities were manifesting
themselves, that humanity as a
whole was going through a
process that every spiritual
aspirant has had knowledge of a
complete collapse of reality,
saying known it, and a waking up
into a more spiritually animated
whole, magnificent, beautiful,
conscious awareness that
humanity was going through this
process. And then in the very in
my 70th session, the very, very
last session, once again, it
gave me kind of a capstone
experience, which took me deep
into the future. And it showed
me the archetypal structure of
this future human, the
archetypal form of it. And
truly, I mean, it brings tears
to my eyes, just to even
remember it, to think of it.
This is a this is a truly
different form of humanity. It's
like the best of the best of us
in it, our hearts healed, our
minds opened. Outside of my
visionary experience, I have no
reason for suggesting what I
have suggested as that humanity
is coming to this turning point,
this evolutionary pivot point. I
know that evolution has dead
ends, and, you know, whole
species die off, and whole
planets could die off, and I
know that there's no cognitively
compelling reason for having
hope. And as we enter the next
century, as we enter what's
going to happen in this century,
we are going to lose hope again
and again, and that's why I
think it's really important to
have a vision, an understanding
of what's taking place at a
deeper level, because it's going
to get bad. I mean, really
realistically, we could be
looking at more than half of the
human population of Earth lost,
and we'll watch it on television
every night, and it's just it's
going to wrack us with terrible
pain, but inside, we're going to
be led to do things that we
would not otherwise do. We're
going to be we're going to be
cracked open in this pain and
suffering, just as in a
meditation, deep meditation,
justice and deep psychedelic
experience, we will reach deeper
into ourselves and we have ever
reached before, and we will
accomplish something that we
might never accomplish without
this ordeal of pain. Now, the
other thing that I was shown in
the 55th session was some of the
mechanism responsible for doing.
Doing this that was in I was
shown this over and over and
over again, taken through it and
until I it was made sure I
understood it. And I'll just
mention it here and point to the
book. And that is, it has to do
with the functioning of the
collective psyche, and in this
time of accelerate, accelerated
and intensified individual
suffering. It's not just our
individual psyches that are be
activated, but all of the
suffering of humanity gathers in
its process at a centralized
level, as more as morphogenic
feel. Sheldrake has helped us
understand and so that the
scenario that was unfolded was
the collective psyche will move
into such a highly energized
state that it will begin to
operate as a non linear system.
Are far from equilibrium system,
and we know something about how
physical systems operate when
they enter into non linear
conditions. They are capable of
accelerated change. Small
perturbations produce expanded
outcomes. Creativity emerges
from within the system in
unprecedented way, hydrogen and
oxygen combined to produce
oxygen, I mean, to produce
water. Things happen that are
unanticipated according to a
system operating in linear
systems. And this was shown me
that this future is going to
take place, this pivot is going
to take place much faster than
we could ever imagine if we used
our calculation based upon the
past, it's going to take pace
faster, more quickly. It's going
to be deeper than anything that
we could imagine in the past.
Now I I know that sounds like
optimism run amok, and I
understand and everybody has to
make their own decisions on
this. All I can do is simply
here, report the vision and let
it go at that. And then we're
all in this together, you and I,
and our children and
grandchildren, we're all in this
together.
Andrew Holecek: Yeah, yeah. I
mean, it's interesting. Part of
me says, May it be so, and
another part of me says, May it
not be so, then I'm wondering,
Chris, as we start to wrap up, I
know your time is valuable.
We've covered so much amazing
material, really, and
prescriptions, what, what? I'm a
level, some, some things are
implied with our time together,
but prescriptions, what what to
do, or in a certain sense, not
to do, how to bring our
individual, empowered selves or
lack thereof, to to actually
help this world, both now and
you know, for our ancestors. So
some let's, let's end on some
prescription notes, if we might,
Chris Bache: in terms of the
transition that I've been
describing, someone that I know
and love and respect very
dearly, who has thought a great
deal about what we can do, how
we can accelerate this process,
how we can remove the worst of
the pain and move into the this
new future better quicker. Is
Dwayne Elgin and his book
choosing Earth is a beautiful
book, powerful book, small book.
He lays out what he thinks the
next five decades are going to
look like, and it's not a pretty
picture, it's it's a frightening
picture. But he also lays out a
series of prescriptions, of
prescriptions for how we can
engage this future, how we can
bring about a safe landing, how
we can change and engage
socially, individually and
socially. And I think he his
advice is worth much more than
mine. Dwayne Elgin choosing
Earth, and he's giving the book
away. You can get a PDF on
Amazon. It's giving he's giving
it away because it's so
important. He's not trying to
hold on or make money on it
himself. He's it's all in
service of humanity. I would
step also add to that reminder
that from a reincarnation
perspective, each one of us,
every one of the 1000s and 1000s
of listeners in your program,
and all of us around the world,
we chose to be incarnated at
this time in history. We chose
to be incarnated at the time and
place that we incarnated with
the talents and challenges that
we brought into this
incarnation. We are exactly
where we are supposed to be in
order to make a creative
offering to this time and.
History, we don't have to go
look elsewhere. The only real
question is, do we have the
courage to actualize, to
activate the potential that we
are standing on right here,
right now, once we make that
commitment, that our life, my
life will count towards the
good. Then we look around us and
we say, Okay, what needs to
happen? What? What are we trying
to become? And then we put our
hands to work. And since we're
all different and we all have
different missions and different
agendas, some of us are in the
medical field, some of us in the
political field and
philosophical field and creative
field, and hard labor, all these
things, every human talent will
be required to bring this about.
So it's not a matter of kind of
looking elsewhere. It's simply a
matter of looking at where one
is already incarnated to make
service spiritual practice is
important, facing the shadow,
clarifying the shadow, becoming
open and individually receptive.
Community is important, not only
practice community, but social
community, learning how to do
more with less, sharing,
restructuring society, political
community is really important.
We see what happens when ego
runs amok in our politics. All
these things are needed. All of
these things are important. All
we have to do is look around and
see what needs to be done and
give ourselves to it completely.
Andrew Holecek: Wow, wonderful.
Wow. Anything that you wish I
would have asked
Chris Bache: any, any, I don't
know, yeah, it's in serious
territory, partner, yeah,
Andrew Holecek: rich, but as we
really wrap up, I mean, there's
so many summary statements here,
but any, any other final
thoughts or questions you felt
should have been directed your
Chris Bache: way? No, you know,
you mentioned the living
classroom in the beginning, and
it's not, it's too late to go
into a large excursus. But the
basic, the core of that book,
which doesn't mention
psychedelics, is the core truth
that's manifesting there is that
consciousness is unified from
the start, so that everything we
do in our individual sphere, our
individual field, radiates out
around us 360 degrees. It all of
our spiritual practice, all of
our actions, everything we do
radiates around it, touches and
interacts with the consciousness
of the beings around us. Knowing
this, then we take more
responsibility for making sure
we're sending out, you know, a
positive experience in the
world. You know, beneficial
experience, and we are never,
ever, ever isolated from those
around us. We it may be
invisible, it may be subtle, you
know, but it's always there. And
the more we act on that basis,
the more we activate the
strength of those sinews that
bind us to life. And if this is
true, of course, not just for
human beings other human beings,
it's true for all the life forms
that surround us. And that's the
core teaching of the living
classroom, that there's an
atomistic quality to teaching,
and then there's a quantum
quality to teaching. So like you
and I have been having kind of
a, in some ways, an atomistic
conversation, but we can trust
that there's a quantum, a
quantum quality to our
conversation, yeah, yeah,
Andrew Holecek: field effect
that is that extends beyond our
limited self sense, which is
illusory in nature, and we have
these, I think, the wonderful
way to end, because really, it
invites us to really discover
that we have so much more power
than we think in both negative
and positive ways, and the
thoughts that we hold, the
aspirations, the motivations,
It's not just encapsulated in
this little ball of skin. It
just, it's a pebble radiating
out throughout the cosmos, not
just this world. And I think
really understanding that will
empower our ways to benefit the
world. So Chris, I can't thank
you enough for spending so much
time with us. I It's really
quite remarkable. I'm thrilled
to have spent this time with
you. I've learned so much. I
applaud your bravery, your
heart, your capacities in doing
this. It's marvelous, and it's
really being of great benefit.
Chris Bache: So thank you for
the conversation, Andrew, thank
you for your work, bringing this
conversation and many similar
conversations into the world.
Conversations change. Lives.
Thank you for what you do, and
just thank you for the
opportunity to talk about these
things together. It's been,
Andrew Holecek: it's been a
delight for me too, and like we
talked briefly last time, this,
this, I haven't really thought
of it before. The dialog, the
conversation, the sharing, is
actually a quality of path
itself is new for me, and I
haven't really thought of it
that way. So it's a wonderful
insight of many that you shared.
So thank you so much for
everything. Let's do it again
with the next book that comes
out.
Chris Bache: Oh no, help me, but
I'm always happy to have a
conversation with you.
Andrew Holecek: Yeah, really,
yeah. It's such a delight,
Chris, till next time, thank you
so much for your time. Good
heart. Love and blessings. Love
and blessings. Thank you, bye,
bye.