Unknown: You You You You Oh,
welcome to om times TV, a
division of OM times media and
broadcasting. You. Sand,
welcome to what is going on for
new thought from the edge of OM
each week on om time's flagship
radio show, veteran broadcaster,
author and media consultant,
Sandy sedgebear conducts thought
provoking interviews with
inspirational authors, artists,
musicians, scientists, speakers
and filmmakers who are working
at the point where spirituality
and science meet consciousness
at the very edge of OM here is
your host, Sandy sedgebear,
Sandy Sedgbeer: hello throughout
the years that I've been
conducting interviews on
science, consciousness and
spirituality, I've read numerous
mind shifting books and heard
goodness knows how many extra
ordinary stories, but the story
you're going to hear today is so
Far beyond remarkable that I've
struggled to find words to
adequately describe it. All I
can say by way of introduction
is that what you're about to
hear is a story that I didn't
know until I read it, that I and
no doubt countless millions of
seekers have been waiting for
our entire lives. Christopher
embeche is professor emeritus in
the Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he
taught for 33 years, a fellow at
the Institute of Noetic
Sciences. He is also adjunct
faculty at the California
Institute of integral studies
and on the advisory board for
Grof Transpersonal training and
the Grof Foundation, an award
winning teacher and
international speaker, Chris
Bache joins me now to discuss
his book LSD and the mind of the
universe. Diamonds from heaven,
which has been held as a
gripping account of an utterly
unique and extra ordinary hero's
journey that opens our minds and
hearts to a new vision of our
universe and ourselves as
inseparable from the ineffable
being that we have called God.
Chris Bache, welcome,
Chris Bache: hi, Sandy. It's a
pleasure to be here with you
today.
Sandy Sedgbeer: This is a long
awaited interview, I have to
say. Chris so little background,
in 1979 you took the first step
on a life changing journey to
explore your mind and the mind
of the universe as deeply and
systematically as possible, with
the help of LSD, if you had
known then that it would take 20
years of excruciating pain,
suffering, bliss and intense
purification, plus many more
years of digesting, processing,
organizing and writing to
publish this book, would you
still have put yourself through
it?
Chris Bache: That's a good
question. I'm not sure that I
would. I think knowing now what
i If I had known then what I
know now, I would have been
gentler on myself. I would have
used in a gentler protocol,
balancing high versus low doses,
balancing LSD with Psilocybin
and Ayahuasca, I still would
have taken the journey, but it
might not have been as taken as
aggressively as I did.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Yeah, yeah.
Well, knowing the outcome, you
can't really say No, I wouldn't
have done it. So you experienced
73 high dose LSD sessions
following protocols established
by Stanislav Grof with the
intention of engaging hyper
intensive states in a way that
would allow the initial chaos at
each new level to clear and also
allow your own biophysical and
psychological systems to adapt.
How did you know the precise
dosage to accomplish that in the
way that you wanted to
Chris Bache: well, Stan was very
clear in his early books and in
LSD psychotherapy. It was
published in 1980 the protocol
differences between psychedelic
and low dose therapy versus
psychedelic high dose therapy,
psyche lytic running doses
anywhere 50 150 micrograms and
high dose psychedelic therapy in
four to 503 50 to 500 and at
that time, high dose psychedelic
therapy was being worked used at
Spring Grove Hospital in
Baltimore, and they were trying
to basically trigger something
approximating a Near-Death
Experience for people who were
dying, they Were terminal
patients and trying to give them
a glimpse of where they were
going. And I thought, well, if
you could do this work three
times safely, then you could do
it more than three times safely.
And I chose to work with high
doses of LSD for a couple of
reasons. One, I I had a false
model of of what the project
was. The model I had was a model
of personal transformation. I
thought this was about my
personal healing, my personal
spiritual awakening. That turned
out to be an incomplete,
profoundly incomplete model. And
I was thinking that, you know
spiritual awakening is about
clearing your karma. Our karma
ultimately is finite, and by
working with high doses, I would
basically being it was. I knew
it would be more difficult work,
but I thought of myself as
basically biting off my karma
and larger bites and clearing it
faster. Turns out that that's a
false model. Personal
Transformation was too small to
describe it, and the doses I
took from the literature, I
basically wanted to push my
system as hard as I could to be
efficient. I mean, I was in a
dual career marriage. Getting
time for these sessions was very
complicated. Had to balance a
lot of schedules, and I wanted
to get as much done in every
session as I could. Again, what
I learned on along the way is,
because consciousness is unified
at its source, that when you
hyper stimulate consciousness,
you're not just hyper
stimulating your personal field
of consciousness, you're hyper
stimulating some portion of the
unified field of consciousness,
and therefore the dynamics that
get activated, the dynamics of
healing and purification and
illumination, are much, much
larger than. Then personal
dynamics.
Sandy Sedgbeer: At what point
did you realize this, this
wasn't going to be a personal
journey at all, that there was
so much more going on.
Chris Bache: Well, for about the
first two and a half years, it
looked it followed very much the
material that Stan Grof had been
tracking. My first two and a
half years of work were very
much perinatal in nature, going
through the Death-Rebirth
process, experiencing, really
experiencing one's birth,
experiencing a profound
confrontation with death and the
meaninglessness of existence.
But then i This culminated in a
crushing ego death experience
and a liberating ego death
experience. And then, according
to Stan's early descriptions,
what I was expecting after going
through ego death, access to
Transpersonal reality would get
easier. But what happened in my
sessions is that I began to go
through the periods of vast
suffering that got deeper and
deeper and larger, terrible
suffering and pain, not
personal, collective, opening up
to the suffering of 1000s and
hundreds of 1000s of people and
1000s of years of time. And at
first I thought this represented
a deepening of ego death, but it
went on for so long and it
involves so many people, that
eventually I had no alternative
to but to come to the conclusion
that what was being healed or
transformed in this process was
not my personal psyche, but some
aspect of the collective psyche
of humanity that just as
personal trauma gets
internalized in our personal
psyche and can produce
pathology, likewise, the vast
quantities of trauma that
humanity has absorbed through
history gets collected and
internalized in the collective
psyche and produces a kind of
Social Pathology at the
collective level. And something
was using my sessions to
basically address and heal to
some degree, this collective
trauma.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So there didn't
seem to be anything random about
this journey, because sometimes
you didn't have a session for
long periods, even years, but
when you went back, you always
seem to, you know, catch up
where you were the time before.
Chris Bache: Yeah, that was my
sense of it, too, that I was
engaging a long and sustained
conversation, communion,
initiation, with a larger
consciousness. And the size and
scale of this consciousness kept
deepening and changing as my
work continued and it I always
felt myself engaging in
intelligence. When this is most
dramatic, perhaps this
continuity across time. I did
four years of work, I stopped
for six years, and then I
started again for another 10
years of work. When I stopped, I
was working on the ocean of
suffering material in the
purification phase of a session.
I was engaged in this ocean of
suffering. I stopped for six
years, six years later, in a
completely different time of my
life with different expectations
when I went into the work again,
the ocean of suffering started
exactly where it had stopped and
continued, indicating clearly
that the the intelligence that I
was engaging was guiding what
was happening. It was in charge
of my sessions, and all I did
was really open up, isolate
myself from the world, open up
and follow wherever it wanted to
take me. And I found that if I
trusted myself completely and
surrendered to where it would
take me, I would go through
these intense purification
processes or death processes.
Eventually it would culminate in
some type of crisis or
breakthrough, and then I would
be spun into ecstatic,
revelatory experiences for the
remainder of the session, and
the next session would begin the
cycle again. So I just, I
learned to trust that process.
Sandy Sedgbeer: But, but the
suffering, you know, there were,
I was listening to it on Audible
as well as reading the book. And
there were times when I was, you
know, speaking to you and
saying, My goodness, why are you
going back? You know, it is so
painful.
Chris Bache: You go back, not
because the, you know, I don't
like pain. Who likes pain for
nothing like that? You go back
for the joy that's waiting on
the other side of pain. You go
back. Right with the
understanding that this, the
suffering, this pain, is in some
way a purification process,
which I did not understand the
full scope of it at the time,
but I trusted Stan's work, and
it was affirmed in my work that
this is a purification process,
and that when you go through it,
then the doors open, and that's
why you do it, for the
revelations, for the insights,
for the visions, for the for the
opportunity to enter into such
deep and profound communion with
the universe.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So the suffering
is the gateway. It's a gateway.
Chris Bache: It's it's just a
Prana. You know, we have to let
go of being small in order to
enter into being large, and it's
not always easy to let go of
being small, but it's not just
let going letting go of your
personal identity. You know, we
in therapy, we often focus on
ego death, and many of the
mystical traditions focus on ego
death, but what I found was that
ego death was just the first of
many patterns of death and
rebirth, so that what one is
letting go of at deeper levels
of the journey is much larger,
much deeper than just egoic
structures. And it's such a
mystery that at the end of the
book, I actually have an
appendix where I ask the
question, what dies when you're
so far beyond ego death and yet
you are still having sensations
of dying, loss of control? What
is it that's actually dying in
that process?
Sandy Sedgbeer: Yeah, yeah,
exactly. And when we listen to
it, you know, we can't help
asking the same question. So I
don't want to focus too much on
individual sessions, but there
was one that I really did want
to bring up, and it's actually a
whole collection of sessions
where you experience life as
many different women in turn,
what do you think was the
purpose of those experiences and
how did they impact you?
Chris Bache: Well, that was my
that was my ego death
experience, where the universe
after about, this is a 10th
session, ninth, 10th session. It
just broke me like a twig. It
just took my identity and
snapped it. Now I had begun the
day as a white Ivy League
educated philosopher,
passionately concerned with the
meaning of existence and the
universe, forced me to become
the exact opposite of that. I
became women. I became women of
color. I became women who were
not interested in the meaning of
life at all, who were not
educated at all, and it did not
allow me to experience I was
myself, but I was myself in all
these other roles, other modes.
And it terrified me. It just
scared the bajeebus out of me,
and I fought it, but eventually,
when I gave up and I
surrendered, and I allowed
myself to become all these
women, then suddenly things
shifted, and I was taken under
the arm of the Great Mother and
initiated into the lives of
Hundreds of women the more
positive side of female
experience, given many
experiences of women's lives,
conceiving, giving birth, loving
husbands, loving children. And I
think that the fundamental
message here was not reclaim
your former lives as women. I
know I have former lives as
women. That has never been a
question for me. I think the
issue was where you were going.
Gender does not exist. Let go.
So I was being taken into a
level of reality where male
female is irrelevant. But to do
that, I had to be broken of my
male identity. I had to allow
myself to go into some larger
identity. And becoming women was
simply just part of that
breaking process.
Sandy Sedgbeer: The whole the
whole 20 years seems to have
been quite a massive break in
process. I mean, you were doing
this. Nobody knew about it
except your wife. You weren't
allowed to talk about it to
anyone, or you didn't allow
yourself to. You were teaching
mature students philosophy. And
often, you know, there were
aspects of things that you were
teaching where your experiences
would have been the perfect
example to offer them, but you
couldn't do that. What was that
like for you?
Chris Bache: It wasn't so bad in
the beginning, but it got
increasingly difficult as I went
on, especially when I could feel
a question coming from students.
That had personal, deep
significance to them, and an
answer would spontaneously rise
from my person which but an
answer that was grounded in my
psychedelic experience, and I
couldn't. Some of them, I could
lay off on the Stan grofs
experiences or other psychedelic
research experiences, but some
of them, I couldn't lay off, and
I could not bring my own
psychedelic experiences forward.
And I began to experience a
catch in my throat. My voice
would actually kind of, I would
lose control for a split second,
and it would sound like a little
bark coming out of my voice. It
was embarrassing. I mean, I was
I was literally strangling on
what I wanted to say and was not
allowed to say, and that became
difficult because the cost of
doing this work I knew would be
my silence, and I paid that
price. But I did not realize in
the beginning that when you
commit to dividing your life in
this way, to have a daytime job
as a straight professor and then
a nighttime job as a Psychonaut,
that it causes fractures in your
psyche which reach deeper than
you may have anticipated in the
beginning and in the end, these
cracks were only able to be
healed when I finally came out
of the psychedelic closet and
began to allow myself to speak
openly about these experiences.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Most people
these days, especially in the
spiritual arena, are familiar
with NDAs, reincarnation,
channeled works that explain who
we are and where we go in the
afterlife, and you've taught
courses on these yourselves, but
your experience took you way
beyond where anyone has gone
before. It gave you a whole new
vision of the Bardo. Tell us a
bit about that.
Chris Bache: Well, the classic
understanding of the Bardo, I
think, was affirmed in my
sessions, that is, there are
many, many, many layers of
spiritual reality, and when we
die, we return to that layer
that reflects our spiritual
development or spiritual
maturity. And it's a, it's a,
it's a social domain. There,
there are other beings. There,
not only other incarnate beings
or discarnate beings, but there
are also guardians and guides
and so forth. And the basic idea
is, after you die, you go
through a debrief process in
which you process your most
recently completed life. You
learn what you kind of what you
did poorly, and what you did
very well. You go through this
process, and then you go through
kind of a returning to the world
of spirit, to returning home,
and eventually you go through
when it's time to incarnate
again, to the choice process of
incarnating again. And because,
because the evolution of the
soul is so vast and covers such
a wide spectrum of development,
it takes many, many, many
lifetimes to actualize the full
potential of a human existence.
And so there are many tiers of
the Bardo domain. And my
experience affirms this classic
vision. I had many experiences
of kind of tapping into Bardo
reality. And it's a collective
reality. I think the ocean of
suffering. Kind of is analogous
to the Buddhist concept of the
hell realm. I tapped into
levels, which would be analogous
to the the high deity realm in
the Buddhist cosmology of the
Six Lokas, of the six realms.
And there are also, there is a
reality that's outside the Bardo
when you get basically, in a
sense, graduate from the Earth
system, when you move beyond
that spiritual echo of time,
space experience, and enter into
the reality beyond all Bardo
existence. And that is
correlated with what I would
describe as the diamond
Luminosity, the domain of
diamond Luminosity.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Why do you call
it that?
Chris Bache: Because that's,
that's, that was the experience
one encounters light, often in
deep spiritual experiences and
near death experiences in
psychedelic experiences, when
you go through a Death-Rebirth
process, often you have the
sensation of being flooded with
light, encountering light. It's
almost a universal in the
spiritual traditions. And I had
experienced light at. Many forms
and many times in my practice.
But when I came to this advanced
stage of my work, which started
with the 45th session, I
encountered a light that was
unlike anything I had
encountered previously. It was
incredibly bright, incredibly
beautiful and clear. The hardest
thing to describe when I say
light, it's almost like it
becomes so refined and so
intense, it becomes invisible.
It's just Clear. Clear. Your
mind is just so incredibly
clear. And I came to understand
what the Buddhists meant when
they say touching this for one
second undoes 1000s of years of
living in the shadows of karma.
It is radically pure, clear, and
once I touched that, I wasn't
interested in exploring any of
the other dimensions of
spiritual reality that I had
encountered before, which
include collective dimensions,
the collective unconscious,
archetypal reality, even
dimensions of causal oneness.
This was something totally,
completely different. And in the
last five years of my work, in
26 sessions, which is 1/3 of my
entire journey, I only touched
this reality four times, okay?
And every time I touched it, it
would trigger more purification,
more detoxification, and a
year's worth of work before I
was able to come back and touch
it again. Wow.
Sandy Sedgbeer: And was that
something having touched it that
kept you going. You know, had
you seeking it again and again?
Chris Bache: Absolutely, yeah,
the last third of my work, that
was my agenda, was to go back,
so do whatever I needed to do to
go back into that reality.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So if I
understand this, right, and you
know, I haven't read a huge
amount about the Bardo, but what
you're saying is that there are
these different layers, if you
like, almost stages, and over
probably millennia, we gradually
go through them, but you went
through them, you know, in that
much time. You know, what kind
of effect does that have on
someone?
Chris Bache: Well, I want to be
careful here. I think what
happens in a psychedelic,
therapeutically focused
psychedelic session, or
spiritually focused psychedelic
session, is that you speed up
what is happening in life at a
slower pace in a natural
process. So reincarnation, as I
understand it, we are growing,
we are evolving. We die, we
return to soul consciousness.
We're born. We contract down
into egoic consciousness. We
die, we go back into soul
consciousness, and that we keep
this up and keep this up over
long periods of time, we choose
lives which challenge us,
stretch us, heal us, allow us to
develop new talents, new
capacities, to deepen the
capacities that we've started.
What happens, I think, in
psychedelic therapy, is that
that whole process is
accelerated. This is, I think
this is true for meditation. In
meditation, when you do long,
sustained retreats of
meditation, you are speeding up
the process that's taking place
at a slower pace in ordinary
life. And so I get you do bite
off larger pieces of personal
karma, but then something else
takes over. It's not about your
personal enlightenment. It's not
about your personal development,
your ties to the human family,
your ties to the family of life,
your ties to the universe
deepen, and you begin to feel a
sense of dance, or a sense of
engagement of this deep,
profound life process. And I
think, I think you can take it
too far, then is comfortable.
You can take it so deeply you
can, you can be dissolved so
completely into these vast flows
of consciousness and vast
dimensions of existence that
it's very hard to come back out
of them. And it's it's hard in
the sense that it's hard to
leave the joy. It's hard to
leave the clarity and the
ecstasy and come back into time
and space. Now that doesn't mean
because you've touched them and
because you've known them. It
doesn't mean that you can
stabilize that awareness back
inside time and space. It
doesn't mean. You have
accomplished what some of the
great spiritual teachers have
accomplished, who can abide one
foot in, one foot out in those
realities. I really, really
emphasize, this is a path of
temporary immersion. It's
temporary you have not just
because you've had a temporary
experience of oneness of life or
Transcendence, doesn't mean that
you are as fully developed a
spiritual being as somebody who
can abide in that reality. And I
all honor truly to the great
spiritual masters who have
abiding the capacity to abide in
that reality. So I wouldn't say
necessarily that I accomplished
all of those evolutionary
journeys in one lifetime, but I
certainly did do something
pointing in that direction.
Sandy Sedgbeer: But you also you
can't unknow what you know, and
when you come back knowing what
you know, it must be hell to,
you know, have to, you know,
move into a world that is so far
away from that that is just, you
know, falling apart on every
level. I mean, how do you cope
with that? It's such a
dichotomy.
Chris Bache: It is challenging.
There are mitigating processes,
though too, because the deeper
your experience of the
intelligence of life and the joy
of the creative intelligence in
manifesting existence, then you
begin to look around you, and
you see the universe for what it
is. The universe is the body of
the Divine. The body of God. The
universe is the manifestation of
the intelligence, of a profound
intelligence, and once you touch
that intelligence, I mean, we
all know what intelligence looks
and feels like. We recognize it
when we meet it in people. And
this is a cosmic intelligence
that just overwhelms you with
its brilliance and its wisdom
and overwhelms you with love.
Unlike beyond anything I had
ever known in this lifetime, and
I've known love in this
lifetime, this is a different
order of love, and once you
experience those things, then it
changes how you see the
universe. It changes how you see
life, and it also gives you a
larger horizon within which to
understand the human experience.
I mean it, I read, I adopted
reincarnation on the basis of
the empirical evidence. Early in
my career, I read Ian
Stevenson's work. I read the
early work on a past life
therapist, and I was convinced
intellectually that
reincarnation was a fact of
life, but it still takes years
to truly absorb and live into
the fabric of a universe that
pulses in a reincarnation cycle,
not just for the individual, but
for the entire human species. So
I had experiences in which I
understood my current life as a
continuity of extending from
previous lifetimes. But I also
had at a deeper level,
experiences of the entire human
species pulsing generation by
generation, pulsing in as a
reincarnation species, and that
all of our individual challenges
and our individual karma was a
fractal manifestation of this
larger species challenge, and
this species karma that we were
working and when you have those
experiences, you look at other
human beings differently. You
look at the planet differently.
You look at the Galaxy
differently. There is a sense of
deeper participation in a
mystery, which you may not
understand the details of, but
you can feel the joy because you
know the you've touched the
intelligence that's behind it,
and that makes it eat, that
makes it more joyful to enter
into it. Now, there is a sadness
that you can't sustain those
peak experiences. But in another
month or two, or I was doing
this about four or five times a
year, I would go back into this
reality, and not every time
necessarily, but I would go back
often enough that I would be
able to drink deeply again, the
full cost of how deep I went did
not really emerge until I
stopped my sessions at the end
of the journey, the universe
basically told me it was time to
stop, and I could feel. Feel
that it was time to stop, and I
stopped, but it was only then,
when I wasn't returning in a few
months to have another deep
communion with my beloved, that
I began to realize the true cost
of overextending, overextending
myself as deeply as I had into
the transcendental side of
existence.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Before we go to
the break, there's a one
question. You said that the
universe is the body of God.
What are we?
Chris Bache: We're part of the
universe. So we are part of the
body of God too. We are part of
the manifestation of the
intention of the universe to
create our mind, just as our
body is rooted in the quantum
reality of life and the atomic
reality of life and the whole
evolutionary story is built into
the nerves in the vascular
systems and the organs of our
body. So we become inseparable
from life as it is manifesting
in the galaxy, in the planet on
this continent. Likewise, our
minds are part of the creative
intelligence that's manifesting
existence. That's why, when we
go deep into our minds, we drop
down into the curse depth of our
personal mind, and we find that
there is no floor at the bottom
of our mind. We fall right
through into the mind of the
species, right through into the
mind of the universe. And when,
when you go that deep, then,
then the Hindu teaching, Atman
is Brahman, the essence of the
individual is the essence of the
totality that just becomes the
most natural thing in the world,
that becomes core truth, and one
of the likewise a core truth is
oneness. To Brahman is one, and
we are part. We are an aspect of
fractal manifestation of that
oneness. Once one has known that
then even when you go back to
paying your bills and doing the
things we do in the physical
world, all you have to do is
step back, and then you can re
appreciate these deeper truths,
which are the deeper pulsing of
life. We're going
Sandy Sedgbeer: to take a short
break now. I'm Sandy sedgebear.
My guest today is eminent
philosopher and theologian,
speaker and author, Christopher
M Bache, whose latest book, LSD
in the mind of the universe,
diamonds from heaven, which
rigorously chronicles his
intensive, systematic, 73
session, 20 years, psychedelic
series of journeys into a
unified field of consciousness
that underlies all physical
existence. This is completely
mind blowing, so I need a break
just to reset my mind so that I
can ask intelligent questions.
We'll be back in a few moments.
Stay tuned. Welcome back. Chris
Bache, you've made it quite
clear that there is an
evolutionary dimension to all of
this. And as you move into the
later chapters in the book,
where you talk about the birth
of the diamond soul, you begin
to see that we are at an
evolutionary cusp, and the
global systems crisis that you
know we're all experiencing
right now is part of that for
what point? What? What is the
ultimate, you know, purpose here
of all of this happening?
Chris Bache: Yeah. Well, let me
break that down into two parts,
the classical vision, first on
reincarnation. A few words, the
classical vision of
reincarnation as it's held in
most Eastern traditions, is that
you grow, you get clear, kinder,
more generous, you cultivate
deeper and better qualities, and
eventually You come to a
spiritual maturing where your
consciousness opens to the core
of your being, and you awaken to
the fact that the essence of
your nature is, in fact, the
essence of all nature, and that
all beings and you are sharing
the same nature. There's an
explosion of compassion and a
deep embrace of the universe and
their interpretation of what
happens next is that you are now
free to leave time and space you
in the Hindus called it Moksha
escape, to escape Samsara, and
this up and out cosmology. All
the religions of the Axial Age,
in one way or another, are all
part of. A pattern of an up and
out cosmology. We don't want to
be on Earth. We got here by
accident, and it's a veil of
tears. We want to get out of
here, either by salvation, our
enlightenment. We want to get
out of here. But that leaves
fundamentally unexplained. What
is the purpose of the universe?
What is the purpose of this
magnificent creation, and now we
have a deeper understanding of
the size of existence, the
magnitude of the universe. How
many billions of years went into
the evolving and unfolding of
the universe. And it just
becomes profoundly unacceptable
short sighted to think that the
purpose of life is to awaken to
your true nature and then escape
into nirvana or escape into some
off planet paradise. At a
critical point in my work, I had
the experience of all of my
former lives coming into me.
They were just coming in, one
right after another, and it was
like wrapping string, white
filament of light, white light
around a kite spool. And at a
certain point, all those lives
fused into one consciousness.
And at that point there was an
explosion of this diamond light
out of my chest, and I was
catapulted into a deeper state
of consciousness than I had ever
touched before. And I was an
individual, but an individual
beyond any frame of reference
that I had ever known. And this
is what I came to call the birth
of the diamond soul. And that
is, I think, that as we
incarnate over and over and over
and over again, sooner or later,
the soul, consciousness that we
return to when we die, wakes up
and manifests inside our time
space consciousness. We
literally the soul wakes up
inside time and space, fully
conscious 100,000 year old being
not 100 year old being fully
consciousness with an intuitive
awareness of the breath of human
relationships and an ability to
enter into deeper communion with
the cosmic intelligence. And at
that point, we don't leave at
that point, we begin to live
differently on the planet. And I
think the entire human species
is evolving into the in this
direction to this point, the
entire human species is evolving
into fully manifesting soul
consciousness. And you know,
when I say soul consciousness, I
don't mean separate, isolated
from each other, fully
transparent. Shunyata,
emptiness. Anita, no self
concept, all affirmed but a soul
manifesting consciousness. And
if you can imagine a planet of a
species filled with souls, fully
conscious souls, that species
would create a different life on
this planet than we've ever seen
before. At another point in my
work, later in my work, I began,
actually, over a period of about
four years, amidst everything
else that was going on in my
sessions, I began to have dumped
into my awareness a series of
visions about human evolution.
And the message was always the
same. We are coming to a turning
point, a point of profound
spiritual awakening, a before
and after in human history, that
it would involve tremendous
collective purification. But
this collective purification was
emptying out the kind of the
pains of history to lay a new
foundation for this infusion, a
new infusion of divine energy
that was rising up within us. It
was clear that, and I was given
a taste glimpses of the future
human. This a transformed
humanity that would emerge out
of this. But it never showed me
how nature was going to pull
this off. It never showed me how
this would would work. And then
several years later, in 1995
when I was already had already
transitioned to the diamond
Luminosity phase of my work. So
I was working at pretty advanced
places on a particular day at
the end of 95 when I was
expecting to be taken, hopefully
back into the diamond
Luminosity. Instead, it took me,
it dissolved me into the
species. And so Chris Bache just
dissolved into the human family.
And then as the human family, I
was taken into the future, into
what I call deep time. And there
I began to experience what I.
Came to understand was a death
and rebirth process that was
impacting the entire human
family, just as an individual
goes through an intense
Death-Rebirth process when they
do spiritual practice or
psychedelic practice, history
was putting the entire human
family into a Death-Rebirth
process. I experienced an
unraveling of life, a profound
loss of control. We were losing
control of all the ordinary
assumptions of life. There was
just a cascading series of
crises that were breaking us
down level by level. I was not
given any details. I wasn't
given any calendar of events,
but this was a global crisis
that seemed to be triggered by a
cascading series of ecological
crises. Beyond that, I wasn't
given the details, but the
whole, the whole system of life,
was coming crashing down, and
then, just when it was at its
worst, Just when it seemed like
we would all be dying, that this
was an extinction event, the
peak of the storm passed, and
things began to get easier, and
we began to pick ourselves up,
and we began to rebuild
civilization. And when we did,
our entire existence was
different. We were suffused with
new ideas, new things, new ways
of thinking, new values, new
capacities within the human
heart, which generated new
social relationships and new
social institutions, somehow
going through this profound
global systems crisis broke us
down, broke us open, and tapped
us into the universe at a deeper
level than we had ever been
tapped into before, so that when
we went through this crisis, we
were changed profoundly as a
species. And what came out of
this crisis was not just a new
civilization or a new economy or
a new industry. What came out of
it was literally a new kind of
human being that this is a shift
in the plate tectonics of the
collective psyche, a shift in
the fundamental core of the
collective psyche. Now, humanity
has been through shifts in the
past like this. There was a time
when we shifted and our brain
size increased 50% that's
enormous shift. This is
something like that. It's a deep
shift of the collective psyche,
so that every human being born
after this takes place, will be
living their individual
awareness will be alive within a
field of a collective awareness
which is different than the
field that we are in now and
today.
This is what I call the birth of
the future human, and I think
the form that the future human
will take will be the diamond
soul. We are giving birth to a
new species on this planet, a
species which is spiritually
awake, a species which is
spiritually mature, and a
species which is a soul
conscious species, a soul aware
species. And by that I mean
something beyond anything that
we've ever talked about soul
before. Because I think our
restrictions, our concept of
soul, have been restricted by
assumptions we've been making.
And that's why I call it the
diamond soul, to signal that
this is something new. This is
something different. And I think
our great spiritual masters, our
great saints and saviors, Jesus,
the Christ, the Buddhas, the
prophets, these have been giving
us foreshadowing insights into
the nature of the being that we
are becoming. They are the
prototypes of the being that we
are all becoming. And then late
in my and even late in my
journey, I was taken deep into
deep time, and was given my
deepest experience of the future
human and this being is most
magnificent being just an extra,
ordinarily magnificent,
beautiful being of a vast heart,
of a mind capable of drinking in
deep from the creative
intelligence and a heart capable
of experiencing the fundamental
oneness of all of life, and a
being that experiences the
fundamental oneness of life
would never hurt another being,
not just another human being,
never heard another being and
such a being would build a
different world than the world
we're building now. So.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Should be in has
no need to evolve.
Chris Bache: Oh, I think this is
simply the next step in our
evolutionary saga. I don't know
how long it's going to take for
this transition to be affected.
I truly don't. I mean, I think
it'll be at least generations,
whether it'll be something that
will be accomplished in 100
years or several 100 years, I
don't know, but however long it
takes, let's say it took 1000
years, which I think is
stretching it, because I think
we'll be dead if we don't make
this transition sooner than
that, we are either going to go
extinct, I think, or we're going
to transition into this new
form. Extinction is a tremendous
accelerator of evolution, near
extinction, the threat of
extinction, whatever, however
long it takes, whatever we
become, evolution isn't going to
stop. We've been at this for
billions of years. We're going
we're going to be at this for
billions and billions of years
more. There's no telling where
we might be going next and then
next after that. So I don't see
it as an end point or a stopping
point. I see it as simply the
next point. And the next point
is to wake up to who what's been
really going on, to who we
really are, to wake up to the
depth and breadth of our
relationships with life itself
and other people and other
species, and then we continue.
Sandy Sedgbeer: It's been 24
years since you stopped. Do you
feel that you have fully
integrated all of those
experiences?
Chris Bache: No, I haven't. When
I finished my sessions and was
beginning the digesting process
my meditation, in my meditation,
the universe said to me, 20
years in, 20 years out. And I
thought, Oh, it'll take me 20
years to assimilate 20 years of
my journey. And as I was getting
to the end, when I was writing
diamonds from heaven, I thought
that was probably an optimistic
assessment. I think it'll take
me many lifetimes to fully
integrate all the gifts that
I've been given.
Sandy Sedgbeer: What do you
think in the light of what
you've told us, what you've
learned, what you've seen, we
most urgently need to address
now as a species,
Chris Bache: boy, there's so
many layers to that question. I
think first we start by taking
full responsibility for our
shadow, for engaging our side,
our shadow, and clearing any
obstacles and blocks which are
impeding our compassion, which
are impeding our healthy whole
psycho spiritual functioning. We
need to reconnect and rediscover
our relationship with the
universe and our fundamental
core identity with the universe.
We need to overcome all these
several 1000 years now of
teaching which places humanity
at the top of the evolutionary
pyramid, and as being unique in
kind, and not just unique in
degree, but unique and kind and
superior to all other life
forms, and all other life forms
serve us and can be used
exploitively by us, all that has
to be transcended, and We have
to enter into a renewed
communion with the universe,
with spiritual reality and with
physical reality. I think we
need to recognize that our body
is divine, not just our mind and
our heart, but our body is part
of the manifestation of
divinity. Sri Aurobindo thought
that humanity eventually would
become so spiritually energized
that the body was sufficiently
psycho plastic, that the body
had the capacity to live
forever. He said his calculation
would was that it would take 300
years of spiritual practice
before we would reach the point
where we could set in motion the
chain reaction that would have
our biological body perpetually
refreshing itself as we live in
communion with divinity. Now I
don't know about that, but I
find it to be an intriguing
vision from a profound teacher
about the potential that we're
activating. What's important is
to realize we're we're just
children waking up in the garden
that's been underway, being
developed for billions of years.
We just are beginning to wake up
to what's going on, to who we
are, to what's happening. We
really are. Like children in the
in the playpen, but where I
think we're about to get out of
the play pen, to walk, I think
we're about to become mature
adults.
Sandy Sedgbeer: You feel that
there is an urgent need to get
psychedelics back on the table
so that their efficacy can be
proven and we can start adopting
them as a way of helping people
to, you know, heal their wounds
and hopefully evolve even more
quickly.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think so. I
think they're very valuable
substance, and fortunately, we
are reclaiming them after our 40
year interruption, because these
are amplifiers of consciousness.
Everything hinges on how we use
those hours of amplification. If
we use those hours of
amplification carefully and
wisely, then these these
substances can help us heal the
wounds of life. We can go deeper
than that. These substances can
help us recover the insights of
our true nature, of our
essential nature, of our
fundamental core identity with
all other life forms. They open
up spiritual platforms within
us. I think that psychedelics
have a profound philosophical
significance. This is a
different way of doing
philosophy where we
systematically temporarily
expand our mind and then come
back and then write it down and
then analyze and crunch our
experiences and compare them to
other people's experiences. One
person's experiences are never
important by themselves. It's
when we get many, many people's
experiences and put them all on
the table together and begin to
find out where the common ground
is. What are the common themes
that emerge? That's where we
begin to develop a truly
trustable epistemology, a
trustable set of insights into
what's going on. So I think
these are enormously valuable.
They have to be used very
carefully. They should be used
with great respect. When one
amplifies one's consciousness,
the dirt comes out of the
system. And if you're not
prepared to meet that dirt, or
you open up under wrong
circumstances, it can be
terrifying. You can do dangerous
things, but if you've taken all
the precautions and you open up
under the right circumstances,
there is nothing that comes out
that can't be beneficial if you
face it with courage and with
grounding and with skill. And I
think we are, we are now
training the next generation of
psychedelic therapists. We are
training people to help other
people use these substances
beneficially.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Well, of course,
you know, back in the 60s, there
was a move. A lot of people were
involved in doing experiments
with these to find out how they
could be useful to humanity, and
they got shut down. Are you
hopeful that this time we will
be able to move forward with
this and find the benefits and
allow people to benefit.
Chris Bache: I hope so. That
seems to be where we're going.
The psychedelic Renaissance is
really focused on personal
healing and by treating the
conditions that are generated by
modern culture, post traumatic
stress disorder, depression,
addiction, death anxiety, we're
using scientific methodologies
and carefully frame studies in
order to document the beneficial
effect of these substances. Now,
once we do that, once we
establish them and bring them
back as legitimate subjects for
discussion in scientific and
just educated society. Then I
think we'll be going into the
next second and third levels,
where we'll begin to realize
that these capacities, these
substances, not only heal, have
the capacity to heal, but they
have the capacity to reveal, to
open, to illumine now
civilizations have known
Indigenous peoples have known
this for millennia. Ayahuasca is
used in South America going back
at least 1500 years. Peyote,
Mescaline mushrooms, indigenous
people have been using these
substances to open up spiritual
communion. For millennia, we're
catching up, and so therefore
the indigenous people really are
our teachers and how to use
these substances wisely.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Do you ever
wonder why you Why did you have
this? Experience and not someone
else.
Chris Bache: Well, first, many
people have used these
substances wisely and have had
these and types of these
experiences. So I'm just a
representative of a whole social
movement, and maybe I pushed the
edge harder than most, and maybe
I because of my training, maybe
I wrote it down and and analyzed
it and kind of worked out the
details more than most. But I
don't see myself as unique in
any way. I see myself as part of
a social movement. When I got
out of graduate school and I met
Stan grofs work, as soon as I
met his work, I said I knew this
was my work. This was my
calling. It was just it woke up
inside why that was the case.
Eventually, it really came back
to decisions that were made when
I was in the Bardo before I
incarnated what my soul's work
was going to be, and my soul's
work really was very much around
education and very much around
healing, but not
psychotherapeutic healing one on
one, but really engaging healing
at a very deep collective level.
And I think that there are many,
many people working at this
level. I think there are many
hidden saints working to bring
about the birth of the huge
human I think there are many
Bodhisattvas in the world. Some
of them are recognized and most
of them are not recognized. But
who really are they invest their
life in bringing about the
transformation of the lives of
others, of helping others and
helping us make it through this
crisis of that we are entering
into, the global systems crisis,
the ecological crisis. Is it
bearing down on us? It's going
to take all of us, I think all
of us chose, to be here at the
time and the form that we
incarnated. I think there are no
victims. There are no there is
no compulsion and reincarnation.
We all chose to enter this time
in history. We we may not
remember why, but we chose to be
here. We chose to be part of
this process.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Chris Bache,
thank you. Thank you for joining
us and sharing your incredible
journey, and thank you for
sharing it with the world.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Sandy.
It's been my honor and pleasure
to be in discussion with you
today.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Likewise so LSD
and the mind of the universe.
Diamonds from heaven. It's
published by inner traditions
beer and company. And for more
information about Chris Bache is
articles, events and his other
three books, the living
classroom, teaching in the
collective consciousness, dark
night, early dawn, Steps to a
deep ecology of mind and life
cycles, reincarnation and the
web of life. Visit his website
at Chris bache.com That's it for
this week. I'm Sandy sedgebear.
I'll be back with another
edition of what is going on at
the same time next week. Till
then, it's goodbye from me and
thank you again to Chris Bache.
Thank
Chris Bache: you, Sandy. You
the.