Unknown: I mean, for for
listeners again, who don't know
like it wouldn't appear as
though this conversation is
couched in your 20 year journey,
your 40 year journey as a
philosophy professor, and a 20
year journey with high dose LSD
sessions. And the book that were
we were referring to earlier is
your book on those journeys, as
well as a number of other books.
And I'm just curious, because
what I'm seeing in the world,
which is mostly the world that
is mediated by a screen at this
point, is not is not the kind of
place I really want to be both
in. I don't both in the sense
of, I don't want to be where it
appears we're going. I don't we
want to be a part of a system
that does the things that it
does, you know, like the I
don't, I don't like the fact
that I'm a part of this
disgusting, distorted thing, and
also what I see from the
behavior of the people around
me, and there's a lot to be said
about how social media
algorithms and and isolation and
mental health crises
acknowledged or not, are
contributing to this, but I see
a lot of toxic behavior, a lot
of toxic people, a lot of toxic
discussion, sort of, like,
draped in this sort of, like,
this sort of self confident,
self righteous, almost
Machiavellian style, like
moralism, of like, the good
versus the evil, and the good is
me, and anyone that disagrees is
Like the violent devil I must
cast out and and whatever else.
And I don't feel good about what
I'm seeing about the world, and
it makes me want to just like,
hide away inside now, yeah, that
said couching this in
psychedelics and looking at it
as as a large psychedelic I'm
using air quotes for listeners
process that's happening
collectively on a global scale,
not just with humanity, but
we're although we don't know
what the feelings and the
thoughts or perspectives are,
the birds and the salamanders
and the and the whales and
whatever. You know they're going
through that with us. So it's
like a planet. It's like a
planetary experience, right?
Yeah, that when I see these
parts of myself in a psychedelic
session, it's no more
comfortable by any means. It's
equally as ugly, yeah, you know?
And I want to hide away from
that too. And yet, yeah, one of
the things you talk about in
your book is that you we need to
learn as a part of the
psychedelic journey. We need to
learn how to not turn away from
our pain, or from that pain. I
mean, like the pain of touching
a hot fire we turn away from,
but this kind of pain that we
learn to turn towards it. And
I'm wondering if you could just
that's not a clear question, but
can you just comment
on, yeah, yeah.
Chris Bache: You know, the
starting point of serious
psychedelic work is taking
complete responsibility for
one's own shadow and and you
just go into a room, close the
door, lock the door, you're
inside by yourself. Nothing
there but you and your mind and
you go into the parts of your
being which are at least
initially, the most daunting,
the most intimidating, the most
frightening, the ugliest ones we
like to acknowledge, the least
you know, and but the commitment
is there to take that on, to
enter into it, when we see that
ugliness being manifested in the
world around us by people who
are not have not yet taken
responsibility for themselves
and they they are still in this
exterior mode where the shadow
was really outside of them, the
evil and the darkness and the
really ugly things were outside
of them. That's a very different
world, isn't it? And I think
this whole process of breaking
down, this breaking down process
that we're going into is
basically going to be breaking
down that defense that we have
to thinking that, you know,
we're the good guys or and the
other people are the bad guys.
And eventually we're going to
have to come to terms with the
fact that we're we did this. We
created this imbalance. We have
benefited from it. We are
continuing to generate it in the
cars we drive, in the lives we
live, in the lifestyles we
aspire to. We have done this. We
will we have done it. There's
going to come a time eventually
where there's no place else to
look but we have to. Take
individual and collective
responsibility for the pain that
is that is alive within us and
lives of everyone around us.
That really is a pivot point, I
think, when we just stop blaming
the other, stop blaming previous
generations, stop blaming so on
so forth. We really settle in.
We're not there yet. Some of us
are there yet. I mean, I think
the psychedelic community
understands these things,
because that's how you make
progress in psychedelic work, is
you confront the shadow. Now,
when you go into the work, you
know that the more you purify,
the more you cleanse, the deeper
the reward, the deeper the
ecstasy, the deeper the
teaching. So the more you
purify, the deeper the
communion. Once you learn that
not only do you become more
comfortable facing the shadow,
but you actually, actively
embrace the shadow. You active,
actively embrace pain and
suffering, not because you like
pain and suffering, but for two
reasons. One is because you
learned that the deeper the
purification, the deeper the
ecstasy. And you don't like to
suffer, but you like what's on
the other side of the suffering.
But the second thing is, you
embrace the pain and suffering,
even knowing that a lot of it is
not yours, because out of the
same compassion that every
father has for His children,
every mother has for her
children, and every teacher has
for all of their children
eventually that everybody has
for other people, and you
embrace the pain, not counting
whether it's yours or somebody
else's, but because by doing so,
you are helping somebody. You
are helping other beings that
you may never meet. And my
experiences has been that if you
do that, if you are willing to
take on more than your fair
share of suffering, you reap
more than your share of benefit.
The universe responds. It can't
help but respond. And I think
that's going to be happening
with us generationally, this
generation, the next generation,
the generation after that, is
going to go through suffering,
more than their share of
suffering, compared to previous
generations. And after they stop
kicking and screaming and begin
to get down to taking it on and
just doing it, I think they will
experience the blessings that
come from that deep generosity,
that profound existential choice
to work with the given, even
when the given is terrible, even
when it kind of crushes your
personal life, but you still
dedicate yourself to The good of
the whole, and in that process,
something begins to change.
Something shifts inside your
person, and the more complete
the surrender to the process,
the more complete the commitment
to that process, I think the
deeper and the faster the
transformation is in our
individual lives in our
collective lives, so that as we
move deeper into this and come
through it, I think
generationally, we will learn
what every psychedelic journeyer
learns, that we confront the
shadow there is Riches on the
other side of this ordeal, and
there's no other way to get to
it, and in the end, the irony
is, you kind of end up where you
were in the beginning, except
you're all cleaned out. You're
just all sorts of this gunk is
out of your system. So you are
you, and you are where you were
before, but you literally are
living a different life, because
stuff that you hadn't realized
was compromising you and
burdening you is no longer
there, and something new has
taken its place. I think that's
where we're going to be going.
It's going to take time. I
Unknown: You.