Chris Bache: Um, I think
Stevenson's evidence is really a
strong evidence for some type of
continuity of an awareness from
lifetime to lifetime, especially
his last two book, which is a
two volume book on philosophy
and on reincarnation in biology,
in which he studied 170 87 cases
of children who not only had
psychological recall from their
previous lifetime, but actually
bore the marks in their body in
the form of birthmarks, which
replicated wounds of death in
the previous incarnation. So
somehow, it was as if
consciousness had been
traumatized in such a way that
it not only imprinted on
subsequent mind, but it
imprinted on the body of
subsequent mind. So after
looking at this data a lot, I
think what it tells us is we
have information in our mind
that predates this body.