Bas de Cock: Thank you all for
joining. I will give a short
outline of tonight that you know
we have two and a half hours
together, which is a great
amount of time, and you will see
the time will pass as fast as
you entered now. So tonight, we
start with an achievement and
meditation to just settle in
with the theme we, yeah, we just
program for this, for this
wisdom, keep us gathering. And
of course, we're gonna, we're
gonna look ahead to the upcoming
hour to hour and a half with
Chris and Duane. So what are
their backgrounds and why
they're here? And you're gonna
see they're coming from two
different angles, two different
perspective, two different
paradigms, I would say. And this
is a beautiful dance we're going
to encounter. What are the
possibilities, especially
creating a new mindset as
humans, a mindset of the whole
universe. Because it's not about
the technological evolution of
the world leaders. You're going
to create a diminishing of
greenhouse gasses. You're going
to drive your electric car.
You're going to put more trees
in the ground. You are more kind
to your neighbors, where that's
the start, where the mindset
starts. And after an hour and a
half a dance with Chris and
Duane sounds like music in my
ears. We have the last 45
minutes, half an hour, to look
ahead for creating more circles
as a as a community, as a human
family, to create and to
practice this new mindset. So
we're gonna we're gonna guide
you through this step by step,
and please sit in your
comfortable chair. Have a good
evening. And before we start, I
would like you to close your
eyes, trust us as hosts, we're
good people. We came with a good
mission. And ask you the
question, so why are you here
tonight? What's your real
intention of your presence
during this gathering with
Dwayne Chris and all this human
family.
Are you here out of curiosity?
Are you here to learn? Are you
here to thrive?
Whatever your attention is
doesn't matter or really sense,
the reason why you're here
that's already in here in this
moment,
visualize your intention for
this evening as if
Unknown: it's the present time.
Bas de Cock: What's your
contribution to this beautiful
world we're living in.
What do you sense from your
core, from your heart, why
you're here to contribute as a
whole, as a whole human family?
And if you have a
deeper understanding why you
contributed tonight, then try to
remember this for the rest of
the evening,
and please feel guided from a
meditation we're going to start
now.
And before we start this
meditation, take some deep
breaths,
just to settle in to
you allow yourself to open up to
this visualization. I'm going to
guide it now for you
sense that you are floating. In
a galaxy, and you have a clear
and bright view on Mother Earth,
it
Unknown: feels at home
Bas de Cock: floating in this
universe and seeing our common
ground, Mother Earth,
you Feel at peace and deeply
connected to this beautiful
planet in a sky full of stars,
you can deeply feel you made
this journey before, And now you
feel so grateful to see Planet
Earth from this perspective
again,
Unknown: excitement,
Bas de Cock: ecstasy And tears
of joy are felt over in this
privacy present moment,
you feel a pool of Mother Earth
pulling you towards her body,
and
you can sharply feel and see all
the continents and the oceans of
Mother Earth coming into your
view,
pulled more closely, you have a
clear view on your own
continent.
You see your country, where you
live, you see more sharply your
province,
and you zoomed in to your own
city. You can feel your
neighborhood, your neighborhood,
you know so well,
instantly you see your house.
And the interiors of your house,
the inside the furniture, and
you see your loved ones sitting
in your beautiful house.
And then you sense your back in
your body. You can feel your
skin.
You can feel your organs. You're
in your bones. You are aware of
your breath.
You are aware of the heartbeat
of your beautiful heart, you
feel instantly at home, the same
feeling when you watched Mother
Earth From above,
Unknown: what a journey, a
journey
Bas de Cock: from beyond. You
Unknown: nothing lasts forever.
No one lives forever. You. A
flower that fades and dies,
winter passes and spring comes
embrace the cycle of life that
is the greatest love.
Go beyond fear. Go beyond fear.
Beyond fear takes you into the
place where love grows
when you refuse to follow the
impulses of fear, anger and
revenge beyond means to feel
yourself start every day singing
like the birds. Singing takes
you beyond, beyond, beyond
beyond. We need a repeated
discipline, a genuine training
to let go our old habits of mind
and to find and sustain a new
way of seeing go beyond the
rights and the wrongs. Prayer
clears the head and brings back
peace to the soul. Go beyond to
feel the oneness of the unity.
Sing, singing, take you beyond.
Beyond. Go beyond.
We are all the same, all the
same, looking to find our way
back to the source, to the one,
to the only one. Go beyond
revenge. Greatest moment in our
lives is when we allow us to
teach each other go beyond, to
feel the oneness of the unity
singing. Singing takes you
beyond, beyond, beyond. Beyond.
Take the journey. Take the
journey inside of you, to become
quiet, to hear the beyond,
to become patient, to receive
the beyond, to become open, to
invite the Beyond and be
grateful. Be grateful, to allow
the beyond be in the present
moment, to live in the beyond.
Start every day, singing like
the birds, singing takes you
beyond, beyond, beyond. What
does love have to do with it?
Love grows when you trust, when
you trust, love heals and
renews. Love inspires and
empowers us to do great things
and makes us a better person to
love. Love makes us feel safe
and brings us closer to God.
When you go beyond,
is where you find True Love.
Keep singing. Singing takes you
beyond. Beyond.
Bas de Cock: You make connection
to your breath again, deep in
your breath,
and take your own time to open
up your eyes and going external
to all people who joined this
gathering, feel free to make
some contact with the people.
Look at the thumbnails the faces
and before we gonna introduce
Chris and Dewayne, I want to
thank you for all the donations.
There are a beautiful amount of
the donations done as a gift for
the choosing life project and.
We're gonna hear, hear more
about it from from Dwayne, I
think so. Thank you for that.
And I also want to take a moment
to introduce mayo, my co host
during the wisdom keepers every
month. And I want to say that
also Melanie is one of the
hosts, but she can't contribute
tonight because she has a course
running. So mayo, before we go
to Dwayne and Chris and we're
going to open up, please feel
free to share something from
your side. Dwayne, your
microphone is still off,
Unknown: everyone. Thank you so
much for taking the time, for
being here with us. Can you hear
me now?
Bas de Cock: Fantastic.
Unknown: It is so important to
have these conversations within
ourselves, but imagine the power
of sharing our ideas and
connecting from a human stance.
And these conversations,
although they're mediated
through this platform, right a
technology that is provided us
the sense of community, even
though we may be continents away
or as bosses, beautiful
depiction of our neighborhood,
in our house and wherever we may
be, this what we are doing and
what we just did through that
guided meditation is truly
beyond it is combining our
energies into one essence, into
this consciousness. So it is so
important to have this meeting,
to have more conversations in
your neighborhoods with those
around you, so you can share
your reality and how we can co
create that reality together. So
thank you so much for being
here. We look forward to growing
with you, to having perhaps a
meeting that is face to face one
day a wisdom keepers face to
face. But for now, let's sit
tight and enjoy the ride.
Tonight's competitions are going
to be very much expanding our
universe into what we can do as
human beings here, now and
today, so that we can come
together as one species in order
for us to thrive as a whole. So
thank you so much for being here
taking the time.
Thank you, Maya.
Bas de Cock: Yes, before we
gonna start with Chris and
Duane, and we're gonna introduce
them, of course, and I'm gonna
also highlight why we are here
together, also with Chris and
Dwayne, I invite you if you have
the feeling you want to write
something down, something like a
question, something like
something coming up, an emotion,
or something you feel in your
system, you want to write it
down. Feel comfortable to do so.
It's handy. The second part of
the wisdom keepers gathering,
that we have a Q, a and a
sharing part, where these things
can be shared, and feel open to
do so, and feel that this
environment is reliable and you
can trust this environment. So
we're here with a good heart.
That's what I want to say. We
were going to see if we're going
to use a whiteboard to share all
our information or to have more,
like an integration of the
things coming up, and we're just
going to feel organically if
this is going to happen. So if
I'm going to show up a
whiteboard, I'm going to explain
how we're going to use the
whiteboard, but we're going to
see, okay, before this idea of
asking initially, Chris and
afterwards, Dwayne came up as
well, in my mind, in our minds,
and It's, it's a beautiful
coincidence, they're both at
this gathering, and would like
to introduce them, both from
from the heart and from
perspective, but I want to say
something personal, because
since I started, I'm a
background medical doctor, an
ENT doctor, trained an ENT
doctor, and then I'm more like
opening up, which is, I think,
more like a calling into into
life, more in integrative
medicine. And now I'm into the
Grof legacy training for
Transpersonal psychology and
psychedelic therapy. And that's
where I met Chris. Chris, I was
at your beautiful course from
the shift network, LSD in the
mind of universe, and it opened
something up about how we going
to take care of this planet and
of this universe, because it's
all integrated and it's all it's
a one life. System, or one whole
world system. So that's thank
you for that. That's what I want
to share personally, and it
until now and after my own
psychedelic experiences, it's
getting deeper and deeper, and
feels like we're creating a
tribe where these important
things can be shared, but it's
creating a mind shift by itself.
So thank you for that, and maybe
it's it's beautiful to start
with you, Chris, because the
initial outreach was via email
to you, and then Dewayne came
in, Chris, you're a professor
emeritus in the department of
philosophy and religious study,
and you're specialized in
Buddhistic studies of the
Youngstown State University. But
you're also related to the
California Institute of integral
studies and also in the Advisory
Council of my training, Grof
legacy training. And then you're
also related to the Institute of
Noetic Sciences. So you're
you're not retired or emeritus
professor at all. You're full
alive and contributing to the
mind shift which is which is
happening. You're an author of
several books, the latest. It's
on my desk every day. And I
would really recommend, if
you're not in LSD, or you're not
in psychedelics, you have to
read it because it's it's very
much important information,
which is in the book. You wrote,
several books, I'm not going to
highlight them all, but LSD, in
the mind of the universe, your
latest book, and for me, was
transformative. So thank you for
that. And in this book, you
described your empirical
research. You did it on your own
with your former wife, with 76
deep, high dose LSD sessions in
which you entered the non other
narrative states of
consciousness and you
encountered a vision of our
impending global crisis and also
the birth of the future human.
So these visions are of
importance, because this come
from a field which we are not so
much aware of. This is beautiful
information. So thank you for
being here, and thank you for
contributing to to this gallery.
It's a pleasure to be here boss
and then Dwayne during the
course of Chris LSD, in the mind
of the universe, you already
mentioned Chris Dwayne's work,
and after the course, I went
through it. And your last book,
Dwayne choosing Earth, was mind
blowing for me. It's so full of
information. And you're an
author of several books which
are all important for us humans,
but choosing Earth. And you can
find in the chat box already the
link to choosing Earth website
and also the book, and you can
just download it by PDF. So
thank you for that, and thank
you for opening up Dwayne in the
early 70s. You worked as a
senior staff of the member of
the Presidential congressional
commission on the American
future of Yeah, of the last 30
years of the last century. So
the 70s until 2000 an important
position. And you were also
acknowledged for this deep work
as a social visionary exploring
the deeper trends that are
transforming our world. And you
were recognized for this for an
international award, a Peace
Award, a recognition of this,
this global vision and
consciousness of lifestyle that
contributes to a more
sustainable and spiritual
culture. So it's an honor having
you here. I would like to open
up the field for you both to
start with our Yeah, main
question of the evening, how can
we create, as humans, a new
mindset, which transforms our
global crisis? Or can we, can we
transform the global crisis? Or
have, do we have to go through
it with a new mindset. So can we
start from there, and then we'll
see how the dance will evolve.
Thank you for being here. You
both.
Chris Bache: It's a pleasure to
be here, everyone. Baz, thank
you for the invitation. You hear
my voice is a little rough. I've
just. Him down with the cold. I
wouldn't have canceled, except
this material is just too
important to let go of the
opportunity to talk about and I
wouldn't pass up an opportunity
to talk with Dwayne. I'd have to
be near dead to pass up this
opportunity. We've been friends
for over 20 years, 25 years now,
and it was first our research
and our writing which brought us
together, but then, as we got to
know each other personally and
understood the human being
behind the research, the
friendship has just deepened
into a deep, lifelong
brotherhood. Now, how Duane and
I have thought about today is
basically, first of all, I want
to say a talk is just an
opportunity to get to the Q and
A, because the Q and A is where
the juice really is. And I'm
really looking forward to that
that part of our discussion. And
I know Dwayne is too, but in
terms of the talk, we see this
is basically a conversation, an
opportunity for Duane and I just
to sink into conversation and
have the kind of conversation
that we have sometimes when we
get together. And so I thought
we might begin by just kind of
affirming some common ground
that Dwayne and I share first,
I'm a philosopher of religion.
I've been an academic all my
life in Northeast Ohio. Duane is
a social activist, a visionary
social activist. We've both
written books. We've both been
completely committed to our
lives project, and we both share
coming at it through overlapping
means. We both share, I think, a
common vision of the universe
that can be reached
intellectually and can be
reached experientially. And that
is a vision of the universe that
is saturated with intelligence,
orders and orders and orders of
intelligence, and also the
intelligence behind the manifest
universe, the intelligence out
of which the universe sprang in
the Big Bang and continues to
unfold and be nourished by this
fertile ground of existence.
This is Common Ground for Duane
and I also common ground is the
sense that our is our nature,
our consciousness. If you just
sit quietly, or if you amplify
consciousness, if you sink into
consciousness, you sink into
your personal unconsciousness.
And then you sink into what Jung
called the collective
unconscious. And if you just
keep going, you sink eventually
into a level, levels of
consciousness so deep they go
beyond the species. They go
beyond time and space, and one
can enter into deep communion
with, I think, what both of us
think of as the mind of the
universe, both the manifest
universe and the universe behind
the manifest universe. And Dean
and I both share the conviction
that this intelligence is
profoundly wise. He asked me,
before we got started, how would
you describe the IQ of the
universe? Boy, that was that
stumped me for a bit, and I had
to think in terms of an IQ on
order of millions and billions.
Because, I mean, look at this.
Is the intelligence which has
manifested everything we see
around us, as far as we can see
and as deep as we can see. How
could we possibly measure the
depth of that, of that
Bas de Cock: intelligence?
Chris Bache: And compassion, and
that's a kind of get to the
tricky point part, because it's
easy enough to see the the
intelligence. When we just look
at DNA and we look at the
structure of stars and galaxies,
we can see layers and layers of
intelligence manifesting, but
compassion on the surface, life
is hard. Life is and one could
easily conclude, and I
understand you could conclude,
that life is basically generated
by a mean son of a bitch. I
mean, it hurts us so much. It
just hurts so terribly. And in
order to see the wisdom of the
universe and to see the
compassion behind this, the hard
conditions in which we live, you
have to look very deep. You have
to look much deeper than sensory
consciousness. You have to much
deeper than the workings of the
personal and collective psyche.
You really must look very, very
deep, deeply. I think it was
Ramakrishna, when he was asked,
when he said, once, in order to
see God, you must be willing to
look evil in the face, and in
order to see the wisdom. Wisdom
of the universe, you must be
willing to sit deeply with the
pain of existence. And there's
nothing Dwayne or I will say
today that would dilute, set
aside sublimate, or in any way
sidestep the deep suffering that
it takes to live fully an
embodied, spiritual existence,
right? So this is just a warm up
exercise, and I want to do is
toss it to Dwayne, and we're
going to toss it back and forth,
and then we're going to move
towards this topic of the times
that we're living in, the
crisis, that we are coming into
the depth of that crisis, and
what we might do to move through
this crisis with courage and to
actually accelerate our way
through it, so we can get
through it with in with
intelligence and with compassion
and exploring what the universe
wants of humanity at this hour,
what humanity what the universe
is inviting humanity to become.
Because both of us share the
vision that we are coming to a
trigger point, a triggering
point. We are coming to a
bifurcation point where humanity
either makes the next step in
its long evolutionary journey,
or we probably go extinct
because we can't survive on this
planet in these conditions,
staying at the level of
consciousness that has brought
us here. We either grow up, as
Dwayne says, or we die, and that
means this extinction or
potential extinction, is an
enormous evolutionary
accelerator. So with that, let
me hand it over to my brother,
Dwayne.
Duane Elgin: Thank you, brother,
Chris. Chris is one of my
dearest, dearest brothers and
friends, and I am so grateful
for the lifelong the journey
that we have shared with our
mutual interest depth looking at
the nature of the universe and
where that is leading us as we
move into this dangerous and
transformative time for humanity
and creative time and the
passions that are present are
really compassions. The presence
of suffering in the world as a
catalyst for our pushing back on
ourselves and awakening freshly
to where we are and where we
might be going from here. So I
appreciated boss saying that he
was a doctor by training, and
early on in my life I was going
to become a doctor, but I
encountered the violence of the
Vietnam era, and I shifted over
a period of time, from physical
healing to now social healing,
and that's one theme I would
really like To explore, and
underneath the social healing is
our connection with the
aliveness of a living universe.
And that is where Chris and I
have found common ground and
common passion in our mutual
explorations of that
possibility, that reality. So
let's, let's begin.
Chris Bache: Chris, right. Where
do you want to start? Dig in?
Duane Elgin: Well, I think it's
important just to acknowledge
where we are right now, that the
crisis of transition isn't
something that's in the future.
It is happening right now. The
head of the United Nations
recently said, humanity is on a
climate Highway to Hell. We're
on a climate Highway to Hell,
and that's just looking at the
climate crisis. We're also on a
an extraordinary path of
extincting a huge proportion of
the plant and animal species on
this earth. It's estimated by
the end of this century, a
million species, different
species, a million species will
be extinct. We're impoverishing
the earth right now. It's
extraordinary. We're also in a
time of overshoot, we're way
overshooting the resource base
of the earth. We can't continue
as we have. It's estimated that
the earth will carry roughly 2
billion people into the far
future, and right now, we have 8
billion people. So if we. We
take that to heart. It means
that we're roughly 6 billion
people over the carrying
capacity of the earth. And so we
are in for a rough ride, a rough
initiation, if you will, moving
from our current condition of
overshoot and collapse, the
extinction of species, the
climate catastrophe, resource
depletion and all the rest, and
come to some new healing and
some new healthy relationship
with the earth and and our
ability to live into the far
future.
Chris Bache: So that's a Yeah.
Let me ask you a question that I
know is on people's mind, and I
know your answer to it, I
suspect. But the question is
this, can we avoid this crisis
now, if we really get off our
butt and mobilize, can we stop
what's happening and bring this
under control? What do you
think?
Duane Elgin: No, it's too late.
Had we started a half century
ago when I began my research on
all of this, in the early 1970s
there was an opportunity that
time to pull back, take a look
at where we were headed, and
choose a new pathway. But we
have used up that half century
to just consume ourselves into a
corner, if you will. And so now
we're up against it, and we do
have the forces, the factors
that I was just mentioning,
overshoot of the Earth's
resource base, a climate
catastrophe that's growing,
species being extincted at an
extraordinary rate, and so on
and so on. Now is the time for
our decision. Now is the time
for choice. And so this is where
we're looking at at this, not as
theoretically in the far future,
but as right now we're up
against it and and now is the
time for a new understanding of
who we are. Where are we? Who
are we? Where are we going from
here? Those are the core things
we need to begin digging into
now, not only philosophically,
but But practically,
realistically as a species. So
let's begin that inquiry.
Chris Bache: Yeah, so the depth
of destabilization that's coming
at us has already started. We
see a deep unraveling in many
areas of the social fabric. We
see our political discourse
becoming increasingly polarized.
We're moving in the direction of
fascism on one side,
totalitarianism on other sides,
repression of discourse, denial
of facts, of science, it's
getting harder and harder to
assume any kind of common
ground, which are all symptoms,
I think, of the fact that the
ground is shifting out from
underneath our feet. It's like
we're in a slow moving
earthquake that's building up
year by year, and it's just
shaking our systems to its
foundations. And if you're if
you just look at the research,
as Dwayne has done, and many of
you have done, if you look at
the research, you can just see
that the foundations of our
culture are just going are
shaking, beginning to shake more
and more, and we're going to
live through this, our
generation, my children's
generation, your children's
generation, your grandchildren's
generation. It will still be
deepening during these decades
ahead. It's hard to envision
just how bad it's going to get.
When I think about this, my
heart explodes with pain.
Everyone I sit with who really
looks hard at the data, their
heart explodes in pain, and they
would do anything to not have to
go through this. But this is
what we're this is what we're
going into and that means, I
think it's particularly
important that we understand
what is happening that because
if we don't understand this at a
deep structural level, if we
don't understand the
evolutionary challenge that
we're facing, we're going to
give way to despair. We're going
to give way to theodicies, which
are which are really deeply
demonic and problematic, we're
going to give way to political,
destructive philosophies. So we
have to understand this deeply.
Pass it to you, brother, yes.
Duane Elgin: Okay, here's what I
have encountered over the last,
oh, roughly 40 years speaking to
people around the Earth, and
often, before I give a talk, I
will ask an audience one simple
question. And the question is
this, if you look at the entire
human family and you look at our
behaviors, what is the life
stage of the human family? Being
expressed by those behaviors,
and I give the audience four
possibilities. One, that we're
behaving like toddlers. Two,
that we're behaving like
teenagers, like adolescents.
Three, that we're behaving like
early adults, and four, like
elders. Four possibilities,
toddlers, teenagers, adults or
elders. And I've asked this, and
I've been very surprised that
around the Earth, it doesn't
matter who I speak with. It
might be a church group, it
might be a college audience, it
might be a business community,
and so on. It doesn't matter.
One response comes back again
and again and again. Roughly
three quarters of every audience
I've spoken to over decades has
one response, and they say we're
behaving like adolescents and
like teenagers. There's no
hesitation regarding that, that
answer. And so if we are in our
adolescent stage as a species,
what will it take us to move
then into our early adulthood?
And in many ways, that's what
we're looking at right now, the
fire of initiation that will
push us into a new sense of
ourselves, a new sense of the
universe in which we live, and a
new sense, importantly, of the
evolutionary journey in which
we're involved. So that is one
key framing for me. It's that
we're in a rite of passage. It's
a time of initiation of our
species, and all the suffering,
all the pain that we're
experiencing right now as a part
of that pain that every
adolescent as an individual goes
through in different ways, but
nonetheless, we don't move into
early adulthood without going
through the fire of initiation.
And so Okay, let's accept that
that is how evolution works. We
are pushed outside of the nest
of our comfort zone and into
this transforming future, and
it's an extraordinary future
that lies before us, and without
a sense of where we might be
going, we're going to be
reluctant to go there. So one
thing that I appreciate about
Chris and his look at his
exploration of the birth of the
future human, and my own work,
that's what we're looking at.
What is the maturation of the
species, about where does that
take us in terms of our
relationship with the universe,
our relationship with other
humans, our relationship deeply
within ourselves? So that's a
conversation that Chris and I
have had again and again over
the years. So clear, Chris,
Chris Bache: your turn. Well, to
give a deeper context to
Dwayne's observations, I want to
point to his second book,
awakening Earth, where he
describes the the the stages of
human evolution in terms of the
conscious capacity, so the
levels of consciousness that
human beings have evolved over
our long evolutionary story. And
I think if I have this right,
Dewayne, you correct me. You say
in the book, and by the way, if
you get the book, read the book,
start at the Epilog. Read the
Epilog first and then read the
book, because the Epilog gives
you the experiential insight
into where the book came from.
But late in the book, he says we
could go through these last
three evolutionary stages in as
little as 500 years, and given
that we're talking about 10s and
hundreds of 1000s of years
leading up to that point we're
talking about that would
represent an enormous
acceleration, an exponential
acceleration, that we're
entering into so very intense,
but exponentially sped up. Yes,
Duane,
Duane Elgin: indeed, we're
moving into a time, obviously,
of intense compression. This is
going to be heated journey, a
heated compression of humanity
in the fire of initiation that
we're already beginning to
experience right now as we look
beyond our nation state
boundaries to the earth as a
whole system, and we're seeing
this will not hold this will not
carry us even to the end of this
century. So we are in
compression times, and we are
going to be pushed outside of
our usual circumstances and into
new conditions as a species, not
simply as nations, but as a
species as a whole. And that's
already beginning to happen
right now, and so that will be
the catalyst, I think, for rapid
acceleration of the evolutionary
potentials that are already so.
Surfacing, and this gathering is
one expression of that the role
of psychedelics, for example, in
being a catalyst for awakening
us to a new domain of
understanding of ourselves and
the human journey. So here we go
as a species, into the fire and
into the initiation and
hopefully into our higher
humanity.
Chris Bache: Yeah. And in that
context, I want to put on the
table one fundamental axiom of
my thought. I know Dwayne shares
this axiom, and I suspect
probably everyone in this group
does too, and that's the concept
of reincarnation. And so this
was my first book on which I
chose to write on reincarnation,
starting with the empirical
evidence, which I believe is
just overwhelming. And I came to
this conclusion as a philosopher
of religion. So when I look at
the world and I see human
beings, I don't see them the way
that most people see them. I
don't see old people as old
people and young people as young
people. I tend to see souls. And
there are old souls in small,
young bodies, and there are
young souls in old, withered
bodies. But the important key
here is understanding that
evolution, that reincarnation is
is a higher order of evolution.
It's one of the fundamental
truths of an self, manifesting,
self, evolving universe. And so
far, we've been telling the
story of of reincarnation,
saturated by the perspective of
theologies and philosophies
which have been individually
oriented. So we tell the story
of reincarnation terms of
individual evolution, the soul's
evolution over countless
lifetimes, the soul's awakening
eventually into individual
enlightenment, but it's
basically been strapped to a
metaphysics which focuses on
individual individual human
beings. And that's not that
that's false. I think that's
really true, but we're missing
something deeply if we think, if
we stop there, when we
understand that not just we and
everyone we see around us is
evolving, but every human being
on the planet is a reincarnating
essence, then we begin to
understand that reincarnation is
a collective driver. It is not
just an individual driver. It's
not just about personal
salvation or personal
transformation. It is an
evolutionary driver of the
highest magnitude. And I'll
shift just for a second and say,
if you ever read my book,
diamonds from heaven, or as the
publisher named it, LSD, in the
mind of the universe, there's a
section there where I report, I
record the experiences that kept
opening up and tearing me Open
and showing me the entire
universe, the entire species
pulsing in and out of time space
every 100 years or so, just the
entire species pulsing and
evolving together all of our
individual karmic agendas being
woven skillfully, intelligently
into a collective karmic agenda,
and the collective karmic agenda
be informing all of our
individual karmic agenda, so
that it became impossible to
separate the evolution of the
individual and the evolution of
the collective. And that became
one of the fundamental core
themes of my second book, dark
night, early dawn, where I'm
talking about the dark night out
of the individual soul of the
end of you know, the dark night
that the mystic goes through
before spiritual awakening, but
the dark night of our collective
soul. So that we I began to
understand from my sessions that
all of our individual work
serves not only our individual
development, but it also serves
directly, immediately, our
collective development. And
there are no such things as
personal problems which are not
also collective problems. Try
and think of one. Think of any
personal issue that we may be
dealing with, and try to find
one that isn't echoed or
reflective of a collective issue
in our culture. So I'll just
pause there. Hand it back to
you. Duane, Well, Chris,
Duane Elgin: Chris held up a
book or two. I, you know, I
can't let that just pass without
holding up one of my own and it
relates very directly to what
Chris is speaking about right
now that a reincarnational
perspective. How can that
happen? Well, here's a book that
I worked on for 30 years, the
living universe, the. Universe,
according to modern science, and
I have encountered this so many
times, is it considered non
living at the foundations, dead
at the foundations. And as far
as modern consumer society is
concerned, it's all just dead
matter and empty space. And
people like Chris Bache come
along and they say, Wait a
minute. No, I've, I've explored
the deeper reaches of the
universe. It's a living system.
In that living system, life can
re connect with itself. It can
evolve with itself, and
reincarnation, then is is not
losing the thread of our
existence as we move through
multiple cycles of life in this
larger aliveness. So we can,
after a bit, maybe begin to
explore the foundations of a
living universe and that
perspective. But I want to give
Chris a chance to perhaps
integrate that connect the
Living Universe with the
evolution of life through that
living system.
Chris Bache: Well, in that
context, I just want to sort of
say something which is hard and
consoling at the same time, and
that is from a reincarnation
perspective, we're always
popping into time space. And we
pop out of time space into a
spiritual meta universe. We pop
back into time space. We pop out
of time space. And from this
perspective, what is death? And
all of the Enlightenment
traditions, all of the you know
the the awakening, spiritual
awakening traditions basically
say the same thing, birth is not
the beginning of our life. Look
carefully, and you will find in
your being, in your physical
body and in your mind, the
evidence of a range of
experience that far predates
your physical body. Death is not
the end of our existence,
because we now, and particularly
if you study with people like
Michael Newton and his work in
life, between life and past life
therapy, we have an abundance of
evidence that there is a
continuity of consciousness that
predates us and postdates our
individual life that we so when
we talk about the deaths that
are coming, I mean, we have to
really relate to it at two
levels, and both of them are
fundamentally true, and to
diminish either of them, I
think, would diminish the truth
of our situation. One of them is
the death of a human being is a
painful, horrendous, terrible
experience. We are ending a life
cycle. Every death is the ending
of a precious cycle of life, and
that hurts like hell. And in
another perspective, we can also
say that in a deeper
perspective, no one dies, cycles
end, cycles begin, but the
consciousness which is alive
within that organism, within
that being is not extinguished,
but simply paused. While we go
home, we recalibrate, refresh,
rejuvenate, and then we enter
back into the fray. So this is,
on the one hand, consoling,
because it tells us that death
is not the end. On the other
hand, if you look at it really
carefully, it means that this
pattern of leaving our loved
ones behind and coming back into
new configurations and leaving
and coming back into new
configurations, this very
difficult and demanding dynamic
of constantly shredding, in some
ways, the social fabric, the
family fabric, our individual
fabric, is part of the ways that
way that life works. We have to
look deeply to understand. And
when we look deeply, we begin to
sort of see that the universe
thinks in very different terms,
and we do. It thinks on a time
frame much, much larger than we
do. It just thinks on a scale, a
completely higher order of
scale. We have to learn to think
as we have to learn to think
like a mountain. We have to
learn to think like the
universe. We have to learn to
really kind of think large and
think deep and look at every
human being we see as a precious
soul who is a companion on this
long journey, whatever our short
term relationship with them are
underneath we stand together in
this long evolutionary
trajectory, working for the
collective good of our planet,
of an entire human family, and
if people. I don't have this
commitment to the human family
if they have only a commitment
to their own personal life or
the even their own personal
family. Understandable, but I
feel sorry for them at a deeper
level, because to be committed
to something large is to is to
activate and to acknowledge that
in ourselves, which is large,
Bas de Cock: and therefore to be
committed
Chris Bache: to your species, to
be committed to your generation,
to be committed to the planet,
to be committed to the other
forms of life that share this
planet with us. These are an
expression of a maturing soul. A
young soul is small, right? A
maturing soul is large. When we
look at Gandhi, Martin Luther
King, great souls, which hold
large swaths of humanity in
their heart, thus are the
symptoms of a maturing soul.
Great gwayne,
Duane Elgin: well, so well said,
Chris, that's a part of growing
up a maturing soul is to grow
into the reality that we do have
a soul, and to keep the fire in
the soul alive so that we can
grow into this future that
you're speaking about, and I
I've often wondered, why doesn't
the larger world recognize what
we're speaking about right here?
This is the wisdom that's known
through history and and across
cultures. Where is that wisdom
today, and you know, I'm
reminded from the American
Indian tradition of three
miracles. This helps to reveal
this. The first miracle is that
anything exists at all. Anything
exists at all. That's a miracle.
The second miracle is that
living things exist, like plants
and animals. And the third
miracle is that living things
exist that know they exist and
that have the capacity to
explore the nature of that
existence. Now we tend to get so
enamored with the third miracle
that's that really elevates our
capacities as a species, and we
tend to then forget the first
miracle that anything is here at
all. And one thing I appreciate
about what Chris is doing with
his life and his journey is not
only speaking and learning about
reincarnation and the individual
soul and our and our movement
through time, but also the
nature of the universe that
would carry that process, the
first miracle, and one thing
that we love to explore is the
nature of the first miracle,
that the universe is itself a
living system and And we are
beginning the the the
evolutionary journey of learning
how to live in that larger
aliveness. Now that's an
extraordinary transition from
living in a Dead universe, and
it's really dead matter, empty
space. Well, what do we have
here? Nothing more than our
physical body, a bit of
biological aliveness. It's here
for a short time. Well, what do
we do with that emphasis short
Well, we consume as much as we
can to get as much pleasure as
we can for a short while before
we're thrown into the mystery of
non existence. Chris is talking
about a different journey. He's
saying, wait a minute. Wait a
minute. We're alive. We're
deeply alive. The universe is a
living system we're moving
through that larger aliveness.
And what we're trying to do here
is move beyond the consumer
society that's over consuming
the earth, move into a greater
wisdom that says, Look at who
you are. Sure you are a physical
body. But beyond the physical
body is the Body of
Consciousness that lives in our
living universe. And that's who
you are, more deeply, more
profoundly. And by growing into
that, whether we encounter that
aliveness through the
psychedelic journey, the
meditative journey and so on,
that is who we are at a more
foundational level. And that is
what Chris is pointing to, and
that is what I am working with,
as well with my own life.
Chris Bache: Yeah, you're
pointing to me, Dwayne. But you
know, come on, brother, you
wrote the book The Living
Universe. You're the one who
really, really spent all those
years looking at the scientific
evidence, trying to marshal the
kind of evidence that would
convince my atheistic philosophy
department, where they just
reject all of this out of hand,
because they're committed to a
materialist perspective, and I'm
presenting them evidence for
reincarnation, they're saying,
oh, that's nonsense, because we
know it all reduces to brain,
and we know where that comes
from, and you know you're the
one. Who took that on and you
just laid out and just hammer
the evidence and the evidence,
and then also drawing upon cross
cultural testimony from multiple
continents that are basically
testifying that to the deeper
mystery, to the deeper
intelligence, which we can
experience. Yeah, that's what my
philosophical colleagues. You
know, they're so skeptical about
who experience, no, no, no. But
come on, I say, let's get
serious. A philosophical
revolution begins with the
question, what is it possible
for a human being to experience,
right? Yeah, yes. They're
telling me you can't experience
the things you say you're
experiencing, and I'm telling
them bullshit. Come on. I got we
have a method. We have hundreds
and hundreds of 1000s of people
who have used this method. Have
done LSD psychotherapy. We've
pushed these boundaries. We have
long now longitudinal studies
that are showing us what happens
when people do these things. You
can't dismiss that and say, Oh,
no, that couldn't be real,
because my metaphysical view
says matter is the only reality,
and you're talking about things
that are not materially
Bas de Cock: based, right?
Chris Bache: Yes, you know
you're knocking on their door
hard, brother,
Duane Elgin: I want to bring in
look. Let's look beyond
philosophy. Yes, Kali, that's
thinking a lot, Chris, let's
look at the direct experience.
Now, the psychedelic experience
is direct. It's immediate. You
don't think about it. You're
just overwhelmed with the direct
experience and encounter with
life in a different way, in a
different mode or different
manner. And so let me share just
briefly my experience in
Parapsychology almost half a
century ago, the US government
began the very first research by
the government into psychic so
called psychic potentials, and
to me, they're not I don't like
the word psychic. I like the
word it's alive. And to what
extent can we relate to and
experience the aliveness of the
Living Universe, and what does
that reveal to us? And there
were two things that came back
after three years of involvement
in in depth research there at
the Engineering Laboratory of
the Sanford Research Institute.
So I had the extraordinary
opportunity, just extraordinary
for over a three year period
funded by NASA, the space
agency, to begin to explore our
intuitive capacities. And they
wanted to know. They said, Look,
if there's an astronaut on the
far side of the moon, is there
any way to intuitively
understand their situation? Can
our intuition reach behind the
far side of the moon and get
valuable and meaningful
information about their
condition. Well, that was the
premise that launched this three
years of inquiry, that after
three years, I dropped out
because it was taken over by the
CIA, because it was so
compelling the information
coming back that it was taken
over by the Central Intelligence
Agency, and it continued for
another 20 years. So but in the
first three years, it was public
information, and here's what was
learned from that. First is that
there are two aspects to our
intuitive potentials, one that
we can receive information way
beyond what we can reach through
our normal perceptual capacities
of the physical body. And then
secondly, we can extend our
energetic impact on the universe
way beyond the close in reach of
our of our body as well. And so
the receptive side was what is
sometimes called remote viewing,
and that was interesting. But
the expressive side, which is
sometimes called psychokinesis
of mind, manifesting in matter,
really took me into the realm of
a living universe, and exploring
the ecology of the living
universe and how we can do a
dance with that universe and and
expands ourselves to our really
are the larger selves that we
actually inhabit. And so we have
a physical body, but that body
is a an anchor for an unbounded
awareness, an unbounded
consciousness that reaches out
without bound, into the larger
universe and beyond. And so we
are bounded for a short while.
Then, as Chris has mentioned,
that boundary gives way. We, the
body dies, but the consciousness
that was carried along through
the body does not it migrates.
It moves into the into the
larger realms of the universe.
And I don't presume to know what
where we're going with that, but
I do presume to have unshakable
confidence that we are learning
to live in this larger
aliveness, and that is the core
journey that we're about right
now as a species. And to the
extent that we think what we're
doing here is, is learning to
consume more so we can be happy
with the material things that we
have. We're missing. We're
missing what this is all about.
We're you. This is a place to
learn about who we are, beneath
and behind and beyond the
physical body, to recognize that
we're a part of a journey of
aliveness that, as Chris has
said, has had infinitely deep
origins and that has infinitely
deep potential is moving into
the further future.
Chris Bache: Boy, do I want to
jump on that hard. I want to
look at this idea of as we
develop our potentials, as we
make this turning point as we
kind of mature as a species.
What kind of human being are we
becoming? What are the
potentials that we are
activating? And I think it's
far, far beyond what we are
seeing even in the science
fiction literature, which so
much looks like cops and robbers
in space, you know, software
beyond the traditional pictures.
But I want to hold that for a
little bit, and I want to build
up to that little bit, and so
I'd like to up the ante in a
different way. I'd like to talk
more directly about
psychedelics. You ready to make
that pivot? Okay? Now this is
something that both Dwayne and I
share, and I suspect if we had a
show of hands, we'd get a pretty
high showing of people who have
used psychedelics responsibly in
this room as part of their own
personal history, part of their
spiritual practice history. Just
as we ask people, How many
people do yoga and I've done
meditation, we'd have the same
type of thing for our
generation. Psychedelics is part
of the the arsenal of spiritual
of not only spiritual healing,
healing the soul, but becoming
more aware of what our lives are
about and what life itself is
about. So let me just speak
personally for a minute. I was
brand new professor, fresh out
of graduate school, read Stan
grofs work immediately I felt
like I saw my life vocation in
front of me. I had to do this
type of work. It had been made
illegal. This was 1978 right? So
it had been made illegal in 1970
I loved teaching. I didn't want
to lose my job, so I basically
developed a sideline to my
career. I was a traditional in
many ways, not, I hope, not too
traditional, but I was an
academic. I was teaching courses
at the University, sitting on
committees, writing papers,
doing all that stuff. But in my
nighttime job, I began a
systematic course of using a
psychedelic protocol that I
inherited from Stan Grof,
totally internalized,
internalized sessions, rigorous,
lying down, eye shades,
earphones, sitter, all that
stuff. You know, you know the
drill. Unwisely. I will admit
now I chose a protocol after
three sessions of working with
very high doses of LSD, because
I was in a hurry, and I thought
this would get me where I wanted
to go faster. I thought it was
about personal awakening,
personal enlightenment. Yeah,
come on, they'll be harder, but
I'll burn off my karma faster.
Let's get there. Let's put the
metal to the pedal to the metal.
Let's go well, I turned out,
turns out that was completely
wrong on so many points. The
goal was not personal
enlightenment. And if you work
with very, very high doses, like
I did, and you do it in a
controlled burn situation, in a
very carefully situation, when
you start shattering the
boundaries. Within a few years,
I was dealing with experiences
where clearly, what was driving
my sessions and what was driving
the purification and
transformational process in my
sessions was not my personal
development, was not my personal
healing or my personal
transformation, but my work had
gotten sucked into a larger
historical drama of our
collective development, and so
much of the healing that took
place in my sessions Were not
about healing Chris Bache or
even Chris bacheous soul, but it
was trying to engage and heal
some aspect of the human family.
And for years and years, has
kept repeating itself, entering
deep into pains which are stored
within the collective unsight.
Collective unconscious
aggregates which are stored from
all the wars, all the all the
unhealed traumas of all the
wars, and all the abuse, and all
the droughts, and all the men
versus women violence and race
versus race, violence and so on
and so forth. All of that trauma
which is not resolved at the end
of any one lifetime is
accumulating in the human
psyche. And for us to make this
evolutionary pivot, we have to
heal humanity. We have to heal
the being which, for me, is a
single being, the human species,
as a single being in which we
are all cells. And in order for
this entire being to make the
transition that Dwayne has
talked about from being an
adolescent stage of the soul
development into a mature adult
stage of soul development, we
have to heal. And healing is the
first step to establish a new
foundation, a new platform where
we can then download deeper and
more mature and richer energy
and light and insight from the
universe itself. It's like we're
we're too we're too dumb, we're
too fragmented to be able to
take advantage of all the wisdom
and all the healing that's
available to us. But as we heal
this work, as we do this work,
then we can take in more. We can
take in we can take in more of
the light of the universe. Now I
mentioned that just to kind of
as a preface to where we go when
you start shattering the shells
that hold our awareness in their
fixed and narrow confirmation,
we can shatter a shell, and
usually the first layers of
shells. People talk about ego,
death, right? Death of our
individual mind body experience.
Then you wake up into you are
reborn into a deeper level of
consciousness. And if you push
those boundaries, if you work
steadily at those boundaries,
eventually that process will do
the same type of purification
process. You'll hit limits, and
you'll go through yet another
death and rebirth. But it's not
ego death repeating itself. It's
a deeper kind of dying. It's a
dying that takes place at the
species level. It brings you the
rebirth that takes place,
pitches you not into your soul
level of individual awakening,
but into some aspect of
humanity's awakening. If you
continue to push hard, at least
it's been my experience that if
you continue this process
Bas de Cock: diligently, and
Chris Bache: we'll talk about
what that means, maybe. But if
you do this work systematically,
and you really take care of your
body, and I don't recommend
doing it the way I did it,
because it's a lot of wear and
tear, if I knew then what I know
now, I wouldn't do it the same
way again. Please don't I'd do
it differently. I'd be gentler.
But if you push like this, if
you keep on pushing those
boundaries, you begin to enter
into a communion with the
intelligence that's within the
species, that's driving the
species, and it begins to teach
you. It teaches you what's
happening. It teaches you where
humanity is going. Now, at this
point, I'll just inject one
point and I'm going to turn it
over to Dwayne again, one of the
things that began to happen
about eight, nine years into my
work, I began to have a series
of visions that just were being
poured into me. And I think of
Black Elk when I try to talk
about this, because Black Elk,
when he was 12 years old, he had
this visionary experience of the
fate of the Lakota people, and
it shook him so deeply. You
know, he almost died. He was out
unconscious for days and days
when he came back, he was
holding this vision. He was so
shaken, he didn't talk about it
for years. In my case, I was
downloading visions of what
appeared to be the fate of the
human species, but it wasn't
given to me all at once. It was
being dropped in piece in pieces
over a series of sessions
stretched over years and but the
fundamental teaching kept
repeating itself and deepening
itself. And the teaching was
this, humanity is coming to a
turning point. Humanity is
entering a very challenging
period, but a time of profound
spiritual fruition. We were
entering a time that would mark
the beginning and end of
history. It's a truly an
ethical, shifting experience. We
were coming into a time when we
would literally begin to wake up
collectively. It wasn't about
just individuals. This is a
species wide awakening. The
dynamics are species wide. The
time of individual salvation is
over. The time of collective
salvation is at our doorstep
right now, over and over and
over again, it was saying, this
is a massive turning point. This
is, this is where we had been
building to this transition for
ions.
Bas de Cock: It kept showing me
Chris Bache: a future that was
just ecstatic, a future, if you
can imagine of our entire
species being a species of
Buddhas and Christ and prophets
totally awakened from the soul
of our center. But in all these
four years, it never told me how
we were going to get there. I
had no insight, given how we
were going to carry make this
transition, travel as far as we
had to travel in as little time
as all the research was showing,
telling us that we had, because
really right extinction is
pressing down upon us, and it's
coming hard and fast. The crisis
is moving in on us right now. I
share this with you because as
I've talked about this, and it's
in my book and LSD in the mind
of the universe, and as I've
talked about this, I've had so
many people come up to me and
say, I've had the same kind of
visions that's been showing me
the same thing in my deep
meditation practice. We're
coming to a turning point. This
is a driving force. This is a
social, collective force. So
there's nothing private, there's
nothing personal about this
experience. It's not my unique
experience. I'm simply
witnessing to something which
many of us have been
experiencing, and I know that
you've been experiencing
experience that type of
material. Dwayne, yeah, yes,
indeed, yeah, I'm turning Well,
Duane Elgin: let me summarize,
from from my perspective, what
we've been speaking about. And
three elements of that come up.
Of that summary, we're a world,
a species, that's not really
recognizing what's going on
here. First of all, we're not
recognizing the nature of the
universe in which we live. The
universe is a living system, and
current science says, No, it's
just dead matter in empty space,
and we're ready to work with the
material dimensions of it all,
and so on and so on. But the
deeper aliveness is not
recognized. Secondly, we don't
recognize who we are. We think,
Well, okay, we're biological
beings in this Dead universe,
and we're making the best of it
in a consumer society. And no,
we're not recognizing that we
are part of that larger
aliveness. And thirdly, we're
not recognizing the evolutionary
journey. And it's dimensions
that we've been speaking about
we think, well, we die and the
lights go out, that must be
pretty much it. And no, we're
going on and on and on. As
Chris, you've been speaking
about the reincarnation
universe. We just need go on
evolving through it all. So
really, the transition that I
see is, first of all, three
fold, a new recognition of where
we are. It's a living system.
Secondly, a recognition of of
who we are as beings we're a
part of that larger aliveness.
And thirdly, where we're going
is way beyond consumerism and
such. It's learning to live in
that larger aliveness. What an
extraordinary journey that we
would be blessed with the gift
of entering into that kind of
journey. And you were bringing
up the good the question, Chris,
well, how in the world do we
make the transition, the three
fold transition, and
understanding the universe
freshly who we are, freshly and
where we're going? Well, a lot
of attention is being put right
now on material systems. Well,
it's a climate crisis, so it
means too much CO two in the
air, which means, well, we got
to cut back on on the cars that
we drive and so on. It's a
material response to a trans
material challenge before us.
And so again and again people
say, Well, what are you going to
do about it? And what? One of
the key things I've been working
on for decades is media, and why
media? Media isn't that the
problem we've got so much media.
It's it's consume is hypnotizing
us into a materialistic mindset,
and all we have to show for it
is more consumerism. No, this
goes way beyond that, because
the mass media is the access to
the mass mind. Here we are on a
call with people in different
parts of. World right now, and
we're beginning to grow the
neurological structures of the
species as we use the mass media
that we have right here to speak
with one another and to grow a
new understanding, a new
consensus, a new consciousness
of who we are as a species. So
one of the critical elements I
feel of a transforming future is
to transform our uses of media.
And this gathering now is an
example, and there are so many
more, we're exploding into a new
opportunity to use the media to
reflect, to use it to reflect on
who are we, and then to
communicate back. Well, I've
seen that mirror, and myself in
that mirror, and I see a new
possibility out there, and let's
begin to evolve into that
possibility. So we're on the
cusp. We're on the brink. We're
on the threshold of using the
extraordinary media potentials
that are out there right now,
two thirds of the people on this
planet have one of these things,
a cell phone. Two thirds of the
people on the planet, all we
have to do is pick up that cell
phone and we have access to a
majority of people on this
planet. By the end of this
decade, it'll be three quarters
of the people on this planet
have access to the to the
collective mind through one of
these so we are over endowed
right now with a with the tools,
the capacities to communicate
with one another and to and to
grow into A new collective
consciousness of those three
dimensions of transformation
that we're just right on the
threshold of pushing against and
the world's pushing back against
us. And so it's a learning time
for the species. It's an
awakening time, a learning time,
a growing time, and we're way
over endowed with all the tools
we need to go through that
learning journey.
Chris Bache: Yeah, this is one
area where our work is
complementary to the other,
because you are deeply
committed, lifelong, committed
social activist, and you
understand in ways that go
beyond me, far beyond my
understanding of how this how
social transformation can take
place. What are the roots of
that are holding us stuck? Where
are the where are the
opportunities for facilitating
deep social change at a
collective level, at a
practical, tangible, manifest
level, my work has been much
more internally focused. So let
me speak to the inside of this
process. Because while my
psychedelic experience has been
deeply collective, it takes
place in one room, you know, in
one house, in on one street. So
it's a very different way to
access the collective. Let me
tell you the next installment,
or just point to the next
installment in my own journey,
personal Death-Rebirth went
through that collective
Death-Rebirth went through that
began to have these visionary
experiences of where the human
species was being taken of this
an extraordinary future, no
explanation of how we were going
to get there. Carried me then
passed that into a series of
profound mystical experiences of
Non-duality and Shunyata
emptiness and, you know, sort of
deep, ecstatic joy. Then it took
me into the diamond Luminosity
work, which occupied the last
five years of my work. And in
the middle of those of those
diamond Luminosity sessions
where I was expecting fully to
be returned, because I was
coming back into the diamond
Luminosity about once a year,
but every five sessions,
purified, purify, purify. Bam.
Diamond Luminosity. Purify,
purify, purify. Boom, more. But
diamond Luminosity and I was
about, I was expecting, about
time to get back into the
diamond Luminosity. But that's
not what happened in what was my
55th session in 1995 coming up
on what, almost what, 2423 years
ago, I went through a process
where I dissolved completely
into the species I just I became
hard to imagine but hard to
describe. I became dissolved
into the collective unconscious
so deeply that my individual
consciousness was basically just
a slow remnant, and I entered
into what I call deep time. I'd
gone beyond linear time many
times before this dissolved me
very, very deeply into deep
time. So I was it was a
transtemporal experience. So I.
Had exploded the boundaries. It
was trans spatial experience. It
was a transtemporal experience,
and it took me into the future,
deeper than I had been taken up
to that time. And suddenly I
began to experience
systematically, methodically,
clear as a bell. I began to
experience the death and rebirth
of the human family. It was like
being able to experience a
thunderstorm where you can see
the patterns, you experience the
patterns of the storm as a
whole, and you experience all of
the individual drops in the
storm simultaneously. So it's a
both an aggregate, but also
collective. And I experienced
the entire human family moving
into a period of crisis. The
ordinary structures of our world
were being broken down and
stripped away. We were losing
control. We were being
shattered. Civilization was
being shattered. Lives were
being torn apart. It was just
extraordinarily painful. The
whole human family was being
shoved to the edge of apparent
extinction. And is built and
built for a long time in the
session. And then just when it
looked like that was it, this
was it. We were coming to the
end of it all. It was like a
hurricane passing over an
island, and the worst of the
storm passed, and things began
to get lighter. They began to
get lighter. People began to
pick themselves up. We began to
find each other after this. And
many, many people had died, but
many survived, and as we began
to survive, we realized we
discovered that we had been
changed. This crisis tapped us
into something so deep. It drove
us so deep into our being that
it opened. It unlocked something
in us. We shed things we just
literally we had stripped from
us all sorts of assumptions and
accumulations that tapped us
into what I came over time to
think of as the one heart, that
all of our individual hearts are
aspects of the one heart, when
we began to find each other and
meet each Other, there was a
there was a creativity that was
catalyzing new social forms, new
forms of cultural creativity.
And this created feedback loops
where creativity fed new
creativity. And there was an
exponential in growth in levels
of awareness that were grounded
in new values, new perceptions
of the good, new understandings
of human nature, new
understandings of nature itself,
new understandings of the
Divine. This is what I think of.
What I came to see was this was
a forecast, not a forecast,
because I was in deep time,
which means I experienced this
transformation from the
perspective in which it was
already happening, and in the
end, I experienced it as
something that had already
happened and something that was
yet to happen. It was this not
confusing, but the kind of both
and experience that sometimes
opens in very deep psychedelic
experience. It took me about a
year to recover from this one
session. What I the way I put in
the book, is when I walked
around my town in Ohio and I saw
all these beautiful beings, all
these souls who did not
consciously at an individual
level, know what they were
coming into, but I knew that at
a soul level, they knew what
they were getting into. At a
soul level, they had chosen to
incarnate at this time in
history, I just felt myself
surrounded by courageous souls
who were entering consciously
into this very, very intense
century of transformation. It
was like walking around
Hiroshima the week before the
bomb dropped. Everyone around me
I saw was entering into this
terrible catalyst of pain, and
yet they were deep and profound
spiritual warriors. It took me a
long time to learn how to live
with that, to hold that, but I
did, and eventually I brought it
into dark night, early dawn, and
then I brought it more fully
into LSD, in the mind of the
universe. And that's a
perspective that I know I share
with you.
Bas de Cock: Dwayne, yeah, it's
intense. Yeah, yeah.
Duane Elgin: As as a long time
social activist and such, I want
to bring a another note into our
conversation before we we
conclude, and that is, um. Hmm,
there are no guarantees here.
We've seen the possibilities.
We've seen the potential. We've
felt it in our souls and our
bones and our being. We know
that's possible, but there's no
guarantee we're going to realize
that as a species, as I look at
the world, I see three great
possibilities for our pathway
ahead. One is what we've just
been speaking about, extra
ordinary invitation into greater
aliveness and possibility. But
there are two other
possibilities that are very,
very real. One is the future of
collapse and and really the
functional extinction, the
species, not the complete
extinction, but the functional
extinction. We're no longer a
force and evolution on the
earth, nor are we connected well
enough with one another to make
a difference in our collective
lives and build the kind of
species body that you're
speaking about, Chris, that we
could end up just so fragmented
and so diminished that we never
have the opportunity to pull
that species body together in
its learning potentials. That's
a second possibility, a third
possibility, very real we can
see now is the authoritarian
future. We can see that in in
Russia. We can see it in China.
We can see it beginning in India
and other parts of the world. We
can see it in the United States,
for heaven sakes, the
authoritarian orientation is so
strong people are ready to
surrender their freedoms. And
what you're speaking about, and
what I'm speaking about, is
claim your freedom. Claim your
freedom to be a living
participant in a living
universe. Grow into that
freedom. Don't surrender it to
the to the scientists that look
at only a material universe,
don't surrender it to the media
and the politicians that say no,
it's just about more and more
material well being for all
people on the planet. There are
three great paths before us, and
the one that you've been
speaking about, and then that I
have, as well, is a narrow
pathway I feel, into the future,
and we're going to have to do
everything we can as a
community, not just as
individuals, but as you say,
Chris, as a community, to
elevate ourselves, to awaken
ourselves to grow into that
future of evolutionary
potential, to learn to live in
that larger aliveness. So bless
you, brother and I. Thank you so
much for your life of
contribution and service in that
and in that future.
Chris Bache: Yeah, and you too,
brother, me before, as we
transition soon into questions
and answers, which is going to
take us into a whole other
journey. Right with this? There
I have the view, and I think
Dewayne shares this view that we
have entered this century is a
century of labor. We have been
gestating the future human for
millennia, for 10s of 1000s,
hundreds of 1000s of years,
we've been gestating it through
reincarnation, over and over,
deeper and deeper, but now we've
come into labor. Gestation is
long. Labor is short. Gestation
can be gentle and take place
while we can keep other things
going on. On the surface, labor
is not like that. Is it? Labor
is intense. It requires complete
interruption of life as we have
ordinary experienced it and we
turn deeply within, and we are
in the process of giving birth
to collectively what I'm calling
the future human. Many people
have seen this. They've felt it.
They give it different names,
Homo spiritualis, Homo noeticus,
all sorts of different names.
But the fundamental idea is that
we are giving birth to a
different kind of human being, a
different level, a different a
more evolved form of humanity.
What might this future human
look like? What is the what is
the substance of the future
human? And here I go back to the
theme of reincarnation. I go
back to some of the experiences
that I describe in LSD, in the
mind of the universe. And there
was, you know, I've done past
life therapy before when I
wasn't doing the LSD work, and I
know about, I've been
familiarized with about a dozen
of my former lives, nothing
special, no one special, just
ordinary, run of the mill,
peasants, for the most part. But
I had a sense of that, you know.
But what happened in this
particular session is that all
my former lives began to come
back into me. They all just
started coming in very fast and
furious. I'd already gone
through. A tremendous
purification process and a
Death-Rebirth process, but then
these lives started coming into
me. It was like wrapping
filaments of light around a kite
spool. Each wrap was one life,
and at a certain point they hit
critical mass. And when they hit
critical mass, there was an
explosion of energy, and I
experienced this explosion of
diamond light blow out my chest,
catapulting me into a completely
new state of consciousness. And
all those individual lives fused
into one, into a singularity,
and then a teaching kept on
holding and explaining what was
going on, first the experiences,
then the illuminating of the
experience. But the basic vision
that emerges is this. It's a
different vision of human of
reincarnation than we find in
many of the Eastern cultures.
The classical view of
reincarnation is okay,
reincarnate, reincarnate,
reincarnate. Get better and
better, more compassionate, more
intelligent, more this, more
that, growing level by level by
level. And when you achieve
enlightenment, when you achieve
a realization that you can
understand and let your mind
sink into the essence of its
source, and you come to that
shattering realization that the
essence of your life is
absolute, is exactly the same as
the essence of everybody else's
life, and the essence of life
itself Atman is Brahman. Yes,
our nature is our Buddha nature.
When we reach that point,
classic thinking is okay now we
can leave. You've achieved
enlightenment. You have achieved
moksha. Escape. You no longer
have to be entrapped within ego,
but you no longer have to be
entrapped within time and space.
You have permission to leave.
Your work is done. But that's
not what came forward in my
session. What came forward in my
session was the birth of the
diamond soul, which meant that,
which was the phenomenon that we
are reaching a point in human
evolution where we have, we have
been working in integrating and
getting rid of all of our
negative karma, purifying
ourselves, healing
relationships, healing the scars
which have been torn into our
heart, healing the social scars,
healing the civilizational scars
we're working and working that
material there comes a time when
our entire history begins to
coalesce, and The early stages
of that coalescing often takes
this form of healing, purifying,
dealing, cleaning out the
basement, so on and so forth.
But there comes a point when
that work is done, and all of
those lives congeal, and there
is an explosion of consciousness
where we no longer experience
ourselves as a one generational
time space, 100 year old being.
We experience ourselves as
100,000 year old being. We
experience ourselves as souls,
and not a human being with a
soul. We experience what a human
being actually is. We experience
ourselves as souls. And this is
what I call the birth of the
diamond soul, because we often
tend to use the word soul as the
spiritual, non embodied, the non
physical counterpart to our
individual personality. That's
not the soul I'm talking about.
I'm talking about the
consciousness that holds all of
our farmer lives, all of them as
one. And now what I think is
happening is usually we
experience that diamond soul
only after we die. You know, we
go small to big when we die. Ah,
yeah, come back to small. We
grow some more, then we die. Ah,
yes, it feels so good to be big
again. But what's happening? I
think if we keep that up, just
keep it up long enough, sooner
or later, the soul wakes up
inside physical existence. And
when that happens, Heaven
manifests on earth when that
happens, Nirvana is Samsara.
When that happens, we realize we
don't have to go anywhere to
experience absolute bliss and
sheer joy. The goal of
evolution, of spiritual
evolution, is not to spiritually
mature and then leave. I
understand where that view came
from. I understand its
historical context. It makes
perfect sense within a context
of 5000 years ago, before we
understood how old the universe
was, how big it was, and how
much intelligence had been sunk.
Into building this universe. The
goal of our spiritual evolution
is to
Bas de Cock: awaken,
Chris Bache: to truly awaken to
our soul consciousness, which
opens us into a different
relationship with all other
beings with whom we share this
planet, and opens us into a
different relationship to the
intelligence that is manifesting
time and space continuously
regenerating it. The goal is to
awaken to that, to embody that
in our physical being, not a
disembodied, transcendental
awakening, but an embodied
awakening, and then to bring
that consciousness into the
making of history, into the
making of the planet, into the
making of a civilization, a
world which truly does work for
all. How far can we take this?
What will it look like? It's not
going to look like, just what it
looks like in the very beginning
stages. What our spiritual
traditions have told us over and
over again is that mind creates
our destiny as the mind leads,
Destiny follows. We are creating
our reality with our mind. When
our mind is fragmented and
conflicted, we live in a
fragmented and conflicted
reality. Now this is we have to
be careful, this is not simply
an individual story. It's a
collective story. There's a
dynamic feedback between our
individual manifestation, our
collective manifestation. But
basically, we are learning, I
think, how to control the
nuclear energy, which is the
soul, the fiery energy, light
energy, which is our essential
divine energy, cosmic energy. We
are learning how to be gods. And
I don't mean that in any
superficial sense. We are
evolving into a being which
truly not only will be at peace
with ourselves and at harmony
with each other, but a being
which has capacity to manifest
creativity inside time and
space, the likes of which maybe
today we only know in the
mystical literature, in the
spiritual literature, what the
Tibetans call The mahasiddhas,
The Great Beings, the great
beings around who have the
capacity to work miracles. They
have the capacity to manifest
consciousness in ways that
absolutely dazzle our mind and
don't make any sense within a
materialist scientific
perspective, because they have
gathered so much conscious power
that they can manifest this in a
way that bends the laws of
physics, so to speak. I suspect
what they're doing is
manifesting a deeper set of laws
of physics than are manifest at
a lower energy level. This is
high energy physics, yeah. So I
think we're coming. We're giving
birth to the future human. We're
giving we're maturing. We're
growing into a mature adult. And
if we ask, well, what does a
mature adult look like? It's not
simply a human being the way we
are now, with higher values and
better values. It's truly an
awakened human being, a soul
centered human being that lives
at peace with themselves and at
peace with each other, and now
we pivot. And of course, this
isn't, this isn't the end of the
story, right? Let's assume for
the minute we make this
transition. One century, two
centuries, three centuries, we
make this transition. Universe
isn't stopping, right? We're
going to be here for millions,
billions of years, right? We
have at least 4 billion years
before the sun goes supernova.
We got to be off the planet in
about 2 billion years. That's a
lot of time you're going this is
just the beginning of a
transition. We're just waking
up. We're like children in the
crib created by the universe,
waking up into this beautiful
room. We're just waking up to
what we are, who we are,
activating our potential and
moving on, moving forward that
now I believe, with Dwayne, that
he's right. The note, there's no
guarantees here.
Bas de Cock: This is
Chris Bache: we have to put we
have to everybody show up.
Everybody has to maximize
everything they can do to
possibly to make this, to get us
through this, to bring us
through this whole transition. I
understand that, and I accept
that, and I think that's true,
but I also would like to offer
you a slightly different
perspective from within my
psychedelic experience, and I
don't know how to reconcile
these two, but from within my
psychedelic experience, I've
been taken so deep into the
future so many times, and in my
last deep vision, the 70th
session was my last, what I call
the great visions, deep. Deep
into the future, and from that
deep future, I experienced this
transformation as a given, as
something that we had
accomplished, not something that
was an open ended possibility,
but something which we had truly
accomplished. So from my own
personal heart. I cannot doubt
that we will make this
transition. I worry deeply about
what it's going to cost us. How
many of our children will die,
how many of our world's children
will die of starvation? And you,
we know it's coming in that way.
That's what I'm worried about,
and it's going to take every one
of us at maximum exertion to
really pull this off. And yet
we're not driving this, right?
Human beings are not driving
this. Nature is driving this.
The creative intelligence of
nature is driving this. We
didn't give ourselves the big
brain 100,000 years ago, we
didn't give ourselves the
evolutionary qualities that are
embodied in ourselves, in our
mind and in our physical body.
Some larger process is driving
this process. The most we can do
is cooperate with it, to
recognize, to wake up, to see
what's happening, cooperate with
it and to become a collaborator,
a co creator of this future
human, which we will then in our
future incarnations, incarnate
into. But I think the shift that
we're seeing taking place, it's
grinding its way forward, is a
shift in the plate tectonics of
the collective psyche. It's a
shift at the very, very deep
structure that after we make
this shift, every human being
born will be operating out of a
different collective psyche, out
of a different level of soul
awareness. And that's the work
of the hour. That's what we and
we all knew we were getting
getting into this. When we were
born, we chose to be part of
this process. And with that
knowledge, we can relax even
while we go to work, we can
relax in that deeper way of
taking spiritual nurturance from
the universe even as we go to
work and do our best.
Unknown: So brother,
Chris Bache: let's open it up
and see what these good people
where they want to go.
Duane Elgin: Yeah, thank you,
brother, this has been a delight
to share this this hour with
you, and I'm so deeply grateful,
I just want to say for our
friendship over these deck
towns. Bless you.
Unknown: Yeah, likewise,
brother.
Bas de Cock: As as said from
this place, what an amazing,
deep words. It's not about the
words about the energy felt
during your dance. It's
transformative by itself. So I'm
really, I'm really honored,
honored by these words. And I
have 1000 questions that I said
off your course, Chris, I gained
1000 questions more, and now
I've got 2000 questions. But
concerning the time, I want to
open up the or the microphone
for the fellow, the fellow
wisdom keepers, people have
questions, sharings, whatever
comes up wants to be shared now
is the time and the place, and
our questions as hosts will
come, maybe at The end. So if
you have a question, if you have
one symptom to share, just open
up your microphone and feel
comfortable to to to go.
Chris Bache: I see Todd has got
his hand raised.
Unknown: Well, it is lovely to
see you both, and I would offer
that your conjoined synergy is
part of that love that gives us
great optimism for future. I'm a
painfully optimistic sort
because of having taste of that
unconditional love and that
complexity that's about and so I
my optimism. We unchanged,
though we do know there's a
collective great n de coming for
the species, but the
transformative power is
wonderful. Just to offer some of
the small kernels that I see
changing is just the fact that
we're talking about psychedelics
are not a panacea for every
individual, but they are so
quickly entering a wider
conversation, and to me, that's
going to be one of the essential
tools to help change the
consciousness individually and
then, of course, collectively,
just as one tiny little nugget,
I received email yesterday of a
group and some of the folks I
know that are deeply thoughtful
and deeply committed toward a
holistic understanding of
existence, and they're putting
together leadership schools,
which. With a psychedelic
component, to those with a
cohort goes through, thinks
deeply about all the things that
you know, a planetary, holistic,
universal idea, but with the aid
of having that transformative
discovery within and then going
forth all together to a with a
greater understanding. And to
me, that's was unheard of just a
few few years ago, let alone a
decade or two. And so for those
to me, are those moments of
showing that there are so many
folks working toward a greater
understanding that that will get
here, even though there's gonna
be great pain before that's
manifested on a wider scale. So
anyway, thank you for your work,
and I share your optimism, and
it's unshakable, dammit.
Chris Bache: And how could we
not mention this great book by
Dwayne choosing Earth. And
there's a film that he and
Colleen have created, there's a
course which they have created,
there are a number of
initiatives and Dwayne, I'll let
you talk about this. But this is
an extraordinarily powerful
book. And one of the things I
love about it, he's given it
away. It's like too important to
try to make any money off it.
He's been giving it away. And if
you get it in the PDF form, all
the references are hot linked.
So you can pop right, right,
right into one article after
another, one Research Institute
after another. It's all hot
linked, and you can move right
into it and go very deeply.
Unknown: Dwayne
Duane Elgin: The one thing I
would say, moderating my
optimism, this book looks, oh,
6070, years into the future, and
I've been doing futures research
for a half century, truly. And
this book is the accumulation of
that half century of work. And I
want to be optimistic, but boy,
I tell you, It's fierce. The
world is coming down on us now,
not 10 years from now, but no
and we could run through the
elements once again. But the
reality is, we're up against it
now, and it requires our courage
now. It requires our collective
consciousness. Now it requires a
new media to reflect back to us,
new possibilities, new
priorities, new perspectives on
on where we are, who we are,
where we're going now. So to the
extent that there are people
watching and this program now,
get on with your work. Get on
with your life. Choose the
freedom that you have off your
creativity to our wounded world
to move into this more
transforming future.
Bas de Cock: So thank you. You
bet, yeah, I see a hand of
Henrik. You can open up your
mic.
Unknown: Hey, thank you. So I
came here as someone who's
curious, and so I am going to
ask a question at the risk of
sounding flippant, because I
obviously don't have the
experience that the three of you
have, but I'm just going to ask
this question from a position of
curiosity and trying to get some
clarity. So I've heard a lot of
things, reincarnation, karma.
You know, the path of the soul
is taking the path of humanity
going forward. We come from a
source and intelligence, and it
sounds like it's a very profound
worldview, right? And I, I came
from a Christian worldview. I'm
no longer in that world for you.
And my question is, what makes
you guys so convinced this is
actually reality, or this is
actually true? And it's not just
the LSD messing with your hats.
To be I told you it was gonna be
flip, but you guys
Chris Bache: absolutely, good
question. Absolutely. Thank you.
I'll take a shot, Dwayne, then
you take a shot. Yeah. Okay. Ken
ring, founder of near death
episode studies, founder of the
Journal of near death studies,
good friend, long friend. He and
I. He asked the same question at
me and asked it hard and pushed
it hard, and we had a back and
forth dialog, and it was so rich
that we decided we'd publish it.
So if you were to go to
medium.com There's an article
that you can track down by that
it's an it's a dialog between
Ken and I, and the title is our
deep psychedelic experiences,
trustable. How do we know that
I'm just not picking up on the
echoes of my personal mind, or
I'm picking echoes of the
collective psyche? What are
their crap? Criteria that we can
use to evaluate these
experiences, and I just lay it
out as clearly as I can. Ken
punches at me. I respond. It's a
good dialog. It's a really
important question, are they
trustable? Right? There's not a
simple answer to that question.
You really have to kind of take
it and look at it deeply as you
go through it, because it's not
enough to say experientially,
they're trustable. There has to
be more meat on those bones. It
has to be more substances. And I
think there is. I think we do
have some empirical evidence
that these experiences are
verifiable and are trustworthy,
some of them, not all of them,
but then there are other ones
which begin to look at cross
disciplinary coherence that adds
another layer of trustability.
Yeah, it's an important
question, but what I would
emphasize is that I would never
say the things that I said today
if I were speaking 30 years ago
now, because if you take a look
at my scholarship, and I know
Dewayne scholarship, it's not
just that We're sharing
visionary experiences. We've
done our homework. I don't offer
reincarnation as a philosophical
or theoretical perspective or
based on an experiential
perspective. I did my homework.
I looked at all the available
evidence for reincarnation. I
looked deeply at Stan grofwork
and the available evidence and
support of the hypotheses and
the cosmology that he's
presented in many of his books.
So it's a combination of
rigorous Scholarship, which has
lots of different aspects to it,
and then carefully recorded
offered psychedelic experiences.
And what we find, of course, is
there's a the cosmology that
emerges in psychedelic work is
essentially the same as the
cosmology that emerges in other
deep, contemplative mystical
traditions. It's not a new
cosmology, it's simply a new way
of accessing that same
fundamental core worldview.
Duane Elgin: Dwayne Yep. Let's
see. That's a really important
question, really important. And
I raised, you know, the book The
Living Universe. I spent 30
years looking across cultures,
through different dimensions of
science and so on to ask that
question, is there any
agreement, as we look around the
world through different wisdom
traditions, that this is the
nature of reality, or am I just
fantasizing that we're living in
this living entity? Well,
indeed, there's a very strong
consensus, and a surprisingly
strong consensus. And if we had
more time, I would love to get
into that. So first of all, if
we look at the world's wisdom
traditions, there is a growing
consensus about the nature of
reality, human identity and the
evolutionary journey. Secondly,
if you want other evidence, as I
said, I spent three years in a
laboratory setting with
experiment after experiment
exploring the intuitive
potentials of the human being.
And that's those are the
potentials that are required for
us to reach into the larger
universe and draw into
ourselves, the insights that
Kristen is so beautifully spoken
of, and I assure you that the
CIA would not continue. The
intelligence agency would not
continue this work for 20 years.
After they declared it secret,
they went for another 20 years,
unless they were getting
meaningful, validated scientific
information about our expanded
capacities as human beings. So
we can go to different sources
of validation and verification,
but it's there, but we're just
beginning to accumulate that
evidence now, and that is now
being presented to us, and
whether through the psychedelic
vehicle or through the
meditation experiences and so
on, but the evidence is there,
and beautiful question, though.
Thank you.
Chris Bache: And in addition to
that article by Ken and I that
dialog. You'll see a reference
there, and you can find it at my
website, Chris bache.com, and
you can also see it in
academia.edu, where I've put a
lot of my major articles posted.
You just look up Chris Bache
there, and there is a section
from the. First chapter of dark
night, early dawn, which really
drills down on this question.
And the section is called the
epistemic value of psychedelic
experience, right? The
epistemological value, and I
really lean on that and hard.
So, yeah, important question.
Unknown: Yeah. I appreciate your
answers. Thank you very much.
Bas de Cock: I see a hand for
Sue, please open up your
microphone.
Unknown: Okay, I just want to
say a huge thank you to both
Chris and Dwayne, because I
think they have the most
enormous courage, and I feel
encouraged to face whatever it
is that may be coming away,
because they have the courage to
go there in detail, both Chris
through I've read your book, so
I know the detail of how much
pain you know, collective human
or other human pain that you
went through. And I just think,
yeah, to have kept going with
that kept going is absolutely
amazing. So thank you. And for
Dewayne to look into the future,
to see really the terrifying
prospects there, and still to
you know, be encouraging us and
going forward. So I just wanted
to say, I wonder whether our
collective consciousness has
gone down rather than up, which
with reincarnation, the idea is
that you learn something and
come back. But I personally, I
feel that the goddess culture is
going back to pre history had a
lot of very high consciousness
going on, you know, the Minoan
civilizations, etc. And I kind
of feel that through our
materialism, our consciousness
has has kind of gone down,
become more limited. So I
suppose I wonder whether the
idea of reincarnation, taking us
forward, how that could fit to a
kind of decline in consciousness
and awareness of who we are in a
living universe. Because I think
there were cultures in previous
times that had that. Sorry, I'm
going a bit crazy on this thing
on my screen. Stop. But so just,
I'd be interested what you
thought about that,
Chris Bache: Dean. You want to
start in this one, and
Duane Elgin: I have a very
simple response to that. We have
just become a collective
species, civilization, only in
the last few decades, with with
the growth of the mass media in
the post, post World War Two
era, we are becoming a
collective entity, a collective
being, if you will. That's not
to diminish the wakefulness of
earlier people and
civilizations, but it's rather
to recognize this is a new
epoch, a new era, a new
condition of the whole human
family being pushed together by
multiple crises that, you know,
we went down the list, the
climate crisis, the species
extinction, all the rest, we are
being compressed and squeezed as
a species to awaken in a new way
that and we did not have those
pressures in earlier times at a
planetary scale, and That's
where we are now. So this is a
very unique situation. It's not
to diminish the past, but it's
rather to awaken to the
challenges of the future.
Unknown: Okay,
Chris Bache: I'd suggest a very
simple analogy. You can look at
it in the context of meditation,
but also in the concept of
physiology. If you fast for
health, if you go through an
extended fast, a safe fast, and
you're doing so for health, what
we find is that after a day or
two, you begin to have all sorts
of flu, like symptoms, you know,
you just feel miserable, you
feel terrible, your nose is
running, and all this stuff. And
then, after several days, you
move through that, and then you
enter a period where you begin
to feel better than you had when
you started. Same thing happens
in meditation. You meditate in
order to feel better. So you
quiet your mind. You get very
still, you fast your mind. What
happens? Your unconscious begins
to throw up all its garbage. I
mean, it's just all the pain
start coming up and all the
emotions start coming up. And
you think, what the hell? Why
this is getting worse, not
better. But if you hold it, it
eventually works its way
through, and you begin to move
into a deeper state, a sense of
well being, understanding that
reincarnation is happening not
just individually, but it's
happening collectively. One of
the ways of understanding some
of the rhythm of the epics that
we've moving into, or have been
moving into, is that humanity
has begun to detoxify itself.
Literally, I think souls are.
Taking into their incarnations,
into their current incarnation,
and it has been for some time
more karma than they might have
in earlier generations and
earlier centuries. They are
literally stacking up more
collective and individual karma
to work on in their lifetime.
And if you looked at this only
from the outside, you would
think that these we are kind of
devolving because we're dealing
with more and more basic
problems and more elemental
problems. But again, from an
evolutionary perspective, if we
hold this, if we hold a
perspective like on meditation,
like on fasting, we are clearing
this past. Humanity is clearing
its path. And it looks maybe
like things are getting worse,
but I think what it is is we're
getting down to business. We're
getting down to some serious
business, and we are healing
that past. But the only way to
heal that past is to confront
it. Is to let it into your
awareness. We heal the past by
expanding our consciousness and
embracing the consciousness of
it, and likewise socially
manifesting states of states of
awareness in our culture, where
we heal the racism, we heal the
gender is and we heal the
speciesism by holding that in
our awareness and saying, No,
we're not going to do that
anymore. We're not going to rape
our daughters anymore. We're not
going to behave towards people
of other cultures and other
colors the way we've done in the
past. We're going to move into
this into a better world. So it
is a complex picture, but I
think from a deep enough
perspective, it can begin to
make
Bas de Cock: more sense. I i
would like to add something as a
holistic doctor as well, because
from a biological perspective,
as you see, our brain
developments during evolution, I
think trauma has a major effect,
especially the collective
trauma, which made us, during
evolution, less receptive for
the collective view, instead of,
yeah, seeing life as separate,
and we're now waking up of these
collective trauma and the
healing, as you said. So I think
there are several aspects which
are very coming together on a
biological but also on the
social, but on the spiritual
level, which comes together
which give us deeper insights of
these evolutionary swings during
our last decades. Thank you.
David, saw a hand of you,
please open up your microphone.
David, you're not audible.
Unknown: You're Yeah, okay now,
yeah, I want to thank you both
so so much. That was so moving,
and I want us to be moved
tonight. I mean, out of this, I
want us to be taking some
action. I'm 80 now. I know I'm
in the final phase of my life.
It might go on 20 years, or
whatever, whichever way you look
at the mathematics, I'm in the
final phase of my life. I don't
have children, so I haven't
passed on genes. But I've been
thinking recently, it isn't only
genes. At this moment, the
important thing is passing on
memes. I'm going back to Richard
Dawkins original formulation of
that he was looking for a
sociological a social thing that
was transferred. And it's the
means that we now pass on to
future generations that are
important. And one of those
memes for me is unconditional
love. I can't go through the
story of how that's come up in
my my life. I did my as a very
mature student. I did my masters
in consciousness and
Transpersonal psychology on the
title of from fear of the other
to unconditional love. I really
looked into the nature of it.
But how do we move? How do we
move from here we've got a
prevailing ecosystem of memes,
which are separation, which, and
with separation comes you have
to make up for this emptiness
somehow, as you say, we are, we
are the one at our deepest
level. So separation leads us to
greed and all all the things
that are happening. And so
that's a prevailing ecosystem.
How do we change it? And
sometimes, if you have a
prevailing ecosystem which
dominates, there can be niches
in that eco system where new
cells can form. And I see as a
and like this is a cell here
tonight, and I'm a consciousness
only person. I think the nature
of. Reality is consciousness,
and I think we underplay the
value of this Zoom meeting, for
example, we think we're all in
separate places. We are, but
consciousness itself is non
local. There's no separation
between our minds at this
moment, if we were in the same
room, your words, Chris and do
it? Do I they would be sounding
the same in our heads, whatever
the medium of transmission. So
right now, we're not separate
here. We're not separate now we
can communicate mind to mind,
and sometimes species have
different phases of their, their
E, of their individual
evolution. Like a fungus can
have a phase as a spore, and
then it can come to earth and
then form, and I think there's a
great possibility in doing you
were talking about this, the of
the medium, right, like this,
that we can form these cells of
spores at the moment, so we're
ready to come to earth, and we
can begin to come to earth now.
And I hope out of this meeting
tonight, there'll be a few
people I want to be part of
cells now, looking at how we can
transform. I I haven't had a
psychedelic path I took. I took
acid once, 50 years ago, a new
girlfriend introduced me to it,
and it blew my it blew my mind.
If I could have continued, if I
could have got standardized
doses and proper supervision, I
definitely would have continued,
but I probably wasn't ready for
it at that time. But I know that
the power come from one that one
experience it, you know, it
changed a lot of things for me.
So what I would like to do is
maybe the conveners of this
meeting could do it. I'll put my
email address. And if anybody
wants to form a cell tonight to
take up some of the themes we've
been talking about, I would love
to be part of that cell, and I
want it. I want us to move from
tonight. So thank you both very
much for such a stimulating and
motivating tool.
Chris Bache: Thank you, David.
And how do we change. How do we
move forward? And when that,
when I'm asked that question in
public lectures, I say, Read
Dwayne Elgin's book. Talk to
Dwayne Elgin. So Dwayne, this
one's yours.
Duane Elgin: Thank you both,
David. First thing I would say
is that separation is, is, is
now breaking down, and like it
or not, we're being pushed into
a sense of unity as a species
organism, and we need to step up
to take care of the emergencies
that surround us now. So first
of all, the separation is true,
and it has been really amplified
by a consumerist, materialist
mindset. But that mindset is
breaking down. It that is the
mindset that's creating the the
crises that we're facing right
now. So the first thing that
needs to happen is we withdraw
legitimacy from that mindset,
that worldview, that paradigm,
and and we are, we are
withdrawing legitimacy from that
paradigm. If you look at the
young people on the planet,
surveys show, a recent global
survey showed that 57% of young
people feel we are doomed.
Quote, quote, we're doomed.
That's what they were saying.
57% now the politicians are
certainly not saying that, the
the corporate people are not
saying that. Typical academics
are not saying that, religious
leaders, traditionally are not
saying that. But it is surfacing
in the world, nonetheless,
because that is the reality.
It's breaking you know,
separation is breaking down, the
legitimacy of the old
institutions is is declining.
And so we have an opportunity to
choose new pathways ahead,
personally, institutionally,
collectively. And so this is a
an extraordinary time in human
history, when, when we do have a
we have freedom. There's this
interval of freedom that we have
to make choices anew. And we
didn't have that like when I'm
80 as well, David. And so when I
was young boy, there were not
there wasn't the freedom to make
those kind of choices. But there
is now, and so this is an
awakening, time for the human
family, instead of time to use
the media and the computer
systems and all the rest create
new memes. Create new memes for
possibility. That's what Chris
is doing. That's what I'm doing.
And it's clearly, it seems, what
you're doing as well. Keep
going. We're just getting
started here. Keep going.
Chris Bache: Let me add a
footnote to that. When I was
doing my psychedelic work, I
never let my students know about
it, never talked about it. I
mean, I taught psychedelic
research, I taught Stan Grof
work, but I never let them know
that I was doing this work.
Personally, I only a few people
and a few friends in my
department knew what I was
doing. So I had these two
separate sides of my life. I had
a silo where I did my
psychedelic work, and then I'd
come to campus and I would be
doing my ordinary teaching work.
But what I found was that the
deeper I went in my psychedelic
work, the more the effects of
that work began to spill over
and show up in my classroom that
my students were being impacted
by my psychedelic journey. Even
though they weren't being
impacted, they weren't knowing
about it. They were I wasn't
talking about it. It wasn't a
physical impact. There was a
sort of a psychic impact. I
began to find that there was a
porosity, where I was beginning
to have access to aspects of
their life, where in my personal
experience, I was just answering
a question. I was reaching into
the fertile void of my
imagination to answer a question
that a student was being asked.
But then I they would come up
and tell me that the answer that
I had given was an actual
reflecting, actually what was
happening in their life that
week, this time, and this was,
this was rattled me so badly
that I began to have to study
what the hell is going on here.
How can my personal work be had,
producing these collective
manifestations. And I worked on
this for a long time, and
eventually I wrote to the book
The living classroom, which is
really not so much about
teaching, it's about the
dynamics of the collective
psyche in groups. States of
consciousness. There is no such
thing as private realization.
States of consciousness are
inherently collective, an
awakened state of consciousness
naturally distributes out around
us. It's like throwing a rock in
a lake. The ripples just spread
out when a person begins to
throw off the layers of
distortion and pain and begins
to enter into deeper and deeper
states of clarity, the people
around us are naturally,
spontaneously and inevitably,
are affected. Now, there are
things that we can do to
accelerate and intensify this
contagion. We can meet online.
We can we can dissolve distances
of 1000s of miles by bringing
our minds together in this one
space. And I believe
psychically, we energize the
field of this mind of this
collective space. If we did this
once a week, every week, for
several years, we would begin to
experience an even stronger
field, because it would be
influenced by Rupert Sheldrake
work and Morphic genetic field
theory, not just by the energy
of this particular group of
people, but by all the people
who had ever come together to
study or to discuss this
particular issue. And that's
what I found in my classes too,
that it wasn't just a matter of
my mind, kind of having a
derivative or an impact on the
present students, but the
students, in coming together to
study these things and to learn
these things, were generating a
field, and the field persisted
after the students left, and it
was reinforced and deepened by
the field by the students who
came next semester, so that
there was A learning that was
taking place within the
semester, and there was a
learning that was taking place
across semesters over years and
years. So we have the psychic
reality that where one of us
goes, all of us go, to a degree,
but then we can reinforce that
by using the technology that
reinforces this collective
sharing, right? And it doesn't
have to be simply a psychic
distribution. It can be a
physical distribution and a
physical creativity, yeah, yeah.
Great question.
Bas de Cock: David, yeah. Thank
you. Thank you. I see through
three questions, also question
the chat box will will serve for
the end. And I want to say this
because David, I want to
reassure you, this movement will
continue. And we, as wisdom
keepers, we already started this
trajectory of this movement. So
everyone has subscribed for this
wisdom keepers or the. Formal
wisdom keepers will be invited
for our next wisdom keeper
circle to keep this alive, and
doesn't matter where you want to
share your Yeah, your your
future perspectives, or your
ideas or etc, you were more than
invited in our next gathering.
Our circle will be on the 18th
of February, that's on a
Saturday, to have space for
everyone to want to be involved,
to continue with the journey and
to learn to grow into maturity.
So great question. David, thank
you.
Unknown: Are they regular
meetings? How far apart are
they?
Bas de Cock: So we want monthly
because as youngsters, we and as
youngsters, I feel I'm almost
50, a male, little bit younger,
but you are youngsters. I do my
psychedelic training. I do my
psychedelic work. I'm a doctor.
I have a retreat center and etc,
so monthly basis. But there are
a lot of groups where you can
share in, but you're more than
invited to to join and to to
join together.
Unknown: Yeah, I'll come. I'll
also put my email address in the
in the chat box. Okay. Thank you
very much. I'll let the
questions move on. Perfect.
Bas de Cock: And I think it's,
and that's, that's an indirect
question. Council of Elders, as
we already discussed Chris
during the LSD in the mind of
the universe. Course, I think
it's wise to invite them as
well, just to open a space for
wisdom keepers to to add their
wisdoms during the meeting so we
can learn and thrive together.
So thank you for that. A
question by Todd, please feel
open.
Unknown: Okay, I'll be brief,
and already had my turn, but one
to mention to Dwayne. First of
all, thank you both again, for
everybody that shows up here for
being part of this living
classroom. But Dwayne, I had
captive here, and I might have
shared with you previously, my
son is a college student and
several of his friends for a
recent upper spring break, and
we used your book choosing
Earth, and we had little
assignments and play and deep
conversation. But I would offer
is that, if we're not amongst
those of that age group, we're
not realizing To what degree the
consciousness is already
changing amongst those great
those folks. I mean, it's, it's
palpably different, and the
questions that they're asking
are starting from a higher or
deeper level of consciousness.
You know, I'm not to in any way
malign you two lovely 80 year
olds, but I'm a great fan of the
actuarial tables. I mean, I
think that's our our continuing
reincarnation blender. And so
when you see these ones coming
up that are having the questions
that they're grappling with have
already been answered in their
line that previous generations
thought were not even questions
were valid. So anyway,
appreciate CH, choosing Earth,
and there are a lot of good
youth out there that are
populating further and farther
and forward. So thank you and
good night.
Bas de Cock: Thank you. Thank
you. Tom,
Chris Bache: aren't they just
amazing? They are so much
farther along the young people
are than we were when we were
their age. I mean, it's just,
it's like when, when the going
gets tough, God sends in the A
team. You know, they are just
extraordinary in their
capacities and their drive.
Terry, you've got your hand up,
Unknown: yeah, I do. And no
one's thanked the wisdom keepers
yet. So thank you for putting
this on and thank you, Chris,
I've been following you a bit
over the years. And Dwayne, I
had never heard of you until I
read choosing Earth. So huge
gratitude for giving that to us
for free. Really, really
appreciate that. And my question
has to do with the labor pains
and the creative intelligence.
Is it is it in the realm of
possibility that things like
like covid, like the climate,
climate crisis, that they're
part of the labor pains to bring
us into an awakening, an
awareness, a connection, a
worldwide union of spiritual
souls, to know that, to know the
truth and to move us forward
into a miraculous future.
Bas de Cock: Yes,
Duane Elgin: absolutely, yes,
indeed the trauma of the traumas
of our time are catalysts for
awakening. And so a trauma is
not something to avoid, but
rather to embrace, to learn from
and to rise above. And so we're
being pushed by the traumas of
our own creation. The this.
Region, extinction, resource
depletion, climate crisis and so
on. These are these are things
we're creating. But now we're
the our creations are coming
back to impact us and and to
push us into a larger sense of
who we are as a species, a
deeper sense of of what is going
on here and where we're going.
So absolutely, this is a part of
the labor pains of the birth of
a species, civilization and
soul.
Unknown: Yes, thank you.
Chris Bache: Yep, I really do.
Yeah. You don't need he got it.
Yeah, you know what we're seeing
going into this century, where
we are now, decade by decade,
things are going to be getting
worse. It's going to be a deeper
unraveling, a deeper falling
apart. We can see some of the
ways in which this is likely to
manifest. It's going to manifest
in ways that we can't anticipate
quite yet, and it's going to
hurt like hell. But as Dwayne
said, these are all. These are
problems of our own making.
These are problems of our own
making. So we're going to have
to confront that in us which has
made these problems. And I,
again, I want to remind you who
is confronting this crisis,
who's going to be going into
this global systems crisis, not
human beings, the way we
ordinarily think of human
beings. Souls will be going into
this crisis. Each human being
carries multiple, multiple,
multiple incarnations woven into
the fabric of their psyche and
into their body. That means that
each human being is carrying
potentially 1000s of years of
experience going into this
crisis. Some of those
experiences are really negative
and kind of, you know,
destructive, but many of those
experiences are are mature,
wiser, and we, if we, if the
world is at odds with itself,
our soul is also at odds with
itself. We're having to come to
terms with our own limitations.
And the important point here is
that what's happening on the
world at large mirrors what's
happening in the world in intra
psychically, the world is trying
to become one, is trying to
confront the limitations of its
past behaviors. But we carry
those, those behaviors. We carry
those tendencies inside our
psyches, so that as the world is
struggling to become one, we are
struggling to become coherent
within ourselves, to become one
soul. And I think there is a
synergy there, so that the the
the drivers of global systems
crisis and global climate change
and and the various uh diseases
that will be hitting us and so
on and so forth, those are
driving a global Awakening, and
simultaneously, they're driving
an inner, internal awakening. So
it's a both hands situation.
Unknown: Thank you. Thank you
both. Thank you, Terry.
Bas de Cock: It's amazing how
two and a half hours already
passed, and it feels like we're
just beginning. And that's it's
a beautiful thing. And I want to
create 10 more minutes for a
rounding part. As we say,
psychedelics needs to be
beautifully round before we go.
I want to invite someone didn't
ask a question, but feel
somewhere deep inside itself.
Want to ask a question, to think
about it, to have this
opportunity to ask or to share
somewhat something. I want also
to give the opportunity to Mayo,
to ask a question from whatever
sort it is. I go to the chat box
now, because I saw there was a
question Kim coming in, and I
have to see where it is. Sorry,
so I can't find a question now,
okay, so please, so I can't find
a question in the in the in the
chat box. Now if you have put
the question in the chat box,
please feel open to to raise
your hand and ask us the
question. Lively mayo, please go
ahead and then Michelle, I saw
your
Unknown: me. Okay, doing Chris,
I love you guys. There's nothing
more to say. But I love you guys
as much as I love everyone else.
As David said, we are
consciousness. And even even
though we are utilizing some of
the systems, some of the actual
technologies that perhaps might
have brought us here, in this
time, in our world, faster than
in the evolutionary history, we
are connected. And this is what
matters the most, for me and
hopefully for everyone else. My
question for both Chris and
Dewayne, Chris, you mentioned
compassion, as well as Wayne,
you mentioned suffering, and in
the other face of suffering,
there's compassion, and with
that, there is beyond personal
compassion and beyond collective
compassion. But what are the
three practical steps that we
can take today to gain this
sense of compassion for Chris
and Dewayne. What are three
practical or at least give us
one practical application in a
sense, I'm looking forward to
what does communication? How
does that play a role in this
sharing, in this understanding
of compassion from our
humanness, not from the
individuality, but from the
humanness that ties us all into
this soul,
Bas de Cock: enriched life.
Yeah,
Chris Bache: good question. Huh?
Dwayne asking us to put it on
the line here, yeah, give us
three specific things you want
to take. The first one, golly,
Duane Elgin: I'm going to give
one that I think he would be
surprised with. So what Heck, I
was going to be a doctor early
on in life, as I mentioned at
the outset, and I was thinking
about being a vet or a doctor.
And so one thing that I do when
I look at the world and how we
humans are creating it, I look
at animal rescue videos. And I
tell you, if you look at at the
creatures of the earth and
different parts of the earth,
and you go online and say, well,
dog rescues or animal rescue.
And the videos start coming up,
and it just breaks the heart
open and and the the love for
the well being of all life, not
just human life, all life is
just floods into your heart,
your soul, your mind, your
consciousness. If you look at
the suffering of animals and and
say, well, it could be better.
It doesn't have to be like that.
Why do they have to suffer so
much? Well, it it pushes back
against us. So number one, I
would say, go online and just
look at videos of animals and
dogs and cats and so on and and
how they're suffering. And this
is goes beyond whether we eat
meat or not. This has to do with
life and how it's being lived by
the rest of the creature on this
earth that we share it with. So
that would be one. It's really,
really powerful.
Chris Bache: I agree. Dwayne,
the thing that came into my mind
first was take some suffering
out of the world. Look at our
lives. Take some suffering out
of the world, not only just
between human beings, leading
towards a gentler life and a
clearer life, but towards other
species. Look at how our life is
impacting and causing suffering
in the world, and take it out in
spiritual practice and in
Buddhist practice, for example,
the first thing you do when you
begin any meditation, any
practice is you cultivate
bodhicitta, which is the
cultivating the desire to save
all sentient beings, which is
you're doing this practice, not
for yourself. The last thing you
do at the end of the practice is
you do what's called the
distribution of merit. You take
all the merit that you've
generated with the practice and
you give it away. You give it
away to all levels of the being,
because this is an attempt to
shatter the illusion of
individual enlightenment. We do
not do these practices for
ourselves. It's not about
personal transformation. It's
about collective transformation,
and in terms of taking suffering
out of the world. Dwayne, how
could you not mention your work,
voluntary simplicity, the first
book you wrote, right? Yeah,
this is, this is common sense
for world that's living over its
means. Voluntary simplicity.
Simpler, simple, not in order to
starve yourself or deny
yourself, but simpler in order
to liberate yourself, in order
to integrate yourself, to give
yourself options that you don't
have if you're committed to
complexity, affluence and so on
and so forth. So gentler, shared
and simpler.
Unknown: Yeah, yeah. Great.
Thanks so much. And with with
that, something that both of you
created a an important note on
is using media as tool. Yes, how
can we utilize the media? And
David also spoke about circles,
besides watching video. Of
animals, and also the suffering
that we have as as a world. What
are some ways that media can
impact what? What can we build?
How can we build these, these,
these real connections with
other human beings through these
videos? Are there any projects
that both of you are involved
that maybe we can jump on or or
expand on that Wayne,
Duane Elgin: well, great
question. The choosing Earth
project, choosing earth.org
really is attempting to do this
build networks of care and
compassion for the well being of
all life that's explicit in the
work that we're doing. It's not
just for we humans, it's for all
life. We all rise or fall
together. And so let's build the
relationships of awareness, of
compassion, of love, on behalf
of the well being of all life.
And it's just exploding onto the
earth right now, and they're
just countless avenues for
tapping into the creativity, the
consciousness and the care, the
compassion, it's there and and
we need to meet what the
opportunity that's now
available, and I'm thinking of
young people as well At the same
time and how far along this path
they are relative to we adults,
we olders. And by the way, I
don't think Chris is nowhere
near 80. He's a kid on the
Unknown: block. Oh, I'm only
Duane Elgin: he's got a long
ways to go, so
Chris Bache: in the broader to
sort of push beyond the sort of
specific media question. I don't
think, to bring this revolution
about, to bring this
transformation about, it's going
to take just all of the skills
that we have all the capacities
had. It's going to take doctors.
Can take social activists. Going
to take educators. It's going to
take politicians. It's going to
take artists. It's going to take
musicians. It's if we start
making an itemized list of what
we need to do, then we
inevitably shrink to some kind
something that reflects our own
personal strengths are on our
personal agenda. I think the the
issue is not figuring out what
we can do. I don't think that's
the hard part. The hard part is
finding the courage within
ourselves to do with what we
know we can do. Right here,
right now, we are already
standing on the spot where we
have chosen to stand as our
awareness. As we come into
awareness, do we have the
courage to do what we know we
can do without delay, right now
or not? And everyone of us who
asks, Who is willing to do that,
we're going to do different
things because we have different
aptitudes, different agendas,
different karmic trajectories.
We don't need to do what
somebody else is doing. We just
need to do what we have the
capacity to do, right here,
right now, as deeply as we can.
And in that lies, I think, a
deep existential satisfaction in
that we can come to the end of
our life and know we did our
part, and that's what we want,
isn't it? We want to know that
we did our part as deeply as we
could Yeah, right. Great
question.
Unknown: Thank you so much, both
of you for existing and for
showering us with Your wisdom
and all of your energy. We
really appreciate who you are
and what you are for all of us.
Thank you. You're very welcome.
Thank you,
Bas de Cock: Michelle. Michelle
adeby, you had a question.
Unknown: Thank you, bass. Just
listening to the last two
answers has just brought up more
questions, so I'll hold those my
original question really
projects far, far into the
future and arises from some of
my own visions that I've had
through meditation and at this
point in our this historical
point as we are at the ends of
our experiment of separation and
materialism, within that
context, we're held within this
very dense physical body.
So
Chris, in your journeys, have
you journeyed to the point or
seen that place where there's no
longer a need for this physical,
dense form, where we actually
are consciousness in our
etheric, emotional, causal
bodies. We don't need a physical
body anymore, but we are living
this experience.
Bas de Cock: In this
Unknown: altered reality, I
suppose it wouldn't be this
dense physical reality.
Chris Bache: Yeah, you know, I
don't question, but that that is
a potential that can be
actualized, and may be
actualized over the long course
of our evolutionary trajectory.
But my focus has been different.
And I think that, I think that
we have, we're coming out of a
period of history about 5000
years old, where we have had a
kind of a transcendent
orientation all the religions of
the Axial Age of about the last
three to 5000 years. I think
what happened was we began to
have experiential access to the
mother universe. We began to be
able to go deep enough with our
meditation, yoga, we our
psychedelics, began to tap into
the mother universe. And when we
did that, we expected joy,
bliss, ecstasy. Clearly, this is
home. This is where we belong.
This is where we want to be. And
that leads, leads to a story of
the fall and then salvation to
get home. The whole project is
to get home, to go back home,
and that the ramifications of
that are to value Transcendence
over immanence, and devalue
spirit over the physical body. I
understand that and that that we
have echoes of that. But I think
now in the 20th century, 21st
Century, now that science has
pulled back the curtain and
shown us how old the universe is
and how big it is, we measure it
in light years, 6 million
million miles in one light year,
and we measure it in billions
and billions of light years, so
big, so old, and so filled with
genius that it doesn't really
have the same appeal to say the
goal is to leave it behind. And
so the My Work what? And it's
not my work. None of my sessions
are my work. I just opened up
and let the universe talk to me,
and what it talks to me about is
embodying spirituality,
transforming the body, bringing
it in deeper and deeper and
deeper into the body that
literally it changes our
biochemistry. It changes it
allows us not only to be
healthier, but allows us to live
longer. Sri Aurobindo thought it
would take, his calculation was
it would take 300 years of
continuous spiritual practice
before we could begin to become
biologically self regenerating,
and we could basically live
forever in a human body. It
doesn't need to break down, but
we have to increase the energy
within it, but first, we have to
extend the life expectancy, to
give us the 300 years to allow
us to do that type of practice.
His vision also is towards doing
more and more and more spiritual
stuff inside the beauty of the
physical universe, to become co
creators with the physical
universe. Now, whether there are
some aspects of this whole thing
which are purely transcendental,
sure, why not? You know how many
physical universes are there? We
don't know. We have reasons. We
know. You know, we know. We
don't know, so we don't know how
big the entire arena is that we
can incarnate into
Duane Elgin: I'd like to reply
to that as well. Wonderful
question, very interesting
question. First of all, I would
point out that our universe,
even though it's 13 point 8
billion years old in cosmic
time. That's an just an instant,
a cosmic instant. And my guess
is that, in addition to, and not
just my guess is that in
addition to our universe, we are
embedded within the life force
of a of a mother universe. So
we're a daughter universe
embedded in the spaciousness of
a mother universe. The mother
universe is completely unbounded
in terms of dimensional
constraints. Here we are living
in the second, third, fourth
dimension, and that means we're
just a couple of steps above a
black hole. We're just getting
started here, three dimensions,
four dimensions. That's nothing
in in the scale and the depth of
the mother universe. And so a
body is very useful. If you're
going to be confined to 234,
dimensions, get a body for that.
But if you're living in the in
the context of the mother
universe and the the aliveness
that goes vastly dimensionally
beyond 234, dimensions into 200
300 400 dimensions, who knows
what kind of vehicle is most
appropriate? Fitting for that
journey. So but here we are,
though, we're just getting
started. We're early in the in
the evolutionary game, I think.
And so let's embrace the
physicality that we have,
knowing that deeper and further
in the evolutionary journey is
the transcendent possibility of
hyper dimensionality and new
forms of being and learning and
loving and living. So, yeah,
Chris Bache: great. Your hand
up.
Unknown: Yes. Thank you both my
dears, friends I would like to
just build upon and add another
thought to the question that was
posed about I think, what can we
do now? Whatever the masculine
three things a numerical
position and Chris, I loved what
you said about each individual,
because we're all, you know,
unique expressions of the great
whole will do something unique
and different, all necessary and
all absolutely equal in
importance, absolutely and so to
that, I want to say that while
we're thinking of media and ways
of doing hyper connectivity and
broad scale connectivity to to
understand that we are ourselves
right between our ears is the
Greatest motherboard of all. And
any thought we have thought, I'm
not even talking about words
now, but any thought we have
when we talk about morphogenetic
fields is broadcast to these
reaches of the universe to which
you were just referring, Dwayne.
There's no end point on this
stuff. So if you want to start
contributing as broadly and as
powerfully as you can at this
from this second on, become a
great student of your own
thoughts and learn to notice
them and check in. Is this
really what I want to be
contributing, both to this being
that's housed in this body, in
terms of my physical, mental,
spiritual, emotional health, but
also, is this what I want to
project out to uplift all of
humanity and beyond, and if, if
it is great, keep doing more of
it. If it's not course correct,
do a tweak here or there,
elevate just a tad. And know
that in that moment, you're
doing a great and massive and
infinite contribution. And to
just add another thought, all of
our encounters, however random
or unimportant in quotes they
may seem to be. And again, we
all go to the grocery store and
we say thank you to the clerk,
if we're not scanning our own
groceries just for a beat, hold
that eye contact so that you
know you've touched soul to
soul, and trust that that
reverberates out infinitely
because that person we were both
nourished by that interaction.
Both of us connected. We found,
you know, it's, it's what
Ubuntu, you know, it's, I see
you and you see me. Therefore we
exist. So yes, yes, all of the
big, loud and broad things we
can do, but never underestimate
that we can do all of that in an
instant from where we are with
what is in us right now.
Yes, amen. Thank you,
Bas de Cock: beautiful
contribution. Eve. Thank you so
much, and it adds so much up to
to our first wisdom keeper we
had in our wisdom. Keep
scattering cute curve and oh
yes, speaking about the hologram
and the information field, where
we can add all our information,
what we transmit directly to
this information field, and and,
and looking at the clerk, really
sensing the souls, it's amazing
information adding up to to the
mind of the universe. So thank
you for that. And if you want to
see the former wisdom keepers
gatherings in the chat box, you
find the most upper parts the
YouTube channel. So if you want
to look look at back, feel free
to do so. I feel we don't want
to go home. We're already home,
but we don't want to leave this
setting, and that's a beautiful
set of setting we created all
together. I invite one more
question, and then I have to be
strict as a moderator. So if one
feels very urgently want to ask
a question or to share
something, feel free to open up
your microphone. Home. It's on a
random occasion.
Chris Bache: Let me try
something. May I make a little
different suggestion? Boss, I'd
like to, and I'd like to just
take this opportunity to the
end, to thank the group, because
I know that Dwayne and I have
been carrying the weight of some
of the discussion, but boy, what
an extraordinary group this is.
Yes, all each one of you have
come into this moment in time
with a long history, long series
of development and the minds and
the bodies and the awareness
which you brought to this
conversation made it the
conversation that it became. I
have expressed such deep
appreciation, not only to bass
and the mayo, but to all of you
for coming together, for holding
these questions, for for holding
this driving force which is
taking us all forward. Thank
you. Thank you so very much.
Bas de Cock: Yes, yes. Thank
you. Chris. Bye,
Unknown: I would like everybody
to put a heart up on their
screen and share a bit of love
at the end.
I don't know how to do that,
under reactions, under
reactions,
Bas de Cock: or use your usual
hands, okay, sending love from
this space to all, and it's all
felt as a community, dear
family. Thank you for your
contribution, the donation as a
gift, as you all contributed, as
it as a community. Beautiful
energy is coming to the choosing
Earth project, so send it
tomorrow, and let's go on
together as a family, and we see
each other along. So thank you
for joining and love from this
space. Thank you. Chris Dwayne
for your work and for your
wisdoms. Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Bye, bye, everybody.
Unknown: Namaste, everybody.
Ciao, ciao. Ciao,
Bas de Cock: you Nice seeing you
again. Bridget David,
Unknown: let's talk.
Bas de Cock: It's long time go.