Unknown: Sand, welcome to what
is going on for new thought from
the edge of ohm each week on ohm
times, flagship radio show,
veteran broadcaster, author and
media consultant Sandy sedgbeer
conducts thought provoking
interviews with inspirational
authors, artists, musicians,
scientists, speakers and
filmmakers who are working at
the point where spirituality and
science meet consciousness at
the very edge of AUM. Here is
your host, Sandy sedgbeer,
Sandy Sedgbeer: hello.
Throughout the years that I've
been conducting interviews on
science, consciousness and
spirituality, I've read numerous
mind shifting books and heard
goodness knows how many
extraordinary stories, but the
story you're going to hear today
is so far beyond remarkable that
I've struggled to find words to
adequately describe it. All I
can say by way of introduction,
is that what you're about to
hear is a story that I didn't
know until I read it, that I and
no doubt countless millions of
seekers have been waiting for
our entire lives. Christopher em
Bache is professor emeritus in
the Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he
taught for 33 years a fellow at
the Institute of Noetic
Sciences. He's also adjunct
faculty at the California
Institute of integral studies,
and on the advisory board for
Grof Transpersonal training and
the Grof Foundation, an award
winning teacher and
international speaker, Chris
Bache joins me now to discuss
his Book LSD and the mind of the
universe diamonds from heaven,
which has been held as a
gripping account of an utterly
unique and extraordinary hero's
journey that opens our minds and
hearts to a new vision of our
universe and ourselves as
inseparable from the ineffable
being that we have called God.
Chris Bache, welcome,
Chris Bache: hi, Sandy. It's a
pleasure to be here with you
today.
Sandy Sedgbeer: This is a long
awaited interview, I have to
say. Chris so little background,
in 1979 you took the first step
on a life changing journey to
explore your mind and the mind
of the universe as deeply and
systematically as possible, with
the help of LSD, if you had
known then that it would take 20
years of excruciating pain,
suffering, bliss and intense
purification, plus many more
years of digesting, processing,
organizing and writing to
publish this book, would you
still have put yourself through
it?
Chris Bache: That's a good
question. I'm not sure that I
would. I think knowing now what
i If I had known then what I
know now, I would have been
gentler on myself. I would have
used in a gentler protocol,
balancing high versus low doses,
balancing LSD with Psilocybin
and Ayahuasca. I still would
have taken the journey, but it
might not have been as taken as
aggressively as I did.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Yeah, yeah.
Well, knowing the outcome, you
can't really say No, I wouldn't
have done it. So you experienced
73 higher dose LSD sessions
following protocols established
by Stanislav Grof with the
intention of engaging hyper
intensive states in a way that
would allow the initial chaos at
each new level to clear and also
allow your own biophysical and
psychological systems to adapt.
How did you know the precise
dosage to accomplish that in the
way that you wanted to
Chris Bache: well, Stan was very
clear in his early books and in
LSD psychotherapy, it was
published in 1980 the protocol
differences between psycholytic
and low dose therapy versus
psychedelic high dose therapy,
psycholytic Running doses
anywhere 50 150 micrograms and
high dose psychedelic therapy
between four to 503 50 to 500
and at that time, high dose
psychedelic therapy was being
worked used at Spring Grove
Hospital in Baltimore, and they
were trying to basically trigger
something approximating a
Near-Death Experience. Variants
for people who were dying, they
were terminal patients, and
trying to give them a glimpse of
where they were going. And I
thought, well, if you could do
this work three times safely,
then you could do it more than
three times safely. And I chose
to work with high doses of LSD
for a couple of reasons. One
night, I had an A false model of
of what the project was. The
model I had was a model of
personal transformation. I
thought this was about my
personal healing, my personal
spiritual awakening. That turned
out to be an incomplete,
profoundly incomplete model. And
I was thinking that, you know,
spiritual awakening is about
clearing your karma. Our karma
ultimately is finite, and by
working with high doses, I would
basically being it was I knew it
would be more difficult work,
but I thought of myself as
basically biting off my karma
and larger bites and clearing it
faster. Turns out that that's a
false model. Personal
Transformation was too small to
describe it, and the doses I
took from the literature, I
basically wanted to push my
system as hard as I could to be
efficient. I mean, I was in a
dual career marriage. Getting
time for these sessions was very
complicated. Had to balance a
lot of schedules, and I wanted
to get as much done in every
session as I could. Again, what
I learned on along the way is
because consciousness is unified
at its source, that when you
hyper stimulate consciousness.
You're not just hyper
stimulating your personal field
of consciousness. You're hyper
stimulating some portion of the
unified field of consciousness.
And therefore, the dynamic that
get activated, the dynamics of
healing and purification and
illumination, are much, much
larger than personal dynamics.
Sandy Sedgbeer: At what point
did you realize this, this
wasn't going to be a personal
journey at all, that there was
so much more going on.
Chris Bache: Well, for about the
first two and a half years, it
looked it followed very much the
material that Stan Grof had been
tracking my first two and a half
years of work were very much
perinatal in nature, going
through the Death-Rebirth
process, experiencing re
experiencing one's birth,
experiencing a profound
confrontation with death and the
meaninglessness of existence.
But then i This culminated in a
crushing ego death experience
and a liberating ego death
experience. And then, according
to Stan's early descriptions,
what I was expecting after going
through Ego Death access to
Transpersonal reality would get
easier. But what happened in my
sessions is that I began to go
through the periods of vast
suffering that got deeper and
deeper and larger, terrible
suffering and pain, not
personal, collective opening up
to the suffering of 1000s and
hundreds of 1000s of people and
1000s of years of time. And at
first I thought this represented
a deepening of ego death. But it
went on for so long and it
involved so many people that
eventually I had no alternative
to but to come to the conclusion
that what was being healed or
transformed in this process was
not my personal psyche, but some
aspect of the collective psyche
of humanity that just as
personal trauma gets
internalized in our personal
psyche and can produce
pathology, likewise, the vast
quantities of trauma that
humanity has absorbed through
history, gets collected and
internalized in the collective
psyche and produces a kind of
Social Pathology at the
collective level. And something
was using my sessions to
basically address and heal to
some degree, this collective
trauma.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So there didn't
seem to be anything random about
this journey, because sometimes
you didn't have a session for
long periods, even years, but
when you went back, you always
seem to, you know, catch up
where you were at the time
before, yeah,
Chris Bache: that was my sense
of it, too, that I was engaging
a long and sustained
conversation, communion,
initiation, with a larger
consciousness. And the size and
scale of this consciousness kept
deepening and changing. Working
as my work continued, and I
always felt myself engaging in
intelligence. When this is most
dramatic, perhaps, this
continuity across time. I did
four years of work, I stopped
for six years, and then I
started again for another 10
years of work. When I stopped, I
was working on the ocean of
suffering material in the
purification phase of a session
I was engaged in this ocean of
suffering. I stopped for six
years, six years later in a
completely different time of my
life, with different
expectations. When I went into
the work again, the ocean of
suffering started exactly where
it had stopped and continued,
indicating clearly that the
intelligence that I was engaging
was guiding what was happening.
It was in charge of my sessions,
and all I did was really open
up, isolate myself from the
world, open up and follow
wherever it wanted to take me.
And I found that if I trusted
myself completely and
surrendered to where it would
take me, I would go through
these intense purification
processes or death processes.
Eventually it would culminate in
some type of crisis or
breakthrough, and then I would
be spun into ecstatic,
revelatory experiences for the
remainder of the session, and
the next session would begin the
cycle again. So I just, I
learned to trust that process,
Sandy Sedgbeer: but, but the
suffering, you know, there were,
I was listening to it on Audible
as well as reading the book. And
there were times when I was, you
know, speaking to you and
saying, My goodness, why are you
going back? You know, it is so
painful.
Chris Bache: You go back not
because the, you know, I don't
like pain. Who likes pain for
nothing like that? You go back
for the joy that's waiting on
the other side of pain, you go
back with the understanding that
this, the suffering, this pain,
is in some way a purification
process, which I did not
understand the full scope of it
at the time, but I trusted
Stan's work, and it was affirmed
in my work that this is A
purification process, and that
when you go through it, then the
doors open, and that's why you
do it, for the revelations, for
the insights, for the visions,
for the for the opportunity to
enter into such deep and
profound communion with the
universe.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So the suffering
is the gateway. It's a gateway.
Chris Bache: It's, it's just a
product. You know, we have to
let go of being small in order
to enter into being large, and
it's not always easy to let go
of being small, but it's not
just let going, letting go of
your personal identity. You
know, we in therapy, we often
focus on ego death. And many of
the mystical traditions focus on
ego death, but what I found was
that ego death was just the
first of many patterns of death
and rebirth, so that what one is
letting go of at deeper levels
of the journey are much larger,
much deeper than just egoic
structures. And it's such a
mystery that at the end of the
book, I actually have an
appendix where I ask the
question, what dies when you're
so far beyond ego death, and yet
you are still having sensations
of dying, loss of control. What
is it that's actually dying in
that process?
Sandy Sedgbeer: Yeah, yeah,
exactly. And when we listen to
it, you know, we can't help
asking the same question. So I
don't want to focus too much on
individual sessions, but there
was one that I really did want
to bring up, and it's actually a
whole collection of sessions
where you experience life as
many different women in turn.
What do you think was the
purpose of those experiences and
how did they impact you?
Chris Bache: Well, that was my
that was my ego death
experience, where the universe
after about this is a 10th
session, ninth, 10th session. It
just broke me like a twig. It
just took my identity and
snapped it. Now I had begun the
day as a white Ivy League
educated philosopher,
passionately concerned with the
meaning of existence and the
universe, forced me to become
the exact opposite of that. I
became women. I became women of
color. I became women who were
not interested in the meaning of
life at all, who were not
educated at all, and it did not
allow me to experience I was
myself, but I was myself in all
these other roles, other modes
and. It terrified me. It just
scared the bejeebas out of me,
and I fought it, but eventually,
when I gave up and I
surrendered, and I allowed
myself to become all these
women, then suddenly things
shifted, and I was taken under
the arm of the Great Mother and
initiated into the lives of
hundreds of women, the more
positive side of female
experience given many
experiences of women's lives,
conceiving, giving birth, loving
husbands, loving children. And I
think that the fundamental
message here was not reclaim
your former lives as women. I
know I have former lives as
women. That has never been a
question for me. I think the
issue was where you are going.
Gender does not exist. Let go.
So I was being taken into a
level of reality where male
female is irrelevant. But to do
that, I had to be broken of my
male identity. I had to allow
myself to go into some larger
identity. And becoming women was
simply just part of that
breaking process.
Sandy Sedgbeer: The whole the
whole 20 years seems to have
been quite a massive break in
process. I mean, you were doing
this. Nobody knew about it
except your wife. You weren't
allowed to talk about it to
anyone, or you didn't allow
yourself to. You were teaching
mature students philosophy, and
often, you know, there were
aspects of things that you were
teaching where your experiences
would have been the perfect
example to offer them, but you
couldn't do that. What was that
like for you?
Chris Bache: It wasn't so bad in
the beginning, but it got
increasingly difficult as I went
on, especially when I could feel
a question coming from students
that had personal, deep
significance to them, and an
answer would spontaneously rise
from my person, which but an
answer that was grounded in my
psychedelic experience, and I
couldn't some of them I could
lay off On the Stan Grof
experiences or other psychedelic
research experiences, but some
of them, I couldn't lay off, and
I could not bring my own
psychedelic experiences forward,
and I began to experience a
catch in my throat. My voice
would actually kind of, I would
lose control for a split second,
and it would sound like a little
bark coming out of my voice. It
was embarrassing. I mean, I was
I was literally strangling on
what I wanted to say and was not
allowed to say, and that became
difficult because the cost of
doing this work I knew would be
my silence, and I paid that
price, but I did not realize in
the beginning that when you
commit to dividing your life in
this way, to have a daytime job
as a straight professor and then
a nighttime job as a Psychonaut,
that It causes fractures in your
psyche which reached deeper than
you may have anticipated in the
beginning and in the end, these
cracks were only able to be
healed when I finally came out
of the psychedelic closet and
began to allow myself to speak
openly about these experiences
Sandy Sedgbeer: most people
these days, especially in the
spiritual arena, are familiar
with NDS, reincarnation,
channeled works that explain who
we are and where we go in the
afterlife. And you've taught
courses on these yourselves, but
your experience took you way
beyond where anyone has gone
before. It gave you a whole new
vision of the Bardo. Tell us a
bit about that.
Chris Bache: Well, the classic
understanding of the Bardo, I
think, was affirmed in my
sessions. That is, there are
many, many, many layers of
spiritual reality. And when we
return to that layer that
reflects our spiritual
development or spiritual
maturity. And it's a, it's a,
it's a social domain. There,
there are other beings. There,
not only other incarnate beings
or discarnate beings, but there
are also guardians and guides
and so forth. And the basic idea
is, after you die, you go
through a debrief process in
which you process your most
recently completed life. You
learn what you kind of what you
did poorly and what you did very
well. You go through this
process, and then you go through
kind of a return. Coming to the
world of spirit, to returning
home, and eventually you go
through when it's time to
incarnate again, to the choice
process of incarnating again.
And because, because the
evolution of the soul is so vast
and covers such a wide spectrum
of development, it takes many,
many, many lifetimes to
actualize the full potential of
a human existence. And so there
are many tiers of the Bardo
domain, and my experience
affirms this classic vision. I
had many experiences of kind of
tapping into Bardo reality. And
it's a collective reality. I
think the ocean of suffering
kind of is analogous to the
Buddhist concept of the hell
realm. I tapped into levels
which would be analogous to the
the high deity realm in the
Buddhist cosmology of the Six
Lokas, or the six realms. And
there are also there is a
reality that's outside the Bardo
when you get basically, in a
sense, graduate from the Earth
system, when you move beyond
that spiritual echo of time,
space experience and enter into
the reality beyond all Bardo
existence, and that is
correlated with what I would
describe as the diamond
Luminosity, the domain of
diamond Luminosity.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Why do you call
it that?
Chris Bache: Because that's,
that's, that was the experience
one encounters light, often in
deep spiritual experiences and
near death experiences in
psychedelic experiences, when
you go through a Death-Rebirth
process, often you have the
sensation of being flooded with
light, encountering light. It's
almost a universal in spiritual
traditions. And I had
experienced light at many forms
and many times in my practice,
but when I came to this advanced
stage of my work, which started
with the 45th session, I
encountered a light that was
unlike anything I had
encountered previously. It was
incredibly bright, incredibly
beautiful and clear. The hardest
thing to describe when I say
light, it's almost like it
becomes so refined and so
intense, it becomes invisible.
It's just Clear. Clear. Your
mind is just so incredibly
clear. And I came to understand
what the Buddhists meant when
they say touching this for one
second undoes 1000s of years of
living in the shadows of karma.
It is radically pure, clear, and
once I touched that, I wasn't
interested in exploring any of
the other dimensions of
spiritual reality that I had
encountered before, which
include collective dimensions,
the collective unconscious,
archetypal reality, even
dimensions of causal oneness.
This was something totally,
completely different. And in the
last five years of my work, in
26 sessions, which is 1/3 of my
entire journey, I only touched
this reality four times, okay,
and every time I touched it, it
would trigger more purification,
more detoxification, and a
year's worth of work before I
was able to come back and touch
it again.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Wow. And was
that something having touched it
that kept you going, got you
know, had you seeking it again
and again? Absolutely?
Chris Bache: Yeah, the last
third of my work, that was my
agenda, was to go back, so do
whatever I needed to do to go
back into that reality.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So if I
understand this, right? And, you
know, I haven't read a huge
amount about the Bardo, but what
you're saying is that there are
these different layers, if you
like, almost stages, and over
probably millennia, we gradually
go through them, but you went
through them, you know, in that
much time. You know, what kind
of effect does that have? On
someone?
Chris Bache: Well, I want to be
careful here. I think what
happens in a psychedelic,
therapeutically focused
psychedelic session, or
spiritually focused psychedelic
session, is that you speed up
what is happening in life at a
slower pace in a natural
process. So reincarnation, as I
understand it, we are growing,
we are evolving. We die, we
return to soul consciousness.
We're born. We contract down
into egoic consciousness. We
die, we go back into soul.
Consciousness and that we keep
this up and keep this up over
long periods of time, we choose
lives which challenge us,
stretch us, heal us, allow us to
develop new talents, new
capacities, to deepen the
capacities that we've started.
What happens, I think, in
psychedelic therapy, is that
that whole process is
accelerated. This is, I think
this is true for meditation. In
meditation, when you do long,
sustained retreats of
meditation, you are speeding up
the process that's taking place
at a slower pace in ordinary
life. And so I get you do bite
off larger pieces of personal
karma, but then something else
takes over. It's not about your
personal enlightenment. It's not
about your personal development,
your ties to the human family,
your ties to the family of life,
your ties to the universe,
deepen, and you begin to feel a
sense of dance, or a sense of
engagement of this deep,
profound life process. And I
think, I think you can take it
too far. Then is comfortable.
You can take it so deeply, you
can you can be dissolved so
completely into these vast flows
of consciousness and vast
dimensions of existence that
it's very hard to come back out
of them. And it's it's hard, in
the sense that it's hard to
leave the joy, it's hard to
leave the clarity and the
ecstasy and come back into time
and space. Now that doesn't mean
because you've touched them and
because you've known them. It
doesn't mean that you can
stabilize that awareness back
inside time and space. It
doesn't mean that you have
accomplished what some of the
great spiritual teachers have
accomplished, who can abide one
foot in, one foot out in those
realities. I really, really
emphasize this is a path of
temporary immersion. It's
temporary you have not just
because you've had a temporary
experience of oneness of life or
Transcendence, doesn't mean that
you are as fully developed a
spiritual being as somebody who
can abide in that reality. And I
all honor truly to the great
spiritual masters who have
abiding the capacity to abide in
that reality. So I wouldn't say
necessarily that I accomplished
all of those evolutionary
journeys in one lifetime, but I
certainly did do something
pointing in that direction.
Sandy Sedgbeer: But you also you
can't un know what you know, and
when you come back knowing what
you know, it must be hell to,
you know, have to, you know,
move into a world that is so far
away from that that is just, you
know, falling apart on every
level. I mean, how do you cope
with that? It's such a
dichotomy.
Chris Bache: You it is
challenging. There are
mitigating processes, though
too, because the deeper your
experience of the intelligence
of life and the joy of the
creative intelligence in
manifesting existence. Then you
begin to look around you, and
you see the universe for what it
is. The universe is the body of
the Divine. The body of God. The
universe is the manifestation of
the intelligence, of a profound
intelligence, and once you touch
that intelligence. I mean, we
all know what intelligence looks
and feels like. We recognize it
when we meet it in people, and
this is a cosmic intelligence
that just overwhelms you with
its brilliance and its wisdom
and overwhelms you with love,
unlike beyond anything I had
ever known in this lifetime, and
I've known love in this
lifetime. This is a different
order of love. And once you
experience those things, then it
changes how you see the
universe. It changes how you see
life, and it also gives you a
larger horizon within which to
understand the human experience.
I mean it, I read, I adopted
reincarnation on the basis of
the empirical evidence. Early in
my career, I read Ian
Stevenson's work. I read the
early work on a past life
therapist, and I was convinced
intellectually that
reincarnation was a fact of
life, but it still. Takes years
to truly absorb and live into
the fabric of a universe that
pulses in a reincarnation cycle,
not just for the individual, but
for the entire human species. So
I had experiences in which I
understood my current life as a
continuity of extending from
previous lifetimes. But I also
had at a deeper level,
experiences of the entire human
species pulsing generation by
generation, pulsing in as a
reincarnating species, and that
all of our individual
challenges, and our individual
karma was a fractal
manifestation of this larger
species challenge, and this
species karma that we were
working and when you have those
experiences, you look at other
human beings differently. You
look at the planet differently.
You look at the Galaxy
differently. There is a sense of
deeper participation in a
mystery, which you may not
understand the details of, but
you can feel the joy because you
know the you've touched the
intelligence that's behind it,
and that makes it eat, that
makes it more joyful to enter
into it. Now there is a sadness
that you can't sustain those
peak experiences. But in another
month or two or I was doing this
about four or five times a year,
I would go back into this
reality, and not every time
necessarily, but I would go back
often enough that I would be
able to drink deeply again. The
full cost of how deep I went did
not really emerge until I
stopped my sessions. At the end
of the journey, the universe
basically told me it was time to
stop, and I could feel that it
was time to stop, and I stopped.
But it was only then, when I
wasn't returning in a few months
to have another deep communion
with my beloved that I began to
realize the true cost of over
extending, over extending myself
as deeply as I had into the
transcendental side of
existence.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Before we go to
the break, there's a one
question. You said that the
universe is the body of God.
What are we?
Chris Bache: We are part of the
universe. So we are part of the
body of God too. We are part of
the manifestation of the
intention of the universe to
create our mind, just as our
body is rooted in the quantum
reality of life and the atomic
reality of life and the whole
evolutionary story is built into
the nerves and the vascular
systems and the organs of our
body. So we become inseparable
from life as it is manifesting
in the galaxy, in the planet on
this continent. Likewise, our
minds are part of the creative
intelligence that's manifesting
existence. That's why, when we
go deep into our minds, we drop
down into the curse depth of our
personal mind, and we find that
there is no floor at the bottom
of our mind. We fall right
through into the mind of the
species, right through into the
mind of the universe. And when,
when you go that deep, then,
then the Hindu teaching, Atman
is Brahman, the essence of the
individual is the essence of the
totality that just becomes the
most natural thing in the world,
that becomes core truth and one
of the likewise a core truth is
oneness. To Brahman is one, and
we are part. We are an aspect of
fractal manifestation of that
oneness. Once one has known that
then even when you go back to
paying your bills and doing the
things we do in the physical
world, all you have to do is
step back, and then you can re
appreciate these deeper truths,
which are the deeper pulsing of
life. We're going
Sandy Sedgbeer: to take a short
break now. I'm Sandy sedgbeer.
My guest today is eminent
philosopher and theologian,
speaker and author, Christopher
M Bache, whose latest book, LSD
in the mind of the universe,
diamonds from heaven, which
rigorously chronicles his
intensive, systematic, 73
session, 20 years psychedelic.
Series of journeys into a
unified field of consciousness
that underlies all physical
existence. This is completely
mind blowing, so I need a break
just to reset my mind so that I
can ask intelligent questions.
We'll be back in a few moments.
Stay tuned. Welcome back. Chris
Bache, you've made it quite
clear that there is an
evolutionary dimension to all of
this. And as you move into the
later chapters in the book,
where you talk about the birth
of the diamond soul, you begin
to see that we are at an
evolutionary cusp, and the
global systems crisis that you
know we're all experiencing
right now is part of that for
what point? What? What is the
ultimate, you know, purpose here
of all of this happening?
Chris Bache: Yeah. Well, let me
break that down into two parts,
the classical vision, first on
reincarnation. A few words, the
classical vision of
reincarnation as it's held in
most Eastern traditions, is that
you grow, you get clear, kinder,
more generous, you cultivate
deeper and better qualities, and
eventually you come to a
spiritual maturing, where your
consciousness opens to the core
of your being, and you awaken to
the fact that the essence of
your nature is, in fact, the
essence of all nature, and that
all beings and you are sharing
the same nature. There's an
explosion of compassion and a
deep embrace of the universe,
and their interpretation of what
happens next is that you are now
free to leave time and space you
in the Hindus called it Moksha
escape, to escape Samsara, and
this up and out cosmology. All
the religions of the Axial Age,
in one way or another, are all
part of a pattern of an up and
out cosmology. We don't want to
be on Earth. We got here by
accident. It's a veil of tears.
We want to get out of here,
either by salvation or
enlightenment. We want to get
out of here, but that leaves
fundamentally unexplained. What
is the purpose of the universe?
What is the purpose of this
magnificent creation? And now we
have a deeper understanding of
the size of existence, the
magnitude of the universe. How
many billions of years went into
the evolving and unfolding of
the universe. And it just
becomes profoundly unacceptable
short sighted to think that the
purpose of life is to awaken to
your true nature and then escape
into nirvana or escape into some
off planet paradise. At a
critical point in my work, I had
the experience of all of my
former lives coming into me.
They were just coming in, one
right after another, and it was
like wrapping string, white
filament of light, white light
around a kite spool. And at a
certain point, all those lives
fused into one consciousness.
And at that point there was an
explosion of this diamond light
out of my chest, and I was
catapulted into a deeper state
of consciousness than I had ever
touched before. And I was an
individual, but an individual
beyond any frame of reference
that I had ever known. And this
is what I came to call the birth
of the diamond soul. And that
is, I think that as we incarnate
over and over and over and over
again, sooner or later, the
soul, consciousness that we
return to when we die, wakes up
and manifests inside our time
space consciousness, we
literally the soul wakes up
inside time and space, fully
conscious, 100,000 year old
being not 100 year old being
fully consciousness with an
intuitive awareness of the
breadth of human relationships
and an ability to enter into
deeper communion with the cosmic
intelligence. And at that point,
we don't leave. At that point,
we begin to live differently on
the planet. And I think the
entire human species is evolving
into the in this direction to
this point, the entire human
species is evolving into fully
manifesting soul consciousness.
And you know, when I say soul
consciousness, I don't mean
separate, isolated from each
other, fully transparent.
Shunyata, emptiness. Anata, no
self concept, all affirmed but a
soul manifesting consciousness.
And if you can. Imagine a planet
of a species filled with souls,
fully conscious souls, that
species would create a different
life on this planet than we've
ever seen before. At another
point in my work, later in my
work, I began, actually, over a
period of about four years,
amidst everything else that was
going on in my sessions, I began
to have dumped into my awareness
a series of visions about human
evolution. And the message was
always the same, we're coming to
a turning point, a point of
profound spiritual awakening, a
before and after in human
history, that it would involve
tremendous collective
purification, but this
collective purification was
emptying out the kind of the
pains of history to lay a new
foundation for this infusion, a
new infusion of divine energy
that was rising up within us. It
was clear that, and I was given
a taste glimpses of the future
human this a transformed
humanity that would emerge out
of this. But it never showed me
how nature was going to pull
this off. It never showed me how
this would would work. And then
several years later, in 1995
when I was already had already
transitioned to the diamond
Luminosity phase of my work. So
I was working at pretty advanced
places on a particular day at
the end of 95 when I was
expecting to be taken, hopefully
back into the diamond
Luminosity. Instead, it took me,
it dissolved me into the
species. And so Chris Bache just
dissolved into the human family.
And then as the human family, I
was taken into the future, into
what I call deep time. And there
I began to experience what I
came to understand was a death
and rebirth process that was
impacting the entire human
family, just as an individual
goes through an intense
Death-Rebirth process when they
do spiritual practice or
psychedelic practice, history
was putting the entire human
family into a Death-Rebirth
process. I experienced an
unraveling of life, a profound
loss of control. We were losing
control of all the ordinary
assumptions of life. There was
just a cascading series of
crises that were breaking us
down level by level. I was not
given any details. I wasn't
given any calendar of events,
but this was a global crisis
that seemed to be triggered by a
cascading series of ecological
crises. Beyond that, I wasn't
given the details, but the whole
the whole system of life was
coming crashing down, and then
just when it was at its worst,
Just when it seemed like we
would all be dying, that this
was an extinction event, the
peak of the storm passed, and
things began to get easier, and
we began to pick ourselves up,
and we began to rebuild
civilization. And when we did,
our entire existence was
different. We were suffused with
new ideas, new things, new ways
of thinking, new values, new
capacities within the human
heart, which generated new
social relationships and new
social institutions somehow
going through this profound
global systems crisis broke us
down, broke us open, and tapped
us into the universe at a deeper
level than we had ever been
tapped into before, so that when
we went through this crisis, we
were changed profoundly as a
species, and what came out of
this crisis was not just a new
civilization or a new economy or
a new industry. What came out of
it was literally a new kind of
human being that this is a shift
in the plate tectonics of the
collective psyche, a shift in
the fundamental core of the
collective psyche. Now, humanity
has been through shifts in the
past like this. There was a time
when we shifted and our brain
size increased 50% that's
enormous shift. This is
something like that. It's a deep
shift of the collective psyche
so that every human being born
after this takes place will be
living their individual
awareness, will be alive within
a field of a collective
awareness which is different
than the field that we are in
now and today.
This is what I. Call the birth
of the future human. And I think
the form that the future human
will take will be the diamond
soul. We are giving birth to a
new species on this planet, a
species which is spiritually
awake, a species which is
spiritually mature, and a
species which is a soul
conscious species, a soul aware
species. And by that I mean
something beyond anything that
we've ever talked about soul
before. Because I think our
restrictions, our concept of
soul, have been restricted by
assumptions we've been making.
And that's why I call it the
diamond soul, to signal that
this is something new. This is
something different. And I think
our great spiritual masters, our
great saints and saviors, Jesus
the Christ, the Buddhas, the
prophets, these have been giving
us foreshadowing insights into
the nature of the being that we
are becoming. They are the
prototypes of the being that we
are all becoming. And then late
in my and even later in my
journey, I was taken deep into
deep time, and was given my
deepest experience of the future
human and this being is most
magnificent being just an
extraordinarily magnificent,
beautiful being of a vast heart
of a mind capable of drinking in
deep from the creative
intelligence and a heart capable
of experiencing the fundamental
oneness of all of life, and a
being that experiences the
fundamental oneness of life
would never hurt another being,
not just another human being,
never hurt another being. And
such a being would build a
different world than the world
we're building now.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So such a being
has no need to evolve.
Chris Bache: Well, I think this
is simply the next step in our
evolutionary saga. I don't know
how long it's going to take for
this transition to be affected.
I truly don't I mean, I think
it'll be at least generations,
whether it'll be something that
will be accomplished in 100
years or several 100 years, I
don't know. But however long it
takes, let's say it took 1000
years, which I think is
stretching it, because I think
we'll be dead if we don't make
this transition sooner than
that, we are either going to go
extinct, I think, or we're going
to transition into this new
form. Extinction is a tremendous
accelerator of evolution. Near
extinction, the threat of
extinction, whatever, however
long it takes, whatever we
become, evolution isn't going to
stop. We've been at this for
billions of years. We're going
we're going to be at this for
billions and billions of years
more. There's no telling where
we might be going next and then
next after that. So I don't see
it as an end point or a stopping
point. I see it as simply the
next point. And the next point
is to wake up to who, what's
been really going on, to who we
really are, to wake up to the
depth and breadth of our
relationships with life itself
and other people and other
species, and then we continue.
Sandy Sedgbeer: It's been 24
years since you stopped. Do you
feel that you have fully
integrated all of those
experiences?
Chris Bache: No, I haven't. When
I finished my sessions and was
beginning the digesting process,
my meditation in my meditation
of the universe, said to me, 20
years in, 20 years out. And I
thought, Oh, it'll take me 20
years to assimilate 20 years of
my journey, and as I was getting
to the end, when I was writing
diamonds from heaven, I thought
that was probably an optimistic
assessment. I think it'll take
me many lifetimes to fully
integrate all the gifts that
I've been given.
Sandy Sedgbeer: What do you
think in the light of what
you've told us, what you've
learned, what you've seen, we
most urgently need to address
now as a species,
Chris Bache: boy, there's so
many layers to that question. I
think first we start by taking
full responsibility for our
shadow, for engaging our side,
our shadow, and clearing any
obstacles and blocks which are
impeding our compassion, which
are impeding our healthy whole.
Uh, psycho spiritual
functioning. We need to
reconnect and rediscover our
relationship with the universe
and our fundamental core
identity with the universe. We
need to overcome all these
several 1000 years now of
teaching which places humanity
at the top of the evolutionary
pyramid, and as being unique and
kind, and not just unique in
degree, but unique and kind and
superior to all other life
forms, and all other life forms
serve us and can be used
exploitively by us, all that has
to be transcended, and we have
to enter into a renewed
communion with the universe,
with spiritual reality and with
physical reality. I think we
need to recognize that our body
is divine, not just our mind and
our heart, but our body is part
of the manifestation of
divinity. Sri Aurobindo thought
that humanity eventually would
become so spiritually energized
that the body was sufficiently
psychoplastic that the body had
the capacity to live forever. He
said his calculation would was
that it would take 300 years of
spiritual practice before we
would reach the point where we
could set in motion the chain
reaction that would have our
biological body perpetually
refreshing itself as we live in
communion with divinity. Now I
don't know about that, but I
find it to be an intriguing
vision from a profound teacher
about the potential that we're
activating. What's important is
to realize weird. We're just
children waking up in the garden
that's been underway, being
developed for billions of years.
We just are beginning to wake up
to what's going on, to who we
are, to what's happening. We
really are like children in in
the playpen, but where I think
we're about to get out of the
playpen, I think we're about to
walk I think we're about to
become mature adults.
Sandy Sedgbeer: You feel that
there is an urgent need to get
psychedelics back on the table
so that their efficacy can be
proven, and we can start
adopting them as a way of
helping people to, you know,
heal their wounds and hopefully
evolve even more quickly.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think so. I
think they're very valuable
substance, and fortunately, we
are reclaiming them after our 40
year interruption. Because these
are amplifiers of consciousness.
Everything hinges on how we use
those hours of amplification. If
we use those hours of
amplification carefully and
wisely, then these these
substances can help us heal the
wounds of life. We can go deeper
than that. These substances can
help us recover the insights of
our true nature, of our
essential nature, of our
fundamental core identity with
all other life forms. They open
up spiritual platforms within a
sec. I think that psychedelics
have a profound philosophical
significance. This is a
different way of doing
philosophy, where we
systematically temporarily
expand our mind and then come
back and then write it down, and
then analyze and crunch our
experiences and compare them to
other people's experiences. One
person's experiences are never
important by themselves. It's
when we get many, many people's
experiences and put them all on
the table together and begin to
find out where the common ground
is. What are the common themes
that emerge? That's where we
begin to develop a truly
trustable epistemology, a
trustable set of insights into
what's going on. So I think
these are enormously valuable.
They have to be used very
carefully. They should be used
with great respect. When one
amplifies one consciousness, the
dirt comes out of the system,
and if you're not prepared to
meet that dirt, or you open up
under wrong circumstances, it
can be terrifying. You can do
dangerous things, but if you've
taken all the precautions and
you open up under the right
circumstances, there is nothing
that comes out that can't be
beneficial if you face it with
courage and with grounding and
with skill. And I think we are
we are now training the next
generation of psychedelic
therapists. We are training
people to help other. People use
these substances beneficially?
Sandy Sedgbeer: Well, of course,
you know, back in the 60s, there
was a move. A lot of people were
involved in doing experiments
with these to find out how they
could be useful to humanity, and
they got shut down. Are you
hopeful that this time we will
be able to move forward with
this and find the benefits and
allow people to benefit.
Chris Bache: I hope so. That
seems to be where we're going.
The psychedelic Renaissance is
really focused on personal
healing and by treating the
conditions that are generated by
modern culture, post traumatic
stress disorder, depression,
addiction, death, anxiety, we're
using scientific methodologies
and carefully framed studies in
order to document the beneficial
effect of these substances. Now,
once we do that, once we
establish them and bring them
back as legitimate subjects for
discussion in scientific and
just educated society. Then I
think we'll be going into the
next second and third levels,
where we'll begin to realize
that these capacities, these
substances, not only heal, have
the capacity to heal, but they
have the capacity to reveal, to
open, to illumine. Now
civilizations have known
Indigenous peoples have known
this for millennia. Ayahuasca is
used in South America going back
at least 1500 years. Peyote,
Mescaline, mushrooms, indigenous
people have been using these
substances to open up spiritual
communion. For millennia, we're
catching up, and so therefore
the indigenous people really are
our teachers in how to use these
substances wisely.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Do you ever
wonder, why you Why did you have
this experience and not someone
else?
Chris Bache: Well, first, many
people have used these
substances wisely and have had
these and types of these
experiences. So I'm just a
representative of a whole social
movement, and maybe I pushed the
edge harder than most, and maybe
I because of my training, maybe
I wrote it down and and analyzed
it and kind of worked out the
details more than most. But I
don't see myself as unique in
any way. I see myself as part of
a social movement. When I got
out of graduate school and I met
Stan Grof work. As soon as I met
his work, I said I knew this was
my work. This was my calling. It
was just it woke up inside why
that was the case. Eventually,
it really came back to decisions
that were made when I was in the
Bardo before I incarnated, what
my soul's work was going to be,
and my soul's work really was
very much around education and
very much around healing, but
not psychotherapeutic healing
one on one, but really engaging
healing at a very Deep
collective level. And I think
that there are many, many people
working at this level. I think
there are many hidden saints
working to bring about the birth
of the huge human I think there
are many Bodhisattvas in the
world. Some of them are
recognized and most of them are
not recognized. But who really
are they invest their life and
bringing about the
transformation of the lives of
others, of helping others and
helping us make it through this
crisis of that we are entering
into, the global systems crisis,
the ecological crisis, as it
bearing down on us, it's going
to take all of us, I think All
of us chose to be here at the
time and the form that we
incarnated. I think there are no
victims, there are no there is
no compulsion and reincarnation.
We all chose to enter this time
in history. We we may not
remember why, but we chose to be
here. We chose to be part of
this process.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Chris Bache,
thank you. Thank you for joining
us and sharing your incredible
journey, and thank you for
sharing it with the world.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Sandy.
It's been my honor and pleasure
to be in discussion with you
today. Likewise.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So. LSD, in the
mind of the universe, diamonds
from heaven. It's published by
inner traditions, bear and
company. And for more
information about Chris Bache,
his articles, events and his
other three books, the living
classroom, teaching in the
collective consciousness, dark
night, early dawn, Steps to a
deep ecology of mind and life
cycles, reincarnation and the
where. Of life. Visit his
website at Chris bache.com
That's it for this week. I'm
Sandy sedgbeer. I'll be back
with another edition of what is
going on at the same time next
week. Till then, it's goodbye
from me and thank you again to
Chris Bache,
Chris Bache: Thank you, Sandy.
You
Unknown: you.