Unknown: Welcome to connecting
with coincidence with
psychiatrist Bernard David
beitman, MD, Dr Byman is the
founder of the coincidence
project. The project encourages
people like you to tell each
other coincidence stories, to
learn more about Dr bitements
work put connecting with
coincidence in your web browser,
you'll find his book, his
Psychology Today, blog and the
interviews from this podcast and
now your host, Bernard beitman,
MD,
Bernard Beitman: welcome to
connecting with coincidence. I
am Bernard beitman. I'm a
psychiatrist. I study meaningful
coincidences. My book called
meaningful coincidences, how
synchronicity and serendipity
happen, is available at a link
for those of you on YouTube
below, and we're talking about
something that psychiatry
doesn't address quite now, but
we got a problem here on Earth,
ladies and gentlemen, and it
tends to be denied. People don't
want to pay attention to it, lot
of different ways of avoiding
it. And we are here to say the
evidence is really strong. We
are in the midst of the sixth
mass extinction of life on our
planet. A mass extinction is a
short period of geological time
in which a high percentage of
biodiversity, distinct species,
bacteria, fungi, plants,
mammals, birds, reptiles,
amphibians, fish, invertebrates
and vertebrates like us die out.
And this definition, it's
important to note that in
geological time, a short period
of time can be a 1000s, 1000s or
even millions of years. The
planet has experienced five
previous mass extinctions, the
last one occurring 665, point 5
million years ago, which wiped
out the dinosaurs. As everybody
kind of remembers. Experts now
believe we are in the midst of
the six mass extinction. And
unlike previous mass extinctions
caused by natural phenomena,
this six one is driven by us
about human activity. Primarily,
they're not limited to the
unsustainable use of land, water
and energy use and the resulting
climate change. We have two very
smart guys here who are coming
at this question in different
ways, and it's the first time
they're ever talking with each
other, but they got their hearts
in common, and their minds are
really good, as many of you
know. Who know each one of
these? First is Chris Bache,
I'll introduce and then Dan
Siegel, Chris is a professor
emeritus in the Department of
Philosophy and Religious Studies
at Youngstown State University
where he taught for 33 years.
Key thing about Chris, besides
the living classroom, was where
I got introduced to him, and the
connection between minds of the
students and his were very
remarkable that one, and also
Chris, has the distinction of
taking, has taken LSD, I think,
73 times, and under control
conditions, high doses, and
explored, not explored,
consciousness, and he's come
away with some ideas about how
to mitigate or what's going to
happen with this mass extinction
we are now facing. Dan Siegel is
a clinical professor of
psychiatry at the UCLA School of
Medicine and founding director
and founding the co director of
the mindfulness awareness
Research Center at UCLA. He is
executive director of the mine
site Institute which focuses on
the development of mindset,
teaches insight, empathy and
integration. And his latest book
just came out this month, intra
connected is just about how this
whole thing we are in is
interconnected, including you
and I, and me and them and you
what we are. They together, kind
of thing we are in this all of
us, and because each of these
men come from somewhat different
perspectives, but again, for me,
their hearts and mind have some
overlap, I've asked them to join
me with a discussion about their
views about what is coming for
humanity and what we might be
able to do about that. So we'll
start off with each of each of
them saying something about
their answer to this question,
and then the dialog will begin
between the two of them. So
Chris, let's start with you, and
then we'll go to Dan.
Chris Bache: Well, I was hoping
you were going to start with Dan
first.
Bernard Beitman: We can start
with Dan first. Okay, okay, Dan,
you're on, Dan, you're on.
Dan Siegel: Okay, well, whatever
I'm happy to go with, how,
whatever sequence which probably
relates in some ways to part of
what I'll talk about. But you
know, my background is a trained
as a scientist and then as a
physician, and. Then as a mental
health practitioner, as a
psychiatrist, and then working
as a researcher in the area of
relationships and the
development of the self, and
then becoming more an educator,
really teaching people in
different realms the work of
mental health, of education, of
parenting, of Policy and
Government, organizational
functioning, things like that.
And then I worked, starting
around 30 years ago, to bring
different sciences together into
one framework that E O Wilson
later would the term he used we
would apply to that called
consilience, finding the common
ground. And so initially it was
all the different scientific
disciplines, everything from
math and physics up to sociology
and anthropology and everything
in between. But then it opened
up this field of interpersonal
neurobiology to invite all ways
of knowing. So religious
studies, spiritual practices,
contemplative practices,
indigenous knowledge, looking at
poetry, at music, at art, dance.
So you know, any pursuit of
exploration of truth is invited
into the conversation. And you
know, we now have 80 textbooks
in the Norton series that that I
founded, and the the focus is on
reality. But one aspect of
reality we look at is the human
mind, and we see the mind as
broader than the brain. So
unlike how Bernie you and I were
trained in psychiatry and in
medicine since the time of
Hippocrates, 2500 years ago,
where the mind was thought of as
a synonym, basically, for brain
activity. And William James, the
grandfather of modern
psychology, kind of reaffirmed
that in 1890 in interpersonal
neurobiology, we say, Well,
that's true, but not the whole
story, that the brain is really
important, but it's actually
broader than the brain, this
thing called the mind, and in
fact, it's bigger than the body.
So then in these last 30 years,
there's been a fascinating
journey to look at what the mind
is from the perspective of what
the proposal is, is that it's an
emergent property of energy flow
that is arising both within the
individual and in the
relationality of the individual
with, you know, other people and
with nature, so people on the
planet, and in that sense, the
mind has features such as
subjective experience, it has
consciousness, it has
information processing. But a
fourth facet of the mind is the
emergent property that's been
assessed by the mathematics of
complex systems studied in 1980s
so pretty recently, it's the
emergent property, meaning the
interaction of elements of the
system give rise to something
larger than the elements
themselves. So we see all these
properties as emergent but one
of them, this fourth property,
is the self organizing emergent
property of a complex system,
and we see it as the system
being embodied and relational
energy flow. And this self
organizing process optimizes its
its unfolding through a process
of differentiating and linking.
And when optimal self
organization happens, this, what
we'll call integration, this
balance of differentiation,
linkage, it leads to a kind of
flow that has five qualities
that feel with the texture of
harmony, and those are
flexibility, F, adaptability, a,
coherence, which is holding
together well over time, C,
being energized with a sense of
vitality, E and stable, meaning
reliable. So this faces flow is
a way you would describe
basically optimal self
organization. And the proposal
from 30 years ago was that that
was the basis of well being, and
that when there's deviation from
integration, this integrative
self organizing process, toward
harmony, you get to either chaos
or rigidity. So in terms of the
question of human life and
individuals life, you can look
at, for example, attachment
relationships, and see that when
they're integrative, the
integrated sharing the honoring
of differences and promoting of
compassionate linkages within a
parent child relationship
actually is a relational flow of
energy and information that is
integrated, that stimulates the
growth of integration in the
child's nervous system and. And
so in the textbook the
developing mind, I wrote now in
its third edition, you know,
there's repeated support in the
empirical scientific literature
that integration is the basis of
well being. Smith and colleagues
in 2015 showed that every
measure of well being you could
find is predicted by basically
how interconnected something
called the connectome is. And
then, in the similar vein, in
psychiatric disorders, anyone
with a mental suffering, it can
be revealed as chaos or
rigidity. And every study ever
done of the brains of
individuals with psychiatric
disorders have impaired
integration. So that's that's
interesting, and then positive
interventions like compassion
training and mindfulness
training, those lead to
increased growth in integration
in the brain in in the very ways
that studies, for example, of
trauma, show that integration is
impaired in children who are
abused or neglected. So all that
being said, integration, then,
is seen as the base of well
being. So in terms of this
question of what's happening on
the planet, the many pandemics
we face. I mean, one is the
pandemic of loss of
biodiversity, known as this,
this mass extinction. But other
pandemics include racism and
social injustice, the covid, 19
virus, even you can look at
issues of polarization and
misinformation, the pandemic of
loneliness in modern culture,
and you know, the addiction we
have to screens. And also just
Climate The climate disaster,
all of those are examples of
chaos and rigidity, and all of
those I'll have you consider are
either worsened by or even
caused by and here's the
proposal for our discussion,
that the way the self is
constructed by the human mind
because of the vulnerabilities
of the human brain we create in
modern culture for a drive to
certainty what we're going to
name as the solo self, a view of
this center of experience as
existing only inside the
individual, and whether that
individual is by themselves or
in individuals like them. So
it's like a plural solo self.
You can basically see that the
heart of these pandemics, um,
including extinction, you know,
might be this solo self. And if
that's true, as you point out,
you know, this condition of the
extinction looks like it's due
to what the human species is
doing. So the proposal in the
book interconnected, and I can
show you the subtitle, so you
can kind of read it for
yourself. You know, it's
interconnected, but it's the
idea of an identity as we me
plus we as the integration of
self, identity and belonging. So
the idea there is that you can
find a way to see how the self
develops in the individual and
in modern culture. And that's
what I do in the book, through a
lifespan examination of how self
defined, as you know, a center
of experience that includes
subjective experience,
perspective and agency. You can
remember that with the acronym
spa, that this really scientific
view of how the self develops as
separate in modern culture fits,
in fact, with what the
invitation is from contemplative
practices from 1000s of years
and indigenous wisdom from 1000s
of years. So that here on this
unceded Land of the Tongva and
the Chumash in Southern
California where I am, you know,
the teachings were always about
humans were part of nature. But
in modern culture, there's a
drive to go from that verb, like
fluid, intra connected, meaning
we're connected within a whole,
not just interconnected, where
I'm connected to you, and that's
the inter, the between. That's
where the word intra connected
is useful. We speak from the
subjective experience
perspective and agency of the
whole W, H, O, L, E, the whole
of reality. And then in doing
that, then what you see is
indigenous teachings have
invited this, contemplative
practices have invited it. And
and this discussion in the book
is really just saying, Can
science join with those ancient
invitations to see how the human
mind's drive for certainty
makes us view identity as an
entity a noun like thing, rather
than embracing uncertainty and
opening to the verb, like
reality, of a more fluid
identity and a belonging that is
universal, and then what the
hope is. And this is, I think, a
realistic idealism, in the sense
that it's an optimistic view,
yes, but it says humanity. We
can, in fact, construct a self
that is interconnected as we and
that can lead to actions for the
greater good that are as if you
had stubbed your own toe of your
body, you take care of your toe,
we would see the whole living
world as who we are. So that's
that's in a nutshell. That's the
notion, and that's how it fits
in with this discussion.
Bernard Beitman: Beautiful,
beautiful, beautiful, Chris
Comments, questions and you
Chris Bache: Dan, that really
was beautiful. I mean, that was
beautifully summarized. And I
just really love the unfolding
of layers and layers and layers
of your research, and the way
you harness so many people's
research to and bring that into
into focus. And I'm sitting here
without any of the scientific
background a different get that
in a minute, but it in total
agreement with what you're
saying. Just being over and
over, from my side of
experience. Everything you're
saying makes perfectly good
sense, the balance of
integration of individual and
larger fields within which we
are contextualized, the ways in
which we push against the limits
at those different times and
where we're being pushed now, I
find it fascinating. I feel so
completely aligned with what
you're saying, and yet I come to
that with with a different with
a different story, coming to it
not primarily a theory based
story or a theory heavy story, a
research story, but an ex purely
an experiential journey. You
know that my psychedelic journey
is purely experiential, so that
in different ways, I experience
the rupturing of that core self
that you talk about, and then
the unfolding into a larger
dynamic field consciousness,
repeatedly, systematically and
then experiencing that field
consciousness itself dissolve
like the small collective self
dissolved into yet another
deeper level of field
consciousness, where I so often
wish that I that I had A PhD in
physics and astrology astronomy
to better understand, assimilate
many of the things that I was
shown taken into, but it was
just an educated layman's
dissolving into the My
phenomenological sense was
dissolving into fields of
consciousness. Within fields of
consciousness and being
acquiring insights or being
given teachings about how those
fields self organize, how they
work. I mean, the living class
and classroom. Bernie, you
mentioned that that book, which
was basically my attempt to
understand the fields of
consciousness that were
connecting my students and my
courses and me as there is kind
of the spark plug within it, and
the ways in which my spiritual
journey was impacting them
through these mysterious
channels of inner communication
that The field of consciousness
is that entire book was
downloaded in 10 minutes in one
session. I had been pondering
the riddle for a long time, but
it just came through clear 10
minutes in one session. And took
years, of course, to open it up
and to do the research for it.
And yet, out of such a
different, different itinerary.
I mean, I've been a professor of
religious studies. I teach intro
world religion courses, Eastern
religions, Buddhism, Psych of
religion, Transpersonal studies,
you know, that kind of stuff,
outside of this modest academic
frame, the experiential journey
that I undertook, starting in 79
going to 99 would lead me to
such experiences that are in so
much in harmony with what Dan
with what you're describing,
Dan, Your way of understanding
the larger patterns of
organization that come up from
underneath. I don't know that I
have much to offer in the way of
ameliorating this, this
extinction crisis that we've
entered. I have, from these
experiences, a certain
historical framework that has
that I use, that has been given
to me to understand what's
happening, a certain conviction
that we do make it through this
crisis, that it doesn't end up
becoming an extinction event,
that we do make it through this
crisis. Consciousness. And
again, I offer that purely on an
experiential basis, not on an
academic basis, not on a
scientific basis, but simply
because in these deep states of
consciousness, time can be
penetrated. Trans temporal
states of consciousness emerge,
and all the contemplative and
spiritual traditions and they
can be harnessed in a way and
penetrated and sustained
psychedelic practice. So that
part of my story is having
experienced the crisis, the
death and rebirth, crisis of
humanity from the future, not
from the present going forward,
but that, but also
simultaneously from the future
as something that has already
happened. And that doesn't make
sense, of course, within linear
time, but within psychedelic
worlds, that becomes possible,
Bernard Beitman: it definitely
becomes possible, and it's
understandable, and that the
fluidity of time is becoming a
calm kind of a common
discussion. Thing about
precognition is one way to get
into it. Dan, you were going to
say something I think,
Dan Siegel: well, I mean, no, I
think it's beautiful. Chris,
thank you and Bernie, thanks for
having us on. You're welcome.
You know, to have this
discussion. I you know there's
so much richness in what you're
talking about, Chris, and also
in in doing this consilience
strategy, that is where you
really have an open mind about
realizing there are many ways of
knowing you know, so that the
teachings from indigenous
cultures, some of whom use plant
medicines, you know, to open
their consciousness for 1000s of
years, you know, have insights
into the way systems function,
that on One level, sees the
patterns and patterns of the
patterns you know, that Gregory
Bateson would talk about. And in
looking at these 1000s of year
old tradition traditions, one
thing is fascinating is from
independent cultures that never
communicate with each other,
they came up with the same
conclusions? Yeah. So that's
just fascinating. The second
thing is that you have
contemplative practices, also
1000s of years old, that in
their own independent ways, have
come up with the same exact
conclusions. The systems nature
of our deep intra, I would call
it intra connected nature, and
so then you have to ask, from a
scientific point of view, where
you're always challenging your
assumptions and challenging your
hypotheses and doubting
everything you know. So it can
sort of drive you a little mad,
but it's a good practice. And
Adam Grant has a great book
called Think again, about
inviting you how to do that, but
in science, we do that. And so
from a scientific point of view,
we would say that, wow. You
know, indigenous wisdom is very
much consilient with systems
science and contemplative
practices very much consilient
with systems science. But then
you realize that in much of what
we do in modern culture and
modern education, there's linear
thinking about a leads to B,
leads to C. You focus deeply on
the details, and some of that is
incredibly useful. Like there's
a virus killing people, let's
look at its particular
molecules. Let's make an
antibody, and let's make it so
we can have RNA that matches it
in some way. And let's make a
vaccine. So now, okay, we have a
vaccination based on RNA that we
discovered because we were
linear thinkers. So we want,
need to embrace linear thinking
however. You know, in there is
another way to think in systems
terms. And you know this
practice that I that that called
the wheel of awareness, where
you take the concept of
integration and take the the
conciliant concept that
consciousness is needed for
change, and then you bring those
two conciliant notions,
integration is well being
consciousness needed for change,
and then you integrate
consciousness. So I did this
with my patients. Then I did it
for my students, and they were
doing it with their patients.
People started getting better.
So I started doing the workshops
before the viral pandemic hit.
You know, my my assistant
counted this up. I did this with
50,000 people, in person, 50,000
and I would get the responses,
and you know what, when they
were in the basically, you
distinguish, you differentiate
the hub of this metaphoric wheel
as pure awareness. There's the
knowing of consciousness, like
if I say hello, you have both
the hello and the knowing. I
said, Hello, you. So we put the
knowing in the hub. We put the
known of, in this case, sound of
Hello on the rim. And anyway,
people do the practice. And you
can do it from my website for
free and and so when, when we do
this, when people bend the spoke
of attention that they're moving
around the rim as part of the
practice into the hub, the
common statements are, oh, my
God, I'm connected in a way I've
never felt connected. My sense
of a separate self dissolves.
Time disappears. You know, love
is there? God, I'm with the
universe. There's just this
eternity and infinity, you know,
this kind of thing, over and
over and over again. Even
people, you might say, well,
it's a selected group of 50,000
people wanted to hear you
select. I've had people drag
there who didn't even want to be
there, or people in, I've done
it at parliaments, you know,
where people did not want to be
at this workshop and they were
forced by their government to do
it. Or their spouses brought
them, and they had the same
experience. They could be never
having meditated before or
running monasteries, and they
have the same experience. So
what, what you'll see in this
book called aware, or this book
called Mind, or this book
interconnected, is a question,
why is it on the rim? People
feel locked into time, like a
thought comes and goes, or a
memory is of a particular time
in your life, but in the hub,
it's timeless. So I did a deep
search. I happened to be
teaching with about 150
physicists at this meeting per
week. So I asked him, you know
what's what's energy, of course,
because I'm fascinated with
that. But what's time? And you
know, this is a controversial
thing to say. Anything in
science is controversial. You
can say A and someone will say,
No, it's B, and you someone says
no, it's C, so you have to be
ready for that. But for some of
the physicists, just to quote
some of them, there are two
realms, and this was on the
cover of Scientific American in
July of 2018 the month before my
book aware came out. And I was
so relieved, because I thought,
people are gonna think I'm nuts,
because aware was all about
these two realms. But the fact
is, according to these
physicists that I was with and
subsequently reading a lot about
that view, and in Scientific
American certainly said it. In
the large object world that
Newton studied 350, years ago,
macro states, large objects,
there's something called the
second law of thermodynamics.
And that law says that as things
unfold, they tend to fall into
entropy, fall toward randomness,
they fall apart. Well, that law
only applies, according to these
physicists, to the Newtonian
macro state world. 100 years
ago, the capacity in Technology
to study small things like
electrons and photons led to the
realization that the micro state
realm didn't have that property
of the second law of
thermodynamics, and it's that
awareness that things are moving
with what's called an arrow of
time, we probably name as time,
so it has a feeling of linearity
to in the Newtonian macro state
realm. But just like you can
walk on land and has certain
properties. You can jump into
the water and you swim. And it's
different properties that's a
different realm, one reality,
two realms, water and land. The
same thing is true. Physicists
tell us that there is a micro
state realm where, because the
second law of thermodynamics
doesn't apply, there is no arrow
of time, and there is no need in
the equations that are super
accurate about probability in
the micro state realm, there's
no need for a t variable. You
don't have a time variable. It's
timeless. So I went to the
physicist, and I said, if I draw
it out like this, does this
work? They go, that's what it
would be if you drew it out.
They hadn't drawn out, but I
drew it out. So I said, Okay,
well, then the mind matches onto
this. For these 50,000 people
that did it and those that
responded, it seems to match
where pure awareness, you're
dropping into the quantum realm,
where it's timeless. And in that
sense, it's you know, whether
you talk about being able to go
the past, future or present, it
becomes meaningless, and self
and other starts to shift,
because the experience in the
quantum realm is verb like
unfoldings that are massively
connected with one another. The
Nobel Prize was just given in
2022 for entanglement being
proven meaning it's non locality
that in the quantum realm, yeah,
you know, there's, there's the
experience in the Newtonian
realm of separation and time and
space doesn't exist. There
things are massively connected,
especially across space which
doesn't have it doesn't impede
relational connections. So I say
all that because. Because, you
know, I've been writing about
this. I've had neuroscientists
chase me down hallways after a
lecture I give, saying, Stop
talking like that. Stop talking
like that. I said, Well, what?
Stop talking like what? They
said, why would you talk about
quantum physics and the mind? I
said, Well, if the mind is an
emergent property of energy, and
the physicists that study energy
more than anyone else in the
world. Tell us there are two
realms. Then I'm just saying
it's a possibility that these
realms explain things like
psychedelic use, yeah, that you
drop out of the Newtonian thing.
So when people heard this, they
had me go to Newton's house in
England, where the original
Apple Tree is there, and we did
the wheel of awareness around
the apple tree. They made a
documentary film of it. It's
hilarious, but we paid our
homage to Newton. Because I say
to people, look when you leave
this workshop, get in your
Newtonian body, get in your
Newtonian car. When you see a
red light, press on the
Newtonian brakes and stop your
car in time, because if you
don't, you will become one with
everything in the intersection,
there's a relativistic world
where you're in a body, and
there's the universal, as
contemplative teachers like
Thich Nhat Hanh would say. So
this, just as a scientific
adding to the discussion doesn't
take the place of to say there
are these two realms. And
listen, when people do the wheel
of awareness and are given the
mystical experience of scale,
they get the same ratings as if
they were on Psilocybin,
Bernard Beitman: yeah, yeah.
Okay,
Chris Bache: Dan, I love hearing
you. Riff, man. I mean, that's
just beautiful. Everything
you're you're doing and putting
together is just beautiful.
Bernard Beitman: Rift is, right,
that's a good word for it. Just,
he just, it. Just needs a little
music, which his son could
provide.
Dan Siegel: And Alex siegel.com
an album yesterday,
Bernard Beitman: I looked, oh,
really, yeah, his son's a
musician. Now, I'm gonna, I'm
gonna do it down to like
somewhere, but in that traffic
jam at the red light, about to
step on the break and bring us
to Chris's classroom, where I've
really first got introduced to
Chris and try there to talk
about intra connection and
experiences Chris had in that
classroom, which was my
introduction to how, another
introduction how it's happening
right now, not just between two
people or not a psychedelic out
into the mystery, but Chris
would be somehow all doing his
own riffing about something as a
as teacher, as teacher, and
people would come up to him as
students would come up to him
afterwards to say, you have just
answered a problem that I have
been dealing with
psychologically, and how that
began to be, what I thought now
is what you're talking about,
about intra connection, that
it's one, it's one we there.
It's one mind of some kind in
that classroom, something, in
your terms, quantum begins to
happen, where Chris is
intuitively, subconsciously
coming up with something
students need without knowing
that he's doing it.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I It's one of
the reasons, one of the many
reasons I'm so comfortable with
what you're saying, Dan, because
it it's so coherent with what my
experience has been in the
classroom, an understanding of a
growing understanding of the
porosity of mind, of the the
feel, nature of our individual
consciousness, The Field nature
of the collective consciousness,
the way that individuals, when
they come together and focus
their intention, they create a
field and that that classes
develop feels over over decades,
they get stronger and stronger.
The more Morphic genetic fields,
the more students study this
stuff around this particular
teacher, this field gets
stronger, and it became what
happened for me is completely
against my will and without my
guidance. I started filling in
blanks in my lectures, just
opportunities to explain some
principle I was explaining with
examples that just came out of
my imagination. And students
started come up, coming up to
me, and they say, this is
exactly what happened to me this
week, or this is exactly what
happened to my mother. And this
kept happening over and over. I
thought, well, first I thought,
Oh, okay. Chance you know, okay.
But it kept happening so much,
and then over the course of
time, as my spiritual practice
deepened, which happened to be a
psychedelic practice, but it's
irrelevant that it's psychedelic
scene. It's really about
spiritual practice. As my
spiritual practice deepened,
this this access to my students,
mind deepened and began to.
Arrow In, it seemed, on places
where they were hurt or where
they were wounded, or where they
were held in block until the
next stage of their life and and
working together or just being
in the classroom with me while I
was opening up to these very
intense, very large, very pure
states of awareness. It just
began to cascade around me in my
classroom. And so I developed
what I call, and I know it's
just just metaphor, I think talk
about the atomistic, the
Newtonian approach to teaching,
and the atomistic, which really
is about individual cells
communicating with individual
cells, transmitting across the
distance, versus what I call a
quantum teaching, teaching
within the reality of fields,
teaching with an awareness that
my mind has an active influence
on the minds of my students
before the class even begins to
meet, and Taking responsibility
for this mind to mind field
effect, especially when you're
dealing with a mind which is
carrying the kind of energy that
starts to flow in you from doing
very intense spiritual practice,
in my case, a psychedelic
practice. So I developed, and I
really Juanita Brown's work in
Cafe conversations were very
helpful to me to how to catalyze
and how to harness this
collective energy that is in the
room, and how to harness it in
conversations and how to distill
it in written form. Yeah, I mean
to me the and in the living
classroom, I don't talk about
psychedelics at all. The
backstory is, I was doing this
psychedelic practice in private.
It began to impact my students.
This is how I worked it all out.
And 1/3 of the book are student
essays, things that they shared
with me. And I didn't want
psychedelics to get in the way
of you know, grammar school
teachers, high school teachers,
college teachers. It's an it's
about the nature of
consciousness. It's about the
nature of mind. It's about, as
you say, Dan, a quantum
understanding of mine, a quantum
envisioning of the human
potential. And it doesn't negate
at all the atomic truth, does
it? You know the reality of
individual mind. I know things
that they don't they want,
things that I know in the
exchange of stuff,
Bernard Beitman: what I what I
hear from what you're saying,
Chris and the classroom, and I'm
wondering about this with Dan
and I get this experience at
dance where it appears that your
consciousness, Chris and
certainly Dan, or your
consciousness when you're with a
patient, because I know that as
well, you begin to form a little
unit of togetherness that begins
to be intra connected, that we
Share some responsibility, each
of us who have some awareness of
the awareness of being in this
group mind with people, and that
what our thoughts do and our
emotions do, and what are the
things that we might not be so
conscious of, can do is
influence that field. So there's
a responsibility involved in our
own thinking about what's going
on here and perhaps what we want
to have happen. I think about
that one.
Dan Siegel: Yeah, that's so
beautiful. And, you know, Chris,
it's, it's great to hear this.
You know, some people would use
the phrase relational sensing,
or relational fields. And with
metabol and Peter Sangay and the
group from MIT, you know, we're
trying to figure out how to
study those things in a
classroom. So we talk about
generative social fields that
that, and we've picked out
several teachers that seem to
create exactly what you're
talking about in a classroom.
We've then brought them
together, and then we asked them
very directly, what are you
doing? Because everyone realizes
when they walk in that room,
they can feel it. And the
teachers say the same thing.
They have no idea. They they
just do it. So we we're making
films of them, and then we're
going to study the films,
because they can't articulate
it. Yeah, break it down. You
know this? So, so you know when,
when Michael Faraday came up
with electromagnetic fields that
you could not see with your
eyes, people thought he was
nuts, right? But now, all of our
electronics are based on these
invisible fields. And my dear
friend, John O'Donoghue, you
know, we used to teach together
a lot, and he would call himself
a mystic, and the people came to
study with him, you know, the
mystics. So I said, John, what's
a mystic? He said, it's someone
who believes in the reality of
the invisible. You know. Know,
and it's a beautiful way of
describing it. It really because
it wasn't my background. He was
a Catholic priest and a mystic
and poet and a philosopher, but
it wasn't my background, and he
didn't have a background in
science, but it really teaching
with him over all those years
really changed me, because I
realized the true scientific
stance is to say you cannot see
visibly everything that is real.
So even with the system stuff at
MIT, you know, we're trying to
say, well, what are relational
fields? You know, is it just the
feeling you get as an individual
from the way other individuals
reacting? Or is there an actual
field. We don't have an answer
to that, but I think the the
experiences are fascinating. And
I was recently on a trip in the
Grand Canyon, and, you know, you
go down the canyon and you're
with rocks that were formed, you
know, 1.8 billion years ago,
yeah. So you get a whole
different sense of, you know,
the term geological time. But
with the humans that were on the
trip, you know, some were
saying, you know, how could it
happen that I get a
communication from a relative,
like, that's 10,000 miles away,
someone's sick, someone had an
accident, someone's dying,
whatever. And I know it, and
then I find out later I knew it
exactly when it was happening.
And I said, Well, no one knows
why, but that kind of very
specific thing might be
explained by entanglement, this
idea of non locality, that if
your minds are in a relationship
with another person's mind,
basically, if that's really a
process of energy flow. And
since energy has these this
quantum property that's now been
proven with a Nobel Prize, you
know that non locality, that is
entanglement, exists where
Newtonian spatial separation
doesn't really change the
relationality of something. So
it's not like what Einstein was
worried that it was spooky
action at a distance. He called
it. But it isn't. It isn't that
something's flowing from here to
there so fast, it's faster than
the speed of light. It's that
there is no such thing as
spatial separation. So that's
been proven now, and it like in
a linear, Newtonian way you go,
that's not possible. It's not
possible. Well, we have to drop
out of the that way of limited
thinking. So then, then, when
you see, and I think Michael
Pollan's book had to change your
mind on psychedelics, you know,
the very last paragraph, he
says, no one really knows how
these work, but maybe it has
something to do that quantum
stuff, you know. So I wrote to
him, and I said, Well, here's an
entire book on that quantum
stuff. You know, the book of
called aware. And you know,
there's a beautiful book called,
you matter more than you think.
You know, the quantum approach
to social change. And very
carefully, and this was a Nobel
Prize winner, did this very
carefully. She she really, it's
Karen. Karen O'Brien is the
author, you know. She very
carefully says, this may not be
true, but it might be true.
Let's apply the findings in
quantum physics to social
change, and it relates to
everything we're talking about
in the six extinction. And what
it does is is it allows us, you
know, and when I was around
Newton's apple tree, you could
feel it. It allows us to honor
linear thinking in the macro
state world, and realize, you
know, stop the car to red light
and all that stuff. And at the
same time, what it does is, it
gives us a pathway, as Joanna
Macy says, you know, in she uses
term the great turning, meaning,
let's get away from the great
unraveling of the Sixth
Extinction, and let's turn the
way humanity is. So when she
read the book interconnected,
she was saying, you know, this
is the evolution and the
revolution we need. And she had
always written about we need a
quantum change in consciousness.
Now, what does that mean? I
think that means the linear solo
self has had its day. It's
created business as usual, which
means, you know, if I'm in a
body and this is all it is, I
better get as many toys as
possible. I better make as much
money as possible. But then when
I get my toys and get my money,
I realize I don't really feel
much meaning or happiness or
anything. So I better get more
toys, more money, and now if I
can build a factory, I don't
care the pollution it's going to
create, because I'm going to
make so much stuff. You're going
to want my stuff because I'm put
out ads telling you you really
need my stuff. You buy my stuff.
I get your money. You get this
stuff, and it isn't enough for
you need to buy more stuff. So I
produce more stuff, etc. So
let's call that business as
usual, and so we're destroying
the planet with that, because
the fundamental notion of modern
culture, in that view, is the
solo self, the self. Only exists
in your body, and this
separation leads to so much
unconscious angst and despair
that it's driven to a
materialistic acquisition
approach to meaning in life,
which is totally unsatisfying
and becomes a kind of addiction
to things that completely make
you feel unsatisfied, but you
keep that path. So yeah, the
notion that we could actually
have this quantum change,
quantum would mean, yeah, a big
change, but literally from a
scientific point of view, it
means getting out of the
Newtonian illusion of a separate
self, which, unfortunately in
modern culture, we're going to
name, could be actually a lethal
lie. So this becomes more than,
Oh, Chris, your explorations of,
you know what matters in your
own LSD journeys, or for Michael
Pollan, who was new to it, you
know, to say, look, all these
things basically get you in
touch with love, and that's one
of the most common things people
say in the hub of the wheel. So
I was teaching in a parliament
once, and they were having all
sorts of tension, so they had me
do a day long workshop with the
parliamentarians. And, you know,
we did the wheel of awareness.
And during the break, everyone's
having snacks, and one of the
parliamentarians comes over and
she goes, Dan, you know I didn't
share during the sharing time? I
said, Yeah, I noticed. He goes,
Do you want to know why I didn't
share? I said, Sure. Why didn't
you share? He goes, Do you know
that part of the wheel practice
when you bend the spoke around
into the hub? I said, Yeah, I
know that part. And he goes. And
he slows down. His eyes get
filled with tears. And he goes,
I have never felt so much love
before in my life. I've never
felt so connected to to everyone
and everything. There's this
silence. And I said, so you
didn't want to share that. And
he goes, Oh no, no. He goes, if
I said, Love they and he points
over to his parliamentarian
colleagues. He said they would
think I was weak. So then his
silence were just kind of
staring at each other. His eyes
are all welled up with tears,
and I said, I get it. You didn't
want to appear weak. He goes,
No, no. I said, So can I ask you
a question? He goes, Sure. I
said, so when you're making
federal law, when you're making
national policies, are you
leaving love out of the
reasoning?
And then his eyes get really,
really big, and he goes, and he
runs over to them. Right now,
this is guy who never meditated
before in his life. I'm you
know, this experience was new
for him, obviously, from what he
was saying, but you can only
imagine that this not being in
touch with this core aspect,
which feels like it's a thread
of the tapestry of reality, that
love is this vital force, that
if people in positions of power,
like a parliamentarian at a
country you know, think love is
weak, you know, then we're in
trouble. You know, we're in deep
trouble. So the idea, then, of,
you know, in this case, it's the
wheel of awareness, but even
just the concept that, you know,
we can actually tap into this
deeper source of awareness that
has love at its core. I'm very
hopeful that we can actually
turn this around in time. I know
we have a very brief window of
time, probably less than a
decade, and so there's an
urgency to this. But while
there's an urgency to it, it's
an ancient message that somehow
modern culture has ignored. So
my deepest hope is that adding a
little bit of the science to
say, hey, you know, this is the
problem, and maybe, as a
physician, I say, Look, if
someone comes in to me and has
pain in the bottom of their foot
and they're limping, and I go,
what's going on? They go, I
don't know. I have a pain in the
bottom of my foot. I'm limping.
I say, Here, come, come here.
Let me take off your shoe. Let
me take off your sock. Let me
look at the sole of your feet,
and let me Oh, whoa, whoa, whoa,
there's a splinter. Will you let
me take the splinter out. Oh,
there's a splinter. Yeah. Take
the splinter out. And now they
walk straight. Their back isn't
hurting anymore. The pain is
gone. We have a splinter in
modern culture, in the soul of
society, that is the separate
self. And my deepest hope is
that this conversation about
interconnectedness and we, you
know, this me plus we, is you
don't have to get rid of the
individual. You don't have to
you don't have to crash in the
traffic intersection. You could
say, I have an individual body.
That's good. That's a me. And we
added we integrate it with we
and you make them we word, or
how are we going to say that in
different languages? And then we
has a way to liberate you from
the lie of the separate self and
allows us to actually find a new
way to go to the great turning
this movement at Joanna. Macy
would say, is away from the
great unraveling, and can let us
to go away from business as
usual. And I think everyone's
going to be better for
Bernard Beitman: it. Yeah, yeah.
And
Chris Bache: the country state
that beautifully, Dan, just so
beautifully, absolutely
beautifully.
Bernard Beitman: The
contribution of awareness of
meaningful coincidences is that
the primary kind of meaningful
coincidence is mind, thinking of
something, imagining something.
It happens in the environment,
and it begins to show us in
individual daily life that mind
and environment are connected,
that we are not separate from
each other. We are not separate
from our surroundings. Being
able to, like, sing a song,
which I was singing along a
river, yeah, the other day, and
I like 50 songs, and I was
hitting like a low note, 1010,
or low note, and right then I
hear a harmonic very much like
the note I am singing as hey,
it's joining me in this song.
And it was, it turned out to be
a truck going across the river,
the river I was nearby. But the
experience of having the
external join what appeared to
be the internal is a sort of
thing that, for some of us is a
slow but persistent daily
reminder of mind being connected
with environment. The basic
message of which is, we have to
dissolve our reliance on the
belief of a separate self, and
then what do we have left? And
so the message from from you,
Dan particularly, and I think
Chris too, is, how do we help
people recognize their inter and
intra connectedness so they can
find the love that's all around
us? There's love all around but
I never heard it singing, no. I
mean, there's a love all there,
and it's so much fun to be in it
and all its many variations. One
of the troubles I've been having
is there's so many different
kinds of love that we can
experience a gradient of them,
and it's fun to try to do
various of them. So being able
to get out there and connect.
Dan, would you? Would you
separate out for this listener,
hear me interconnected versus
interconnected? Sure.
Dan Siegel: Well, the origin of
that word, you know, I was
working with these systems
scientists at MIT, and we, we
went on a retreat together to
deepen our experiential sense of
systems. So we were up in the
Colorado mountains with John P
Milton at the way of nature. And
part of that retreat process is
to go for three days by your
individual selves in the forest.
So, you know, we had our
experience, and we came out
after the three days, and we're
together. And everyone was
saying these beautiful
experiences they had, of being
interconnected with the forest,
of being interlaced with the
forest interwoven. They used
Thich Nhat Hanh, beautiful term
inter being. And then it came
time for me in the circle to
speak. And I'm I'm kind of a
particular person for the
meaning of words. And I said,
you know, I resonate with
everything you're saying,
everybody but the experience for
this body was not so much a
betweenness. It was like a
within this. I mean, I was the
creek, I was the tree, I was the
sky, I was the body called Dan.
There was a within this to it, I
don't know, I couldn't say
interconnected, because there
wasn't a separation of me
connected to that. So I guess I
would say interconnected, and
everyone's like nodding, fine,
fine. We went back to the, you
know, the place we were staying,
and back to technology. I turned
on my computer, I want to take
some notes on the three day
experience, and I kept on
writing. Well, you know, I was
interconnected, and the word
processor auto correct, kept on
changing it back to
interconnected. So I said,
What's wrong with my computer?
And then I looked it up. There
is no such word as intra
connected. You know,
connectedness of within. And so
I just had the feeling that, you
know, if we don't have a word to
speak from the perspective and
and speak on behalf of in terms
of agency, or even the
subjective feeling of the whole
then we've got a problem in, at
least in English, but it turns
out, there really isn't a word
like that in many other
languages. So So then I thought,
you know, I need to write some
kind of appeal to our human
family, that modern culture, at
least in the way we experience
it now, you know, has created
this experience where the self
is only separate, so that would
be interconnected.
Interconnected means, you know,
the three of us are here, and
there's connections between us.
That's the inter and there's
connections. Connections, and
that's beautiful too. So it's
it's better to have
interconnection than no
connection. But we need to take
it one step further to realize
we can speak on behalf of the
experience of the whole the
whole forest and whatever life.
Bernard Beitman: What I get from
just your riff there is. I like
going from intra to Inter. I
like the connection and the
separate. It's all. I'm part of
it. It's part of me. And then I
get to experience myself as
somewhat separate, but still
connected
Dan Siegel: Exactly, and that's
exactly Bernie. The idea of
integration is you have a me and
a body, and no one is saying,
Get rid of it. And then you have
a we in a relationality. So
there's an inner and an inter,
and when you put the inner and
the inter together, it's the
intra, right? So, so that's a
way of just wording it. And what
was fun about writing the book
is, you know, to take the reader
on a kind of journey together,
looking at lifespan development,
so looking at the science of
self and how it develops. You
know, in utero, in in infancy,
in toddlerhood, in the early
years of school and adolescence
and adulthood, what's the
resistance to change and really
trying to review, not in an
academic way, but just in a
useful way, like what is
practical about what science has
said? So it was like a synthesis
of a whole bunch of science in a
very short way, to say, here's
what happens across the lifespan
in modern culture, to actually
be developing the false view of
a noun, like separate self
entity. And then here are the
opportunities to actually open
that up, not getting rid of the
individual, but realizing you
are inner, you are inter and you
are the wholeness of it all the
intra.
Bernard Beitman: Yeah, Chris,
Chris,
Chris Bache: uh, just beautiful.
Again. This has been, of course,
the the ancient message of the
spiritual traditions, and now
the scientific voice you're
saying is joining that chorus
with its own particular
epistemology. But the core
message is the finite self is a
limited self. Is not an ultimate
self. It's a functional self,
the contextual self, or as the
Buddha saw in his night of
awakening, he awoken and saw a
self not anywhere in the world,
not in him, not in anyone else,
and in anything else. And one,
when one enters this deeply into
transparency, as you say,
interconnected is just too small
for it interconnected. It's it's
a wholeness of life where the
the beginning and ending of my
life dissolves completely in the
beginning and ending of all
other lives, and one lost, in or
not, lost or dissolved into the
communion of life in its
totality, functioning in its
beautiful individuality and yet
incredibly complex and balanced
harmony in community to
experience that, if we can
stabilize that experience, if we
can tap into that experience and
generalize that experience and
make it part of our living
culture, then we really have a
foundation for a very different
culture on this planet. And I so
encouraged by your description,
Dan, and and I also think that
this is happening at a kind of a
another level, where I think all
of our former lives, which live
within us in the various ways,
just we carry the history of the
planet in our soul. We've been
every race. We've been every
religion, with every variation,
and as the planet is coming into
this cataclysmic process of
compression, we are psychically
coming into this inner process
of compression. And I think that
this transition into a quantum
sense of self, a quantum sense
of wholeness a quantum
entanglement. And I love that,
that word from, you know, Dean
Radin in his book, and entangled
mind. I think we're coming into
a compression point in history
where it's just like extinction
is an evolutionary driver, and
it's a very powerful I think
you're right, that the ego, this
is a civilization, a culture,
that's been built on the the
ego, and which is a beautiful
structure, but it's it's a it's
an imprisoned self, and it leads
and builds a divided world. And
we don't have the luxury of a
planet any longer being guided
by an egoic civilization, even a
well intentioned egoic
civilization, we need to give
birth to a higher, more
inclusive form of human
identity, which I think this
inclusiveness that you're
pointing to Dan also correlates
with an escalated intensity of a
sense. Enter integration, so
that what I call the diamond
soul isn't is a summation
individuality, but it also is
because its very nature. It's
also a transparent
individuality. It's open to the
field. It lives in constant
feedback with the field, it's I
don't have any the faster we
move through this crisis, the
better, the more we all begin to
understand what's happening and
align ourselves with becoming
the kind of being that history
needs us to be at all those
levels, then the fewer children
have to die, the fewer
grandchildren will have to die.
I guess I see this price of this
crisis deepening for decades,
not on the basis of psychedelic
visionary not not at all, but
just in terms of what the
environmentalists are telling us
in the crisis that they seem
kind of coming at us. But I do
think, I do think it is about
releasing something splendid in
the human heart. It's about
actualizing our divine potential
in a higher order, a higher
register, same divine being,
same cosmic nature, but
actualized into a higher self
expression. And I just am so and
I take such strength in your
description, Dan, it's really, I
feel such deep resonance with
it. It's a
Bernard Beitman: real, well,
good. I thought you might,
Chris, and you have, and you do,
and I'm just like, looking at my
next dance step, you know, I
kind of, I mean, I can be fairly
academic. I've done it that that
a long time, but the next dance
step I see is somehow being able
to facilitate not only the
recognition, but the experience
of the Self as being part of
something greater. It's not just
this me, it's me, and it's me
with others. It's me with
nature. It's me with this whole
planet. It was with me with
Gaia. I am part of it, and you
are part of it, and we are all
part of it. And have that
experience, and I like the
differentiations that come out
with doing that, that there's
some, there's some, there's
there's, there's centers of
intra connectedness. A family is
a center of of a mind, that of
which each person is a part, for
example, or a group. And again,
it dances, where I get to
experience that sometimes. So
what we're as we come to the end
of this, I really, whether you
guys like it or not, I don't see
this as just the end of anything
here. I think it's a beginning
here we've got, and it's been
going on for a while anyway, but
here we are, the three of us
talking about this, and we've
got to dissolve the self, at
least temporarily, to be able
to, like, modulate that. It's
just me thing, which is
defensive right now. I mean,
people are doing it now, being
scared. There's a lot of reasons
to do that. I, and you've
described very well, I don't
have to try to do that. But our
mission, each of us, in our own
way, I think, is to be able to
help that singular, singular
identity of self is separate
from everything else, begin to
have an oscillation between self
and environment. And I think
that's what we're doing. I think
that's a mission we're all on in
some way or other, in our own
ways, with our own songs and
with our own dance and our own
people and our own way of doing
it, and each of you have that as
what you're doing, and I'm so
glad that we've been able to at
least get a touch of it. So I
thank each of you for for
joining me in this discussion
and clarifying something I kind
of knew, but making it clear for
people who are listening to us
that this singular ego thing has
to be replaced with something a
little more broad, but still,
the integration is part of the
vacillation. So I'm we'll end
this with each of you having
some closing comment, and then
we'll, we'll stop So Dan,
Dan Siegel: no, it's beautiful
to be here with you, Chris and
Bernie, as you know it sits.
It's a moment in our human
evolution when I think if we
realize that a process that is
really established, called
cultural evolution. Yeah, it's
very real, and everyone can have
participation in something
called pervasive leadership,
where every individual can take
whatever role fits with your
life to find a way. To to sense
into a self that yes is inside.
That's the inner Yes, that's
connected to other people and to
nature Yes. But that also,
besides inner and inter is
intra, and this is the me plus
we. Is we, you know, term and
what? What I invite everyone
listening to just consider is
that cultural evolution happens
by one person, one relationship,
one conversation at a time.
People often quote Margaret
Mead, the anthropologist is
saying, you know, don't ever
think that a small group of
people can't change the world,
because, indeed, that's the only
thing that ever has. So if we
can just have that pervasive
leadership now, you know, with
the grounding in indigenous
wisdom and contemplative
teachings from 1000s of years,
and with the additional, you
know, support of modern views
from science, you know, we
actually can take the steps we
need in the time we can do it.
So the issue is not whether we
can or can't, because we can
this cultural evolution can
happen very rapidly. The bigger
question is,
Bernard Beitman: will we and we
will, because we have to, well,
that's, I'm with you. That's a
big driver. That's a big driver
keep those grandchildren around
being able to do their thing.
That's because we're, we're part
of trying to make that happen,
Chris,
Chris Bache: but Dan, I would
just underscore everything you
just said, and put my initials
right beside it, because I
certainly believe everything
you've said. One of the things
that was shown me along the way
was you talked about fields and
quantum fields and and part of
my experience was at one point
that the intensity of the global
crisis we're coming into is
going to hyper stimulate not
only our individual fields, but
the collective field of
humanity. So it's going to drive
it into non linear conditions.
We know something about how
physical fields behave in non
linear conditions, chaos theory.
Now if we make the assumption
that the psychic field of
humanity under non linear
behavior, far from equilibrium
conditions, will have some of
those same qualities. Then we
have a way of looking at
emergence coming out of the
depths of the human psyche, new
the emergence of new forms,
crystallizations of that weren't
even available previously, but
represent an actualization of
latent capacities within human
nature. So that feels deeply
aligned with what you're talking
about, and it helps us
understand how we can make as
big a change as we need to make
in as short a time as we have,
because in in the instability of
of a, of a when we come to trick
uh, trigger points, bifurcation
systems, of course, very
susceptible to small
perturbations, so that the
influence of individuals
increases the more we move into
a period of crisis that gives
added weight to each one of our
effects on the outcome. And
yeah, that's and I just, I just
really support what you're
saying.
Bernard Beitman: Yeah, that's
really good, really good. So
hopefully those listening to
this and watching us will be
part of joining us and trying to
be able to facilitate the intra
connection that's also
interconnected and also about us
individually. So thank you both
for joining me today. It's been
a great discussion.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Bernie,
thank you for getting us
together.
Dan Siegel: Thank you Bernie,
Thank you, Chris. Great to be
with you all. And this is a it's
an exciting moment, and we can
do this. Yes, is
Unknown: our mental is our
mental atmosphere,
Dan Siegel: like an hologram
Unknown: of cosmic
consciousness.
Oh, you.