Chris Bache: CH, we can't solve
the problems, I think, which
we're facing at the level of
ego. So we either grow up or we
go extinct. And what growing up
looks like, I think, has to do
with the maturation of the soul,
the real sort of transition from
ego identity to soul identity,
because the soul lives in the
world differently than the ego
does. The soul has an awareness
of its history, and therefore it
has an aware an awareness of its
extended relationships with all
with people that it sees around
it. And so since we have been
black, white, red. We've been
all the colors. We've been all
the religions of the world.
We've been rich, poor. We've
been through that when the soul
matures, there is this
tremendous sense of compassion
and generative freedom in that
process, and that's what I think
we need in order to solve where
we're going.
Lauren Taus: Welcome to embodied
life, the podcast. My name is
Lawrence house, and this show is
a space for you to move past the
traffic of the mind and into the
stillness of your heart. The
journey is inward, and a
courageous traveler welcomes the
wide range of their human
experience. We are meeting
pioneers, healers and change
makers, who are showing us the
way with important guides and
maps, feel whatever it is that
needs to be felt so that you can
return home to yourself. Let's
go. Let's get in bodied.
Chris Bache is professor
emeritus in the Department of
Philosophy and Religious Studies
at Youngstown State University,
where he taught for 33 years. He
is also adjunct faculty at the
California Institute of integral
studies, Emeritus fellow at the
Institute of Noetic Sciences,
and on the Advisory Council of
Grof legacy training,
an award winning teacher and
international speaker. Chris's
work explores the philosophical
implications of Non-ordinary
states of consciousness,
especially psychedelic states.
He has written four books,
translated into eight languages,
life cycles, a study of
reincarnation in light of
contemporary consciousness,
research dark night, early dawn,
a pioneering work in psychedelic
philosophy and collective
consciousness, the living
classroom, an exploration of
teaching and collective fields
of consciousness and LSD and the
mind of the universe, The story
of his 20 year journey with LSD
between the years of 1979 and
Chris had 73 high dose LSD
experiences. We sat down to talk
about these experiences and the
book that he wrote about them. I
enjoyed every moment of my time
with Chris and I hope you enjoy
our conversation. Take a listen.
Thank you so much for taking the
time to share your extraordinary
experiences and wisdom.
Chris Bache: I'm happy to share
as much as I can. I'm also very
much aware that your work has
been working primarily with the
therapeutic applications of
psychedelics, and of course, my
work is very different from
that, so you'll have to sort of
show me how I can support your
work with what I have
Lauren Taus: very happy to do
so. And I think that there's a
larger conversation that I'm
part of and that I'm weaving
together around consciousness.
And for me personally, one of
the biggest parts of the
medicine is to sense into what
else we're part of.
Yes, and I think that's a lot
where you come in.
Chris, okay, all right, so
can you tell me a little bit
about how you started your
explorations in the psychedelic
space?
Chris Bache: Well, that I have
to go back to 1978
when I had just started my
university position at YSU. And
that first year, I encountered
the work of Ian Stevenson, whose
research on reincarnation turned
my worldview upside down. And I
also encountered the work.
Stanislav Grof, who turned me
upside down even more because he
gave me a method. He showed me
the method that would allow me
to explore these deep states of
consciousness. Now, I was
trained as a philosopher of
religion. I'm not a clinician,
but what interested me about
these substances were their
capacity, not only to heal or to
clarify my personal
consciousness, but to explore
the deeper structure of
consciousness itself, and
eventually the mind of the
universe. So that's where I
began, and that's where I began
doing the work. And of course,
to do that, my most of my life,
or a good large slice of my
life, had to go underground,
because I was working at a state
university. I was working, you
know, in a public environment,
the age of
legally sanctioned psychedelic
research was over in 1970 This
was 78 so I divided my life into
my public life, and then in my
private Life, I began this
psychedelic work.
Lauren Taus: And you took 73
high dose LSD trips over the
course of 20 years, yeah, and
really high dose,
Chris Bache: yeah. And I
wouldn't recommend that. I
wouldn't do it the same way
again myself, and I really
strongly recommend that people
don't do it that way. I would be
much gentler with myself, and I
would have a much more modulated
approach, but yeah, that's what
I did. I started. There were
three sessions of medium doses,
about 250 mics, and then for the
remainder of all the sessions, I
was working at 500 to 600
micrograms. What inspired you to
double the dose and continue in
the way that you did.
Well first I saw Stan's early
work and the distinction between
psycholytic therapy and
psychedelic therapy, so that I
knew that working with high
doses was safe and could be
managed effectively. I knew that
the sessions would be more
difficult working at that
intensity, but I thought if I
were, you know, in focused on
confronting my shadow, that I
could work with those doses, as
long as I could manage the
intensity of what was emerging.
But I started working at those
levels, frankly, simply because,
in the beginning dual career,
arranging a session day in a
dual career, marriage and so
children would be there was just
it's hard to do, so I figured I
wanted to make the most out of
every day. But then, after I
worked with these doses for a
while, I developed an aptitude
for them. I liked where they
were taking me, and I just
continued to press on in it
Lauren Taus: for the sake of a
listener who might not have as
much knowledge as we do. Can you
name the difference between
psychedelic therapy and
psychedelic therapy?
Chris Bache: Psycholytic therapy
is low dose, LSD therapy,
working with doses anywhere from
50 on average, about 150
micrograms, up to maybe 300 but
mostly in the 150 or so range,
and it's a it's an amplification
of consciousness. It causes your
unconscious to surface, layer by
layer, you know, different
layers of your personal
unconscious, and then the
perinatal level of
consciousness. Psychedelic
therapy is high dose therapy was
which was originally developed
to work with terminally ill
cancer patients to try to blow
through all the levels of
consciousness and to trigger a
Near-Death Experience, or an
approximation of an interior
death experience, so they could
have a an experience of where
they were going when they were
dying. And it was quite
successful. So I thought, you
know, if you could do this
safely, one it was limited to
three times in that early
protocol. So I thought if you
could do it three times, you
could do it more than three
times safely. What I hadn't
counted on is that when you do
do it like that, things happen
and things are started that go
beyond the framework of the
early psychedelic therapy.
Lauren Taus: Chris, when you
started this work yourself, did
you anticipate that it would go
for 20 years and that you would
continue at such high levels of
exploration and experience?
Chris Bache: I didn't. No, I
didn't. I didn't anticipate
where it would go. I basically,
I mean, I worked. Let me back up
a little bit. I worked for four
years. I did 17 sessions, then I
took a six year break, and then
I worked for 10 years very
intensely. I was doing about
five sessions a year on average.
During that time, I didn't
really have a plan, I didn't
have a strategy. I was just
really following the
experiences, following where
they went, and as long as I
could manage it, and as long as
they were continuing to unfold
new levels or new experiences
that were philosophically
productive and personally
productive, I just went with it
until I got towards the end. And
as I explained in the book,
things developed that just led
me to know that it was time.
For me to stop. That's when I
stopped.
Lauren Taus: What were the
questions that were leading you?
What were you looking to answer
or experience with the
psychedelic work?
Chris Bache: Well, as I said, I
was trained in Western religious
thought. I was trained in
philosophy of religion, so I had
all the kind of questions that
people take into philosophy in
that classical sense of the love
of wisdom, not in the modern
sense, which is highly
mathematized types of inquiry.
So I, you know, I wanted to
understand what the structure of
reality was. I wanted to
understand why life is the way
it is, and why our life's life
is the way it is, and what are
the what are the working
dynamics? What's the rule book?
What's the manual in this damn
thing? And I wanted to
understand the deep structure of
the universe as much as I could.
That's the drive so and I
learned a lot, I mean, the
universe. What I found is, if
you approach these things
conscientiously, and if you
approach them in a way that
encourages clear contact and
clean contact and high
retention, and if you really
work on recording your sessions
and integrating your sessions as
you go, it's It's as if the
universe sees that you're
working hard to absorb the
teachings from it, and it starts
to pay you attention. And it
took me systematically through
levels of consciousness and
levels of experience that I
always felt, you know, the
intelligence of the
consciousness that I was engaged
in?
Lauren Taus: Can you describe
those levels?
Chris Bache: Well, it took me a
while to sort of figure it out.
After I was done with the work
in 99 and I was sort of plotting
what the larger trajectory was,
what is the story that what I
would be telling in this book? I
eventually differentiated five
levels of consciousness that
seemed to be operational. The
first one is takes place at the
level of personal mind, where
you're basically going beyond
your personal time, space
identity, culminating in what we
classically call ego death,
which is simply just the
explosion of your consciousness
beyond the parameters of your
physical experience. The second
took place at the collective
level of mind, at the species
mind, lots of experiences in the
collective unconscious of the
collective psyche. Third Level
took place at the archetypal
mind, going deeper beyond simply
the species mind going deeper
into archetype of reality.
Fourth was the one mind, causal
reality, the where the domain
is, where the fundamental theme
is oneness. And there are many
degrees of oneness and many
permutations of oneness, but
basically, that's the core
domain. And then in the last
five years of my work, I entered
what I came to call the diamond
Luminosity work, which is the
clear light of absolute reality,
as it's called in Buddhism
Dharmakaya.
Lauren Taus: How is this not
therapeutic. I mean, all of
these journeys and all of these
kind of dimensions are so
important. I mean, I can only
grasp at some of them from a
conceptual basis, but I imagine
there must be tremendous relief
and and ease when you can access
dimensions.
Chris Bache: Sure, it's very
healing. You might think of it
as healing at the soul level,
rather than healing at the
personal level. I mean, there
were healings that took place at
the personal level, like
everybody I had issues going
into this work,
and there was personal healing
in relationships and early
childhood relationships. But
overall, I didn't walk into this
life with a whole lot of trauma,
so there wasn't a whole lot of
deeply buried trauma in my
psyche.
But at a deeper level, it was
very healing at the level of the
Soul, in that when one begins to
have what we often call mystical
experiences, or experiences of
oneness, when you're taken by
the what I experienced as being
taken by the universe and being
shown how life works, how
reincarnation works. What's the
larger trajectory of the
reincarnation dynamic being
taken deeper into the
evolutionary dynamics that are
that underpin our very existence
back from billions of years back
and billions of years forward.
You know, those are questions
that I had been holding and
wanting to understand for many
lifetimes, and in that respect,
it was very healing at a soul
level. And very satisfying,
because it gave me enough of a
sense of what's going on that it
allowed me to, in a sense,
relax, and it quieted that
existential hunger that we all
have to understand the game of
life better.
Lauren Taus: Yeah, and I know
that you had these experiences
with your wife as your sitter,
yeah? And she's a psychologist,
right? And you're, you would do
these journeys on Saturday
mornings, usually, yeah, and
that, you know, music was a part
of it. Did you ever have one of
these 73 high dose LSD
experiences, or 70 because the
first three were medium you
mentioned, with different
conditions or without a sitter.
Chris Bache: I have done
sessions without a sitter, but
never with these in when I was
doing this high dose work, I've
done sessions after this
particular phase of work ended
lower dose sessions or with
gentler substances. But when I
was doing the high dose series,
I always had a series. So I was
always protected from the world.
I was always working in
isolation from the world. I was
always buffered. I was always
taken care of by a sitter. There
was always music involved. I
only had contact with my sitter
during a session, largely
through the music. Not a lot of
conversation. When you're
working with doses of LSD this
high, your verbal functions are
pretty much knocked out. You're
not really in strong contact
necessarily with the room. So it
was a very, very controlled
environment. I called it the
Kiva. It's this kind of, you
know, you climb into the Kiva
and and then you pull up the
ladder and you're there for the
duration of the experience.
Lauren Taus: Yeah, were you able
to control or direct the
sessions in any
Chris Bache: way? No, not
really. When? Again, difference
working at low doses, where you
maybe can hold on an idea of
something you want to work on.
When you're working with doses
of LSD this high, the most
effective thing you can do is
just surrender completely to the
process and not knowing where
it's going to take you, but just
trust that wherever it takes
you, there is an intelligence
behind it that's larger than
yours, and you can trust that
intelligence. So I didn't try to
control it. In fact, I really
there were times when I was
begging it, please take me this
way, but it would take me that
way, you know? So, yeah, I just
would surrender to it all and
let it go.
Lauren Taus: Did your wife ever
participate? Did you ever What
was that like for her? I mean,
obviously it's best asked to
her, but I'm curious about what
that was like for her. What that
was like for your marriage,
like, what was
Unknown: what was that like?
Chris Bache: No, she never
participated. She supported me.
She really wasn't fond of the
sessions. They were not natural
to her mode of spirituality.
Carol had an early in her life
orientation towards meditative
practice, contemplative
practice. She is a serious
Vajrayana practitioner. After
our separation in 2000 she has
gone on to complete her three
year, three month retreat in the
classic Vajrayana tradition. So
she's a serious practitioner.
She was never attracted to
working with psychedelics, so we
just kind of, and I followed her
into the Vajrayana community. I
sort of, I benefited greatly
from learning the vadna
practices that she was learning
in various retreats and
settings, but she wasn't
attracted to the psychedelic
work. It was too violent. It was
too too intense and and she
really, she had other criticisms
of it. It just it wasn't her cup
of tea, and we just accommodated
that difference in our marriage.
We just, we navigated that
particular difference
comfortably enough.
Unknown: Nice,
Lauren Taus: you mentioned the
violence of psychedelics. And
often we speak in the space
about
the, you know, the dying, right?
The death and rebirth. How has
that process impacted you? And
how was that for for you
personally, during these
experiences? Yeah,
Chris Bache: well, violence
maybe is not quite the right
word that shows up in the early
stages when you're going through
the very powerful kriyas, and
you're doing this tremendous
physical and emotional
detoxification, which can leave
you going into convulsions,
bouncing around the mattress,
where your body throws off vast
quantities of physical stress
and emotional stress out of your
body. But there is a certain
quote. Violence in dying. But
over the course of the work, I
learned that the deepest
breakthroughs followed the
deepest purifications, and the
deepest deaths yielded the
deepest ecstatic joys on the
other side. So as that became
clear over the course of the
work, death became my closest
ally in the work. And so rather
than kind of trying to navigate
through bad trips or trying to
avoid that type of harsh
confrontation, I would do
everything I could to facilitate
the emergence of that type of
confrontation. I would go right
at it, and that was that was not
because I like suffering. That
was because I like what was on
the other side of that
suffering, I came to understand
that even death in a psych in a
psychedelic context, is a form
of purification. It's a form of
letting go of reality as you
know it at one level in order to
gain access to reality at a
deeper level. So it just became
part of the work
Lauren Taus: I certainly relate
to that any any of the
psychedelic experiences that
I've had that have confronted me
with my own mortality and the
dying of have been generative
and life affirming and
liberating, and yet, like in
this field, it's one of the
scarier things for most people.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I understand
that, and maybe I pushed it a
little harder than most. That
makes some people in the
therapeutic community may be
uncomfortable, but once you
understand that, once you
learned that the deep
purification, the deep
confrontation with the limits at
any level, leads to ecstatic
deliverance from those limits at
another level, then it's the
most natural thing in the world,
right?
Lauren Taus: Well, it's quite
natural for us to die, yeah. I
mean, nobody survives the game
of life and and I think that we
live in a culture that's just so
uncomfortable talking about and
engaging with content around
death,
Chris Bache: because we don't
understand what death is. You
know, we're just so kind of
chronically constricted to
within time, space, realities.
We don't understand what happens
to us when we don't when we die.
We don't understand the
liberation that death involves.
And it's not just psychedelics
that show us this. But of
course, near death episode
research shows us this hypnotic
regression past life therapy
work can show us this. Michael
Newton's work, for example,
shows us this, once you begin to
understand the larger circle,
once you understand that life is
a circle, that there is a birth,
a deep internalization of
circumstances and challenges
learning, and then there is a
death, which basically is a
phase of Homecoming, a phase of
returning to the light, then
what's to be afraid of dying?
Dying is graduation. Birth is
when the hard work begins.
That's when the you should be
afraid of.
Lauren Taus: So you're not
afraid of dying.
Chris Bache: No, not at all. In
fact, just the opposite. I look
forward to it, because I've been
through that death process so
many times, and I've been
privileged to be given
experiences of where I'm going
when I die that I'm looking
forward to it very much,
Lauren Taus: not rushing there
no
Chris Bache: my work is here as
long as I can be productive and
as long as I can contribute to
the larger project that we're a
part of, but it is nice to know
that it's particularly as you
get older. I'm 70 now, you know,
and you get older, it's nice to
know that the one thing that
life cannot do is stop you from
returning to paradise. So it's
like sliding down a sliding
board, leading you to plunge
into a swimming pool of pure
light. You know, it's just joy
waiting for us at the end of
this life.
Unknown: What's the point of all
this?
Chris Bache: That's a big
question, isn't it? Well, there
are lots of ways, I guess, we
can begin to answer that
question. But any early answers
that we give to that question
would need to be kind of, we
need to stack them up, because
it has so many layers to it. You
know, part of my work is in the
psychedelic work, and before the
psychedelic work involved
reincarnation. So I see
reincarnation as a natural fact
of life, so extending over
multiple, multiple generations,
hundreds, 1000s of lifetimes,
we're constantly learning. We're
constantly growing. We make
mistakes. We learn from
mistakes. We're going through
this developmental process. I
think. One of the things that's
happening in this process is not
simply the good that we do or
the growth that we undergo in
every individual life, but
cumulatively. It's not just like
we're going from first grade
second grade to graduate school,
layer by layer, but
cumulatively, I think all of our
farmer lives eventually, sooner
or later, they congeal into one
integrated consciousness, the
totality of our consciousness a
being of hundreds of 1000s of
years old. We know that we
return to that consciousness
when we die, because that's the
rhythm of reincarnation. We go
from soul when we die to
incarnate. We're ego, soul. Ego,
back and forth over and over
again. But eventually it comes
into, I think sooner or later,
the soul manifests in its
entirety on Earth. So I think in
part, the process is about
learning. It's about activating
the capacities which are
inherent in our nature. And our
nature at its core, classically,
is the nature of divinity. Atman
is Brahman, so the
consciousness, the capacities
that we are activating are the
same capacities that created the
physical universe, the
capacities, the capacity that
creates galaxies, we're learning
how to activate that and use
those and use those to create
heaven on earth eventually. Of
course, there are all these
intermediate stages. You could
say, well, we're learning love
and we're learning service, and
that's all true. We're learning
to surrender violence. We're
learning compassion, and those
are all intermediate aspects.
But at a deeper level, I think
you could say we're learning how
to be gods, and I mean that
modestly, but I mean that
literally. We're learning how to
create, how to literally
manifest the deepest capacity of
our being to create our reality
in the very demanding
circumstances of time and space.
And time and space is a very
demanding environment. It's much
more demanding than spiritual
reality, but it's very useful in
that respect,
Lauren Taus: I work as an
academy and assisted
psychotherapist, and I had a
session recently where a client
said, time is just an adjective.
It's not really a thing. And had
this whole journey around the
infinite. And what's it like?
Can you speak into the
experience of transcending time
and space?
Chris Bache: Well, there's a
tremendous sense of freedom.
Just your entire physical life
will kind of falls away. And
I've had experiences where all
the leftover desires or
unfulfilled ambitions from my
historical existence just fall
away in the face of the most
elementary conditions or
possibilities of being conscious
at these deeper levels, there's
a tremendous sense of
Homecoming, deeper and deeper
levels of Homecoming, kind of
there's a tremendous sense of
remembering. And you ask
yourself, How could I possibly
have forgotten this? How could I
have forgotten this for so many
billions of years. So there's a
tremendous sense of being where
you belong, being where you came
from, in some essential way,
this extraordinary sense of
peace, just, you know, a peace
that,
as the Bible says, The peace
that surpasses all
understanding. Something along
those lines, it's an
extraordinary peace. And at a
deeper level, when you dissolve
into the radiant light. In my
cosmology, I understand that all
physical existence ultimately
merges out of light, and the
light emerges out of the primal
void. But when you dissolve into
light, to actually be light, to
become light, or to dissolve
into that light, so that your
being has the quality of life,
it has the infinite extension,
the simultaneity, the clarity
and of light.
Unknown: Yeah, that sounds
pretty
Lauren Taus: No, you know,
Chris, right now my mind is is
very much holding on to the
world that we live in. I'm like,
very and I'm looking at a very
binary world, yeah, man, woman,
black, white, yeah, good, bad.
And you've spoken about your own
personal transformation,
shifting into a. Collective
transformation you've spoken
about experiencing profound pain
that wasn't yours, but was sort
of systemic and maybe ancient,
given the environment that we
find ourselves in. Now can you
and how do you relate to to this
sort of historic suffering and
this, these historic systems of
oppression within the context of
like the light and the oneness
and like outside time and space.
Unknown: Yeah.
Chris Bache: Well, again, you're
asking, it's a it's a very large
question.
Lauren Taus: It is, it is, and
may not be a fair question, but
as some of the
Chris Bache: repair, okay? It's
just large, that's all, yeah,
you know, reincarnation is not
simply a personal thing. It's
not a matter of simply a
personal soul, evolving, making
better choices, learning and
growing, becoming more it's also
a collective thing. Every 100
years, entire generation. I
mean, we're constantly the human
species is reincarnating. All of
our individual incarnations are
part of the single intelligence
of our species incarnating. So
there, the human species is
reincarnating and growing in
this dynamic way. And a lot of
it involves actualizing and then
transcending kind of lesser
forms of our capacity, lesser
our lower self are, you might
say our animal self, if you want
to put it that way, I wouldn't,
but and so I think you know
humanity, like individuals, are
growing deeper, better, sweeter,
stronger, more courageous.
Humanity is growing in that way
as well. But we find ourselves
at all sorts of we're at a pivot
point. I think we're coming to
and this was, well, let me back
up just a little bit. When I
began this work, I thought, Oh,
this is about personal healing,
personal enlightenment, personal
spiritual realization. But after
a couple of years, most of my
work was not focused on personal
work at all. It became very
much. I was drawn into some
collective project that I didn't
understand the beginning, and I
began to understand only slowly.
A lot of the the engagement, the
pain I was engaging, as you
mentioned, seemed to be
collective pain. I seemed my
sessions were being used by a
larger intelligence to clear
collective trauma, which I
understand is kind of the trauma
of history that's stored within
the collective unconscious. But
there always has been a strong
collective theme in my work, and
so starting in the 23rd session,
and continuing consistently,
intermittently all the way up
through the 70th session. A
reoccurring theme in her work
was the evolution and the
transformation of humanity. And
there was this recurring series
of teachings that I was given
that humanity is coming to a
turning point. Humanity is
coming to a major breakthrough.
Humanity is entering a great
awakening, a profound spiritual
transformation, a before and
after point in history that's
going to change everything,
which I eventually came to
understand as a change in the
fundamental architecture of the
collective psyche, so that when
the architecture, when the core
blueprint of the of the human
psyche, changes, then all
individual incarnations
subsequent to that point in
history will be actualizing
their individual life in the
context of this shifted
archetypal blueprint for the
human psyche. And just as
individuals, as they go into, as
they work towards mystical
union, go through a dark night
of the soul, a very intense
purification process where they
have to let go of everything
which is keeping them small in
order to open to that which is
large. Humanity seems to be
going through the same process
we're having to let go of
everything which is small in
order to open to this new to
give birth to this new human.
And what are the things which
have kept us small? Our hatreds,
our divisions, our self,
preferential treatment, by race,
by religion, by class, by
country, all the ways in which
we've divided history, all the
ways in which we partitioned the
planet, in these ultimately
socially constructed, but
ultimately unreal divisions. And
we're all of these. It's kind of
like the sins of our fathers and
mothers are coming up on us now.
It's like we're vomiting up the
racism. We're vomiting up the
gender abuse. We're vomiting up
all these sort of terrible
things that we've been doing to
each other in the past in order
to permanently remove them from
our system, in order to confront
our past. Right, but we're doing
this not simply to heal that
past. I think we're doing this
to lay the foundation, the
energetic Foundation, for a
different communion with the
divine, a deeper communion with
the universe, a more porous
communion, and one which will
reconnect us, not only with each
other, but will reconnect with
us with the universe, and allow
a more intimate rapport with the
universe to develop, and a
rapport, I think, which has
immediate consequences. I think
that since all the intelligence,
all the things we could ever
want to know, all the problems
that we could ever want to
solve, the answers already exist
inside the divine mind, inside
divine reality. And of course,
when I use the word divine, I
don't, I hesitate to use that
language because I don't mean it
in a theistic sense. I don't
mean it in the God in the
narrow, culturally defined kind
of sense. I mean it in a in a
post religious kind of broader
horizon. I mean it in the
horizon on the scale that
science has shown us of a
universe millions and billions
of years old, a creative
project, billions of years in
the making, a framework which
just dwarfs all the religions of
history. But this process is
basically taking us into a new
opportunity and an unprecedented
opportunity, and this so means
this is a hard time, the time of
birth, and I think that's what
we are entering. Is a time of
labor. Gestation is long, labor
is fast, and we have been
gestating the future human for
1000s and 1000s of years through
our evolutionary reincarnation
dynamic. But the time of giving
birth to this new human is now.
It's short, it's intense, it's
very hard. It's very painful,
but it's magnificent. The
project is coming into a time of
fruition, a hard time, because
it's hard to let go of our
habits of the past, but a
magnificent time, a time of
grace, and I think that's,
that's what's happening to us
now. I think we're in a very
tumultuous time, and we're being
pulled very, very fiercely by
forces which are trying to pull
us back to the past, back to the
old ways, back to the divisions
of history, back to patriarchy,
back to my religion is better
than your religion, and my race
is better than your race. And
then there are the forces you're
pulling us into a future, into a
future of more intimate
equality, more intimate
communion with each other, a
different relationship with the
Earth, a different transformed
relationship to the Earth
itself. And it's all on the line
right now because I don't think
we can this world was built by
ego. That means it was built by
a species at a certain level of
its psycho spiritual maturity,
where it had matured into self
consciousness, but it had not
pressed its maturity to the
point where it really grasped
the truth of our
interconnectivity, the truth of
our profound participation in
each other's lives and in the
life of the planet. We can't, we
can't solve the problems, I
think, which we're facing at the
level of ego. So we either grow
up or we go extinct. And what
growing up looks like, I think,
has to do with the maturation of
the soul, the the real sort of
transition from ego identity to
soul identity, because the soul
lives in the world differently
than the ego does. The soul has
an awareness of its history, and
therefore it has an aware an
awareness of its extended
relationships with all with
people that it sees around it.
And so since we have been black,
white, red, we've been all the
colors. We've been all the
religions of the world. We've
been rich, poor. We've been
through that when the soul
matures, there is this
tremendous sense of compassion
and generative freedom in that
process, and that's what I think
we need in order to solve where
we're going.
Lauren Taus: I gotta take that
in for a second. Well said,
Chris. And there's so many
different pieces along the way
that really echo in the chambers
of this soul. And when I look
outside, I feel like it's one
giant Ayahuasca vomit, and
there's like, all of it's coming
forth and it's coming out, and I
want it to, like, bring it,
bring it on, so that we can let
it go. Yeah. And I've also
likened this process to giving
birth, which, in my mind, if you
just look at a woman giving
birth and you. Have no idea
what's happening. You might
think she's dying and there's
blood and poop and pee and
screaming and crying and and
it's not pretty. Yeah, yeah, new
life, and it's beautiful.
Chris Bache: And I think that's
why I know you're a yoga
teacher, and so I think that's
why disciplines like meditation
and yoga and operating within a
therapeutic awareness is really
important, because there's a
tremendous amount of poison
coming through our systems. Is a
tremendous amount of
conditioning. And if we don't
have a system where we're every
day purifying ourselves this
energy, which is a collective
energy and it's part of our
personal story, but it's a
collective story, if we, if we
don't constantly do something to
let it go through us, it can get
stuck and get lodged in the
system. So never has it been
more important, I think, to have
regimens of purification, self
transformation as part of our
daily habit,
Lauren Taus: couldn't agree
more. And I've heard you also
say, Chris, that sort of the the
twin anchors for the work that
you did were courage and
grounding.
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah, courage
to face the difficult
experiences when they rise, and
grounding to bring back the
insights that one is given and
ground them into your daily
life. And what we're finding
with psychedelics is that it's
it's getting easier and easier
to have extraordinary
experiences with psychedelics,
and now we're beginning to pivot
to, in some ways, the harder
task, or at least the equally
hard task, of holding on to
those experiences, integrating
those experiences, literally
into our body, into our minds,
into our social relationships.
Yeah, do
Lauren Taus: you have any
particular strategies that
you've found to be effective in
terms of integration? As a
clinician that, again, is
working with psychedelic
medicine, I have my worksheets.
I invite my clients to journal,
to create art, to dance, to do
whatever feels relevant to the
individual and the the learning.
But, um, yeah, I think that
commonly, profound experiences
are not met with profound life
changes. And how do how do we
bridge that gap?
Chris Bache: Yeah. Well, the
things, all the things you
mentioned, I think, are really
good things, which are basically
using all our talent, whatever
our particular talents are, to
reach out, grab and hold on, to
talk about them, to write about
them, to create music about
them, to draw them, and most of
all, I think, to follow the
teachings which we're given.
Because in our psychedelic
sessions, we are given
teachings. We're given
instructions, and you have to
then put those into practice.
You have to practice them every
day, you know, so as you go
through and I think we have to
sort of self modulate, and this,
I wouldn't say I've been very
good at that, but we have to
sort of pace ourselves to know
when we are, when we should slow
down, when we should speed up,
when we've gotten enough that we
need to digest it longer rather
than taking on more. For me, of
course, being an intellectual,
in the sense it's my work is to
sort of be mentally oriented. I
spend a lot of time thinking
about and trying to understand
my experiences and understand
the implications of the
experiences. But someone like
Alex Gray, while I'm sure he's
intellectually absorbs his
experiences. Look what he does
with his experiences. I mean, he
creates these magnificent works
of art. You know, other people
are doing are plunged into
social activism to actually
bring about the social
transformation that has a chance
of saving this planet from us,
of taking us into this great
future. So different strategies
for different people, but it all
involve some type of way of
basically taking the time and
paying attention to make those
wonderful insights or those
wonderful experiences, not just
memories, but part of our living
tissue of our life.
Lauren Taus: And you've said, I
don't remember exactly the
language. But essentially, these
experiences give us a taste of
the infinite, and integrating
that into the finite body and
psyche of an individual is a bit
challenging. And you've said as
well that it took you 10 years
to to really kind of digest what
you experienced in the 20
Chris Bache: Yeah, when I came
back, when I stopped my work in
99 I thought that I would just
be able, since I had, by that
time, been given so many gifts,
I thought I could simply
withdraw and would be able to
nourish myself. Health by the
continued digesting and
assimilation of those gifts. But
what I found was that it was
more complicated. I found that
that was true, but that was only
half the truth. The other half
that I had to confront was the
tremendous sense of loss that I
had of not being able to enter
this deeply into into the
communion with the universe. So
there was a real sense of a loss
of communion, because I could
not sustain this deep communion
in my daily life. There are some
beings who can. There are some
great teachers. And the great
masters of the meditation
traditions have always been my
heroes, and they can hold these
experiences in an abiding way
that wasn't the case for me, and
so it did. It took me about 10
years to get over my sense of
loss and to get to basically
recommit myself to being as I
was, who I was, what I was,
where I was, for the remainder
of my life, and do as much as I
could with that time. Yeah,
yeah. And for me, the other
thing that made it hard to come
back was, of course, our
society's rules that we can't
talk about these things. I could
not I could not teach. I'm a
teacher. I love to teach. I
could not teach from this
knowledge. I could not share it.
And so writing LSD in the mind
of the universe has been a very
satisfying part of integrating
my work, of publicly, owning my
experiences, beginning to teach
on the basis of those
experiences, and not just my
experiences. Of course, if my
experiences weren't supported by
the psychedelic experiences all
the other people who are working
in the psychedelic community,
then they would amount to
nothing. But given the fact that
I'm simply part of a movement,
and there's a tremendous
coherence in this movement,
that's the significance that we
are entering into the systematic
integration of psychedelics into
our culture. That's the exciting
part. That's that's the teaching
moment.
Lauren Taus: Having community,
for me has always been one of
the most important integrative
tools. And people who know me in
my journey work. And I know you
said, you know, I was in I was
not in San Francisco, I was not
in LA or a place where this was
something that was fair ground
for conversation. And then, of
course, the risks in terms of
being a philosophy professor and
not feeling safe to talk about
what you were experiencing,
yeah, I'm glad that those
conditions
Chris Bache: have shifted. They
have shifted. I'm glad too,
because that cumulative what I
found was that it's kind of
schizogenic. It kind of makes
you I mean, I know I divided my
life into these two halves, but
I didn't realize the wear and
tear that that division was
going to cause. Because when
you're constantly checking
yourself, when you can say one
thing to one person, you can't
say something to somebody else,
you're living a divided reality.
And those divisions begin to
enter into your psyche, and they
produce cracks, which I had not
anticipated in the beginning,
and so coming out of the
psychedelic closet was, in some
ways, just as liberating as
coming out of any closet. And we
know what some of these closets
have been, and how same making
it is to come out of those
closets.
Lauren Taus: Yeah. What do your
children think about this work?
Chris Bache: Well, I think they
understand it to varying
degrees, some more than others.
They have an aptitude for it
more than others. I think some
have some intellectual
reservations. Some completely
understand and rejected and
accepted. Others are kind of
understand it, but kind of from
the sidelines, that not as a
participant, a
Lauren Taus: range, there's a
range, there's a range. One. I
think my proudest achievement,
and I've done a lot of
interesting things in my years.
It's converting my father to
psychedelic experience in his
70s. And my dad is my
prescribing MD In my clinical
practice. And, you know, I've
developed, as well, a
relationship with a lot of the
Maps team and and Rick, for
example, talks so much about the
importance of talking about
these experiences and coming out
of the psychedelic closet, and I
think doing so in Family
Constellations is also really
healing and important. Yeah, I
ask now i Chris you 500 to
600 micrograms, like I know you
said you don't recommend it.
Yeah? But what was like the
gift in that
Chris Bache: the gift is that
it's like taking a month
meditation retreat and cramming
it into five hours. The gift is,
again, I don't recommend it, but
having gone through it, I just
try to describe it objectively.
It is a very, it's a very
accelerated explosion of your
life. It's not It's very
different than low dose
psychedelic work, where you sort
of soften the boundaries of your
life and you have certain
amounts of cognitive functions,
and the shadow begins to
surface, and you begin to engage
it. And working with very high
doses, when you're amplifying
those doses with very intense
music and in isolation, so on so
forth, it just basically, it
just blows your psyche
completely apart, layer by
layer, until eventually you're
dissolving yourself into the
universe. So you basically, on
Saturday morning, you're in time
space, and then you just blow
yourself apart and you dissolve.
It's not like you're not there,
except by continuity of thought,
pro of consciousness, but you're
not functioning as Chris Bache,
having an experience, you
dissolve as Chris Bache, and
dissolve into some stratum of
existence and some, some field
of reality. And you you
literally have to work as I did,
at least. You dissolve and you
become that reality. You
dissolve into that reality. And
you have continuity. If you do
it well, you have continuity of
memory in and out. But you don't
have continuity of identity in
the sense that in when you are
dissolved into these fields of
consciousness, you can do things
that my Chris Bache could never
do, and you can experience
things and learn things that
Chris Bache could never learn
within his ordinary time, space
reality. You're just blown into
these realities. You get to live
there for a few hours, and then
slowly the second miracle
happens, which brings you back
into your integrated time space
identity. I seem to be have a
psychological makeup that makes
it easier. I seem to be able to
dissolve into those realities
without too many problems, and
to congeal without many
problems. And both of those
rhythms are important, the
letting go and dissolving into
and then the coming back and
becoming a single human being,
again,
Lauren Taus: so profound and
given that you don't recommend
that, what would you advise for
someone who is potentially
seeking to access some of these
experiences?
Chris Bache: Well, I would
recommend a more balanced
regimen, I would recommend low
dose session, high dose
sessions, balance with low dose
LSD sessions. I would recommend
balancing LSD with more body
grounded psychedelics like
Psilocybin or Ayahuasca, because
LSD tends to be I think of it as
kind of a high altitude
psychedelic. And it's very, very
different from Psilocybin, which
is a much more kind of body
emotional, you know, sense of
psychedelic. So I would
basically, I'd be more nuanced.
I would just be more balanced in
the rhythm. What if I had a
breakthrough session, I would
balance that in the subsequent
sessions with Psilocybin
sessions, which would help me
integrate and absorb the very
intense energies that I had
gotten dissolved into. Because I
just mentioned, one of the
things I learned was every step
into a deeper state of
consciousness is a step into a
higher level of energy. So
you're constantly having to
transform your entire psycho
physical system to enter into a
state of energy, and to do it in
a way that you can maintain
cognitive coherence at that
level. Because it's one thing to
just touch them briefly in a
confused way in a session, but
if you want to enter a state of
consciousness and learn how to
hold that level of awareness, so
that you can engage that with
continuity of memory and
continuity of consciousness, so
that the universe can meet you
there and engage you there, then
you have to acclimate to that
energy. You really have to go
through all this
transformational process to be
able to stabilize at that level.
And I found, for example, that
after every major breakthrough
to another level of
consciousness, the next session
was always very difficult, very
challenging, very turgid,
because it involved ahead to
sort of once. Broke into a new
level of purity, then I had to
go through a process of cleaning
out in my system all the levels,
all the different components of
my being that were lower than
that level so that I could
return to that level with clear
and sustained focus. So it's
it's an energetic thing as well
as a cognitive thing,
Lauren Taus: for sure. And
you're working on, like, you
know, from a psycho spiritual
level, it's you're utilizing
energy of the body, energy of
like, Transpersonal space,
collective space. What's the
story that you're telling with
your book?
Chris Bache: The story I'm
telling is basically just what
happened. It's basically saying
among all the psychedelics that
we have on the table today and
all of the experiences that
people are cultivating today,
this is one person's experience
with one psychedelic used in a
very specific manner. It's a
extreme in certain ways. And so,
you know it, I think I drilled
an unusually deep bore hole in
the universe. But I didn't
explore a lot of the levels that
I was moving through. I just
went very deep and very far. And
so the story is basically when I
was always sort of falling back
and thinking, Oh, my God, how
can I, how can I tell him this?
How can I I know it's a radical
story, and therefore I know
it's, it's, it's a challenging
story to absorb, and it was a
challenging story to write. But
in the end, I always fell back
on, just tell them the truth.
Tell them what happened. No
judgments. Let them do with it
what they will just as best as
you can tell them what happened.
And towards the end of my
sessions, the universe just
asked me. It said, Let them see
me as you've seen me. That's
all. They'll know what to do
with it. They'll know whether it
fits or doesn't fit them. Let
them see what you have seen, and
that's it. I'm not really trying
to do anything else. Did you
Lauren Taus: write much of it
during the course of these
experiences in terms of the app,
like the integration process, or
was it reflections, looking
Chris Bache: back? Reflection
looking back? I basically had
all my sessions were recorded
within 24 hours. So I had about
400 pages of session notes which
I had studied and blocked and,
you know, and I took them apart
and put them back together
again, and I diagrammed them in
different ways, but basically it
took years for me to finally
kind of piece together what is
the storyline, and also what to
leave out and what to include?
So I left out a lot of the
personal stuff. I left out the
personal healings. I left out a
lot of the personal small
things, because those were not
the important parts. You know,
everybody has a personal story,
but it's when, to me, as a
philosopher, it's when the
process takes you beyond the
personal psyche into the deep
waters of the psyche, that's
when the philosophically
interesting story begins. Now,
the therapist story is an
important story the healing of
the personal psyche. That's a
really important story and an
important work. That's just not
the story that I'm telling, I'm
telling the story of a love
affair with the universe and a
love affair with the
intelligence of the universe.
And that's why I call my name
for this intelligence that I
engaged as my beloved. It's just
my beloved, because it activates
such profound love in your being
to engage that, to dissolve into
that. That's your it's the most
intimate kind of true, becoming
one to a pre existing one. It's
a love affair. It's it. I wish
it were not a love affair, but
an abiding marriage, and maybe
one day it will be. But working
with these are temporary states.
They're not permanent states.
You have to come to terms with
that temporalness, but they're
temporary states. So it very
much is like an affair. You
enter, you make love in some
way, and then you come back and
you try to live it as best you
can, inside time and space
Lauren Taus: for so listeners
are not going to be able to see
my face, but my I'm My face
hurts from smiling, and my heart
feels like, like it's exploding.
I mean, I love this love, and I
think it's, I think it's a
really healing love. And as
somebody who does work with the
individual psyche, and you know,
in our initial conversations,
you're like, Well, I'm not
working on that, like part of
this conversation. And for me,
you're really contributing to
this part of the conversation,
and I'm incredibly grateful to
share your voice, your wisdom,
your experience with my
community. So deep, deep
gratitude. Tuned and reverence
for for you and your time and
your wisdom.
Chris Bache: Thank you. It's a
joy to share, and my hope is
that you know in some way, my
story or my experiences will
support you and all the other
people in their story and their
experiences. They'll know what
to do with it. They'll know what
to take from it. We all have
different journeys, but in the
end, we're all in this arm in
arm. We're all in this together,
you know. So everything you do,
everything I do, all it, reaches
out into the larger collective
network, every morning, every
day, every minute. So yeah, it's
a joy to be of use to people I
feel the same.
Lauren Taus: Thank you for
listening to this episode of
embodied life, the podcast. You
can learn more on my website,
www.embodiedlife.com and stay
connected with me on my
instagram at Lauren dot Taos, I
look forward to sharing lots
more with you, So stay tuned for
more inspiring in body
conversation.
Unknown: You ding.