Chris Bache: One the last great
vision that the universe gave me
in one of my sessions. It took
me deep into deep time. It took
me deep into the future, and it
gave me my last experience of
the future human. It was as if
it took me into the future and
allowed me to try on for size,
the fundamental blueprint of the
human psyche at that point in
the future, this was the most
extraordinary being. Just I
can't describe to you quickly,
what an extra ordinary being
This being is. Just picture the
highest, finest qualities we've
imagined. Picture the highest
spiritual capacities we can
imagine a mind completely open
to the universe, a heart
completely open to each other,
just extraordinarily magnificent
being. That's what's at stake
here. That's what we're trying
to become.