Simeon Mihaylov: Simon, welcome
to the secret to Seeker podcast.
My name is Simeon, and it's my
honor to introduce to you today
our first ever guest on the
podcast, Dr Christopher M Bache.
Chris is Professor Emeritus at
the Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he
taught for 33 years. His work
explores the philosophical
implications of Non-ordinary
states of consciousness,
particularly psychedelic states.
He has authored four books, his
latest one being LSD and the
mind of the universe, or as
Chris prefers to call it,
diamonds from heaven. In
diamonds from heaven, Chris
combines his expert knowledge of
the world's wisdom traditions
with the insights he personally
gained from 20 years of intense,
high dose, psychedelic work
undertaken in secrecy and the
cosmic plan that revealed itself
to Chris is both astonishing and
beautiful and carries great
implications about the way we
should understand our individual
and our collective existence.
Chris and I split our
conversation neatly into two
parts, so in the first half of
the podcast, you can get some
more details on the general
areas that Chris's work focuses
on, and the general chronology
of his work. But if you're
familiar with Chris's work, feel
free to skip ahead halfway where
we delve into issues that Chris
hasn't spoken about in length
before, such as the nature of
suffering and evil and also how
reincarnation and the non self
can both be true at The same
time. One final note, please
bear with me as I get this
podcast up and running. I know
that video quality and audio
quality on my end are pretty
bad, but I promise better
quality in the future, and
fortunately, Chris does most of
the talking here, so it
shouldn't be too much of a
issue. I hope the beautiful
conversation Chris and I had
brings you joy and wisdom, same
as it brought me, and I hope you
enjoy.
Thank you for watching good So
to begin, would you like to kind
of give a general overview of
your work that kind of you talk
about in the book, what the book
is about and what your
experiences really were.
Unknown: Yeah, well,
Chris Bache: it all began right
after I finished graduate school
in 1978 I had started. I started
my career as a professor of
religious studies at Youngstown
State University in Ohio, and I
read Stan Grof first book,
realms of the human unconscious,
and I knew immediately that this
was critically important work to
my discipline, which was
philosophy of religion. And Stan
outlined a methodology that
allowed us to enter
systematically and carefully and
unsafely into these deep states
of consciousness in which we
could not only heal but explore
the deepest levels of our mind,
and entering into those levels,
dropping into deeper levels of
consciousness that went beyond
individual mind. So that excited
me very much. As a young
philosopher, I thought this was
great. This is a whole new
philosophical method. So I began
to do this work, and to do it,
of course, since it was illegal
at the time, I had to make a
choice. And I don't like doing
things illegal, but I made a
choice to divide myself in half
and in my daytime job for the
next 33 years, I was a professor
of religious studies at
Youngstown State University,
teaching courses and doing the
things that people do. And then
my nighttime job, I began the
systematic journey into deep,
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness using LSD. And I
used LSD because that was the
substance that Stan had worked
with in his early years, that's
what his research was based on,
primarily, and I trusted what I
saw in his work, so I used that.
And after my sessions, my work
was always following the
protocols that he laid out in
his early book, LSD
psychotherapy. They were always
protected from the world. They
were always private. I worked
with a sitter. I was always
lying down with carefully
choreographed music, pacing the
stages of opening and closing in
the sessions. And I made a very
careful and. Sustained effort to
record each session faithfully
and completely after the session
was over. So I began this work.
I did it intensely for four
years, and then for reasons that
I describe in the book, I
stopped the work for six years,
and then I resumed it for
another 10 years of work I
started in 1979 and I finished
it in 1999 I did 73 high dose
sessions. Over this 20 year
period, I started with three
medium dose sessions and then
went into all the rest of my
sessions were high dose
sessions, which I worked at 500
to 600 micrograms, which is a
protocol that I don't recommend.
I don't recommend such a long,
sustained hammering of the
boundaries of consciousness
exploding so relentlessly into
these this work. I would work
much differently if I did it
again today, I would work more
slowly. I would alternate high
doses with low doses, and I
would work I would balance LSD
with more body grounded or
psychedelics such as Psilocybin
and Ayahuasca. But what happened
on the journey, basically, is
that I went through not just one
death, not just ego death, but
the universe took me in
gradually through multiple
layers of reality, deeper and
deeper, through deeper levels of
consciousness. And I found that
entering deeper levels of
consciousness, and therefore and
through them, accessing deeper
levels of reality required going
through a series of deaths,
dying at one level of
consciousness to enter a deeper
level of consciousness, and then
mastering or learning the ins
and outs of that level, and then
going through yet another death
to enter in a yet A still deeper
level of consciousness. So when
I got to the end of the journey
and was looking at all of the
years of work, I basically asked
myself, How many fundamental
levels of reality did I
experience, or how many cycles
of death and rebirth? And I came
up with five. There was a level
that took place at the level of
collective mind, excuse me,
personal mind, ego, death. Then
there was a level that took
place at the level of collective
mind, the collective mind of our
species. Then there was a level
that took place at archetypal
mind, and then the level of
causal reality, the level of
oneness. And then, in the five
last years of my work, the level
of diamond Luminosity, what I
call diamond Luminosity, what
Buddhism calls the absolute, the
absolute, the clear light of
absolute reality. So after I
finished my sessions, Spirit
said to me in my meditation, 20
years in, 20 years out. And I
took that at the time to mean
that it would take me 20 years
to fully assimilate and
integrate, 20 years of my
sessions, as it turned out, LSD
in the mind of the universe, or
as I prefer to call it, diamonds
from heaven, was published
exactly 20 years after I
finished my sessions. So there
was 20 years of exploration,
followed by 20 years of
digesting, reflecting,
integrating, and finally,
telling the story of this
journey, and I share it in the
hope that it will be useful to
other people, both people who
are journeyers, but also people
who are not journeyers, who are
involved in spiritual practices
other than psychedelics, because
of the I hope the cosmology that
emerges in the story and the
understanding of some of the
cosmological processes that
we're all engaged in will be
useful to people.
Simeon Mihaylov: Yes, yeah, your
work is definitely fascinating.
And one thing I think that is
very important to address
whenever somebody is talking
about psychedelic states and
insights that arise from them, I
think the go to argument of the
skeptic is these are states that
appear while the mind is under
the influence of a substance.
Therefore, why should any
insight gain be legitimate? But
even to take this argument
further, when you are exploring,
when you're having your
experiences under the influence
of these substances, how do you
know what you are studying? How
do you know what you're seeing?
Is this the call. Most Is this
your personal psyche? What is it
that you are experiencing?
Chris Bache: Yeah, really an
important question, isn't it?
Can we trust what emerges in our
awareness, in psychedelic states
of awareness? Well, I took my
starting point from Stan's
observations and many other
psychedelic therapists in the
early years, and that is an
understanding that psychedelics
don't give you an experience.
What they simply do is amplify
your own consciousness. They are
an amplifier and a catalyst of
your own mind. And if you use
these hours of amplified
awareness carefully, if you
focus them and internalize them
and keep your vision focused on
the stream of awareness that's
arising within you, you begin a
process of purification and a
process of confrontation with
different blocks and pains and
things we'd rather not look at
in our daily life, your system
just spontaneously moves to
eliminate those challenges which
are lodged in our history.
Sometimes our history from just
this lifetime, sometimes our
history from former lifetimes.
In the early stages, we know
that we can judge the legitimacy
of what's what we are
experiencing, because these are
activating memories from our
lifetime. We can verify those
memories. We can explore them.
They have the texture of memory.
And when we confront the pains
that arise there, there is a
liberating experience, there's a
healing experience which has
demonstrable impacts on our
daily life after a session has
ended. So there's a tremendous
sense of verification of the
truth of what one is
encountering. And that tends to
give confidence that when one
moves beyond the familiar, when
one moves beyond the domain of
one's immediate life, that there
is a truth also in these
experiences, even though they're
coming from a more foreign level
of consciousness, this process
repeats itself so one enters
into a reality which is
completely foreign, unknown,
strange. And at first, maybe
what stands out is its
strangeness, but the more
frequently you go back into that
reality, the more you become
familiar with its landscape. And
my experience is that if you
engage these hours carefully,
and if you record them and work
hard to retain them, listen to
what it's teaching you, the
universe enters into a dialog
with you. It's like now it knows
you're paying attention, and so
it's speaking to you, and it
takes you through an educational
process, it takes you through a
series of lessons about how
reality works. Here, what's
going on at this level of
reality and in the early stages,
there are certain qualities that
relate to your personal life.
Maybe you experience your
personal life in a larger in a
larger spiritual trajectory. You
may have insights into former
lives. You may have insights
into your deeper former life
history that clarifies and heals
relationships in your present
life, and because these have
such a dramatic impact on our
present life. Once again, their
legitimacy is confirmed in your
own life experience and as one
goes deeper into collective
mind, into archetypal reality,
into deeper into spiritual
reality. In this case, I had I
was fortunate in that I had a
PhD in philosophy of religion. I
had a lot of opportunity to
study some of the great
spiritual traditions of the
world. So I was familiar with
some of the ins and outs of
spiritual practice as those had
been developed in different
countries. I had an
understanding of their maps of
what lies in the spiritual
world. And so I had a reference
point to compare my experiences
in psychedelic states with the
experiences that other spiritual
seekers were having in their
traditions, using meditation
methods, yogic methods, or
psychedelic methods, to explore
reality from across the world.
Now, I've always taken a global
perspective when I teach. I
taught intro to world religions
for years, I taught courses on
comparative mysticism. I've
always found that the deepest
patterns emerge or the first.
Me, the most interesting
patterns are the patterns that
emerge not simply in one
culture, in one spiritual
tradition, but in multiple
traditions looked at
simultaneously. And when you can
hold the world spiritual
traditions in your consciousness
all at the same time, then you
begin to see patterns that
connect the different lineages
into larger holes, and I found
that my psychedelic experiences
fit comfortably within that
larger landscape, and I have to
qualify because it fit
comfortably. And yet, as I went
deeper, it also pushed the
boundaries of those experiences
and took me deeper. But I guess
in addition to this sort of
personal verification and then
collective, global spiritual
correspondence, which is a kind
of verification, there is an
experiential quality to these
experiences, you pay a great
price to enter into these
states. You must go through
multiple, multiple cycles of
purification, detoxification,
confrontation with your own
limitations, layer after layer,
in order to enter into clear
states of perception, clear
states of awareness. These
states of awareness have a
quality where it's just
transparently clear that you are
experiencing something real,
something genuine. It doesn't
mean necessarily that you're
seeing all that exist or
everything is there or that, not
that there can't be limitations
or distortions in your
experience, but you know you are
confronting something which is
just as real as what you
confront in time, Space,
reality. So in this dialog, in
this dance, Mike, conviction
grew that I was on a journey, a
journey that had philosophical
value, a journey that was
producing genuine insights into
how our universe works. The
structure of the universe
doesn't mean that everything I
saw is necessarily perfectly
correct, but there is a
fundamental conviction that
these are real, that these are
valuable, and they're shared by
other persons. If it were only
my experiences, then maybe they
would just be a solipsistic
fantasy. But by comparing your
experiences to the experiences
of other psychedelic explorers,
and in this respect, Stan Grof,
compendium of so many hundreds
and 1000s of psychedelic
journeyers and their experiences
gave me confidence that what I
was experiencing was not simply
a personal illusion or personal
fantasy, But was flowing in
accord with what other
psychedelic journeyers had
experienced, and then by
comparing them to the
cosmologies of meditation
traditions, it gave me
confidence that psychedelics
were not psychedelics were just
a key that were giving us Access
to states of awareness, which
are universal, and you can get
access to these states using
other methods as well.
Simeon Mihaylov: I see so and
you began your work with the
motivation to explore the
universe. As a philosopher, is
that
Chris Bache: correct? Yeah, that
was my intention. I'm not a
therapist. I wasn't I mean, I've
received much healing in this
work, and always grateful for
it. But that was not my primary
intention. I was trained as a
philosopher of religion. I
wanted to explore the universe
as deeply as I could and
understand not only my nature,
but understand the larger
landscape of the universe,
Simeon Mihaylov: and you're
saying that despite the fact so
the fact that your experiences
fit in kind of the larger body
of religious and philosophical
traditions we have as a species
gave you confidence that what
you're experiencing is genuine.
But at the same time, you also
push the boundary in terms of
seeing things that you had not
encountered before and
elsewhere. So keeping this in
mind, do you believe that
psychedelics offer the promise
of new insights that we can gain
philosophically and spiritually
that we have not uncovered
before. How do you see
psychedelics fitting into the
future developments of
philosophy and spirituality of
our
Chris Bache: species? Yeah,
well, this is an exciting time
and exciting territory. I became
convinced early on that psyche.
Psychedelics represented a true
before and after development in
philosophical reflection,
because in philosophical
reflection, in one way or
another, we are always
reflecting upon the breadth of
human experience, not only our
own experience, but other
people's experiences, and we
here have an opportunity to
temporarily deepen our
consciousness, deepen our
awareness, and push the
boundaries of awareness. And I
think this opens up not only
individual selective insights
into the nature of
consciousness, but it also opens
up the possibility of an entire
new method of exploration, which
was first articulated, I think,
by William James. Well, in
modern times, there are ancient
prototypes of this work in the
elysinian mystery schools and
the Ayahuasca churches of
Brazil, but in Western
philosophy, probably first
articulated by William James,
and that is a systematic rhythm
of expanding consciousness,
experiencing what you can
experience, coming back,
recording it, evaluating it,
comparing it to other bodies of
knowledge, comparing it to other
people's experiences, and then
expanding again, going out
again, coming back, same
process, writing it down, this
rhythm of expansion and then
evaluation. Expansion and
evaluation, I think, opens up
the possibility. It allows us to
explore dimensions of
consciousness that are for the
most part, for most people,
unless they have are lifelong
spiritual practitioners of some
of the meditative arts. For most
people, these dimensions of
consciousness are invisible.
They just lie outside the
purview of their awareness. But
by systematically entering into
these temporary states, we can
explore them, we can taste them,
we can sample them, and we can
gather insights about how the
universe is working, because we
find that all the awareness, all
the intelligence, all the
compassion, which is inside us
is not something which has been
assembled by Mechanical chances,
by mechanical processes which
are driven by random variation
as of the modern mind thinks,
but we find that our mind opens
into an infinite mind, something
which is ultimately an infinite
mind. It opens up into the
species mind, the collective
unconscious of our species, into
deeper and deeper levels beyond
the species and ultimately into
the mind, which is the
generative mind of the universe
itself, at least that's my
experience. Now philosophically,
we've been talking about that
mind for years, even in denying
its existence if you choose the
atheistic alternative, but we've
been wanting to know about we've
been asking questions about our
larger place in the cosmos,
whether there is meaning in our
lives, whether there is
intention in the evolutionary
project, what the hell is going
on? Why does life hurt so much?
Why is there so much suffering?
These are core philosophical
questions that in the modern
mind, many philosophers have
just abandoned and just said
they're unanswerable. We can't
know, so we're going to change
the topic of discussion. But
still, as long as we live, we
want to know the answer to these
questions. Psychedelics, I
think, give us an opportunity to
systematically and rigorously
engage these questions, and
that's a turning point, because
ideally, for example, I think we
would want to take 100 people,
say the best educated people,
most creative people with PhDs
in multiple disciplines, and
then go through the same
systematic regimen of disclosure
encounter, and then compare the
notes of all these people and
see what is the collective
patterns that they're what is
the common ground that they see
and recognize this tokens? I
think this is what's beginning
to happen. This is what we're
doing. This is what we will be
doing for hundreds of years. And
this is a turning point
philosophy. This really marks a
difference between old
philosophy, which was done on
the basis of just sensory
consciousness, and a new
philosophy, which is done on the
basis of this new technology,
this new technology of
encounter,
Simeon Mihaylov: that's that's
really momentous changes that
seem to be coming within
psychedelic Renaissance, which
seems to be happening at the
moment. But for for our viewers,
that in your book. Have a really
nice section where you describe
a day in the life of you doing
your psychedelic session. For
those of our listeners and
viewers that are not aware of
it, would you go through it and
tell us what your protocols
really were and how a typical
session they would go,
Chris Bache: Well, there's a
chapter in the book basically a
session day, because some of the
readers, early readers of the
manuscript, asked me to do just
this, to kind of take him into a
typical day. So here's a typical
day. All my sessions took place
in my house or in my wife's
therapeutic office. They always
began in the early morning. I
was always I would begin with
meditation or yoga or some type
of centering practice to get
myself centered. And the more I
worked with these states, the
more important I paid to more
parts I understood was the
preparation, not only the
preparation of set and setting,
which is well appreciated today,
but a lot of attention to my
emotional state and my physical
state, a lot of practices
purifying my body, making sure
that my literally, my physical
bone structure was aligned.
Because when you enter into
these states, if you are not
really balanced, open, porous,
in good condition, you can get
into all into various
complications and energy gets
jammed up in your body. But the
dates, they would start early
morning, I would go through my
practice, and then my sitter for
all the 20 years of my work was
my first wife, Carol, who was a
clinical psychologist. And
basically, after these early
preparations, I would take the
psychedelic and then I would
turn over responsibility to my
condition, to her to my
protection. She would take care
of me. She would make sure I was
safe. She would make sure that I
would stay focused inwardly,
that I would not allow myself to
get distracted or act out in any
dangerous way. I for the most
part, because I was working with
very high doses of LSD. There
was no verbal interaction. I was
listening to music. She was the
curator of music, responsible
for intuiting when to shift from
one stage to another. There are
certain stages in a psychedelic
session, I would basically do
the work as long as it lasted,
which is usually six to eight
hours. She was with me the whole
time, making sure I was safe
until I was back, and
consolidating. And then I would
spend that evening reflecting on
the sessions, thinking about it,
trying to put together the first
map of what had happened in the
sessions. And often, I didn't
sleep much the day after a
session, but the next day, it
was always a priority to make a
written account of the session.
And when you're entering really
foreign territory, making an
accurate written record can be
challenging. Now, some people
who have artistic abilities can
draw them or paint them. Alex
Gray's work, such wonderful
work. Other psychedelic artists,
I don't have those skills. So
for me, it was making a written
record, and in order to learn
how to capture experiences that
are so elusive and so far beyond
our ordinary way of knowing, I
developed a technique. I called
it, standing at the edge of the
well, the day after a session,
you're still porous around the
edges, but your verbal and
cognitive functions have
returned. So what I would do is
I would play the music that was
used in the session in exactly
the same order that it had been
played in the session, and I
would get back into the mood or
the psychological space of the
that I was in when this music
was being played. And from that
condition, one foot in the
session, one foot out, I would
write up that portion of the
experience. And when I was done
with that, I'd shift to the next
piece of music and play it over
and over until I had captured as
best as I could what had been
happening during that music, and
when I was done, I had my draft
of the session. Once I had that
draft, I locked it, I didn't
change it. I learned that by
trying, sometimes trying to
improve the text or make it a
little more positive. Published
that you lose something that is
contained in the original, raw
language. So once I had that
text, I locked it, yeah, and
then I would spend weeks,
months, sometimes basically
studying the sessions, trying to
understand it, put it in the
context of previous sessions. On
average, I was doing about five
sessions a year. That's kind of
statistically, that's what it
worked out. So I had plenty of
time in between my sessions to
digest and assimilate them. And
I was also doing spiritual
practice during this time, I was
always meditating. So the day
after a session always began
with meditation, which is a
nice, spacious place to be able
to open up and just let the
energy that had been running in
you during a session flow in you
in your meditative space. So
that's basically what a session
looked like I would not eat
anything before breakfast.
Always an empty stomach, because
I would throw up often. Because,
you know, people don't think you
throw up on LSD, but you do. You
know this is it's one of the
symptoms of shifting states of
energy. Your body has some
challenge adjusting to these
more intense states. And I would
eat something light at the very
end of the day.
Simeon Mihaylov: There's so many
things I'm curious about your
particular approach. But one
thing in particular for me is
music. I want to ask you about
the way you use music, because
music and psychedelics have
always had a very special
relationship, I think, and there
have been different approaches.
So, for example, Terence McKenna
is famous for saying five dry
grounds in silent darkness. That
was his recommendation. And he
he once famously joked that if
you come out of a psychedelic
session saying Bach was a
genius. Well, you know,
everybody knows that. So his
approach, rather, was to kind of
let the experience take you
where it takes you. But you
were, as I read in your book,
were very particular in the your
choice of music, and it changed
as you progressed in your in
your work. There was also one
very funny moment in which your
city put on the wrong piece of
music, but this actually helped
you get out of a very kind of
difficult situation. So yes,
what's your approach with music?
Chris Bache: Well, music does
influence our experience, and I
do value working without music.
I mean, I've continued to work
with psychedelics after stopping
my high dose LSD work, but and
during this post, LSD work, I
often will just enter into
meditative space with Psilocybin
or Ayahuasca. And in the
psychedelic work itself, in the
late years, in the late
sessions, I would often end the
music in the second half of the
session and just move into
meditative space. But basically,
I followed the protocol that was
kind of laid out in the early
psychedelic research and the
understanding here is not that
music gives you experiences, but
that music can support the
underlying immersion of your
unconscious into your awareness,
so it just kind of provides a
background that makes it easier
for you to detach from the
habits of your mind and to go
with the flow, as it were, into
what eMERGE is emerging. So I
think of it as supporting and
reinforcing what happens when
you do go simply into the dark
without any music at all. And we
know that there are stages of
the LSD experience. There's a it
takes so many minutes for it to
begin to become active. It
builds in potency again. You
have to look carefully at the
psychedelic you're using the the
curve of activation on it, the
depth of activation. It's
different if you're working with
low doses of LSD than if you're
working with high doses of LSD,
working as I did with high dose
levels, it was a tremendous
acceleration of consciousness, a
tremendous speed with which your
body and your mind is adjusting
to the extraordinary increase of
energy and awareness as you
begin to break through the
bounds of personal
consciousness. And so they're
Helen Bonnie's early work on the
stages of psychedelic of a
psychedelic session and the type
of music that supports that
session. So I follow. Of those
early guidelines, which have
been further expanded in the
Holotropic Breathwork network,
which has a good, large library
of musical recommendations, I
found I came across early on in
about by about the fifth or
sixth or seven session, I came
upon some indigenous chanting,
types of indigenous chanting,
and I found that that music had
a much more powerful impact on
my on my experiences, than
listening to classical music,
even new pieces of Classical
music. And I did listen to lots,
but they still kept within
conventional they kind of kept
within a more conventional
framework. And I found that
indigenous music, that was
foreign, that was unknown, that
I didn't understand the words of
and they had a more of a
cathartic opening effect in my
consciousness. So I found it
very useful. And like I began to
collect all manner of indigenous
music and different cultures
from around the world, and I
incorporated them into my
sessions. And then when you are
at peak, when you've gone
through you've announced you've
gone through the purification or
the death process, and you've
transitioned into deeper,
ecstatic reality, into visionary
states. You want music which is
more expansive, which is kind of
gives your mind room to work, so
to speak, just very, very
expansive. And then as you begin
the long, slow descent. LSD has
a long tail, so that's a long,
slow process, which is really
one of the nice advantages of
LSD. It gives you time inside
the session to integrate,
reflect upon, to compose
yourself with respect to the
experiences that you've just
had. So you want long, gentle,
gentle, expansive music in all
of the work until the very end.
You don't want any words in
English or any words in your
native language, words which you
can understand, because you
don't want them to script your
experience best to Well, I found
that I would only really could
use music three times before I
had to let it go for the most
part, because by the time you've
used music several times, it
tends to get saturated with the
experiences that you had with
that music. So when you listen
to the music, it tends to take
you back into where you were
before, not where you are now.
So I would really limit myself
to using music only a few times,
and then I had to find new music
when you're in the downward
slope, when you're coming back
into your more familiar life.
Then that applies less. I am
more comfortable using more
familiar music in the spacious
return.
Simeon Mihaylov: I see also,
well, another thing about your
sessions, also, I think which a
person who is not familiar with
your work and who is not
familiar with the psychedelic
work at all would think, okay,
here is this person. He's having
this visionary experiences. It's
so very nice and very
interesting, and he's writing
about them. So it must be very
exciting, very pleasant work.
But I think anybody a little bit
familiar with the psychedelic
experience would know that these
are especially high dose
experiences are very difficult
experiences to go through. So
some especially, I know that
your initial sessions, you write
about them, they were very
expansive, very exciting, but as
time went on, they became more
and more difficult, and
difficult times started
appearing more often and they
were harder to go through. So at
some point, I'm sure it was
difficult for you to to kind of
go through it again, knowing
what's probably waiting for you
that it's going to be a day of
really difficult experiences. So
so in the light of this, how did
you work with daily spiritual
practice to help you prepare for
this, and also, not only for
this, but also to kind of
incorporate your insights into
your daily life. Because, as
you've said previously, these
psychedelic experiences, we
cannot hold on to them, so we
need to find ways to integrate
them.
Unknown: Yeah, yeah. Well,
Chris Bache: let me try to hold
on to two parts to your
question. First of all, the
method of working with high dose
LSD, and then issues of the
challenges that come up. Of the
three things. The challenges
that come up in high dose work,
and third, integrating those
experiences into daily life. So
if I get lost in my answer, you
bring me back to those three
Stan's, early work
differentiated very clearly
between low dose psyche therapy
and high dose psychedelic
therapy, low dose psyche lytic
therapy is kind of much more
similar to what is being done
today. The goal here is to
amplify consciousness, but not
but do it in a way where the
unconscious unfolds itself
gradually, layer by layer,
taking us systematically, kind
of more less traumatically, into
the inner confrontation that
heals their psychedelic work was
very different. And what stands
out in my mind is their work at
the Spring Grove Hospital in
Maryland, where they were
basically working with a
different population. They were
working with terminally ill
cancer patients. So they were
working with people who were
going to die. And they were
trying to trigger an encounter
with cosmic reality. They were
trying to trigger, essentially,
an n de, a Near-Death Experience
that would give them a foretaste
of where they were going when
they died. And they this
protocol limited high dose
sessions to three sessions, no
more than three sessions. So
this is very different protocol.
It wasn't really trying to heal
all the layers of personal
issues. It was trying to blow
through the personal unconscious
and go into cosmic reality, just
to get a taste, to get a sample.
So I thought, well, if you could
do that three times, you can do
it more than three times, and
just, let's go for it. Let's
just go for it and see how
deeply we can go. And in doing
that, I found it took me about
two years of work, about 10
sessions, to basically go
through what Stan calls the
perinatal level of
consciousness, where I lived my
birth and relived various very
strong, physical, emotional
confrontations, existential
crises, questioning the meaning
of existence, the
meaningfulness, the futility of
life, all the things one goes
through in those initial and
early experiences. And then I
went through kind of a classic
ego death experience, where my
my individual identity was
shattered. It was turned inside
out. I was forced to become the
exact opposite of everything I
knew myself to be. And in that
process, Chris bacheous, life,
crispicious historical
existence, ceased to be the
container of my consciousness, I
just moved into a more expansive
awareness beyond the historicity
of crispicious life. As I went
deeper, I began to experience a
very, very different order of
challenges that were not
personal. I began to be
systematically taken into vast
territories of pain and
suffering, violence and wars and
just brutal, just like Dante's
Inferno, except many times
worse, and this was much harder
than experiencing my the doubts
of metaphysical anxiety or the,
you know, my personal ego death.
This was something different.
But here's the thing, I would
spend hours in this condition,
and it was difficult, and going
back into it to the next
session, I had to really steel
myself to prepare myself to
enter into this domain, once I
knew that it was coming. But I
would spend a couple of hours or
a few hours in this process, and
then it would reach a crescendo,
and it would spin me out into
the visionary state. It would
spin me out into the ecstatic
visionary state. And when that
happens, the pain of the very
intense pain of the ocean of
suffering was balanced and
proportioned to the great
ecstatic joy that followed in
the ecstatic portion of those
sessions. So when you understand
this cycle, when you understand
the pattern that there will be
this very intense period of pain
in some form or another, but
this is going to be followed by
an even deeper immersion into
ecstatic visionary experience
Unknown: you have. Uh,
Chris Bache: it's not just that
the sessions become pain filled.
There is a new layer of pain,
but there's also a new layer of
insight and ecstasy and joy, and
that's what gives you the
strength to return and keep
coming back to these states, and
that tremendous sense of
ecstatic, visionary encounter,
cosmological inquiry. And so as
I went as the the ocean of
suffering lasted two more years,
and I went through that level,
and then I went through yet
another Death-Rebirth process,
and then came into another
deeper level of consciousness,
archetypal reality, and moving
deep into the collective psyche
and archetypal psyche, and then
going through yet another death
and rebirth, went into the
ecstasy of oneness, the ecstasy
of causal reality for an entire
year, just experience after
experience of different levels
of of oneness, parameters of
oneness. So the challenge does
increase, but the payoff also
increases as you go deeper. So
it's I've always considered that
trade off a good exchange. I've
always been a volunteer in this
process. Nothing was done to me.
I always was willing to go
there, and the rewards that I
was given for the engagement
always made it worthwhile. I
wouldn't trade these 73 days for
anything, any of the treasures
of the world
Simeon Mihaylov: that's
beautiful about the psychedelic
work. One thing that I've
noticed is that they psychedelic
work parallels, in a certain
way, just what people would call
normal spiritual daily practice.
So let's say, if somebody reads
your book but entirely forgets
the fact that you were entering
into psychedelic states, they
could read it as a report of a
person going through intense
daily meditation practice. Let's
say, because I think these
cycles of purification and then
expansive insight and bliss
appear in normal states of
consciousness, so in a merge in
a much kind of smaller scale.
But I think there's essentially
a mirroring, almost fractal like
parallels between psychedelic
state and real life. And kind of
why I'm really interested into
how you've used daily spiritual
practice is because I
essentially think that there
shouldn't they should be.
Discontinuity between daily
practice and psychedelics is
very important, I think, because
Ram Dass used to say that, you
know, going on an LSD trip is
like being with Buddha or Jesus
in a room for two hours, but
then you have to leave, and then
the artist kind of staying in
that room for as long as you can
without any assessment. So what
are your views on that?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, I
completely agree with you that
there's nothing unique about
psychedelic experiences because
they are amplifiers of
consciousness. So it's
consciousness that does the
work. In the end, it's not
psychedelics that do any unique
work. It's consciousness. I've
had many readers write me and
say, you know, I've never taken
a psychedelic in my life, but I
completely relate to what you're
describing. It mirrors my own
experience in terms of these
breakthroughs and levels for
this particular part of the
experience. So I know we know
that there is a profound overlap
and continuity between our work
in ordinary, spiritual, let's
say non psychedelic spiritual
practice, and psychedelic
spiritual practice. And it's
more than just that. I mean,
basically, in order to
understand what happens in
psychedelic sessions, we have to
have an understanding of what's
happening in life, what how life
works. Now for me, reincarnation
is just a fact of existence. You
know, that's my first book was
on reincarnation, and I consider
the empirical evidence
supporting a reincarnational
worldview is just overwhelming
at this point. It doesn't mean
that we understand how it all
works, all the details of it,
but that there is a continuity
arcing through multiple
lifetimes in a larger
developmental evolutionary
process is really important to
understand. So in order to
understand this rhythm of where
we are, we die. Die, and we our
consciousness gets large into
the soul territory. We
incarnate, and we get small and
focused, and we die, and we get
large and we incarnate, we get
small and focus, and we keep
going back back and forth. And
it's like every time we
incarnate, we choose a certain
set of issues. We choose a
certain set of challenges that
we face and confront, and as we
face and confront those things,
our life develops it. You know,
sometimes we don't do so well.
We flunk the course. Other times
we do very well. We're past and
moved on. And this rhythm shows
itself inside every life and
across multiple lives, when we
are when we go through, if we
look at long strings of our of
lives as in past life therapy or
that type of work. And in this
sense, I think what LSD, what
any spiritual practice does, and
psychedelic spiritual practice
does is that it accelerates this
process where reincarnation
moves very slowly and grinds
very finely. But if you want to
speed up the process, you can
turn awareness back onto itself
and look at where awareness is
coming from, examine, engage
their challenges that you are
facing in the outer world in
their core nuclear form, when
they exist as thought forms
within your consciousness. If
you don't do that, they will
eventually, these thought forms
will manifest as your outer
physical reality. But if and
you'll learn from them. But if
you speed up that want to speed
up the process. You can look at
them in their nuclear form and
engage them before they manifest
in the physical world. This
happens in spiritual practice,
in meditative practice, and it
also happens in psychedelic
practice. So I completely agree
with you. The more I've worked
with psychedelics, the more I'm
convinced that if you want to
open yourself up to these
temporary states of
consciousness, it's very
important to be practicing. Have
a daily spiritual practice. In
fact, the deeper the state of
consciousness you enter
temporarily, the stronger should
be your daily practice, because
when you open to these vast
fields of energy, these vast
territories of consciousness. It
places tremendous challenges. It
makes it tremendous strains, in
a way, not only on your mind,
but on your body, on your subtle
energy system, and it's really
important, I think, to bring
those experiences into a daily
spiritual practice, so that your
the conditions you move into in
your spiritual practice, in Your
daily practice, give you the
greater capacity to absorb and
integrate and to navigate not
only the insights but the the
experiences that emerge in your
psychedelic states. In my
psychedelic states, I was given
many practices. I was given not
just teachings and experiences,
but I was basically told, Do
this, do that. You know, I was
given practices, and I would
take those practices into my
daily spiritual practice in the
last five years of my work. And
this, I discuss this in the
diamond Luminosity chapter I
entered into Vajrayana Buddhism.
I had always been a meditator,
but I began a more formal
relationship with Vajrayana
teachers, and I began to
practice within this Buddhist,
Tibetan Buddhist tradition. And
I found this was very helpful
for where I was working at the
time, because I was working at
that time in very, very pure and
very intense states of
awareness, diamond Luminosity,
and I was finding that it was
getting increasingly difficult
for this, for my subtle energy
system, to sustain The encounter
with the enormous flows of pure
energy in this diamond
consciousness. And when I began
to do these ancient practices,
when I began to do Chud in the
various deity practices of
Vajrayana, I found that my
physical and psychological and
subtle energy systems were able
to breathe more freely. It was
like my Vajrayana practice gave
me a space to enter that was
midway between my physical
consciousness and my psychedelic
consciousness, and by entering
those states, I was able to
breathe and flow the. Energy
that came into my psychedelic
sessions, I could, I could
channel that energy. I could it
just kind of moved more freely.
It gave me a way of dialoguing
with the universe that allowed
my body and my mind to sort of
breathe more comfortably. This
was very helpful at the time. So
I completely agree with you. I
mean, the most important thing I
think, to remember about
psychedelics, in terms of
spiritual practice, is you can't
take a psychedelic when you die.
When you die, you go into the
universe. You're all on your
own. The mind you take is the
mind you got so knowing that
everything you do in your
psychedelic work should be
preparing yourself for that
final encounter when you let go
of the body and you enter into
that world, you can't take
psychedelics when you're dead.
Now, I think psychedelics can
give us can teach us a lot about
where we're going, it can
prepare the soul for where it's
going. So that territory, which
may strike us as kind of strange
and intimidating for an ordinary
person when they die, we can
encounter it as you know, just a
familiar route that we've
traveled multiple times before
in our psychedelic sessions. So
I don't I understand the tension
for some teachers of classical
meditation and their criticism
of psychedelics as kind of a
false spirituality or
distracting experiences. I
understand that, but for me,
I've never found it to be an
incompatible approach to
spiritual a deepening spiritual
experience. It's not the same.
It does open up different types
of experiences. But if you
understand spiritual practice,
if you understand how
spirituality, what spirituality
is, I think that spiritual that
psychedelic work, can reinforce
and accelerate our daily
spiritual practice in ways that
are really very beneficial.
Simeon Mihaylov: Yes, I agree
with that. And also myself, I'm
very interested in how one can
achieve synergies between
between the two. Now, in this
last answer that you gave, you
already touched upon some of the
kind of deeper territories of
your work. So I'm wondering
whether you'd like to move into
this and discuss the cosmic
blueprint that was revealed to
you during your work. One, one
of the one of the things that
you talk about is reincarnation,
and I find this very interesting
reading you, reading your book
gave me kind of almost a
permission to be interested,
intellectually interested in
reincarnation and not be shy
about it. And you, your work has
really made me consider
reincarnation in a serious way
for the first time and kind of
discuss it with other people. So
you mentioned a number of books,
a number of authors, in fact,
the kind of a large literature
that exists that has documented
cases that are suggestive of
reincarnation. So I was curious
what has convinced you of
reincarnation in your reading
and in your personal experience.
Unknown: Yeah.
Chris Bache: Well, when I began
my teaching at Youngstown State,
I told you that Stan Grof was a
major turning point in my life,
but there was another author who
was also a major turning point.
And this is Dr Ian Stevenson at
the University of Virginia, and
he's passed on now, but the work
continues at Virginia, and he
had spent a lifetime he and his
team studying children from
around the world, different
cultures, different religious
backgrounds, or non religious
backgrounds, children who, as
soon as they begin to be able to
talk, when they're two years
old, they begin to speak very
matter of factly about their
other life that they remember
having lived. They describe
people and places and events.
They often have a very powerful
emotional attachment to that
previous life, they will run
away from home, sometimes just
to return to the family that
they knew in their previous
life. So Stevenson has studied
1000s of cases like this, and
he's published hundreds of
cases. Most of the cases he
studied do not meet the highest
levels of rigor we. Required for
verification and publication.
But an amazing number of courses
do allow themselves to be
verified. So when I read his
book 20 cases suggestive of
reincarnation, it just it
absolutely showed me something
that I had never encountered in
graduate school, never in many
my studies that reincarnation is
a simple fact of life, these
children who know things that
they shouldn't know, that we can
reasonably exclude other
possibilities that they could
have come through this knowledge
through normal or physical
channels, their parents talking,
or their neighbors talking, or
something they saw on television
or in a newspaper that we can
reasonably eliminate those
possibilities, and we have to
confront the fact that these
children know things that other
people that about other people's
lives and have an emotional
attachment and identification
with what with that knowledge
that seems clearly to indicate
that there is continuity between
the life experience of that
previous life and their present
life. And at the end of his
career, Stevenson publishes
monument Opus in which he
demonstrated not only that our
memories continuous, but in some
cases, even our bodies bear the
marks of events that took place
in our previous lifetime that
children he studied. 187 cases
of children who had birthmarks
our pigmentation are seeming
scars on their body that
reflected the death
circumstances of previous life.
So someone who was stabbed in a
previous life, and they have a
memory of that life, had a
birthmark where they were
stabbed in a way that replicated
that, or someone who was hung
had scars on their neck that
seemed to correlate this an
absolutely fascinating study.
And from there, once I was
convinced by Stevenson's
research that reincarnation was
simply part of life, I went on
to study the work of multiple
past life therapists who were
working with their clients to
heal the wounds of their present
life. Most of the time when you
work in therapy, the wounds of
your present life go back to
some trauma or some disruption,
some unhappiness from our
present life earlier in our
life, but he past life
therapists consistently find
that there's a certain
percentage of pains which are
not healed when you go back to
your form, to your present life,
but when you allow your mind to
open into your deeper history,
then all of a Sudden, you are
reliving a deeper story. You are
remembering things that happened
when you were a different person
than you are now, but you
remember them with the same
sense of identification and self
sense that you have for your
present life. And when people do
this, when they go back and
relive the pains and the trauma
or the conflicts that were
present in their previous life,
it has a healing effect on their
present life. And after reading
hundreds of cases like this, it
just became more and more
obvious to me that reincarnation
is part of the larger rhythm of
our life. It doesn't mean I
agreed with all the
interpretations of
reincarnation. In fact, that's
one of the things that came up
in my sessions, was an expansion
of the model of what's taking
place in reincarnation. But the
fact of reincarnation, the fact
that one life rolls into another
life rolls into another life
with time in between. I mean,
Michael Newton's work, a past
life therapist, life between
life. His books, journey of the
soul, journeys of the soul and
destiny of souls, has done
fascinating work he was doing
conventional kind of past life
regression therapy, and he he
made a mistake one day in one of
with one of his clients, he gave
an ambiguous instruction, and
suddenly he realized that his
patients were described. His
patient was describing what
happened to them after they died
in the former life they had been
reliving. So he discovered that
people had the capacity not only
to remember their former lives,
but to remember what they were
doing in between their incarnate
lives. And so he after he had
regressed hundreds of people
back in. To this in between
state, he began to write a
series of books, journeys of the
journeys of the soul, journey of
souls and destiny of souls, in
which he basically compiled what
his clients were telling him
about the interlife state. And
in there it becomes, it's part
of his discovery that people
choose consciously their present
the conditions of their present
life, that there is a process
when you die, there is a
debriefing process, a process of
integrating back into the soul,
integrating into the world of
spirit, a process of maybe
healing some of the
unhappinesses that have been
collected in your present
lifetime. But then there is a
period of refreshment and
restoration and learning
continues, and there is a social
structure to the postmortem
condition. There comes a time
when it's time for class to
resume. The soul begins a
process of choosing the
conditions of its next
incarnation. This is that that
basic let's really opens up a
whole new understanding, in this
sense. Now I think that just as
kids and people in college, some
people choose their courses very
carefully and systematically
with great forethought, and some
people choose their courses kind
of haphazardly or randomly, just
picking what comes what works in
their work schedule, and they
get different results. I think
it may be also the case for the
soul. Some souls choose more
carefully than other souls. But
the idea that we choose our
incarnation, we choose the
circumstances of our
incarnation, that it's an
intelligent process, and by
making choices of what we want
to experience, doing our best in
that experience, expanding out
by becoming male, female, rich,
poor, Warrior, Priest, artist,
all these different varieties.
We grow faster than we would
grow if we lived all these years
as one person, the same person.
So sometimes with my students, I
would say, imagine that you are
the creative intelligence of the
universe, and you had two
options. You could create a life
that would live 100,000 years,
or you could create a life that
would live the same 100,000
years, but in 100 year
increments, and every 100 years,
they would change the
circumstances of the life at the
end of 100 years. Which do you
think would produce the greater
learning? And I think it's clear
that the 100 Year increment life
would produce the greater
learning. That's understanding
that underneath the short term
experience of our present life,
there is an accumulation taking
place at the level of the Soul,
that the soul is learning, the
soul is accumulating the
experiences of all of our many,
many lifetimes. And they aren't
that learning is not necessarily
present in each individual life,
but it's holding them like a
library in the spiritual
reality. Now this was I saw this
also in my sessions. I
experienced, in some cases,
former lives with people that I
was engaged in. In this present
lifetime, there was healing that
took place in these encounters.
But I also was taken into a
series of experiences which
pushed the boundaries.
There was a particular session
which I call the birth of the
diamond soul, in which I
experienced all of my former
lives coming into me very quick
just there was tremendous work
had been done earlier in the
session, and I was in a state
where I was just seemingly
integrating streams of
consciousness from multiple
lifetimes. And it was like
wrapping string around a kite
spool filaments of white light,
and they seemed to hit a
critical mass at one point, and
when they hit a critical mass,
they fused all these lives,
fused into a single energy
entity. And when they fuse,
there was an explosion of
diamond light that it just
exploded from my chest, and it
catapulted me into a completely
different state of
consciousness. I was an
individual, but I was an
individual beyond any frame of
reference that I had previously
known. I wasn't Chris Bache, but
I was a being that Chris Bache
was part of, and all of these
other former lives were part of,
and this is what I came to call
the birth of the diamond soul.
I. Is the idea that life grows,
that part of the intelligent
process of life is growing human
consciousness, layer by layer,
semester by semester, as it
were, grade by grade, course by
course, allowing us to expand
and grow, hopefully, more
intelligent, more compassion. We
make mistakes, we learn, but we
learn from those mistakes, we
grow, we grow. But the process
is not simply about becoming
incrementally, gradually, more
than we were. Sooner or later,
there comes a time when all of
those lives, all of their
learning fuse and the soul
consciousness awakens within us.
I think in the normal process of
reincarnation, we experience our
soul when we die. So we go from
ego to soul, back to ego, back
to soul. But if we keep this up
1000s and 1000s of years, 1000s
of years, sooner or later, it's
a natural process that the soul
wakes up inside time and space.
I think this is what's
happening, not only for us
individually, but it's what's
happening for us as a species.
We are in the process through
our long, long history, our long
evolutionary journey, our long
learning process. We are in the
process of transcending the ego
and waking up. The soul is
waking up inside time and space.
This is, I think history is
taking us into a time, into an
epic, when the diamond soul is
waking up on Earth.
Simeon Mihaylov: That's
beautiful. Concerning this
vision of reincarnation that you
gained through your experiences
and through your reading. There
are three particular issues that
I two particular questions that
I have which I think are very
difficult to answer. They arise
as many other issues from the
fact that it's difficult to talk
about these things. But the
first issue everybody knows, how
can reincarnation? Yes, how can
consciousness travel from one
biological mechanism into
another? But we can leave that
alone, because it's probably
beyond each one of us at the
moment, but then two other I
think the answer is, we don't
know.
Chris Bache: Yeah, no. We don't
know what the physics of the
soul is. We don't know how our
memories leave our biological
base and how consciousness kind
of reprograms or returns to and
integrates with a new biological
body. We just don't have the
answer that question. But we
won't begin to find the answers
to that question. And still, we
start asking different
questions, we have to open up to
a more complex cosmology of a
multi level universe, and stop
acting as if our consciousness
is being generated and created
by our brain. That's a reductive
cosmology which doesn't allow us
to even begin to find the
answers to the question you're
asking. So I hope you're right.
We don't know, but I think in
time, we'll get more and more
knowledge in that area.
Simeon Mihaylov: Yeah, hopefully
that's that would be a very
interesting thing to realize how
it works. But also, when you
talk about the soul, that's
something that I'm very
interested in, because, let's
say, if somebody is just doing
meditation practice, one of the
key insights, I think, of
meditation, is non self,
Non-duality, the CO arising of
everything. So how does that
stack up with the idea of a soul
reincarnating? And what is
reincarnating? Is it the doer,
the thing that makes choices in
the life, or is it the weakness,
the thing that kind of just is
conscious of all of these
things?
Chris Bache: Yeah, I've had
those experiences of Non-duality
and what Buddhism calls
emptiness, Shunyata, emptiness
of self, where there is an
experience of such intimacy that
there is no self inside you, and
also no self anywhere in the
world. Everything is just open
and pours and magnificent
experience. And I think it
depends on how you think of the
soul, if you think of the soul,
and I think this is kind of the
way we have, by habit and by
custom, have thought of the soul
in the past. It's kind of what I
think of as an atomistic theory
of the soul, in contrast to a
quantum or field theory of the
soul, if you think of the soul
as a fundamentally isolated
unit, which does. Not change and
is fundamentally isolated from
other souls or other beings,
then you have a problem, because
Non-duality and Shunyata
emptiness is cut is it
contradicts that atomistic
notion of the soul. But if you
have kind of a quantum model of
the soul, if you have a soul as
a field, as a as a learning
system, which is never isolated
from the surrounding being
surrounded from the surrounding
world, which is always in an
energetic exchange with that
world is always kind of
incorporating information and
energy from in the waves of
life, then I think we can
concept, understand, an
understanding of soul, which is
one dynamic. It's always
changing. It's never fixed. It's
always evolving through time.
And it's porous. It's a reality
which is porous, and yet it has
individual, an individuality it
has, it is, I think, the
universe is a learning
environment. It's learning in so
many ways. It's learning at a at
a species level, but it's also
learning at an individual level.
We are learning. We are growing.
We are holding on to our
experience. We remember our
experience, we acquire insights
on the basis of that experience.
It doesn't mean we're isolated
from the world, and it doesn't
mean we're static, but we are
developing an individuality
which is a porous individuality.
So in the end, I don't think
there is any contradiction
between affirming an emergent
individuality in creation and
the fundamental condition of
Non-duality. And I think this is
also affirmed in the spiritual
traditions. Even the Dalai Lama
has written that what Buddhism
rejects in rejecting it in its
anata doctrine, it's no self
doctrine. What it's rejecting is
not individuality. What it's
rejecting is a static soul, a
soul which doesn't change in
time, and a soul which is
independent of other realities,
independent of surrounding
reality. Once you want to, once
you kind of shift your
understanding of soul to this
kind of open field vision, then
I think it's completely
compatible with Shunyata
emptiness
Simeon Mihaylov: and this open
field vision of the soul. I
think it also kind of leads into
your observation that
enlightenment isn't a private
process. You were talking about
how in particular, one thing I
found very interesting is you
would talk about how your
experiences of purification and
healing, you could see them
affecting not only your personal
sphere, but also the larger
collective of humanity, which I
found very interesting. And I
wanted to understand how that,
how that works, and how that
feeds into your vision of the
future human. And yes, please
tell us, say a bit more about
that?
Chris Bache: Oh, that's a big
question. You know, when I began
this work, I thought I was doing
this work for my personal
edification, you know, from my
personal healing, maybe even my
personal spiritual realization.
But I found that even though
that was maybe my mindset, that
wasn't the universe's mindset,
it wasn't what was going on from
its end. The Mystery of the
collective ramifications of our
work, the collective import of
our work, it's only a mystery if
we start with the assumption
that we are fundamentally
private entities, but in the
nature of the experience, both
in classical, meditative
spiritual deepening and in
psychedelic spiritual deepening,
we discover that that's not the
case. We discover that we are
always and forever and always
have been, always will be part
of an interwoven network of
life. And the image I like to
use for this is the image of a
tree and a leaf, leaf
consciousness and tree
consciousness. So imagine you
were seeing a tree where all you
could see all the leaves, and
imagine all the leaves were
individually conscious. They had
individual personalities. And
imagine that everything that was
covered in bark was invisible,
so all you could see were the
leaves, but you could not see
the trunk and the limbs of the
tree. And imagine that one of
these leaves decides to explore
what is the real nature of his.
Or her being. So he goes deep
within, and he finds that place
in their inner being where they
connect to the twig and pushing
their consciousness deeper into
the twig, into the limb, into
the branch, eventually into the
very core of the tree, and
suddenly has the exploding
awareness of what a tree is,
sees the tree, experiences the
tree, and therefore knows what a
leaf is. The leaf is not a
separate, private part. A leaf
is a living aspect of a much
deeper, larger being, and that
the well being of the leaf is
connected to the well being of
all the other leaves in the
tree, that we truly are all in
this together. And when that
awareness dawns, then if that
consciousness works its way back
up into its leaf again, back
into its leafness Now, it sees
all the other leaves in the tree
as an aspect of it, of this
deeper identity which all leaves
share. It would also say strange
things, like there is no self.
Shunyata, it is anata, meaning
there is no private self. We're
all here together. Compassion
would spontaneously manifest,
because one would know that what
you do to another leaf, you do
to yourself because you're doing
it to the tree. We're all
individually connected. These
are things that surface in all
deep spiritual traditions, in
the psychedelic practice, what I
found is that when I would open
deeply within quote myself, I
would be involved in healing
work and cleansing work that was
not related to my personal
history, but expanded beyond my
personal history in some way, it
would be as if I were working to
heal all the leaves on one
particular branch of this
particular tree. And this just
happens spontaneously, because
nature doesn't hold the
boundaries that we imagine exist
in our private, small mind.
Nature lives as an integrated
whole. Our species lives as an
integrated totality. So it's
just natural that when we open
up to that totality, as we do
with psychedelics, we we enter
into and we can dissolve
completely into that reality. So
it's not just that the leaf has
a leaf experience of the tree.
The leaf can dissolve into the
essence of the tree and
experience how the tree
experiences life. The same thing
happens in psychedelic work. We
enter into purification
processes which affect the tree
lows around us and we enter into
ecstatic joy, ecstatic
experiences of intimacy with
life, intimacy with the divine,
which naturally you can't
contain it. It naturally
radiates through your awareness
into the awareness of all the
beings around you. All spiritual
traditions have recognized that
our spiritual practice radiates
through the fabric of the world,
not just the human fabric, but
the fabric of all reality, also
the the animal fabric of the
world. So, you know, I'm getting
a little lost in the thought of
that. It's just, it's just it
becomes so natural, it becomes
such a repeated experience that
it helps me understand, in some
ways, the Buddhist tradition
that at the beginning of every
meditation session or any
spiritual practice, you begin by
cultivating what they call
bodhicitta, which is the desire
to save all sentient beings. So
you open you're doing this
practice not for your personal
benefit. You're doing it for all
beings. At the end of your
practice, you give away all the
benefit to all the beings of the
universe at all the levels. So
what you're doing is not just
for your is not for your own
benefit. You're doing it for the
benefit of the totality, and in
doing that, you strengthen your
awareness that you are a fractal
aspect of the totality. And in
that awareness, there is great
liberation, there is great joy,
because you know you're you just
allow yourself to live and begin
to live the larger life. In the
larger life is what all those.
Spiritual teachers and saints
have been talking about the
compassion that treats your
enemy as as friends, the
compassion where you open into
deep time and you know that you
are more, that you are not just
the small you, which usually
takes so much of our time and
attention. You know that what
you are is a piece of life which
has infinite extension and
infinite range and reach, and in
that knowledge, there is the
great relaxation, the great joy
you just it dissolves
alienation. It dissolves
loneliness. One becomes, once
again, what one has always been,
but forgets. One becomes a
joyful aspect of the totality.
Simeon Mihaylov: Chris, here I
have just all the quotes that I
have taken from your book, and
so difficult choosing which one
to go with. But there is one,
one particular section in which
you I'm going to quote you
directly. Here, you talk about,
kind of the purpose of this
whole exercise of reincarnation
and learning. And you say, you
say, on the other hand, I also
felt an exquisite tenderness
coming from the Creator who
experienced with us every pain
we had taken upon ourselves.
Humans were so precious to the
Creator that not a single ounce
of pain, not a single cure was
wasted. The depth of that divine
care so moved me that no
sacrifice seems too large or
unreasonable, and I think here
you're talking about all the
suffering that is involved in
this process of learning and a
vision in which of this kind of
made sense for you, as in it
didn't seem as meaningless
suffering anymore. This remind
me, I don't know if you, if you
have ever read the brothers
karma by Dostoevsky. It's a
great novel that talks about
these issues. And at one point
there are these two brothers,
Alyosha and Ivan karmazov, and
they discuss the existence of
God. And basically, Alyosha is a
faithful kind of servant of God,
very pure of heart, but not so
smart. And then there is Ivan
karmazov, who is exception. He's
essentially a genius, successful
in every manner you can imagine,
but a complete atheist. And when
he talks about why he rejects
God, He gives pages upon pages
of examples of cruelty inflicted
upon children, and actually the
safety had taken that out of
actual accounts of children
being tortured, being killed,
being maimed. Then this is very
interesting, because it reminds
me of your experiences where at
certain point of your journey,
you were faced by these not just
images, the experiences of
children being killed, the
killing of the children. Yes,
exactly, yeah. And I think that
is really the ultimate argument
you can raise against this
cosmic plan. What justifies the
suffering of innocent beings?
What can justify this suffering?
Because eventually, Ivan
karmazov says, perhaps there is
a God. Maybe I do believe in
God, but I do not accept the
world that he has created. So
what's your comment on that?
Chris Bache: That is the hardest
part of all of it, isn't it? How
can we affirm an intelligence,
let alone a compassion behind
existence, operating through
existence, when everywhere we
look around us, there is so much
pain, so much brutality, so much
horror, compounding over and
over again, so much suffering.
Unknown: I you
Chris Bache: know Ramakrishna,
the great Hindu saint, he said,
If you want to understand God,
you must be willing to look
suffering in the face. And I
really, I hold that, and I
really respect that, and I think
it's really true. You you can't
you must understand suffering.
You must confront suffering and
engage suffering if you have any
hope of understanding the true
divine. Now I'm really I'm very
comfortable with atheism, and
atheism is a rejection of
theism, and depending upon the
theism that we're talking about,
most of the theisms that I know
deserve to be rejected. Most of
them are too small. Most of them
are the the gods of so many
religions are terrifyingly small
and. That the vision of life
that comes with them are
terrifyingly inaccurate and
inadequate and do not provide
anywhere near an adequate
understanding of existence to
help us understand the enormous
pain that we're seeing. And I
don't think I'm going to be able
to succeed and in answering this
question satisfactory, but it's
a question I live with, and so I
can only offer you a few things.
I
in order to understand the
suffering in life, we also have
to understand genius in life, in
order to understand what's
happening in life's deficiencies
children who are born without
brains, you know, without you
know, we have to understand the
larger trajectory of life. My
sense of it is, and my
experience of is, when I have
dissolved into what I experience
as the creative intention of the
universe. I dissolved into a
process of creation, a process
of manifestation, self
manifestation, first, that was
just vast, just huge and
ancient, just extraordinarily
old. Been going on so long,
billions, billions of years, 13
point 8 billion years, they tell
us, since this big bang. And
we're not at all sure that this
is the first of the Big Bangs so
and that the creative capacity
of the universe extends not just
to, you know, the
microorganisms, and the
organisms on this planet, but
entire galaxies and stars and
the collapsing of stars and the
emerging of planets and the
evolution of life on the planets
and just countless galaxies,
countless galaxies. So we now
are the first generation to
truly appreciate the scale of
the universe that we're involved
in, both of its age and its
expanse. And we've all been
fascinated by the wonderful
images coming from the Hubble
telescope and other Prana other
scopes that are giving us these
magnificent pictures of the
scale of existence. And it's in
that context, I think that we
have to look at our own
existence, our whole species
existence, and ask, what are we
doing? What's happening here? If
there is intelligence, how is
this intelligence expressing
itself here in our life, and in
particular, why is it so hard.
Why is life so hard? Why
couldn't life be made easier?
It's like so I can believe in
God, but I don't believe in I
don't accept the universe that
this God has created. And and I
agree with those deep
sentiments, because they honor
our children, they honor life,
and there is no justification on
the surface like that for their
suffering and their pain. But
again, if we look at this in a
context, a human being is a
growing intelligence a human
being is growing, and its growth
rests upon the shoulders of the
primate kingdom, which rests
upon the shoulders of other life
forms which preceded the
primates and so on down the
evolutionary ladder. If we want
to assess the condition and
judge the condition. Certainly
we have to ask ourselves the
question, are we at the end of
this process? Are we? Are we all
that there is, is this where
it's going to end? Is this? Is
this what's happening? If you go
to see a play and it's a 10 act
play, and you're only in the
first scene of the first act.
Clearly, you don't have enough
information to know whether the
play is a good play. You must
see it through to the end. If
you're on a car assembly plant,
and you're only at station
three, and there 215 stations of
the sembly plant, and you're
seeing something being built,
but you don't even see enough to
understand where it's going or
what it is, then you just can't
understand the process. And part
of the advantages, or one of the
great advantages, of working
with psychedelic states, is that
it allows you, under certain
conditions, to expand beyond
this moment of time. Be. It
allows you to expand and to
dissolve, not only into the
intelligence that's manifesting
as the universe that's
manifesting as the life forms in
the universe, but it also allows
you to experience not only the
distant past of this self
manifesting universe, but also
the future of this self
manifesting universe, entering
into what I call deep time. And
my experiences in deep time have
convinced me that there are
dimensions in which the universe
knows itself, which go far
beyond this present moment, and
in those encounters, in those
dissolving into the deep future,
been able to experience, or have
been given, the experiences of
something of the creative
process, something of the how
creativity is expressing itself
in human beings, and we come
here to make choices. We make
choices, and we learned. We make
bad choices, we have bad
consequences. We make good
choices, we have better
consequences. But we're just
getting started. We only became
self aware about 5000 years ago.
I mean, we only became aware of
the consciousness that lies at
the center of our being, our
common our deep consciousness.
We only began to have access to
that about 5000 years ago. Self
Awareness came earlier, but what
the self is began about 5000
years ago, and we are just
getting started. We are just
beginning to exercise the full
potential which lies latent
within the human being. And in
that process, in that creative
process, we are dealing with a
very incomplete creation, a very
incomplete planet, an incomplete
species, and a species which in
some ways is still living out of
very barbaric, primitive levels
of self understanding And in its
primitiveness, inflicts great
damage on the beings around it.
It's like the pain of being of
an individual leaf is so
terrible we go insane and we
inflict damage on other leaves.
But it's not just that. It's
like
the process of evolution itself
is incomplete. Is still working
it out, working things out. The
process of organic evolution is
incomplete. Sri Aurobindo said,
humanity is a transitional
species. We are not the end of
the line. We are simply a
transition going from a lower
order of awareness into a higher
order of awareness when then,
when we stabilize at a higher
level of awareness, we're going
into yet on higher and a higher
level of awareness, the ability
of mind to be able to influence
matter, The ability of mind to
be able to manifest joy. Grace,
fruition inside matter is still
being developed. The ability of
our mind to be able to control
the diseases of the body,
they're still being developed.
We are basically so profoundly
incomplete. Nature is so
profoundly incomplete. My basic
response to suffering is that it
does reflect, in certain ways,
the incompleteness of the
universe. It also reflects the
terrifying demands of learning
through experience of
experiencing the consequences in
some instances, not at all, but
in some instances, of learn, of
inheriting the consequences of
choices that we've made so that
we can learn from those choices
and make better choices in the
future. But not all suffering
really derives from human
choices at all. Some suffering
just devised from what we would
call the cruelties of nature.
This planet is a severe place.
Hurricanes come through and wipe
out 1000s of lives. Earthquakes
wipe out 1000s of lives. Biology
takes out 1000s of children.
This is a very, very intense
world, we must be willing to
look suffering in the face if we
want to understand the deeper,
the deeper intentionality that
is expressing itself in this
very incomplete. Place in time.
We tend to sort of see God as
all perfect and static and
unchanging, and therefore we
hold God responsible for making
this that the other. But I don't
think that's the way it is at
all. We are cells in the being
of God. We are cells in the
being of the Divine. The Divine
is not separate from any of the
pain that the children are
experiencing. But Divine is not
other than or distant from
what's going on, what's taking
place, but we ourselves within
the emerging the divine. We are
aspects of its so the pain is
always felt, always registered,
always held. We are all in this
together, and we are growing
together. Now, here's the thing,
if we were to stop the whole
process right now, if we were to
hold the creative intent, the
designer, accountable for just
where we are right now, that we
would have to conclude it's a
bastard. He's a bastard because
it's just too much pain. There's
too much pain. But if we were
able to go forward in time, if
we could go even such a short
distance of time of 100,000
years from now, and experience
an evolved humanity, what we are
becoming, what we are in the
process of becoming, we would
experience a much kinder
humanity, a much more gracious
humanity, a much more
intelligent humanity, a much
more compassionate humanity, a
humanity that was much better
able to manage still the
fluctuations of nature, which
are so painful and so
catastrophic and we just it's
hard to envision where this is
going, where this is taking us
now. This brings me to the
deeper part of your question.
Where are we now in this
process, where what is, what's
happening in our historical
circumstances? What is the
future, the immediate future for
our species?
Unknown: And here,
Chris Bache: I know that I'm
sharing just my own visionary
experiences. I know that what
may be powerful and true for one
person would not necessarily be
powerful or true for another
person. So I can only share with
you what my experience has been
early on in my sessions, oh,
starting in around the 23rd
session. So for the last 50 of
my sessions, one of the
recurring themes of my sessions
was that where humanity is
going, where we're what's
happening, and the vision was
over and over repeated. We are
coming into a turning point in
history. We're coming into a
decisive before and after point
that we were poised on the edge
of a magnificent transition into
a higher level of functioning,
that there was that there was a
greatness in emerging within
humanity. And when I look around
at history, I thought I'd say,
Well, I don't exactly see that.
I see people being just as
stupid now as they were, you
know, 5000 years ago, in so many
ways, and just as cruel. But my
sessions kept saying, no, no,
look deeper. There is an
emerging greatness in humanity.
And again, I understand this
within reincarnation, there is
to see humanity. Is not just to
see the present generation, but
is to see the living pulsing of
life, incarnating again and
again over many 1000s of years.
And the greatness that is
emerging is a greatness that's
emerging at that deeper level of
accumulation of the soul, which
is collecting and harvesting,
all the learning, all the
suffering, all the
experimentation, all the
courage, all the innovation
that's been we're cultivating
through all of these lifetimes.
So the My Sessions kept showing
me that there is a greatness
emerging in the human story, and
that there was a we were coming
into a decisive turning point in
history. But it never showed me
how it was going to realize
this. I had no idea how this was
going to come about. And then in
the 55th session, it took me
into what I call the Great
Awakening session. It took me
deep into the future, and it
took me there in order to allow
me to experience the death and
rebirth of the human species.
And I don't mean that as a
physical death and rebirth, but
a sort of a psycho spiritual
death and rebirth, but a death
and rebirth. It did involve much
physical suffering and many
deaths. And I had this
experience, not as Chris Bache
or not as even Chris Bache, of
an expanded version of myself,
but I had the experience as the
entire species, my consciousness
had dissolved into the
collective psyche. So I
experience a profound crescendo
of suffering and a birth coming
out of the suffering that was a
birth of a new human being, a
new form of human being.
Basically, I experience a
historical period of an
unraveling, loss of control, an
inability to control the
circumstances of our life, a
tremendous kind of confronting
of the sins of the fathers. We
are our own fathers, of course.
So a confronting of our past, a
confronting of all the foibles
and the limitations and the
divisiveness of history and the
short sightedness of our forms
of governance that we had
emerged and it was a global
systems crisis that seemed to be
driven by a global ecological
crisis, but a global systems
crisis where humanity was
basically forced, ultimately,
into simply trying to survive.
And for a time it looked like we
weren't going to survive. It
looked like it was an extinction
event. It looked like we were
going to lose our place in
existence altogether. But just
when the storm was at its peak,
just when things were at their
worst, it was as if a hurricane
passed over the island and the
skies began to clear. And when
the skies began to clear, there
were many survivors. There had
been many deaths, but there were
many survivors. And when the
survivors began to pick
themselves up and began to move
forward and find each other,
there sprang forth from within
each of them, individually and
from within the collective, new
ways of knowing, new ways of
feeling, new understandings, new
insights. Fundamentally at its
core, there was the birth of an
appreciation of oneness, an
experience of oneness, not as a
theory, not as kind of an
ideology, but an experience of
that tree that underlies
individual leaf consciousness,
that we truly are one. We truly
are connected to each other, and
in that birth of that awareness,
we began to build a new world,
not the world created by the
ego. And the ego is a
magnificent expression of
creativity. The ego is
magnificent, but the ego is
divided from the fundamental
springs of consciousness and
from each other, and the world
which ego has created is a
divided world. It's a world
which favors some portions of
society at the expense of
others. It's not a world that
works for all, but with the
birth of oneness, with the birth
of this transformation, we began
to build a new world. We began
to build a world which truly,
truly did work for all, in which
there was, there was truly a new
beginning. And this creativity,
these new ideas, they fed upon
themselves. So there was a
cascading of more and more
beauty, more and more knowledge,
more and more understanding. And
I think what was taking place,
what I experienced, was a
collective birth of the diamond
soul, that the soul was waking
up on Earth, that we were waking
up and understanding ourselves
to be not simply 100 year old
beings. We were waking up and
experiencing ourselves to be
100,000 year old beings with
relationships 100,000 years old.
And in that awareness, we not
only experienced a much deeper
compassion with other human
beings and other life forms
altogether, but we experienced
greater transparency to the
creative intelligence of the
universe itself. We were no
longer experientially isolated
from the cosmic intelligence of
the universe, but we could take
in deeper downloads from the
intelligence of the universe,
and with these deeper downloads,
there was no technological
problem which we could not
solve, because we were awake
intellectually at deeper levels.
We could understand things.
Understandings came easier.
There. Was no technological
barriers to what we could
accomplish in this world. This
is the birth, what I call the
birth of the future human. And I
think the future human is the
diamond soul incarnating in
history in my one of the last
great vision of my journey, in
the 70th session when I thought
I was beyond all the meltdowns
that I'd gone through before.
I'd gone through so many
meltdowns, it put me through the
worst strip down of my entire 20
year journey. It just broke me
down terribly. And I think it
was necessary in order to give
me the experiences that
followed, and it took me deeper
into the future than it had ever
taken me before. And in this
condition, one of the
experiences that unfolded there
is that it gave me yet again,
and my deepest experience of the
future human, it was as if I was
allowed to try on for size, the
new archetype of the new human
that had emerged had been
birthed in the in evolution, and
just touching this being
Unknown: was so extraordinary.
Just
Chris Bache: if I try to
describe it, I don't think I can
do it without crying. Just a
magnificent beauty, just a
completely healed humanity,
healed of all the scars that had
accumulated through all those
1000s of years of incarnating a
heart, an explosively large
heart, a magnificent and
magnificent mind capable of
illumination that staggers the
imagination. This is the child
which we're trying to give birth
to. This is the child which I
think we are beginning to give
birth to in this century. I
think we are entering the dark
night of our collective soul,
and just as in mystical
traditions before, in order for
full spiritual realization to
emerge, there must take place a
dark night of our soul, which is
a time of purification, a time
of confronting the poisons that
are left over from our past
behaviors and opening. And as
this dark night comes to
fruition, there is a a death, a
death to that old self, and a
birth of something new. And when
that new opens, it basically all
the mystics and all the great
saints tell us the same thing,
it makes all the purification
worthwhile. It makes all the
hardships worthwhile. That's
when a mother gives birth, when
she holds her child, then the
pains of labor are forgotten.
They're worthwhile. I think
something like that is happening
for humanity. We are in the
process. We have been gestating
the new humanity for 1000s and
hundreds of 1000s of years,
reincarnation, lifetime by
lifetime, we've been gestating
the new humanity. Gestation
takes a long time. Birth is a
short time. Birth is a very
intense process, and I think we
are in a collective dark night
of the old of the soul. Now we
may just be in the early stages
of it. I think we are maybe in
what John of the Cross called
the dark night of the self,
which is the early stage of
purification and transformation.
But these will be followed by
deeper purification, deeper
transformation, until
eventually, we'll let go of our
past, until eventually, when it
hurts so much to stay as we
were, we'll begin to open up
into who we can be and who we
need to be in order to save life
on this planet. In that process,
I think we're giving birth to
the new humanity. And when we
give birth to the new humanity,
we will look back over the whole
of human evolution and all the
suffering that has been
involved, and we will say not
that it wasn't real, not that it
wasn't terrible, but that in a
larger order of things, it was
worth it, because now we are
operating at a completely
different blueprint of the human
psyche. So I think we're in hard
times. We're in for hard times
ahead. But I think these are
magnificently important times,
extremely creative times and
times which will demand a great
deal from us, individually and
collectively. But if we engage
them conscientiously, if we
engage them heart and soul, I
think they're going to change
our life individually and the
life of our children. And our
grandchildren and our great
grandchildren forever. So
that's, that's the visions that
were poured into me, and so
that's, I just share them with
you.
Unknown: Wow. That's, uh,
Simeon Mihaylov: really leaves
me speechless. It's hard. It's
hard. Now I want to say to that,
that's beautiful, absolutely
beautiful. I can see how, I can
see how that removes any
anxiety, really, about death and
about life and about future of
us as individuals of species.
It's just a beautiful, beautiful
vision.
Unknown: So
Chris Bache: every time we die,
you know, of course, at a
deepest level, all the spiritual
traditions tell us no one dies,
we just transition into a
different level of reality. And
I'm not making light of death,
and I'm not trivializing it all,
but just affirming this deeper
insight that everything we are
survives the death of this body,
and at the end of every
lifetime, we return to where we
came from As a resting place,
and we are restored and
refreshed, and then we return to
the challenges of history, you
know? So it's, it's, we don't
have to go through all the
evolutionary future in order to
know freedom from fear of death.
In fact, one of the, if they
were one thing from my
psychedelic experiences that I
wish I could, I could give to
the world, it would be
eliminating the fear of death. I
not only am not afraid of dying,
I'm looking forward to it,
because death is homecoming.
Always death is home coming.
Simeon Mihaylov: I know
different spiritual traditions
have said that in different
ways, but I find Carl Jung, he
says at one point that life is a
short period between two
infinities, which in the end,
might just be one. So I think
that's a beautiful way of
putting it. Yeah.
Chris Bache: Beautifully said,
yeah.
Simeon Mihaylov: There is one
more thing that he says that I
want to ask, how you see this in
light of your experiences? Karim
used to say, I can I can either
be good or I can be whole. So he
had a tremendous respect for the
dark side of the psyche, for
evil. Yeah. So how do you see
it? Do you see evil falling away
as our egos fall away when we
become this future human? Or do
you see some deeper logic to
evil continuing and becoming
integrated and then serving some
higher purpose?
Chris Bache: Well, I would begin
by differentiating between
darkness and evil. People often
fuse those, but I think that
they're different. Darkness evil
is a kind of a twisting of life.
It is a process in which life,
in some way, has turned in upon
itself and has cut itself so
deeply off from its source that
it has become twisted cancerous
and needs to be restored, needs
to be healed. Darkness, on the
other hand, is simply part of
the inertia of existence. It's
part. It's kind of like, what,
what the Big Bang explodes into.
It's what it's, what is the
resistance to the creative
process itself. But I think when
When Jung talked about, I'd
rather be whole than be good, he
was claiming all the parts of
his life which weren't
necessarily socially good or
even that he would deem good,
she was claiming the whole of
his life. And I think that's
that happens in spiritual
practice, and it certainly
happens in psychedelic practice.
We grab the whole of our life.
We grab all aspects of it, even
the parts that we're embarrassed
by and the parts we're ashamed
of, are the parts that we feel
are unforgivable. We embrace
them all, and as we embrace them
all, all those twisted or
unintegrated or injured aspects
of our self are brought back
into healing and are brought
back into wholeness, so that
there emerges out of that
wholeness a higher order of
goodness, a different order of
goodness. Uh, but it is, it is
that commitment to embracing the
shadow, to let no corner of our
being be excluded from
redemption. We might say,
nothing can be left out
otherwise. The the system is
incomplete. It's like there's a
chorus, but some of the voices
are gone. We have to have all of
them present for the course to
be complete, so that in
evolution, in our social
evolution, in our spiritual
evolution, clearly, there is
much darkness in the world.
There is much twisted so we
could say there is much evil,
but I don't think of evil as a
cosmological process. I've never
experienced it that way. I've
never experienced evil in that
way. I experienced darkness,
I've experienced confusion, I've
experienced pain and suffering,
but not evil as such. And I
think that's what Sri Aurobindo
I mean, what Ramakrishna meant
when he said, If you want to
understand God, you must look
suffering in the face. And
suffering doesn't come from a
second principle. It doesn't
come from an evil Demiurge. It
comes from the Divine suffering
is part of the Divine
expression. We have to
understand how life works, and
we must look deep. If we're
going to see the compassion and
existence, we must be able to
look very, very deep, because,
because there is so much
suffering. But, and I think the
suffering is in the process of
being redeemed in history, in
the sense that it is part of a
self learning process, which is
taking us somewhere, and it's
taking us somewhere exciting and
somewhere magnificent. So I
guess I would say that darkness
is being redeemed in evolution.
I don't think, I don't know what
will happen as we make this
transition into this higher form
of humanity. I'm sure that even
if we did make this transition
within 1000 years, say, or even
sooner, into a higher
manifestation of human
experience on the planet, it
doesn't end there. You know,
we're going to keep going for
millions of more years, billions
of more years. So I'm sure there
will be challenges that we'll
face, there'll be thresholds
that we'll face, but along the
way, I think we're we just have
to let go of some of the early
stories that we've been telling
ourselves, that somehow evil has
its hand on the earth, or
somehow that there is a
malevolent force that intends us
to suffer this way, or that we
can escape this suffering by
simply being good, experiencing
salvation and going to heaven
when we die, and leaving the
earth behind and just not being
here anymore. We just have to
let go of a lot of our old
stories and open up into a
deeper understanding of the
cosmological process of
creation, self manifestation of
the creative intelligence.
Simeon Mihaylov: Chris, I missed
the realize that I'm taking
quite a lot of your time. So
before we finish, I want to ask
you, now that you've written in
your book, because correct me if
I'm wrong. But you discontinued,
you finished your LSD sessions,
and then you took 20 years, was
it? And then you published your
your book 20 years later. So, so
how has the writing of your book
and then doing of you know,
speaking about your experiences,
how has that changed your
insight and what is left for you
to do in this lifetime? What?
Chris Bache: Yes, learn to cook.
Well, maybe let me back up a
little bit and describe what
happened when I stopped my work,
because that'll lead into the
writing of the book. I stopped
my work in 99 and I stopped it
for a number of reasons, but
foremost among them, I stopped
it because the domain of diamond
Luminosity that I entered. And
in those last five years and 26
sessions, I entered this reality
only four times. And in between
those four entrances into the
diamond Luminosity, there were
very, very intense purifications
and healings and catharsis that
were taking place. But I entered
that joy of dissolving into the
light, and it made coming back.
I reached a point where it was
just too painful to come back
into time space and. So there
was a sadness in coming back,
and I knew I had to. I couldn't
take being separated from the
universe that deep intimacy
again. I couldn't take entering
into the joy and then coming
back out of the joy anymore that
I had to let go. There were
other things going on. I was
also running enormous energy in
my body that I realized I was
really kind of at a subtle
energy level. I was running too
hot. I needed to stop and let my
system calm down and let my
subtle energy system
recalibrate. But the primary
reason I stopped is because of a
heartache. I couldn't I couldn't
take coming back anymore, so I
stopped, and I had been given so
many blessings through the years
and had been shown so many
things that I thought I could
just stop and I would continue
to be nourished by the treasures
that I had been given, by the
diamonds that I had been given.
And it that's true, and that did
happen, but that turned out to
be only half of what happened I
found over the years that
followed a deep sadness emerging
in my life, and I began to
realize that underneath all the
things I was doing, publishing
and writing and taking care of
my children and teaching, that
there was a sadness, a longing,
that I was suffering from a loss
of communion with the divine. I
was suffering from a loneliness
with the divine, and I basically
was just waiting to die. I was
living my life, taking care of
everybody, but in my heart, I
was just waiting to die so I
could return to my beloved and
years went on, and it didn't get
better, and I began to realize
that this is not this is not
good. It's not good living your
life waiting to die. It's good
to be completely fearless of
death, but it's not good to be
waiting to die. That somewhere
along the way, I must have made
a mistake. I must have done
something wrong. Somewhere my
life was screaming failure to
integrate. But because I had
taken so much care to integrate
each individual session, it
wasn't clear where my failure
lie lay. So I turned to find
where I had made a mistake, and
in time, I came to understand
that there was an imbalance in
my life. It was like I had
plunged myself so deep into the
transcendent divine that I had
lost my foothold in the manifest
divine. I had gone so deep into
the transcendent dimension that
I had lost hold of the other
truth. I mean, I knew it
intellectually, but I wasn't
able to live it fully. And that
is the truth of the physical
universe. And my being as part
of the physical universe is the
divine. The physical world is
the body of the Divine. So when
I began to see that the problem
was this imbalance between
Transcendence and immanence, I
made a decisive move to embrace
the my physical existence more
completely, to really by a force
of will and by a cultivation of
practices, to live my life as I
was in its incompleteness for
the remaining days on this
earth, and to recommit myself to
Being here inside time and space
on this planet and as part of
this process, and it took me
about 10 years to get fully
comfortable being inside time
and space again, which is maybe
one more reason why no one
should do the kind of work that
I did. You know, I hope that
people don't have to go through
what I went through. I think
maybe it's better to work in
smaller doses and more
incremental stages and make
maybe smaller progress, but also
hold on to more of the progress
that you do make in opening up
to Transcendence. But along the
way, I also learned that there
was a second reason for my kind
of estrangement or unhappiness,
and the second reason was what I
call the sickness of silence.
I'm a teacher. I love to learn
and I love to share what I've
learned, but because of the laws
surrounding psychedelic.
Colleagues, and because of the
our psychedelic phobic culture,
I wasn't allowed to talk about
what I experienced. I wasn't
allowed to bring my psychedelic
knowledge into the classroom. I
wasn't allowed to share it with
my colleagues. So the silence
which had allowed me to do this
work at this time in history was
also not allowing me to fully
integrate it into my personal
life, into my public life. I
integrated them privately,
psychologically as best I could,
but I couldn't integrate them
into my historical presence. I
couldn't be in the real world,
in the physical world, who I
knew myself to be in the
shamanic world. And in this
respect, writing diamonds from
Heaven has been a deep healing
process. To finally, now that
I've retired, and I retired a
little early in order to write
this book, but to finally be in
a position where I'm able to say
what I did, to say what happened
to me in these sessions, and to
share the experience of the
universe, and not that I think
my experience is in any way
unique or special, because it's
just I'm one person among a
whole psychedelic community
that's having all of these types
of experiences, but to finally
be able to be completely honest
and candid that this is what
I've been doing all these years.
This is who I am in my inner
life, behind my public persona,
of my academic life, that has
been very healing, and it's also
done some interesting things as
I've was working on the book in
the years working on the book,
and as I've begun to talk about
it, my psychedelic memories have
begun to congeal and to live in
me differently than They lived
in me before I was talking. So
just to be able to talk about
these things with you and with
other people has allowed me to
be more whole within myself.
It's like the psychedelic half
of my life and the physical half
of my life are coming together,
and something is happening,
something there is a deepening
of integration and a deepening
of transparency to spiritual
reality, and I don't know where
it's going to go. I truly don't.
I think in three years from now,
I could be in a very different
place than I am now, and I'm in
a different place now than I was
before I wrote the book. So I
think, you know, Pim Van Lommel
is a near death episode
researcher, and he wrote a
wonderful book on near death
episodes, and he says at the end
of the book that his experience
with people who have near death
experiences is that integration
can't really take place until
they can talk about their
experiences and share them. And
I think that's true with
psychedelic experiences too,
that at some levels, we can't
fully integrate our experiences
until we can share them. And I
think writing diamonds from
Heaven has been part of sharing
my history, hopefully that'll be
useful to other people, and
it'll support them in their
work. And as we go into this
intense historical period, so
there's been a birth of a new
joy, in a way, a birth of just
being able to be
who I really am, which is a
flawed human being who has had
some pretty unusual experiences
and loves to be in conversation
with other human beings who have
also had unusual experiences, so
that we can together see what
our experiences have taught us
about the universe that we're
in.
Simeon Mihaylov: Yeah, well,
Chris, your experiences and your
words are truly diamonds from
heaven. And I'm sincerely
grateful, and I want to express
your gratitude for for well, for
your courage to undertake these
experiences and to share them
and to speak about them, not
just to me, but to so many
people. And I know I can speak
for myself, and I know for
others that your work really
touches people's people's hearts
and people's lives. And I think
it's very important work. So I
really thank you on the behalf
of not only myself but the
greater collective. So I thank
you very much. Again, I really
don't want to take too much of
your day, but is there anything
that we didn't touch that you
would like to talk about? I.
Chris Bache: Maybe just one
piece, because I think there's a
lesson for me in this, and maybe
a lesson for others. I had an
experience in the 50th session,
which was the second diamond
Luminosity session, the second
time I was taken deep into
diamond Luminosity. And so this
was the deepest I ever got in
any of my sessions, into the
deep structure of the universe.
And I was in a place of
extraordinary bliss and joy, and
I had dissolved completely into
the boundary less condition of
just pure light, just hyper,
hyper. Clear, clear, clear
light, just so clear. And just
when I was at this peak of 50
sessions and all these years of
experience, all of a sudden my
entire visual field rotated 90
degrees, and a space opened up,
and I saw reality Far, Far in
the distance, filled with an
even higher form of light, and a
beam of light came out of that
reality and hit me, and it
absolutely shattered me, and I
realized at that point that the
journey into the divine, or the
journey into the universe, was
infinite. There's no end to it,
because, like many people, I had
thought that you did this work,
you took the journey in order to
get to the end, in order to get
home, in order to get to back to
source, become one with God, or
to dissolve into the primal
void. But I had become one with
the Divine, and I had learned
that there are many levels of
oneness, and I dissolved into
the void. And I learned that
there are many levels of of the
void to dissolve into. But this
experience showed me that even
using this extraordinarily
powerful method, I would never
ever be able to explore the
universe in its totality. It's
just so big, so vast, with so
many layers to it, such
wonderful expanse. And this was
this represented a fundamental
pivot. First, it just shook me
to the core to realize the true
expanse of what I was involved
in. And then it relaxed me into
into just a deep sense of
existential relaxation. And this
is why, if I were doing this
work over again, I would be
gentler with myself, because
I've learned that the goal is
not to try to get to some
destination, not to get to some
place. Because no matter how
hard I pushed, new doors kept
opening, and new doors kept
opening. Now I understand that a
better way to think about this
work is that we open ourselves
and we make ourselves porous to
the totality of life, and we let
in as much of this knowledge and
as much of the energy and as
much of the compassion as it's
possible. We let it in, and we
try to hold it and bring it into
our being and enter and become
more porous to it and open to
it. So it's it's not a process
of kind of going out and
exploring. It's really a process
of intaking, bringing it in and
and bringing it into the very
roots of our being. Let it
change not only our mind and our
convictions, but letting it
change our biology. Literally,
it reaches into and changes, I
think, us at very subtle
physiological levels that we're
maybe just beginning to
appreciate and haven't begun to
map yet. And once you understand
that it's not about trying to
get to the end of this road, but
it's really about becoming more
conscious and more skillful as
we stand between two realities,
one reality in time space and
the real, the reality outside of
time and space, the nurse in the
mother universe and the daughter
universe. We are in the daughter
universe. We are always
surrounded and infused by the
mother universe. And if we can
stand astride both worlds and
integrate the constant inflow of
the life from the mother
universe in increasing measure
inside the daughter universe,
then that kind of that brings a
an instantiated joy, an
incarnate joy, a sense of richer
and richer presence inside time
and space. We allow time and
space to become increasingly
trained. As parent to that which
created time and space. So I
would encourage a gentler, a
gentler psychedelic process, a
gentler entry into the great
expanse. And I would be I'm more
patient now with how long
spiritual unfolding takes than
maybe I was when I was a young
man. You.