Unknown: Given where we are,
given what's happening. And
maybe you've already said this,
you've already answered this
somehow, but given where we are
from the perspective of the
deep, psychedelic work that
you've done, you know, what does
it mean to be a good person
right now? What is it what does
it mean to be what does it take
you know, yeah,
Chris Bache: man, it's a large
question. I
I think of a half dozen ways to
answer that question pop into my
mind, and all of them are wrong.
So I'm kind of sifting through
layers. I
in some of my deepest
experiences, there are moments.
There are times when and even
after a session, but under the
influence of the learning of a
session, when something just
falls away, something opens you.
Earth, and I experience the
world truly as living and
breathing as one. I feel like my
feet are rooted in the earth the
way a tree is rooted in the
earth. I look down at the grass
and I feel complete continuity
of being between everything
around me and my own being. I
feel us breathing the same air.
I feel us all different species
sharing the same moment in time.
I feel the pulse of the universe
in its utter simplicity, not
paying attention to any of our
divisions of species or moods or
incarnations or anything like
that, the entire universe just
being itself, and I am part of
that in grateful it's not even
communion, because communion
implies a subtle duality, and
this is when all of that falls
away and a Great transparency of
being opens from within that
position. You
I experience an opening of my
mind, kind of a delicious sense
of presence. It gives me an
intimacy with grass. And then at
a deeper level, I experience an
opening of my heart in which the
idea of harming anyone is the
farthest thing from my mind and
the idea of helping everyone is
the most natural thing in the
world. It's not being good, it
just it's it's being alive
within this reality of oneness.
So to me, goodness is simply an
approximation. Or it's a, it's
a, it's a compass needle that
points in the direction of this
fundamental truth of oneness.
And the truth of oneness has all
these derivatives that flow from
it circumstances, but at
essence, it's very, very simple.
And I think compassion,
goodness, in that way, fairness,
justice, are all aspects of
oneness. Are all kind of fractal
manifestations of oneness. So
what does it take to be a good
person today? I think it takes a
willingness, a commitment, to
serving a collective good, to
serving a good that's not
private, that opens up to future
generations, that opens up to
people. People who are unlike me
and species who are unlike me
just an honest confrontation
with what is in order to bring
about a better life for other
beings. I know this is very
simple, but to me, goodness is,
is, is simple. It is, is that
simple? It gets complicated in
the enacting of it, but in the
at its core it it's an action
that comes out of oneness, and
if it's not coming out of a deep
grounding in oneness, then maybe
there's something not to trust
in it, because deep goodness
comes out of oneness. I think,
now I don't know if this really
addresses the depth thought of
which your question is coming,
because I understand the true
the true angst, not angst, but
the true kind of quandary from
which that question comes. But
the deepest answer I have in
response to it, I'm afraid, is
just a mystical experience, a
mystical experience of oneness,
in which that context goodness
just becomes an insignificant
component, a spontaneous
component, just like the way you
react when you see something
beautiful. It's just, it's an
arising. It comes up inside of
you. Goodness is simply an
arising that comes up inside of
you when you're in the condition
of oneness.
Unknown: I have a have a, maybe
a more sort of serious response,
and I have a more joking
response. And the more serious
responses is saying along the
lines of, like, what? What does
it what does it look like to
what does the dance look like?
You said, it becomes difficult
in the enactment. You know, what
does the dance look like
between, okay, having that
experience, because I've had
that experience, and I can tell
you fully 100% honestly, that
anywhere from 10% of the time to
99% of the time, I'm not there
at all. There's no sense of it
whatsoever in my experience, you
know, and I am and I'm not in
the ground of that as I'm as,
I'm as I'm showing up in the
world. And I'm wondering, yeah,
you know, in the same way that
also the playful response was so
we all should all take 500 mics
of LSD, right? No, no, in the
what does it look like to have
had that experience? Because the
way that you speak about it, and
I think naturally it makes
sense, like when you're there,
goodness just flows from you,
right? It is the most organic
and natural expression of being
in the world is when you're
coming from that place. And yet,
having a deep and profound
experience doesn't make you a
deep and profound person.
Experiencing oneness doesn't
mean that you now walk through
the world inspired and infused
in all your actions. You know
oneness just streams from your
fingertips, and every
interaction is a blessing with
the world from the depth of the
oneness that I have embodied
simply by taking enough
mushrooms to touch it once. So
what does it look like then? I
mean, maybe this is a question
around integration. What does it
mean to remember that, and what
does it mean to to catch
ourselves in forgetting?
Chris Bache: Yeah, that's that
is, you know, we we go up on the
mountain, we see some things, we
may be given some blessings, and
then we come down, and then we
have to go to work on Monday
morning, and that's over and
over again. It means a matter of
constantly engaging, being aware
of how you're engaging, checking
yourself, recommitting yourself
to doing a better job, over and
over and over again. For me,
much of it was in my work as a
teacher, constantly, always
enjoying it, always loving to be
with the students, always
wanting to do it better, but
constantly catching myself
making assumptions, making false
inferences, not doing a good
enough job, being a little
tired, letting my students down
on a particular day, coming back
and trying to do better, coming
do better. The next day, do
better, the next week, better,
the next semester, over and over
again, trying to live up to the
things that we know to be true.
So integration is a is a strange
term, I'm not sure. I'm glad
that the psychedelic community
is paying more attention to
integration, because it's
really, really critical. But and
there are dimensions and aspects
of integration, and the word
integrate carries us a certain
distance, doesn't, doesn't carry
us so far, but it's it's hard to
live our visions. It's hard to
live the truth of what we've
seen it because it commits you
to constantly being aware, if
you take the time to remit to
pay attention to yourself, how
bad a job we're doing at living
those truths. But that's just,
that's the nature of the beast,
though we just it's constantly I
mean, if we are, if we live
around people who are really
good, people who really have a
deeper natural instinct for
goodness and kindness and
generosity than we have. Then it
makes it easier to sort of face
our own shortcomings, because we
have someone that we can look at
and say, Ah, that person doing
this better than I do. So this
gives me a measuring stick. I
can do better. I'll do it better
tomorrow. I'll keep working on
it. And that's why, you know, in
the Buddhist tradition,
spiritual friends, people who
are also have committed
themselves to awakening. That's
really one of the great Sangha
community is one of the great
pillars of progress. So, yeah,
you're right. It's wonderful to
have the experience, but we
don't walk around in that state,
but we practice and practice and
practice and then maybe 10 years
later, we were in a little bit
more. 10 years later, maybe
we're in it a little bit more,
but practice and practice and
practice. And if we ever think
that we're really there, then
all we do is ask our young
children, and they'll remind us
that we're not really there as
far along as we think we are,
our our kids will set us
straight.
Unknown: Or perhaps, or perhaps
we could. I think it was a Baba
Ram Dass said, If you ever think
you're spiritually awake and go
spend a week at your parents or
something like that, so maybe
it's the other way around.
Chris Bache: Yeah,
Unknown: you.