Chris Bache: And all of a
sudden, my visual field pivoted
90 degrees, and I saw reality
Far, Far in the distance. Again.
It looked kind of like galaxies.
And out of that reality, a beam
of light came and hit me, and it
absolutely shattered me. It just
it was a more powerful light
than even the diamond Luminosity
that had become my ultimate
reality, 50 high dose sessions
in and just in that one second,
it completely changed my
understanding of reality.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Thank you,
Chris, thank you for being
willing to hop on with me.
Chris Bache: Glad to be here
today. Luke, cool, everyone.
Luc Briede-Cooper: This is
Christopher M Bache. He's a PhD
and professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he
taught for 33 years an award
winning teacher and
international speaker. Chris's
work explores the philosophy
philosophical implications of
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, especially
psychedelic states. And today,
we'll be primarily discussing
ideas related to his book, LSD
and the mind of the universe,
his story of 20 years of his
journey into the mind of the
universe through 73 high dose
sessions of LSD. Welcome Chris.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Luke,
it's good to be here with you.
Awesome.
Luc Briede-Cooper: So I thought
I'd figured I'd start by just
sort of tracing the path that a
lot of people may explore with
psychedelics, first being that
the first encounter people may
have, at least now today, is
they may encounter psychedelics
for biohacking or for
productivity, say, with like
micro dosing. And then once
they've experienced that, maybe
they'll discover the therapeutic
power of psychedelics. And then
in those therapeutic journeys,
maybe they'll discover that
psychedelics are powerful tools
for spiritual awakening. But
there's a level even deeper than
the level of spiritual
awakening, and it's the path
that that you took. Could you
tell us about that?
Chris Bache: Well, that path I
call cosmological exploration,
and it's a path which clearly
overlaps with the healing
capacity of psychedelics and the
spiritual awakening capacity,
but it's different. I think the
spiritual awakening basically
invites us to clean our
consciousness and clean our
system in a way that allows us
to abide more comfortably and
consistently in a transparent
condition, transparent to what
the Buddhists would call one's
essential nature, one's Buddha
nature, or other traditions
would call one's divine nature.
Cosmological exploration is
different than that. It really
is seeking to explore the deep
structure of consciousness and
the deep structure of the
universe, to basically
understand at a deeper
philosophical level, how reality
works. Why are things the way
they are? What are some of the
deep structures of cosmic
reality? Awesome?
Luc Briede-Cooper: And I'd love
to ask you more in a bit about
reality itself and those and
those layers. But could you tell
us a bit more just about what
the path, the sort of protocol
you followed, and what that path
looked like as he
Chris Bache: went along. Well, I
was just out of graduate school
back in ancient history in 1978
and I read Stan Grof first book,
realms of the human unconscious,
which had been published in 76
and immediately I recognized the
significance of Stan's work for
my discipline, which is
philosophy of religion. I'm not
a psychologist, not a therapist.
I've never been particularly
interested in the therapeutic
applications as Stan has, but
I'm really have been interested
in its philosophical
applications. So recognizing
kind of a call I began my work,
which ended up lasting 20 years.
I did four years of very intense
work. I stopped for six years,
and then I followed that with 10
years of very intense work. I
chose to work with high doses of
LSD, and by high doses, I worked
at 500 to 600 micrograms. This
is a regimen that I don't
recommend today. I seriously
don't recommend, and if I were
doing it over again, I would do
it differently. I would be much
gentler use, lower doses and a
wider distribution, a wider
spectrum of psychedelics. But I
chose to work with high doses of
LSD for couple of reasons. One's
first LSD, that was the
substance that Stan had done
most of his research on, and I
trusted that research. And
again, this was 1978 so this is
pre Ayahuasca, pre, some of the
early. Uh, appreciation of
organic and shamanic tradition,
organic psychedelics used by
shamanic traditions. And I, I
worked with high doses because I
was still thinking within a
model of personal
transformation, our personal
spiritual awakening, and the
spiritual traditions basically
taught that our karma is finite.
And if I understood LSD
psychotherapy as a process of
cleaning up one's karma, so to
speak, you know, basically
unearthing problematic material
from one's personal unconscious
and clearing that material, I
thought by working with high
doses, I could basically clear
up my karma in a fewer number of
sessions, essentially taking a
bigger bite out of the apple in
every session. Turns out that
that assumption was completely
wrong, because the assumption
that that the human psyche, that
this process was primarily
focused on human transformation
was a mistake, a personal
transformation. The collective
dimensions of the psyche surface
in my work very quickly on after
just a couple of years, and the
broader ramifications of
entering into communion with the
universe at large presented
itself soon thereafter. So what
I basically did, I worked in
therapeutic protocol. Stan's
therapeutic protocol outlined in
his book LSD psychotherapy,
which means working in total
isolation with a sitter, lying
down, eye shades, headphones,
carefully curated playlist of
music, staying internalized all
day long, I would work in the
early morning through to
evening, staying internalized in
the session, and then making
detailed records of my
experiences the day after. So
that was the that was the
protocol.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Got it
awesome. And of course, reading
the book, I know a little bit
about where that went in the
end, but I'm curious. So I know
in another interview, you
mentioned that you had since
partaken in Psilocybin and
Ayahuasca journeys, and at one
point in the book, you mentioned
that one of the advantages of
LSD being sort of a longer
acting substance around eight
hour journeys that it kind of
buffs the diamond more in that
time, so to speak. I know
there's other psychedelics that
are now entering the potential
use for people in society, and
Ibogaine is one substance that
has a very long active time
about like 24 to 48 hours. And
we could contrast that with like
five Meo DMT, which is an active
period of like 1520 minutes,
something like that, would
eyeball game potentially be a
better contender for that
reason, if not for cosmological
exploration, but for spiritual
awakening. And what might the
protocol look like if you were
to use something like five mu
DMT?
Chris Bache: Well, first of all,
I've never used Ibogaine, and so
I'm not really qualified to
speak to that in terms of
comparing its function or values
just looking at the window
issue. There are other issues
with psychedelics. Every
psychedelic has a mind
amplifying quality, but the
texture, or the nuance, the way
it opens consciousness, the
spectrum of consciousness that
it opens us into varies from
psychedelic to psychedelic. But
just looking at the window, the
reason I think the window is
significant, and this is
basically reflecting on people's
experiences with DMT initially,
which is a relatively short
acting psychedelic. And Rick
Strassman, in his book DMT, the
spirit molecule, basically found
that his his clients were not
really changed very deeply by
very having very significant DMT
experiences. And in looking at
his experiences in his data,
comparing it to my data, I think
what happens is, you know, in
order to explore the universe,
you're you're going, you're
using your small mind to explore
big mind, you're using your
individual, personal
consciousness to explore this
vast field of consciousness. And
when you have a long window, it
gives more time for the large
field to interact with the small
field and do the cleansing and
purification that's needed in
order to have deep experiences
of this cosmic reality. If you
have only a very short acting
psychedelic, you don't have much
time for the large consciousness
to impact and be absorbed by the
smaller consciousness, which
means it has less of an of an
activating effect, less of a
transformative effect. You.
There are other variables, of
course, in the
psychopharmacology of
psychedelics, but just the
window is, I think, an
interesting variation. The short
acting psychedelics have been
like five Meo are. It's a
remarkable psychedelic. It gives
us quick access if you use it in
high doses to very deep cosmic
realities, but our time there is
short. Again, I don't have a lot
of experience with five Meo, and
I certainly don't work with it
clinically with other people.
I've talked with a number of
therapists who work with five
Meo at different levels of
intensity for working with
clients. I know it has
remarkable transformative value,
but I not really too comfortably
comparing its transformative
potential with the
transformative potential of LSD,
other than to make this simple
relation between a time window
and opportunity for
transformation.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Got it
awesome. Thank you. Yeah, and
one of the things that stood out
about the book was how very, not
exaggerative. You know what I
mean? Like, it isn't you don't
necessarily go too far from the
experience itself, and maybe
that's your inclination as a
philosopher and academic, but I
really appreciate that.
Chris Bache: So I tried to just
truly, it's a huge challenge, of
course, to try to document or to
present 20 years of such
dramatic experiences. So the
choice I made was really try to
keep close to the phenomenology,
keep close to the experiences,
because the experiences were, to
me, much more valuable than
anything I would say about them,
any interpretation I might
offer, just the raw experiences
themselves.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Got it so I
got a question. Now you don't
recommend that people do what
you did. And reading the book,
initially, I was feeling
inspired. I was seeing your
courage. I thought, wow, this is
amazing. Maybe this is something
I could explore by the end. That
sort of shifted. But overall,
psychedelic, psychedelic use for
spiritual awakening is basically
inevitable at this point, at
least for many people in
society. So for someone who
might use psychedelics for
spiritual awakening and not
necessarily cosmological
exploration, what might you
recommend as a protocol or
structure for people who want to
do like a slower psychedelic
path, and how might that
integrate with the slow burn
traditions?
Chris Bache: Well, I'll make a
suggestion. But again, I want to
emphasize that I'm not a
clinician. I don't work I don't
have a history of working with
other people. I basically have
made a self conscious choice not
to work with other people, but
to be simply a solitary
explorer, pushing my system
hard, making basically a map of
the dimensions that I entered
into, but I don't that doesn't
give me a lot of experience
working with other people to
answer your question. But
basically, as I've read the
literature and process my own
experience for spiritual
awakening, I would recommend
very low doses. Basically,
spiritual awakening is about
dissolving the glue that holds
the ego in place, dissolving the
structures that keep us fixed in
these repetitive patterns of
thoughts and emotions. And so
you've got to kind of ferret out
the ego where it lives in the
world. And I think this is done
well with low doses of LSD, low
doses of LSD combined with
sustained meditative practice,
once in a while, doing more in
order to challenge the
boundaries of consciousness. But
basically, if the goal is
spiritual awakening, I think low
doses of a psychedelic would be
the way to go.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Cool,
awesome, awesome. Thank you for
that. Something that was
interesting that I think some
people do get a sense of from
their own journeys, whether or
not they've had just a few over
time, is there, there seems to
be a kind of effect of having
just the right amount of
experience as they needed at the
time. In that journey, you
experienced something similar in
in your journeys, in your book,
could you tell us about like
that sense of guidance?
Chris Bache: Well, in all of my
work, I always felt myself
engaging and being engaged by a
larger consciousness. This
consciousness did not take
concrete form. It never took
personified form. It never took
concretized form and it changed
or the core. Qualities of this
consciousness change the deeper
I went, so that I began to
understand the way I think of it
is the consciousness that we
enter into communion with in
psychedelic states, is an
infinite consciousness that's
capable of generating any number
of different types of
experiences, or types of
awareness within us and our mind
acts as a seed catalyst, a seed
crystal that catalyzes a certain
set of experiences from this
infinite consciousness.
If you do this repetitively over
repeatedly, the experiences that
you have and you integrate,
internalize and go through the
various purification processes,
it changes your consciousness,
and therefore the consciousness
that you take into the next
encounter is a different
consciousness that catalyzes a
deeper set of experiences from
the infinite potential of
consciousness. And that means
that the what you experience as
this guiding intelligence, the
this massive intelligence that
you meet at different levels is,
in a way, a consciousness that
arises at the intersection
between your individual mind and
this universal mind, and as you
change, the intersection changes
so that, from my experience, the
consciousness, which I felt was
always guiding my sessions, was
always invisible To me, but was
always felt it didn't adopt
concrete form, or very seldom
adopt concrete form, because the
form would change as the
experiences deepens. So you know
that formless quality is, I
think, something innate to do
with the consciousness itself,
and then in going beyond the
collective level of
consciousness, between beyond
the collective psyche and even
beyond human history. When
you're pushing so deep, you're
going beyond Jung's category of
archetypal consciousness, you're
letting you're going beyond
human history altogether, all of
the interpretive frameworks, all
the images, all the concepts
that we associate with our
religious and spiritual history,
they just fall away. Basically,
if several 1000 years or five or
10,000 years of religious
history just fall away and
you're moving into states of
consciousness that go beyond any
category of gods or deities or
angelic beings, you're in a
completely different world. So
yes, always guidance, always an
intelligence engaging me, but
formless.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Yeah, yeah,
amazing, amazing. I have yet to
get to that level in my
particular journeys, but perhaps
some day. And I'd like to ask
more specifically about sort of
the forms that can appear,
partly because I know from
YouTube, a lot of people are
searching that I can see the
analytics that entity encounters
is a very popular and
interesting point of
conversation. And you mentioned
you explored a little bit more
in the book, and you speak about
how devotion is related to these
entities. But let me ask this,
like a guy I was speaking to an
integration circle in Victoria
here not too long ago, he
mentioned he had a mystical
experience where he encountered
none other than Ganesh, the
elephant god of Hinduism. And
when people have these
encounters, they may ask a
question that you asked in your
journeys, which was, you know,
what is the meaning of what I
experienced? So, for after your
journeys, how would you reflect
on sort of the meaning of
encountering, say, a particular
form of a deity or or something
like that?
Chris Bache: First of all, let
me qualify. I don't consider my
experiences normative, you know,
in any generalizable way, you
know there are so many different
medicines, so many different
ways of using those medicines,
and so many different
personalities that are using the
medicines to engage this
infinite depth of consciousness
that it would be foolish to
think that any one person, their
experience would be a map or
chart for other people's
experiences. So I just I begin
my position is to be very
interested in other people's
experiences in a very non
judgmental and supportive way.
So whatever I say here, please
take it in that context. Uh,
when we experience realities
that are beyond us or
consciousness dimensions of
consciousness that are beyond
our own, and when we're tapping
into those qualities that are
like infinite compassion and
infinite intelligence and
infinite creativity, these are
qualities that we tend to
associate historically with
various deities, and it's not
surprising that our mind would
put together the qualities of
the phenomenology of the
experience with the qualities of
the deities which we may or May
may have had experience exposure
to intellectually and sometimes
we counter deities that we
haven't they're not part of our
own personal lineage and may not
have been part of our they may
not have been something even
that we knew about. It comes
completely out of left field,
and yet it bears the form of a
culture's form of this deity
like Ganesh or Jesus or Mary or
the Prophet Muhammad or
something like that. So my
understanding of it is that when
you are working or when you are
engaging, entities or forms that
have this quality of an entity
that is identifiable in our
historical traditions, my sense
is that we are engaging a
collective thought form, or a
spiritual being that is wearing
the clothes of a collective
thought form. And by collective
thought form, I mean if you have
millions and millions of
devotees that meditate and pray
and offer devotions to a
particular deity, form which has
been identified in their
scripture, which is painted in
their culture, statuary is all
of this form. If you have
millions and millions and
millions of being over 1000s of
years, in devotional attachment
to these forms, or devotional
focus on these forms, I think it
creates a certain structure in
the collective psyche, a
collective thought form. And I
don't minimize those forms, I
think they're extraordinarily
powerful, including secular
thought forms like greed, power,
anger, those you know, very
powerful in our system. So when
we encounter the deity in a or a
deity in a particular form, we
are either encountering a
spiritual principle which is
beyond form, which is wearing
the form of this collective
garment, or we're experiencing
the collective garment straight
out in itself. Either way, the
collective psyche is implicated.
The collective psyche is part of
our experience, which is all
perfectly normal and perfectly
well and good. I think at the
same time, I would hold out that
it is possible to go beyond all
collective thought forms and to
go beyond human history in one's
experience, and when one does,
those forms tend to fade away. I
know there's a lot of discussion
of entities, because
particularly DMT and DMT
derivatives often expose people
to entities. And I'm not
suggesting that those entities
aren't real or the entities
don't exist, but to me,
personally, and again,
limitations, but personally,
those entities reflect different
levels of reality, that as you
go deeper those level that that
kind of granular quality of lots
of individual beings tends to
yield to levels of reality which
are less granular, fewer
individual beings, kind of
constituting the population of
those levels of reality and
opening up into vast tracks of
consciousness which are less
individual, less entity, like at
least it is, in my experience,
Luc Briede-Cooper: got it
awesome? Totally, yeah, that
definitely seems to resonate in
terms of it being sort of a
matter of levels, and after
seeing sort of where you go in
those levels, it makes a lot
more sense that at some point
even those dissolve and become
something different. So speaking
of levels, you mentioned that
there's sort of a transition
that you make, and relatively
quickly, I think you said two
years for a young person, maybe
that's a lot, and that one of
the transitions that happens is
a sense of. The Journey, sort of
being about yourself, to being
to be about the individual, to
being about the collective. And
you speak about Well, I'll let
you speak about it. And part of
that transition, certain things
became obvious to you, and one
of those being the sort of fact
of reincarnation and past lives.
And I'm curious, could you let
us know, sort of what the
different levels were and how
your experience changed as you
went up or deeper into them?
Chris Bache: All right? Those
are sort of two questions rolled
into one. So let me take the one
on reincarnation first and then
bring me back. If I don't come
back to the first question,
bring me back to it. Got it when
I finished graduate school and
was beginning my academic life.
Two people's work changed my
life. One was Stan Grof, and
that's what we're talking about
today. The other person whose
work changed my life was Ian
Stevenson, professor at the
University of Virginia, who is
the Charles Darwin of
reincarnation. He basically has
generated the data. He's tracked
down the data small children who
have spontaneous recall of their
former lives in sufficient
detail and that we can basically
exclude natural or physical
explanations for how they would
have these memories, and he's
done this in book after book
after book. So Stevenson
convinced me that reincarnation
was a fact of life, and he
convinced me before I was really
very deeply involved in my
psychedelic work, but that
concept was affirmed and
expounded and deepened as my
psychedelic work deepened. So it
was already part of my
intellectual furniture, but it
just I began to understand it
more and more deeply as we went
now, in terms of levels. Again,
I was working at very high dose
levels. So you can count it in
terms of years, or you can count
it in terms of sessions. It took
me about 10 sessions to go
through what Stan calls the
perinatal level of
consciousness, which is that
level of consciousness which is
right at the interface between
personal consciousness and
Transpersonal consciousness,
where they overlap is this
level, which is at the one hand,
the basement of the personal
psyche and the doorway into
spiritual reality. So that one
goes through many experiences of
death, experiences of sometimes
reliving your own birth,
confronting all your anxiety
about whether there's anything
good in reality beyond physical
existence, tremendous
existential pain, quandary, and
eventually this culminates in
ego, death. And so the ego is
shattered, and you're
transcended. You move into
levels of consciousness that go
considerably beyond anything
that could be explained in terms
of your personal history. It was
at that point when I was
expecting actually to be get
granted, more comfortable access
to spiritual reality, what I
found was that the entire
Death-Rebirth cycle repeated
itself again, but this time at a
completely different level. I
began to have tremendous
collective experiences,
experiencing collective rage,
collective anguish for a long
this went on for another two
years and another 10 or so
sessions to another 12 sessions.
In the beginning, I thought this
was simply another variation, a
deepening, of ego death. I was
still thinking in terms of a
personal model. I thought that
somehow this collective ego
death, this collective death,
represented a deepening of my
personal death. But in time, it
went on for so long and it
lasted for it was so the content
of the experiences was so
inherently connect collective
that eventually I came to a
different conclusion, and that
is the conclusion I came to, is
that the patient in these
sessions wasn't me personally,
but in some way, the patient had
become my human family, the
collective species of humanity,
and that I was being drawn into
collective Coex systems that
held the pain and suffering of
human history, that just as my
individual psyche collects my
individual trauma in Coex
systems, the memory of our
species collects its collective
trauma. Lama in these vast
collective COIC systems that I
call them meta matrices, so that
eventually what I came to
understand took me a long time,
because this was so paradigm
breaking, and it was so foreign
to and it sounded so arrogant,
that somehow something I was
doing in my sessions was somehow
impacting the the psyche of
humanity. Mean, my God, that
just looks like megalomania. But
it's not that. It's simply
following the natural course of
the deepening of the
Death-Rebirth cycle, so that it
churns at the personal level,
and in my case, then it churned
at the collective level for
another two years, and
eventually it culminated in this
orgy of of pain and suffering,
of the ocean of suffering. And
then it spun me into archetypal
reality, and it the collective
the ocean of suffering never
returned after that point, it
just stopped. There were still
very intense purification
processes to come, but this
particular quality of collect,
this collective ordeal, stopped,
and I went into a whole nother
cycle of death and rebirth. So
yeah, that's basically the the
driving force behind my book,
dark night, early dawn, is
basically to understand the
relationship, or why, why these
collective experiences were
showing up in my therapy. When I
thought I was individual
therapy, what were all these
people doing in my therapy?
Turns out it wasn't that at all.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Right, that's
funny. Oh, and also, for people
who don't know, Coex system is
termed from Stani Grof and is
sort of the collection of
biographical traumas, going down
to perinatal traumas around
birth, and then going deeper in
the Transpersonal in that stack
of that pattern, stack with a
similar feeling tone, is a Coex.
So then the meta coexist,
interesting concept.
Chris Bache: Thank you for the
clarification a system of
condensed experience, an
aggregate that's compiled of
many experiences and memories
and fantasies around a
particular theme, around an in
the individual so meta matrices
suggest that the same dynamic
happens at the collective level.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Yeah, got it.
Do you relate that to the idea
of ancestral healing? Or maybe
that's different, actually, than
sort of like family trauma,
Chris Bache: interesting, uh,
variations on a theme, aren't
they? Both of them are trans
individual, ancestral still is
working within the lineage of
the individual, some type of
biographical lineage, right?
Whereas, I tend to focus, I
mean, I haven't done a lot of
work with ancestors in the work
that I've done, so I don't want
to presume to be able to speak
on that area. For me very we
very quickly I go into the soul,
reality. And the soul, of
course, jumps historical
lineages all over the place the
soul is. We've been every race,
we've been every culture, we've
been every occupation that's
available through history. So to
me, it broadens out very quickly
into the human story, the human
family. But other people have
had an experience of working
with their personal trauma,
ancestral trauma, you know, in
that kind of directed, linear
fashion. And so, yeah, I think
there, there should be some
relationship between what I
experience as these meta
matrices of human trauma and
what other people experience as
ancestral trauma gatherings at
an ancestral level.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Yeah. I
wonder if maybe the difference
is so the soul capital S, soul
being the collection of your
experiences, of your awareness
across multiple past, all your
past, reincarnated lifetimes. I
wonder if maybe the it speaks to
a differentiation between like
biological trauma and passed
down, also socially passed down
from parent to child. Maybe
that's sort of where that comes
from. And then the soul is like
a different thing. I don't know.
Does that resonate with you?
Chris Bache: Potentially, here
it does. And I think one day we
will understand this much more.
I mean, we basically are right
at the edge. We're collecting
the phenomenology the
experiences, but actually
interpreting this complex, new
complex of experiences is going
to take some time.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Yeah, got it
totally right. Interesting
question. So you mentioned
species mind and coming into
this call. Ocean of suffering,
of collective pain. Where do
animals fit into this?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, of
course, many psychedelics have
very powerful experiences with
animal species, with the various
totems of various species. They
have powerful experiences of the
planet filled with the minds of
these species, not just the
individual species, but the
minds of these species and
aggregates of mammalian mind and
so on so forth. That hasn't been
the thrust of my experience. The
thrust of my experience has
really been working with human
consciousness, but the nature of
my experience of human
consciousness completely opens
me to the reality of animal
consciousness in all sorts of
different forms. I think the
reason I've been focused on
human consciousness, for reasons
not of my choosing, just count
being driven at a deeper level,
is that humanity represents the
greatest danger to life on this
planet. We are the We Are The
Life destroyers. We are the
driving force of the Sixth
Extinction. If we can heal
humanity, then all the other
animals, all the other mammals
and life forms on the planet,
will be safe. And that has been
the focus of my work. Seems to
have been vocally focused on
that human story. Other people
have been retrieving the
consciousness story of other
life forms, even rock life forms
and insect life forms and animal
life forms, bird, fish life
forms, absolutely important
work, essential work, it just
hasn't been my personal work.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Yeah, got it?
Yeah. It's very interesting, and
maybe it's that I read this
book, levels of energy by David
Hawkins. I don't familiar with
it, but basic point is, he uses
a method to, in his framework,
identify a number to the level
of consciousness, or the level
of energy of a being or an
object or a mineral or whatever,
and he and interesting enough,
like a bacteria, lands on the
scale somewhere they're very low
three or something I don't know,
and I don't know what might come
first is the acknowledgement of
the consciousness of, say,
animals and working our way
down, or the acknowledgement of,
say, consciousness above us. But
it seems either way, it sort of
they, they, yeah, make the other
aware, something like that.
Chris Bache: Let's imagine that
there are as as many levels of
consciousness as there are,
quote, below us, simpler and
simpler and simpler, you know,
moving all the way down through
the evolutionary tree. Imagine
that there are that many levels
of consciousness above us, and
that we're not, in any way, the
top of the chain, but we're
maybe somewhere in the midpoint
of that chain totally.
Luc Briede-Cooper: And an image
comes to mind of, I think you
mentioned at the end of the book
of the idea that an ascension of
us in consciousness is sort of
like a pulling down of something
from a higher level. And I
thought, Oh, hey, how does that
work? For like, like, our our
tissue cells, like, if they
they're sort of reliant on us in
some way, and we're also reliant
on them, and there's this, like,
bottom up, top down
relationship, but so I'd love to
ask you speaking about levels
again, I think we touched on
breaking through to archetypal
what you the best language you
could find being archetypal
reality, and something you
mentioned experiencing at that
Jump was a shift in your sense
of the realness of everyday,
ordinary life and ordinary
states of consciousness. I'm
curious. Did Did your sense of
reality change continuously? Did
it change in certain jumps, or
maybe just that one jump? And
how did your sense of reality
shift?
Chris Bache: My sense of reality
changed repeatedly at different
levels, when everything was said
and done, when I was processing
all the experiences and trying
to organize them in some form,
to present them and share them
with other people, I
differentiated five different
levels, core levels of
consciousness, personal mind,
collective mind, archetypal
mind, causal oneness, so the
causal mind and then diamond
Luminosity overlapping levels,
and it's somewhat arbitrary
where you draw the lines, but
basically those divisions so
that the jump from personal.
Consciousness into collective
reality was a significant jump
into it's like, this is how
reality is organized at a higher
altitude, right? And then when
that culminated and I was spun
into reality, into arc, what I
called archetype of reality,
this was a quantum step into a
still deeper modality of
consciousness. And in this, one
of the striking features was I
repeatedly had the sense over
this next year and a half of
work that I had entered a
reality that was more real than
time and space, and I was
dealing with phenomena that were
more real than my personal
existence inside time and space,
or even time space itself. And
this, of course, touches on an
ancient idea that we trace back
to Plato, that there are
structures. He called them
archetypes. There are arche
structures that in create and
inform time, space, reality, all
right. And he conceived these
structures as eternal ideas in
the mind of an eternal
unchanging ideas in the mind of
an eternal Deity, an eternal
Divine Principle. That's not how
I experience them. I experience
them as living entities, as
moving in time, but on a
completely different scale of
time. So an analogy that came up
in my sessions, if you think of
the earth spinning around real
quickly, and then spinning
around the Sun pretty quickly,
but then you look at that in the
context of the galaxy, which is
moving incredibly slowly, but
vast. It's always moving. And
inside you have the sun moving.
It's kind of like that
archetypal reality. These
archetypal beings, to the extent
that I was able to experience
them clearly at all, were vast
living structures on a
completely different order of
causality, in a different order
of time. I could not I could not
wrap my mind around them. I
could not see them cognitively
coherently. I experienced this
enormous living intelligences
and the best my mind could do to
give them some type of
representation was to see them,
ask galaxies. So we've all
looked at the Hubble telescopes.
We've all looked at these
galaxies. We've seen the
pictures we if we really sit
with them and meditate them, we
understand more deeply what
we're looking at and these
things are billions of light
years across, containing
billions and billions of stars
and so on so forth. That's what
my mind did, just to frame this
experience in some way. But I
could not penetrate beyond that.
They were just too big and too
foreign to me to give them form.
At a lower level of archetype
reality, I entered what I would
call sort of a Jungian level of
archetype reality, where I
experienced repeatedly the human
psyche and the human species as
a single organism, a single
integrated organism. And I
experienced networks, physical
and mental networks connecting
this organism, kind of like the
neurology of this organism. And
I was shown repeatedly how the
individual is hardwired and
soft, wired into this matrix of
consciousness of the species
mind and the species mind how it
informs our individual
consciousness, and how our
individual consciousness reaches
out and informs and structures
future species consciousness. So
I saw things like each one of us
carry a holographic, fractal
piece of the diseases of our
time, of the mental diseases, of
the physical diseases, and as we
heal ourselves of these mental
and physical diseases, we
actually contribute to the
healing of the collective
psyche. So the collective
psyche, in a sense, you would
say it's more real than the
individual psyche, but I would
give it maybe a little different
vocabulary. The individual is
real, the collective is real.
They have different kind of
scales of their reality, and
they are mutually implicated in
each other, and both of these
are transcended by the platonic,
archetypal levels of reality,
which are radically beyond our
human. Collective psyche, yeah,
perfectly understood, yeah. From
that point on, from archetypal
reality and beyond, everything
was about going into deeper and
deeper levels of what is real in
the world. And we're not used to
thinking of physical reality
being on surface real, and that
there are structures that are
more deeply real. But I think
that quantum theory is
comfortable with that. String
theorists are comfortable with
that we should be able to be
comfortable with that in
psychology.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Got it? Yeah,
I was just going to say
perfectly understood. Can
visualize it perfectly,
understand completely. But
there's something really
intuitive about it that
resonates. And actually, people
do have experiences of a sense
of degree of reality sometimes.
So just sticking to the reality
point, just for a minute,
there's, I don't know if you
ever heard of this, but there's
this condition called
depersonalization, de
realization disorder. Now, as a
disorder, it's relatively rare,
but the experience of de
realization is something that
that, I think, something like,
upwards, more than 50% of people
at some point in their life
experience at least a moment or
something of de realization. And
that dpdr, the acronym is, of
course, a like a DSM mental
illness. There's also the
condition schizophrenia, which
has some kind of interesting
relationship to mystical visions
that Carl Jung noted, and at
least psychedelics themselves
can induce or worsen
schizophrenic cysts, symptoms
and the visions that people
might have in schizophrenia can
overlap with sort of the visions
people might have with
psychedelic stuff. So there's a
there's a connection there
between there's some kind of
connection there. I'm just
curious if your sense of just
bouncing off those, if your
sense of mental illness has
changed after your journeys.
Chris Bache: Well, that's a
complicated topic, isn't it? And
better answered by someone with
psychedelic experience who is a
clinical psychologist or a
psychiatrist, who has much more
training than I do in pathology
and in our psychological makeup,
it has changed some was it
Huston Smith who said a mystic
learns to swim in waters that
the psychotic drowns
Luc Briede-Cooper: in? I think
that was Joseph Campbell, I
believe, yeah, yeah.
Chris Bache: So what's what we
have in common is opening up
into a reality that is beyond
the private reality or the
personal reality, we open up to
a larger expanse of reality,
which can be very destructive if
you're not ready for it. It can
be very injurious. It can be
very traumatic. It can be very
tumultuous. It can churn things
up inside of you, just opening
up to collective dimensions. And
that's why I really like all
psychedelic therapists, I
emphasize the importance of
accessing these dimensions and
very carefully controlled
circumstances with therapeutic
support. You know, when you go
into them, and this is work
that's not not advisable for a
wide range of people. I mean,
this is not necessarily, it's
not universally safe. It really
depends upon a lot of variables.
There are screening criteria
which have been developed to
help screen people who are good
candidates for working with
psychedelics and those who
aren't. Nothing unusual here.
It's just part of the regimen.
I'm less interested in trying to
refine my understanding of
disease and pathology, other
than in very broad senses,
understanding that people can be
having legitimate access to
Transpersonal reality, but in a
way which is fractures or
injures their ordinary their
ability to function in the
ordinary world. What I'm more
interested in is differentiating
those confusions, those kind of
lower level confusions between
individual experience and these
larger planes of reality from
those breakthroughs where we
begin to enter these larger
horizons, but either because our
original equipment was
sufficiently strong or because
our methodology is sufficiently
rigorous and focused. We don't
experience it as traumatic. We
don't experience it as
confusion, confusing. We
experience it as clarifying, and
not the clarifying of an
illusion or a delusion, but
truly, truly, metaphysically
clarifying, so that these be.
Become great spiritual and
philosophical initiations into
the deeper fabric of reality,
the sensation of that
experience, I think, is very
different than the kind of
tumultuous confusion that can be
generated in a in a pathological
context, yeah.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Got it
totally Yeah, and yeah, when you
get to the collective level,
then it becomes something very
different. So that's so thank
you for that. You mentioned the
sort of five levels that you lay
out that there's the personal,
the collective, the archetypal,
the causal oneness and the
diamond Luminosity. And just
curious, if you could take us up
through to those levels. I know
in another interview, you said
you hate that question, because
it's so challenging to talk
about. I don't press you too
hard.
Chris Bache: We've gone into
archetype of reality with the
collective dimension. And that,
in my experience, what happened
was, after about a year and a
half, which is 1112, sessions,
not very much time. I mean, it
really wasn't a lot of time,
because this is a reality.
Archetype of reality is so vast,
it's so huge, that I basically
kind of went through it very
quickly, not experiencing the
breadth of it, but just
penetrating through it pretty
quickly, and then entering going
through yet another death and
rebirth, kind of dying out of
the greater real into an even
greater, greater real this
letting go of another level of
set of assumptions and entering
into a year of tremendously
powerful experiences, which I
kind of grouped together into
this category of causal oneness,
because that when you when you
first enter Transpersonal states
of awareness or first enter
spiritual levels of reality, our
experiences there are highly
conditioned by our Time space
experience, so that in time and
space, we all exist as separate
individuals. So when you move
into spiritual reality, you
often tend to experience
spiritual reality as composed of
separate individuals, but
they're without a body. They're
just but they have that granular
quality of individual psyches or
individual souls or individual
entities. If you go deeper into
from psychic level to subtle
level of reality, using Stan
Grof categories, the units of
consciousness become larger,
you're still in levels of
consciousness which are
dualistic in the sense is more
than one of you present. But the
cons, the the entities are
become increasingly large, so
that it becomes species
consciousness, or earth
consciousness, are angelic
realms, they become just very,
very large. So you move from a
level of consciousness, such as
highly conditioned by time,
space consciousness, into a
deeper level of consciousness,
which is less conditioned by
time, space consciousness. And
then when you move into causal
level reality. The distinctive
quality of that is that the
entire universe is experienced
as a single organism. Now there
oneness is a core, core truth,
of course, and it it manifests
at many different levels. I
don't mean to over
differentiate, you know, these
levels and suggest that it's a
it's literally climbing a ladder
of consciousness. But my
experience is basically unfolded
in this kind of fashion. When
you experience the world as one,
it's it's not like experience
intuiting the oneness of life.
So that's part of it, but you
literally dissolve into the
universe as it appears to be
experiencing itself, and as the
universe experiences itself at
that level, there are no
separate objects. There are
separate there are gradations
and differentiations, but all of
those start taking place within
the tapestry, within the matrix
of oneness. And that's what I
mean by causal oneness, that I
entered into a reality that I
experienced as being, in some
ways, beyond the archetype,
beyond those divisions in which
I experienced the world as a
sea. Painless fabric of reality
and all other realities, Star
realities, Galaxy realities,
personal consciousness
realities, collective psyche
realities, all took place as
organs within this larger
oneness. In that context, I had
experiences of deep experiences
of what the Buddhist call
Shunyata, emptiness, emptiness
of form, transparency, where the
experience, the way it's put in
Buddhist scriptures, the Buddha
awoke, you know, in his
meditation and saw self, no self
in himself, and no self anywhere
in the world. So the way we
usually experience the world is
composed of separate entities,
and we are one of those
entities. But when you
experience the world in the
causal perspective, you don't
experience yourself as a
separate self, and you don't
experience a separate self
anywhere in the world. Now, what
is the world if there's no
separate self in it, no separate
molecules, no separate trees, no
separate life forms, it is a
living, thriving singularity, a
oneness and a one organism. So
there were experiences of that.
There were experiences of cosmic
love. And love, of course, is
the, in a sense, the emotion of
oneness. When we experience
love, we are experiencing the
emotional counterpart to the
fact of oneness, experiences of
the void, the primal void out of
which the universe arises in the
Big Bang. And experiences for
part of me at this period was
the birth of the diamond soul,
which was a long lesson where
reincarnation is taking
humanity, where is this singular
consciousness taking this little
bitty species on this little
bitty planet in this little
bitty solar system. That's what
I mean by calls a reality, the
fundamental, a deep, deep
encounter with the oneness of
life. And then for me, after
about a year and a half at that
level, I went through yet
another Death-Rebirth process,
which is, it's not ego death
again, it's it's not collective
ego death. It's a deeper layer
of dying and being reborn. And I
was brought into states of
consciousness, which I
experienced as being hyper,
hyper, hyper, hyper, Crystal,
clear, clear, beyond
imagination, just clear.
Experiences of light, but I had
known light, you know, many
times up to this point, but this
was an exceptionally clear form
of light, Mark, just striking. I
know I'm saying the same word
over and over again, but that
was the quality. It's like my
ordinary mind felt gauzy and
shadowy compared to this, even
collective mind and even
archetypal mind felt like
shadows compared to this, which
was clear beyond imagination.
Over the next four years, I
entered this state only four
times. So in 26 sessions, I
entered this reality only four
times during in between those
real in between those four
sessions, lots of episodes of
cleansing, lots of episodes of
healing and purification.
Purification, because if you're
going to maintain clear
cognition at these deeper levels
of consciousness, you must go
through a purification process
that allows your entire system
to acclimate to the levels of
energy and the levels of reality
that you're entering and so it's
it's just a natural course that
I've discovered that every time
I entered into a deeper level of
reality, I was entering into a
higher level of energy, and so I
had to go through this
purification process, otherwise
my experience at this new level
would not be clear. It would not
be I would not be able to
remember my experiences clearly,
and you literally have to train
yourself. I know this a little
off the point, but you have to
train yourself to maintain
cognitive coherence in these
deeper levels of reality.
Otherwise, you may get glancing
insights, or, you know, short
glimpses here and there, short
touches. But your mind in order
to truly stay that this reality
for hours and hours at a time,
you have to go through this
deep, transformational process.
So for me, I went into the
diamond Luminosity and went
deeper into it for two of these
four sessions, and then things.
Changed. I had a particular
experience, and from that point
on, things changed. I wasn't
going deeper into diamond
Luminosity. The diamond
Luminosity was crunching itself
more and more deeply into my
physical body, into my mental
body, into my psychological and
emotional body. And then I had
one last, what I consider one of
the last big visions of my
entire journey, and then it was
wrapped up two more sessions,
the universe has kind of wrapped
it up, and said, sayonara, since
see you so
Luc Briede-Cooper: Wow, amazing.
And the breath of life, the
expansion, the contraction. You
see that in your journey, it's
everywhere. And one of the two
thoughts, one of the striking
things that I took away from the
book personally, was the shift
in understanding of
ineffability, and that different
levels being hard to find
language for is a matter of
stabilizing and familiarity and
not necessarily a complete
inherent lack of understanding
that. So that's one takeaway,
and then the other one, maybe
even a bigger one. I just opened
up a page to the book here,
where you mention it is one
small little section called
Beyond the diamond Luminosity
and the humor of the failure of
language, you know, going from
clarity beyond clarity to all
capitals, hyper clarity and
beyond the light of all light,
better than more light than the
other light, going to absolute
light. And you're understanding
that this points to there being
more than just there, being like
infinite number of levels,
potentially as being the
takeaway from that.
Chris Bache: Let me say
something about that, because it
does it that did represent as
major turning point for me. So
setting the stage. I'm now 15
years into this journey, I've
gone through the ocean of
suffering. I've gone through ego
death. I've gone through
archetype of reality. I've gone
through lots of experiences of
causal of reality, and then i i
get dropped into this communion
with this infinitely satisfying,
clear diamond Luminosity, what
Buddhism calls Dharmakaya, the
clear light of absolute reality.
So I get back into that the
second time, which is the 50th
session. Second time I'm in that
reality. I'm as deep into the
universe as I've ever been
before, I couldn't ask for
anything more than I was being
given at the time. And all of a
sudden, my visual field pivoted
90 degrees, and I saw reality
Far, Far in the distance. Again,
it looked kind of like galaxies.
And out of that reality, a beam
of light came and hit me, and it
absolutely shattered me. It just
it was a more powerful light
than even the diamond Luminosity
that had become my ultimate
reality, and just in that one
second, it completely changed my
understanding of reality in that
I had adopted the belief from
multiple sources that there was
an end point to this work. You
know, you want to get to the
goal. You do this become one
with God, or to dissolve into
the void, the primal void of all
existence. And I had become one
with God in many different
variations, and I had entered
the primal void, but I I still
had this sense that there was an
end point to this journey, and I
was pushing so hard to get to
the end point. I don't know what
was I was expecting to be
waiting for me at the end point,
but I knew it was going to be
good. And what this session
showed me was that it is an
infinite universe I'll never get
to the end of it. It's just too
vast, too huge. And it's 50
sessions in, 50 high dose
sessions in and I was shown this
glimpse of a reality far, far
beyond anything that I would
reach in this lifetime. And at
that point, I let go completely
of the idea of reaching a deeper
or an end point reality, and it
changed into trying to absorb
the reality that I was being
opened into as deeply as I
could, into my into my personal
being. So yeah, that was a major
turning point, and that's one of
the reasons I would if I were
doing this over again, I would
be gentler with myself, because
one of the reasons I was pushing
so hard was because I had
adopted a false belief. There is
an end point. Now I should be
careful. There are homecomings.
You go through experiences of
coming home, and there's a
tremendous sense of return and
tremendous sense of ecstasy and
joy of Homecoming. But even
those, I don't think they are
not ultimate. At least they're
not. In my experience, they are.
They're markers on longer
journey. And that's why I would
be gentle. I would have a
different orientation for what
the purpose or what the value of
these exercises are
Luc Briede-Cooper: totally,
totally and I think my shift in
understanding through the book
too. Also, that one paragraph
changed everything for me in
similar way. I thought, yeah, I
want to reach the end point too.
And then that changed that so.
So I guess following that
thread, coming back down the
mountain, as you've gone through
these experiences, you had a
vision of the future and of the
of what may be coming in the
future. And could you tell us
about what that was like, what
that looked like, and how that's
evolved for you since, I know,
since you published the book,
The covid pandemic happened.
Chris Bache: Yeah. Well, this is
not so much coming down the
mountain, but still climbing the
mountain. It actually started
when I was in the end stages of
the ocean of suffering work.
When I was in the chapter the
initiation of the universe, I
started being given visionary
initiations into the human story
and the stages of human
evolution, and in particular,
the story that I was being
initiated into was the story
that humanity was coming to a
turning point in its
evolutionary development. It was
coming to a major transformative
pivot that would change the
nature of life on this planet.
And I just had a series of
visions over four years in the
early to mid 1990s of what I
call the visions of awakening,
was that the that there was an
historical process that was
trying to awaken not just
individuals. It was trying to
awaken the entire species. That
was the historical work at hand,
a transformation that was truly
collective, a transformation not
simply of our psychological well
being or some levels of
psychological truth, but a
transformation of the
fundamental plate tectonics of
the art of the collective
psyche, the archetypal structure
of the deep psyche, was in the
process of undergoing a
revision, a transition. So this
for four years, these visions
kept coming into me, and this
completely surprised me,
because, again, I was at the
tail end of thinking this. My
work was about personal
transformation, and yet these
visions were consistently about
collective transformation.
Nowhere was I shown how nature
was going to pull off this
transformation nature, or
divine, or whatever you think of
it's the driving force. How are
we going to undergo this
profound transition that I was
being shown? And then in 1995
when I was in the middle of the
diamond Luminosity work, and I
had entered the diamond
Luminosity twice, and it had
that experience we just talked
about, I'd done a year's worth
of more purification, and I was
expecting, given the rhythms of
what had gone on before, I was
expecting to be taken back into
the diamond Luminosity material
again. But that's not what
happened. What happened was,
first I dissolved radically into
the species mind. I'd gone into
that territory before I had
learned how to go through this
process. So I dissolved into the
mind of our species, and I
ceased to function as Chris
Bache and I began to function in
somehow. I know this sounds
extreme, but in somehow, I was
functioning as the species of
humanity. At some core level, I
had become the human species.
And then I was also I was taken
deep into deep time. I'd gone
into deep time many times
previously. This took me deeper
into deep time than I had gone
before. And basically in that
session, I experienced the death
and rebirth of humanity. I
experienced a global crisis that
we were coming into, and I
experienced it at. Species will
experience it. It didn't give me
the details. It didn't tell me
when, where, how, exactly it
told me. It showed me the fact
of this crisis. It showed me
that we would make it through
this crisis, and it gave me
certain key insights in how of
the mechanisms of transformation
that were involved in this
crisis, but basically what I
experienced in this session was
humanity coming to a turning
point in its history and a
profound unraveling, a deep de
construction of reality as we
had known it, an undoing of all
the assumptions that we were
making, it seemed as if this was
a global systems crisis that was
being driven by a series of
ecological crises at the time. I
should say this is 25 years ago,
right? I didn't know. I knew
next to nothing about the global
systems crisis. I didn't know
about ecological crises. I
didn't you know this was I was
totally naive about these
things. But what I experienced
was humanity came to a point
where we basically lost control
of our lives. We were not able
to control the reality of our
lives. We basically were on an
extinction trajectory, and just
when it reached its peak, we
went through a threshold, and
the danger began to subside, and
we began to, as it were, pick
ourselves up on the other side
of this years, decades, long
series of crises, and when we
picked ourselves up and when we
began to reorganize ourselves
after this crisis, we found that
we had been profoundly and
deeply and permanently changed
by this crisis we had, it led to
we were changed at the core
level of our essential psyche,
of our of our collective psyche.
This crisis opened up our heart
to one another and opened up our
mind to the universe in a way
that was collectively
unprecedented, and as we began
to interact in this post crisis
reality, there was a synergistic
feeding off of patterns and
trends and feeding back and
forth All circulating around new
values, new perceptions of the
good, new understandings of
life, new understandings of
ourselves, new understandings of
the universe, new capacities
that were opening within the
human heart and the human mind.
Then in the 70th session, one
that what I refer to as this
last visionary experience. I was
taken deeper into deep time and
given one last Coda on this
trajectory. But the net result
of all of this is that I came to
see or what I was being shown,
was that humanity was in the
process of giving birth to its
next evolutionary form, to the
next higher form of being, a
human being. And if you ask,
what is the form of the future
human? What will the future
human look like? I think the key
is understanding reincarnation.
This refers to another series of
lessons that I was given where I
was shown experientially,
personally and experientially,
where reincarnation is taking
humanity, where are we going?
And this was different than the
Eastern traditions that I had
assimilated in graduate school
that that vision is you grow and
you grow and you grow and you
change. You achieve some type of
spiritual breakthrough to your
individual essence. You know,
Atman is Brahman. We are divine.
And when you have that spiritual
breakthrough, you achieve what
the Hindus call Moksha escape,
which means you escape Samsara.
You no longer have to be
incarnated. You achieve
realization, you achieve
enlightenment, and then you
enter parin nirvana. You leave
the physical universe behind.
What was paramount in my
sessions was not that. It was
the vision that we grow and we
grow and we change and we grow
and hopefully more
compassionate, more
understanding, more talent, so
on, so forth. But there comes a
time. Well, the way I understand
reincarnation,
we die, we expand to our soul
consciousness. We make a choice
to incarnate. We contract into
egoic consciousness.
Consciousness, we expand into
soul consciousness, come back
into egoic consciousness, and
we've been doing this for 10s of
1000s, possibly hundreds of
1000s of years. And if we do
that, sooner or later, soul
consciousness wakes up inside
individual historical
consciousness. So that my
experience was, I had an
experience where, at a critical
point in one journey, all of my
former lives started to come
back into me. And I had known I
had done, you know, past life
therapy. I knew a dozen or so of
my former lives in detail, but
all of my former lives started
to come back into me, and at one
particular point they seemed to
reach a critical mass, and they
there was an explosion of
energy, and this energy fused
all those individual lives into
a single consciousness, and I
was catapulted into a state of
consciousness that was
individual, but a form of
individuality beyond anything
that I had ever understood. And
I think that's what's happening
to us on this planet. We, and we
have been gestating the future
human for 1000s and 1000s of
years. We are about to give
birth to that future human in
history. In the century, I
believe gestation is long, birth
is very short, traumatic. I
think that we're entering a time
of history which is going to be
traumatic. It's going to be very
painful. It's going to be very
difficult, the way labor is
difficult, but I believe, based
only on my psychedelic
experience, that we do make it
through, and we are deeply
changed in the process. And we
grow up. We grow up into our
next evolutionary form, the
future human. And on those few
occasions in my sessions when I
was allowed to experience the
future human, they were deeply
and profoundly ecstatic
experiences, just totally
humbling and just, you know,
just a radically transform
humanity coming out of this
process. And I think that this
chapter, the birth of the future
human in the book, is the most
important chapter in the book,
because it if it's true, it
concerns your children, my
children, our grandchildren, our
grandchildren's grandchildren.
It concerns all of us, what's
happening at a very, very deep
level. And it also helped me
understand some of the
historical currents that were
taking place in this context.
Covid is, to me, it's like a
little shot across the bow. You
know? It's like a little
overture. It's not the real
symphony. It's just the overture
to the symphony. It's just, it's
a taste of how vulnerable we are
to deep and profound disruption
and how quickly the entire
structure of our society can
pivot. That's what we should
have. Should be learning from
covid and our interdependence
and how much we have to work
together to rise to the
challenge that's coming at us.
The challenges will be much
deeper than covid and much
longer lasting and much more
serious and life threatening, I
think.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Yeah, thank
you. Yeah, the vision is very
powerful, and I didn't have the
vision. I can't speak to it
directly, but there are
obviously signs of that
happening, you know, ecological
signs. And I know there's tons
of literature on systems crisis
and vulnerability, and we see
that financially, that's for
sure. We've seen that play out
when covid happened, one of the
things we saw here in Canada was
just toilet paper ran out.
Everyone was doing the rush for
toilet paper. A little hint at
what can happen, right? How
quickly it can happen. And what
comes to mind is the, I think
it's Chinese proverb, I don't
know. Maybe Einstein said it.
Maybe something, it was
something like, you know,
society will be good, or the
world will be happy when people
are willing to plant trees that
will only be seen by the next
generation. So the idea that it
seemed so intuitive, something
clicked when he said about the
souls fusing together, about
being able to understand and see
that we'll have reincarnations
in the future, and so we'll
actually be on this planet when
we die again. So something very
intuitive
Chris Bache: change, isn't it?
Yeah, American traditions of
making your decisions based upon
how they impact seven
generations, recognizing that we
will be those generations. So
the earth we leave is the earth
we inherit. Spirit, and it just
it broadens our sense of
responsibility. And grant
Ellison says this, basically, we
have to move from being a
species stuck at the adolescent
level to the mature adult level.
And when you're at the mature
adult level, you you look at the
broader impact across society
and through history, of the
decisions and the choices that
you're making. And my sense is
we no longer can afford to try
to run this planet based on
egoic consciousness. The culture
that we have created, the
history that we have lived, is a
history that has been created by
the ego. Now, I know the ego
gets a bad rap in spiritual
traditions, and I think the ego
is beautiful to me. It's an
exquisitely beautiful structure
of consciousness, but it's
fundamentally isolated. It
doesn't really experience the
deeper fabric of our connective
tissue we can no longer afford
to run this planet by or have
this planet run by human beings
who are operating only out of an
egoic level of consciousness,
because that inevitably creates
push pull, that creates wars. It
creates upper classes and lower
classes, those who have and
those who don't, the privileged
and the unprivileged. We need to
grow up. And we need to
basically grow up into our soul
consciousness, knowing that now
our soul ahead, we have
experienced lives as all the
races on the planet, all the
nations on the planet, all the
classes on the planet, all of
those are alive within us and
making our choices out of that
level of consciousness?
Luc Briede-Cooper: Yeah, can
only imagine what that would be
like. So I've, I've got
something for you, Chris, I've
got a gift for you, because that
when you you share the vision in
the book, I'll just read it, you
say, I saw the future human
standing up, and this seems
significant against the
background of many seated
Buddhas, this being was standing
upright. So you mentioned that
your form of art is writing, and
that's beautiful. Some people,
they use visual art, like Carl
Jung, for visualizing their
visions. Well, one tool that we
have available to us now is the
tool of AI art, where you can
put in prompts and receive
images and things. So I just
emailed to you just right now, I
just hit send an AI art image I
generated. Of that image as best
as I could represent it.
Chris Bache: I see it, yeah, I
see it. That's beautiful. That's
beautiful. Yeah. So my sense is
that in history, we've hit
basically the meditating Buddha.
The meditating Buddha, or any
meditating being in an awakened
condition, gets quiet and quiet
on the outside in order to still
the mind, so the mind can
penetrate through the layers and
touch the deeper sense of
reality. And a standing Buddha
is someone who incorporates the
clarity of that sitting monster,
but the dynamism of standing and
walking and acting. And I think
that's that's where we're going.
It's not about simply awaking
up. It's a waking up and acting
on that awakened consciousness
and bring it forward. Thank you
for that image. That's really
beautiful.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Yeah,
awesome. Yeah. It's a very large
scaled one, so feel free to do
whatever you want with it. Yeah,
awesome. So awesome. So we're
shifting more so I've there.
I've got some specific things I
want to ask you about two and a
half. I'm glad that we've
covered all this so far, because
now it contextualizes it. I'm
very interested in I love that
it's sort of bringing back
those, those concepts and
experiences, back down to here
and now, like on earth at this
level of consciousness and
operating here. And some of the
things that we contend with here
are the reality of needing to
operate in the world that we
have sort of traditions from the
past that we have handed down to
us. Edward was born in in this
life, and we see that there are
religions that we can certain
paths that we can follow, and
there's certain deities that can
be worshiped, and there are many
choices in how to how to
navigate this world. And that's
been a very strong question for
me personally, at least, and how
do I want to walk in life? Now,
I guess maybe the first question
is, so how is your understanding
of God and religion change
through your journeys, and how
might that relate to the lack of
one ultimate level and meta
coexistence?
Chris Bache: That's a big
question. Yeah, that question. I
need to drink some water. Yeah.
Yeah. Well, you know, I was a
religious studies professor, and
I started, I mean, I, my first
vocation in life was my, I
wanted to be a Catholic priest.
I was raised in the Roman
Catholic tradition, and I was in
the seminary for four years, and
the Catholic tradition treated
me well. I didn't get any
trauma. And it was, you know, it
was a good shake, but, and then
I did my masters. I did a
degree, undergraduate degree in
Theology at Notre Dame, and then
I did a master's in New
Testament criticism at
Cambridge. And then I did
philosophy religion at Brown and
by the time I finished graduate
school, I had pretty much
studied my way out of religion
altogether. I kind of had
recapitulated the transition
from medieval theology in the
Catholic tradition to the
scriptural Revelation, the
scriptural revolution in
Protestantism to the scientific
critique of religion in the
modern mind. And basically, I
finished essay pretty
sophisticated agnostic with very
high standards for any
possibility of conceptualizing
beyond something beyond time and
space, something approximating
God's dimensions. So I had let
go of concepts of God I and I,
since I had studied not just one
religious tradition, but I had
studied multiple religious
traditions, I began to
understand the common threads,
but also the differences in the
world religions. And I also
studied how religions came into
existence, and they say that
dogma is like sausage. You
really don't want to see it
made. And when you really watch
how dogma is created
historically, it's so filled
with human errors and human
foibles that you just don't want
to eat that kind of stuff. So I
had gone through that, and I
pretty much had scrubbed my mind
of all things having to do with
theology and deities and things
like that. And that's that was
the mind that I started the
psychedelic work. And what
happened was, of course, the
psychedelic work initiated me
into the reality that was behind
those concepts, and it took me
into the spiritual reality that
had given birth to these
approximations through history,
but it took me into it. On the
one hand, it led me to affirm
the reality of the deeper
intelligence that lies behind
the physical existence, but it
did not lead me to to affirm any
individual lineage of deity or
teachers and even collectively.
The nature of my experience was
to transcend even the collective
religious enterprise so that it
entered it drew me into the
reality, a reality of the
Divine, which is so far beyond
our historical attempts to
conceptualize the divine in
history that truly, you know, we
say I'm spiritual, not
religious. It's that's a trope I
know, but it's kind of like
that. I did not relate, and I do
not relate in any devotional
sense, to any of the religions
on the planet, while I respect
them enormously, and I
understand them and I respect
the polishing that they can give
human nature. My psychedelic
experiences took me in a world
beyond that world. So on the one
hand, I I affirm a divine
intelligence, while I don't like
the word divine, and that's why
I talk about the mind of the
universe, because I'd rather
speak in those categories than
in theological categories, but
that there is an extraordinary
Infinite Intelligence and
infinite compassion that gives
birth to existence and that
embodies that the physical
universe is the body of this
being, of this manifest being,
and there might be other
universes. And you know, our
universe is not necessarily the
only universe in existence, but
there are other universes with
all the levels and complexities
that ours has. So it's, it's,
it's a complex answer, isn't it?
It, on the one hand, it affirms
a spiritual reality. It affirms
divine reality. And I also don't
feel. People inclined to narrow
my love of this intelligence to
any historical religious forms.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Got it very
tough topic, 100% and I
definitely see the hesitation to
or not hesitation, the very
clear sense of not wanting to
start your own thing, bacheism,
the psychedelic path, what a was
doing that. And so there it's
interesting, one hand, people
speak about the meaning crisis
that we face in the West, that
scientific materialism is sort
of gras hold, and we've
completely wiped out any higher
realms from our sense of
reality, and in, you know, the
coming just challenges that
we're going to face, if that
culminates in a, in a in a
global crisis, as you describe,
or otherwise that we have to
contend with the world and we
need to navigate in the world
and a sense of meaning and
purpose and self understanding
as part of that leading up to
this future human we have
decisions and actions that we
can take as individuals, and not
everyone can. Can walk the
psychedelic path to necessarily
realize these things themselves.
How do you see people preparing
themselves or moving forward in
light of this understanding of
the Great Awakening?
Chris Bache: Well, you're
absolutely right. We are living
in a time of a crisis of meaning
because the materialism of early
science, not post quantum
science, but of early science,
which still tends to dominate
humanities and the social
sciences. Is a world that's
stripped of meaning. It's a
world that has no meaning, and
there is nothing beyond physical
reality, and physical reality is
seen as evolving by pure chance.
So there's no existential
significance your life has no
meaning associated with it.
There is no existential
significance to the challenges
that you may be facing
psychologically or physically or
socially. It's just pure,
random. Nature is blind, it's
violent. And I all my life, I've
been working with students at
university campuses, and that's
the philosophy that they've been
taught in all their other
courses. You know, that reality
to be real, you have to face the
meaninglessness of existence,
and then you push on from there.
That is one of the great values
of psychedelics, because that
psychedelics can pop that
bubble. You know, it doesn't
take too long to pop that
bubble. You know, give me one
weekend a month for one year,
and we can pretty much shatter
that so at least we can see that
there is a reality that's behind
the physical universe we can
experience, to some degree, the
intelligence of design that is
expressing itself in The
creative manifestation of time
and space, and the structures in
time and space, that's a very
powerful breakthrough. I think
that's one of the major
contributions that psychedelics
can make for us. Is not simply
healing us of our trauma and
healing us of our wounds, but
initiating us, initiating us
into this, on the one hand,
ancient and on the other hand,
new world view that the world is
alive. The world is saturated
with intelligence. And there's
layers and layers and layers of
intelligence. And we can commune
with this intelligence. We can
download from this intelligence.
We can, you know, enter into it,
just to, just to have this sense
that there is a purpose to life,
there is an intelligence
expressing itself. That's one of
the reasons why I think
reincarnation is so important,
because we have hard data that
reincarnation is true because,
you know, we have those verified
memories of our deep past, and
that tells us that gives us a
deeper understanding of what the
what might be driving the things
that we undertake in our
lifetime, that there is a hidden
purpose, a hidden project folded
into the details of our life
circumstance. This is just one
of the things that comes very,
very clear in past life therapy
by expansion, when we begin to
see the purpose, not only in our
individual lives, but the
purpose that's percolating
inside our collective evolution,
and the purpose that's behind
biological evolution, the
emergence of life, the emergence
of self aware life, and so on
and so forth. That gives us some
grounds for beginning to hope
that there is meaning behind
this crisis that we're coming
into, that this crisis is going
to be terrible. I mean, it's
going to be just terrible. Well,
this is not we're not going to
get through this easily, and I
believe we will survive it, but
we will not survive unchanged.
We will be deeply changed by it,
and to enter into this process
with this belief that somehow
it's all an accident and it has
no meaning, it has no
significance. Is a terrible,
terrible philosophy to take into
what's coming Now, having said
that the experience of the
meaningfulness of existence or
the the intelligence that runs
throughout all of life, that
doesn't mean necessarily that
our first or second or third
take on this intelligence is
necessarily correct, because
there's a sense in which just to
touch the enormous scale of
creation is a humbling
experience, and it tends to lead
you to hold on to your concepts
lightly, delicately, because you
know that your concepts are only
small approximations of
something which is much, much
larger than your mind is going
to wrap itself around. But just
to have the experience that
there is this power manifesting
itself in life encourages us, I
think, to live our life with
deep integrity, to live our life
with deep purpose, and to
actualize the purpose of our
incarnation as deeply as we can.
My understanding is that before
we incarnate, we choose our
incarnation, and there's lots of
research that suggests that. So
my sense is that every one of
us, every human being on the
planet now, chose the
incarnation that they are
currently living, right? And if
that's the case, then all we
need to do is do is do the best
we can with the incarnation that
we are living, and the rest will
take care of itself, right? And
I think that's a pretty healthy
way to engage what's coming at
us, to do the very best we can
and let the end results work
themselves out beautiful.
Luc Briede-Cooper: And of
course, immediately begs the
question, what is the best that
we can do? You know, although
there there's something
immediate about that, we have
things that immediately call us
in our in our environment. So
there's, there's definitely
something else to that. Okay, so
I hear what you're saying about
attaching ourselves to concepts
lightly and at the same time
with our practices, or spiritual
practices, we may have a
stronger hold on those as the
process, maybe not attached to
the meaning that we attribute to
the end goal or things like
that. I'd like to explore this a
little bit more specifically
too. And one of the ways that we
can that we confront the world
comes to a basic principle, as
far as I can understand it, is
that where attention goes,
energy flows. Is the idea you
mentioned earlier, that when we
sort of worship or give praise
to entities or say, collective
principles, that it can kind of
give rise to those as images in
the collective unconscious. And
the way I understand worship is
being like a it's like a
practice of of directing
attention to the highest value,
the highest good, some some aim
that you have, that you know,
whether that's nirvana or
whether that's creating the
kingdom of God on earth in
Christianity, or the Gnostic
image of separating from the
earth, sort of up and out image
that the Gnostics had. What the
worship does is it helps people
sort of realign their values and
their actions to maintain
themselves as they walk on that
spiritual path. And you know,
certain concepts become
devalued, and it sort of
maintains a structure of reality
with certain things having more
importance than others. Big
question, but how are we to
worship in light of the diamond
Luminosity and pun intended?
Chris Bache: Well, I'll tell you
how I worship. I worship the
universe. I worship the the
diversity of life on the planet.
I worship the manifestation of
galaxies and solar systems and
star systems. I worship, that's
what's I worship, the the
manifest abundance and the
unfolding complexity of life
itself, and I honor the hidden
drivers of this reality. And
you. You know, science is
telling us what 95% is, dark
energy and dark matter. 96% is
and dark energy and dark matter,
which we've never seen and we
really don't understand, only 4%
is visible in any realistic
form. So it's not that big a
stretch to think that the
universe is growing. It's an
unfolding out of an
extraordinarily complex and
infinite reality. So I honor the
man of the universe as the
manifest body of this
intelligence, and I honor the
intelligence which is
manifesting as this body at the
same time. So to me, you know,
the medieval cathedrals of
Europe were created in order to
you walk into them and they the
idea is they lift your eye to a
higher horizon, to a deeper
understanding. To me spending
time digesting the images that
were given to us by the Hubble
telescope and its successor.
Those are spiritual experiences.
Those are profoundly rich
spiritual meditations on on the
intelligence that's manifesting
itself as our universe. And then
for me, I I reflect on my own
experiences. I mean, I I can't
manifest the experiences that
I've had inside my time, space,
body. I wish I could, but I
can't manifest diamond
Luminosity in my daily, daily
consciousness. But I can
remember and I can meditate upon
and I can bring those
experiences into my mind, and I
can enter back into the edges of
those experiences as part of, as
part of a deepening of my own
living process, right? And I'm
also deeply moved by other
people's experiences of this
infinite intelligence. So that's
why I really enjoy reading other
people's psychedelic
experiences, because I don't
want to get trapped simply in my
lens, in my particular lens, I
like to see this infinite
mystery as it's experienced by
many different people, because
that enriches my sense of its of
its complexity.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Wow, wow. I
think I wrote wow, like 50 times
as I was going along. What comes
back for me is coming back to
the scientific materialism. And
maybe the an immediate thing
that that could happen is a
softening of our concept of
scientific materialism, and
hopefully psychedelics can play
a part in that. I do want to
mention interesting maybe
coincidence, maybe it's not
strong enough to be a
synchronicity. But for me,
reading your book, when you
mentioned Carl Jung a few times,
I thought, Oh, my God, no way.
And then you specifically
mentioned Carl Jung's, the Red
Book, which I'm in the middle of
right now. Just crazy. And then
you mentioned Richard Tarnas a
few times, and he and then he
specifically said one point he
mapped out history of the ideas
of Western thought. Lo and
behold, I'm in the middle of
Richard Tarnas is the passion of
the Western mind at the same
time, very interesting book, and
you realize just how immature
Well, recent, let's say
scientific materialism is like
300 years something scale of 10s
of 1000s. So that was a funny
coincidence for me. So if we can
wrap it around, psychedelics are
a tool, not necessarily for
everyone. How could we best use
psychedelics for spiritual
awakening in light of the coming
challenges that we may face?
Chris Bache: Well, I hope we use
them for more than spiritual
awakening. I think, for example,
the whole movement in the
psychedelic Renaissance towards
healing is really important.
Because for I think when I look
at human beings, I don't simply
see a human being. I tend to see
souls. And so when I look at
children, I don't see I don't
see young beings. They could be
very, very old beings in a young
body. And when I see old beings,
I don't necessarily see, I mean
old people. I don't see old
beings. It could be a very young
soul in an old body. And so I
tend to look at the qualities of
soul that are present in an
incarnation. And my sense is at
this particular time in history,
people are incarnating with lots
of former lives active in their
current life, and they're
incarnating with lots of
unfinished business at the soul
level. Alive in their life,
there's a sense and that means
that healing is a very important
contribution, not only to their
individual well being, but to
our collective well being. So my
sense is that we are incarnating
generations of pain and
suffering in this generation, in
these generations, and that by
clearing this pain and
suffering, we are clearing out
the whole system of all the
garbage of our leftover from our
egoic consciousness through
1000s of years of incarnations,
and we're opening up and
creating space for this deeper
infusion of cosmic consciousness
to enter into our lives. So
psychedelics can be a
significant part of this
healing. So that's the one
second if healing is allowed to
deepen, then it becomes a tool
of initiation into the
intelligence of the universe,
the intelligence that lies at
the very core of our being, and
it can psychedelics can help us
experience, even if only
temporarily, the truth of our
divine nature and the truth of
our inclusive nature, so that it
really is like we are all leaves
on a tree, and every leaf truly
is part of my being. And only at
the surface level does it look
like we are separate leaves, but
as a tree, we experience that we
are all implicated in each
other's lives, and so naturally
compassion arises, fairness,
justice arises out of that. So
psychedelics can help us deepen
and accelerate this process. A
whole separate issue is the
balancing of psychedelics with
spiritual practice which is non
psychedelic. I mean, I that's a
whole separate issue. I don't
think psychedelics by themselves
is necessarily a very wise way
to proceed. You need the support
and grounding and insights that
have been kept alive in our
spiritual traditions, our
meditative traditions and
contemplative traditions that I
think these two work hand in
hand, well with each other. So I
think those are maybe the most
important. One of the is the
hate, the accelerating of
healing and the deepening of our
insight into our true nature and
into the nature of the universe.
And then, if we want to push
farther cosmological
exploration, just takes that one
step farther into a conscious
opening to layers of reality
that lie beyond simply our
physical senses. And I think you
don't have to push it as far as
I did, to do a little bit of
cosmological exploration, which
can be very healthy and very
supportive. I think I just
pushed it so far, so hard it,
you know, it just, it becomes a
life defining project, and
there's no need for it to become
a life defining project for many
people. But I think psychedelics
have multiple layers of benefit
that they can give us at this
time. They can help heal us.
They can help us come to our
spiritual senses, and they can
help give us a sense of the
deeper mystery that we're part
of.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Got it
beautiful. Yeah, I'd like to
bring us back to just one little
point I kind of skipped over,
one little thought I want to ask
you about. And just coming back
to the the understanding of
there being infinite levels that
are higher and higher and
higher, or by Huston Smith's law
of inverse analogy, deeper and
deeper and deeper. How do we
align ourselves with the highest
if there is no highest?
Chris Bache: Oh, yeah, your
question, catches the paradox.
Doesn't catches the issue. Yeah.
Yeah, you know, let me, let me
give you. This is going to sound
a little off target, but it'll
be, it'll I'll focus it in. I
often think that the
relationship of physical reality
to spiritual reality can be
modeled on an apple, and
physical reality is the skin of
the apple, right? So, the entire
physical world and all the
levels is the skin of the apple.
And if you if an apple starts
and it's expanding, you know,
there's like the. The universe
is expanding and getting bitter.
The skin is getting bigger, but
the meat of the apple is
spiritual reality, and we have a
tendency, because we think of
psychedelics as mind expanding,
mind opening. And there is a
subjective sense that the
reality that we're entering is
bigger than our physical
reality. That tends to convey a
sense that spiritual reality is
bigger than physical reality.
But I don't think that's
necessarily an insight that
generates when you go deeper and
deeper, that sense of expansion
into deeper space changes. So
I'd like to give a different
metaphor. If you go underneath
physical reality, you get into a
layer of spiritual reality. And
if you go deeper in a deeper
layer of spiritual reality, you
start to drive towards the
center of the apple. And as you
drive deeper towards the center
of the URL the apple, of course,
forms fall away, because forms
are part of the emergence of
physical reality. And the light
gets brighter and brighter and
brighter as you drive to the
center of the apple is because
you're at the center is light,
and light eventually manifests
the green textures of the apple
skin, but in the end, it's
light. So you're asking the
question now, how do we orient
ourselves to the ultimate, even
knowing that the ultimate is
beyond our intellectual grasp?
And I think the key to that is
recognizing that the essence of
my life and the essence of your
life is fundamentally the same
essence. We all come from the
light. We are all fractal
embodiments of the light. We are
all evolving expressions of this
manifesting intelligence, this
self manifesting intelligence.
And at that very, very deep
level, my essence is the same as
the essence of mosquitoes and
ants and leaves and everything
on the planet. And that's why
when, when I go into a
transcendental state, that is, I
drop into selflessness, or
Shunyata, I experience the world
as one. And as the shamans would
shout out, all my relations, all
other levels of reality, all
other beings are my relations.
We're all kin in this planet,
even though we may not be able
to adequately conceptualize this
essence, individual essence, the
Atman, the Brahman, we can tune
to it. We can know it. We can
let it suffuse our being. We
can, we can let go of anything
small, which keeps us smaller
than it, and we can regularly
cultivate the practice of tuning
to it. And that's not that is
only partly an intellectual
exercise. It's, it's deeper than
an intellectual exercise. It's
more of a tuning exercise, and
that we can do even without
having an adequate understanding
of the final goal. It's just
like it's an enjoyment. There is
a sense of peace, there is a
sense of harmony. There is a
sense of Infinite Challenge, the
challenge of infinity, but
there's a profound sense of
alignment that comes about in
our person and in our
relationships, the closer we
draw to that reality. And we can
do all of that without having
any solid answers to what is the
nature of ultimate reality.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Got it. I
mean, not really got it, but I'm
glimpsing it that what comes to
mind is the distinction between
process oriented, say, spiritual
practice or religion, and then
goal oriented religion or
spiritual practice, is that
useful?
Chris Bache: There it can be. I
mean, basically one way of
putting that. We can live in a
world of nouns, or we can live
in a world of verbs. Verbs are
more accurate than nouns, right?
That's just one of the insights
that science and philosophy
gives us so we live in a world
of process, rather than a world
of objects, right? And it's all
process a human being is, is a
process which begins lives and
dies. You know? It goes,
consciousness goes, evolves and
completely, constantly changing,
constantly changing. Changing.
Neither you or I are the same at
the end of our conversation as
we were at the beginning. We've
been changed by this contact. So
it's all verbs. It's all process
Luc Briede-Cooper: and looking
noting the time. Maybe one
thing, one more thing on this
topic I'll just bring up. It's
just, it's just, this is what it
comes back to, at least for me,
is, you know, in in certain
scriptures, I just will pick
Christianity, you know, Jesus
says Not one word will change in
the Scriptures until all is said
and done. And other ones, Islam,
you know, worship no other God
but me or whatever. This kind of
exclusionary thing doesn't seem
to just be like a cultural
interpretation of it. It's like
right there in the core of the
revelation of the religion. I
don't know what do you make of
that? In two minutes,
Chris Bache: I understand I
understand it. You know, there
was a time in our history, not
that long ago, where religions
existed basically on specific
continents. They were just kind
of before the invention of the
steam engine. Religions existed
in a valley in a particular
landscape. There wasn't mass
migrations of populations moving
around. The religion was part of
a place. It was tied to a place.
And when you bump up against
other people in another place,
there is a conflict between how
your people see the reality and
how those people see reality,
and so the honoring the
integrity of the vision was part
of the process of people owning
their identity in contrast to
other people who have a
different vision and a different
identity. But of course, all of
this changed with the invention
of the steam engine, and then
with the invention of travel,
and then with the invention of
the internet. Now everything's
getting blended. And now, ever
since the 19th century, scholars
have been putting together these
amalgams of gathering the
world's wisdom together into
these massive compendiums of
trying to understand it all.
We're wrapping our mind around
the entire planet in that
context, I think what we
recognize is that what may have
been a virtue in the ancient
past now can become an
encumbrance. It can become a
limitation. So now, I think the
greater wisdom is in
understanding all of these
religious traditions
simultaneously, and
understanding that the part the
whole is greater than any of the
individual parts, and so that
the pattern of spirituality for
the planet as a whole is a
larger and more interesting
story than the pattern of
spirituality in one particular
tradition versus another spirit
another particular tradition.
Okay, so it's just a different
truth that comes forward in
different historical
circumstances. So on the one
hand, I recognize, I recognize
the sentiment that you
described, and I honor it as an
historical sentiment, but I
don't feel beholden to it. To
me, the greater challenge has
been to try to understand the
world's diversity of religious
beliefs and spiritual beliefs,
and then to, in my particular
case, to take the exploration so
deep that it radically eclipses
all of our human experience in a
larger landscape that emerges in
deep spiritual experience.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Wow. And just
to wrap it up, I'll just add I
got a sense of that. The first
thing I ever read that led me
down this deepening the
spiritual path was Joseph
Campbell and his writing about
exactly that, this global sense
of all the world's traditions.
Yes. So thank you, Chris, so
much. So much to meditate on.
Chris Bache: Luke, it's been a
pleasure. I thank you for the
conversation. Thank you for
giving me a lot of room to work
and for your very thoughtful
seating of questions. I
appreciate
Luc Briede-Cooper: it. Thank
you, and I hope that this and
other interviews will help you
in digesting your own journeys
and having the community finally
to share your experiences with
so I feel that I feel part of
the same community with you, and
I'm excited to see what you put
out in the future.
Chris Bache: These conversations
do help me in sharing is good,
and I hope they're useful to
other people, but they truly
help me too, because it it helps
me digest all these things.
Luc Briede-Cooper: Got it
awesome. Thank you, Chris. You.