Chris Bache: When one works with
very high doses of LSD, one goes
through a series of
Death-Rebirth experiences. In
this image, the drop at the
center underneath the line
represents our egoic
consciousness, our private
consciousness. Everything above
the line represents spiritual
reality. Transpersonal
consciousness, the first
Death-Rebirth experience takes
place at the interface of our
time, space consciousness and
the beginnings of spiritual
consciousness, and it's usually
referred to his ego death, it is
the complete destruction of our
personal time, space, identity
and the beginning of an opening
into spiritual reality. But if
we continue this process, if we
press deeper and deeper into
spiritual reality, we go through
more deaths, more cycles of
death and rebirth at the
psychic, subtle and causal
levels of consciousness. To use
terms that Stan uses. Now, I
have no vested interest in a
particular cosmological map that
delineates the various strata,
strata of Transpersonal
consciousness. Here, I'm simply
trying to make a point that as
you go into deeper levels of
consciousness, you come to
certain gateways, and at these
gateways, you must give up
everything, everything you have
known up to this point in time
in your journey, in order to
enter into the new fields of
consciousness that are beginning
to open to you. You.