Regina Meredith: Chris, hi
everybody. We're going to have a
phenomenal conversation in just
a moment here with Christopher
Bache, who I consider to be and
I know he'll be blushing if I
say this, but really a hero of
our times for being willing to
take on a journey that most of
us would not be able to
withstand, to find out about the
nature of consciousness, the
mind of the universe. In his
book, LSD the mind of the
universe, he shares with us his
experiences of some, I think, 73
different journeys he did with a
very prescribed protocol and
with someone sitting with him
and protecting him over decades
to be able to journey
sequentially further and further
out into what the future of
humanity looks like. So here we
go. Meet Christopher Bache, if
you don't already know him,
hello, Christopher. It's so good
to see you. How are you I'm
doing well, I'll tell you. I say
that very sincerely, after
reading your book, and the other
people who I know who've read
your book as well, the question
that comes up about halfway
through is, why in the world,
did he continue when you went
through that much pain, that
much suffering, enough that it
took months, even a year, to
recover from a journey, but you
would come back. You were
relentless in your search. So to
just set it up really briefly
for people, what made you do
this? You're a professor of
theology philosophy, what made
you go on this journey starting
way back when?
Chris Bache: At first, I think
it was a foolish strategy to
push it as hard as I did, but I
didn't know any better at the
time, or I was young and stupid,
but I was trained as a
philosopher of religion with a
passionate desire to understand
the deep structure of the
universe. I had studied some of
the great minds in our western
philosophical and Eastern
traditions. When I found this
methodology that Stan made
available, I just decided to
push it as long and as hard as I
could. And there was a great
deal of suffering on it,
episodically and periodically.
But at the end of every episode
of intense suffering, there
would be a breakthrough into an
episode of phase of deep,
ecstatic bliss and deep
Transpersonal encounter, and the
value of those insights and that
ecstasy balanced out, more than
balanced out, the transient
episodes of suffering in
Regina Meredith: the beginning,
when you first started the
journey, the very beginning part
was What you title in the book.
And it took you 20 years or so,
after all these experiences, to
finally write this book and put
it out for the rest of us. Was
called the death of the ego.
While you were in the midst of
it, you were saying, What was I
thinking? So let's just set it
up with what that very first.
And we only have about 45
minutes, people are going to
have to read the book
themselves. We're going to
hopscotch through the phases you
went through. But let's start
with what was I thinking? What
happens upon the dissolution of
the ego?
Chris Bache: If you want to
allow your consciousness to
expand into the broader
dimensions, the deeper
dimensions of consciousness, you
must surrender the narrow
bandwidth of your individual
body, mind, ego. And so this
happens slowly or fast,
convulsively or smoothly, but
that identity that we hold has
to be shattered, has to be kind
of destroyed. And when it's
destroyed, then your
consciousness does naturally
explain, expands into a deeper
register, a wider spectrum of
consciousness. If you do this,
if your journey continues
repeatedly, as we'll get to you,
go through many such death
sequences, but it's not
repeating the original ego
death. The original ego death is
kind of the first transition
from your time space identity
into a deeper spiritual
experience of the universe.
Regina Meredith: Thank you for
that. And on the subject of
death, as you come to say toward
the end of the book, you
relished the death process. By
the end, death was something you
looked forward to in each one of
these journeys, because it freed
you so much from all of the
constraints in terms of
consciousness, and so we'll
build up to that. But one of the
parts you went through was you
became a woman. You started
experiencing the life birthing
all these elements of being a
woman, which was part of your
identity, is to be a male, to be
an academic, and so forth, just
briefly. What was your
experience? What did that do to
you when you suddenly connected
with the female experience after
being male
Chris Bache: about two and a
half years into my journey,
about 1011, sessions and the
universe put me into the
situation where I could
experience nothing except. Up
from within feminine identity, a
feminine identity, and it was a
feminine form, a womanly form
that was the exact opposite of
my own male, academic,
intellectually oriented form.
And it was totally terrifying to
experience myself being me, but
not being me within a framework
that I'd ever known before, and
it just snapped me. And so when
I let go and I yielded, then I
became hundreds, potentially
1000s, of women, and was given a
journey into the world of women
under the arm of the great
mother. And it was an ecstatic
experience, a wonderful
experience. In fact, when it
opened, I thought, what was I so
afraid of? What was going? Why
was I afraid of this? This is
marvelous. And what was the
universe was doing? Was it was
basically teaching me that where
I was going gender does not
exist. So all gender, all roles
based on gender, and any aspect
of my historical personality had
to be surrendered if I were
going to experience more
intimately what is there in the
universe.
Regina Meredith: So I would ask
you this, on behalf of the men
and women watching this, what
was the most either terrifying
or irritating and difficult part
initially, of being confronted
with a woman's reality,
Chris Bache: the most terrifying
part in the beginning was it
just wasn't my reality. It was a
reality, but it wasn't my
reality, and I couldn't get out
of it. I was trapped within a
feminine mode of experience that
just wasn't me. There was
nothing inherently frightening
about it. And then when I let go
and flowed with that experience,
oh, what a it was like having
half of the human race open to
me that had not been open to me
before. Now I believe in
reincarnation, and I believe
we've been men and women many
times, so there's nothing
foreign in that way. This was
different. This was kind of
opening almost into, I don't
want to say, an archetypal
dimension of womanhood, but
certainly to the collective life
being lived by women in history,
in time. So the joy was just to
experience a whole different way
of being alive than I had known
as Chris Bache, as the
Regina Meredith: academic, as
the male, engaging in academic
conversation, and here you're
dealing with a very different
kind of connection and flow
between women. Yeah, I thought
that was fascinating. It's an
interesting part of your book.
Chris Bache: I wish every man
could have an experience like
this. It truly, it does change
things profoundly,
Regina Meredith: you know, and
the other way around. And women
should have the other so we
understand what each other is
contending with in our bodies,
in this reality. So let's move
forward to session 11, and this,
there much has happened since
then. Time has passed, of
course, but when we go into
session 11, it really becomes
about archetypal, deep mass
suffering that you had to go
through witness and experience.
And if you could tell us what
that body of, body of memory,
collective memory, felt like,
and what it looked like to you,
that would be helpful, because
we're still in it,
Chris Bache: my transition from
an ego death process, which is
very personal, related to what
came over the next two years. So
it's a series of excruciatingly
difficult, horrendous waves of
vast landscapes of human
suffering, war, violence, just
unimaginable suffering. It was
transitioned by an experience
called the killing of the
children. And I just want to
mention that, because it's an
important signal in between
those two, I had this experience
of being an old woman
confronting soldiers who were
just killing 1000s and 1000s of
children, just smashing their
heads on rocks, just terrible,
terrible ordeal. And I think
this experience was given to me
to prepare for me for what was
going to come, this ocean of
suffering phase that is, it
awakened a depth of compassion
in me, which I think was
embedded at a soul level, to
prepare me to take on the work,
which is something my soul had
chosen to do in this lifetime.
What I learned was that just as
individual trauma gets buried in
our individual psyche and can
compromise our individual
health, the trauma of history,
is buried in the collective
psyche of humanity. And so
anything which is not resolved
by the species, that any one
generation accumulates in these
massive memory structures that I
call metacoic systems. And what
I think was happening was that.
Something guiding my sessions
began to use my sessions in
order to confront, absorb and
transmute vast territories of
collective anguish that were
embedded in the collective
psyche, meaning the patient
stopped being Chris Bache, and
in some way, the patient became,
became some aspect of the human
species.
Regina Meredith: So with that, I
want to ask you about something
in that's happening currently.
We have all of this going on in
the Middle East between
Palestine and Israel, and we
have collective side taking. We
have collective anger,
depression, anxiety all
occurring, and we have a
propensity toward people who
have been have proclivities
toward prophecy. To look at this
as the End Times, whether it's a
Christian community wedding for
rapture, whether it's conspiracy
groups saying, No, this is a
planned end time for humanity,
we get into these End Times
stories that start circulating,
but I want to ask you, having
been through what you went
through, you have this overlay
to it in your psyche that I'd
like to know about. Could you
tell us how you see these times
laid into what you went through,
Chris Bache: jumping many years
ahead in my work and I
summarized my experiences of our
time in history, what's
happening underneath the surface
where we're going in a chapter
called The Birth of the future
human. And there I was given a
number of visions over many
years of humanity coming to a
turning point, humanity coming
to a spiritual breakthrough, an
evolutionary turning point, a
shift in the plate tectonics of
the collective psyche. And then
eventually, in 1995 was taken in
a very deep experience,
dissolved into the species mind,
dissolved into what I call deep
time, being taken into the
future, and where I experienced
a death and rebirth process of
the human family, altogether,
not as an individual, but the
death and rebirth of humanity.
It was a global systems crisis
that was seemed to be
precipitated by a series of
escalating ecological crises.
Now, beyond that, I wasn't given
any details about it. I wasn't
given dates. I wasn't given any
specific nothing about
artificial intelligence, nothing
about a third world war, nothing
like that, just the experience
of the human family going
through a prolonged period of an
absolute loss of control and a
collapse of everything they had
considered the normal and
necessary goods or our standards
of their world. Ever since that
time, I've lived with this
awareness. And for me, it's not
a projected fantasy. It's not
something which I envisioned.
It's something which I
experienced. So for me, I can't
I don't question the truth of
it. So I experienced this period
of history. That's a period of
increasing a destabilization and
increasing escalation of
conflicts and breaking down all
our norms and our norms and
conflict between races, conflict
between religions, complex
between conflict between sexes,
between classes, all the
tremendous things that we've
been doing to each other,
terrible things over 1000s and
1000s and 1000s of years. We
have to go beyond where we are
and grow spiritually into the
next form that's emerging, I
think, in an evolutionary sense,
in the human as the human form.
So I think this is what we're
going into. That's why we're
beginning to experience so much
destabilization. And I think
what's happening now is not, in
any way, a final or turning
point, or at any final register.
I think we're going we're in a
process which will continue to
deepen for decades and decades
to come. So this is, I think,
just the overture of what's
coming and the terrible events
unfolding in the Middle East and
other countries, in many African
countries, other places, in the
United States, these are
bringing to the surface age old
hatreds, and we have to
transform these hatreds. And I
don't offer any political,
social solution to the events
we're looking at. My perspective
is not at the ground level. My
perspective is from the level
far above the Earth, looking at
the long evolutionary trajectory
forms.
Regina Meredith: Thank you for
that incredibly thoughtful and
articulate answer. And now what
we'll do, because we did jump
ahead a bit there, which will
work our way back toward there
are some other things in there,
but let's go back now to session
number 15. Where you learned
about karma, because all of this
has karma embedded in it. You
learned about the essence of
karma. And tell us what you
learned about karma at that
time, I had
Chris Bache: already, I mean, I
was an academic, and I was a
professor of religious studies,
so I had an intellectual
understanding of karma, which is
simply cause and effect
generated by choices that we
make their physical cause and
effect processes. And there's
psychological cause and effect
processes. And in traditional
worldview of karmic thought,
every choice we make sets in
motion a series of events, which
eventually we receive the
consequences of. We receive the
effects of. And by receiving the
effects of our choices, we learn
from those choices, and we make
a new set of choices. What I
learned in session 15 wasn't so
much a theoretical
interpretation of karma, because
I had that. It was a seeing and
being shown the karma of my
particular life. I went through
a series of sessions for a year,
over and over again for seven,
seven sessions where I
experienced the entirety of my
life, from beginning to end, as
a happening, as a totality, as a
finished, complete totality. And
this is my first entry into what
I came to call deep time. And in
that context, when I looked at
relationships, my the
relationships around me, Thy
people. When I looked at the
issues that I was working with
in my in my professional life, I
could see how deeply embedded
they were in a deeper series of
karmic, causal processes, that
my position in history was not
accidental the people I was with
were not accidental. It was a
meaningful fabric. Then the
question became simply, how do
you respond most effectively to
a meaningful fabric that your
life is part of?
Regina Meredith: Okay, that
brings us to something that I
wasn't going to ask you about,
but it seems like the right
point you just spoke about,
every decision we make has an
effect. And so yesterday, two
days ago, a book was released by
Dr Robert Sapolsky, and it has
to do with the Science of Living
with no free will. The title
something like that, as I
recall. But essentially, he came
to the conclusion that there is
no such thing as making a
decision in free will, that
we're machines, and we cannot
lay anything that we do upon
ourselves any more than we would
any other machine. So I would
love for you to respond to that.
Chris Bache: Well, I haven't
read that book, of course, and
so no just came out, yeah. And
but that's a very familiar
position among my philosophers,
in my department, among
philosophers in general, and it
derives from a vision of the
universe which is based upon a
kind of a 19th century
metaphysics, which sees the
universe as a machine, as a
deterministic machine, and all
the parts are determined by the
larger movement of the whole,
and we have no freedom. But I
think that's a deeply outmoded
and outdated vision of reality.
We're now looking at a quantum
world. We're in a world which
values indeterminacy, that there
is a there's much more
flexibility and in the system
than we had previously thought.
96% of the entire of reality is
dark matter or dark energy, and
we don't know anything about it.
I think if we just step back,
it's clear that much of our
psychological life is clearly
highly conditioned, but within
that highly conditioned context,
we make choices, and the choices
we make can increase the
conditioning or it can reduce
the conditioning exactly, and we
can increase our freedom. But
nobody exists in pure, absolute
freedom, except perhaps the
awakened, the fully enlightened
beings. But we can increase the
freedom by skillful choices.
Regina Meredith: I hope you're
enjoying this video, because if
you are, there are dozens more
like it on my site, all
supported by people like you. So
if you'd like to keep this work
rolling in and join our
community, just click on the
Patreon button at Regina
meredith.com that also gives you
access to Insider commentary my
live book club and other live
events with special guests. So
join in. Thanks. I was very
disturbed, because the media
picked right up on this, and he
got a loud speaker off of this
one. I thought this is so
archaic and essentially saying
we have no self responsibility
either. Yes, we can't take
credit for the best of us, but
we also don't take credit for
the worst of ourselves. We have
no part in what we do as acting
as machines. I thought like you,
how outdated is this,
considering the quantum reality
that we're becoming aware of? So
one thing I wanted to read out
of your book, because your talk
is. Feeds into it, the notion of
us. We have a soul. We have
something that transcends this
physical reality, which that
author does not recognize, by
the way. So you in when at the
end of the karma, it says energy
started must simply complete
itself, and that's the nature of
karma. So then I go into this
area that I chose, where you're
defining the soul itself.
Because a lot of people wonder,
what, what is it I'm made of?
You know, at the most, the most
etheric, most, uh, sublime part
of myself, it says a story of
individual consciousness,
ultimately sourced in the
creative intelligence of the
cosmos, systematically moving
back and forth between the
physical universe and a surround
Metaverse in a long journey of
self development. I think that's
one of the best definitions of
soul, and the one I probably
relate most, relate most
strongly to in my own system of
understanding anything that you
care to add to that so people
can understand that this soul is
here for expansion, experience,
choice, and anything you'd like
to add to that, in terms of you,
what you came to understand is
what our soul is and what it's
here to do,
Chris Bache: just as we have a
center of integration that
integrates all of Our
experiences from this lifetime,
and we're not quite sure how to
describe that or what it is, but
it's we know what it what it
feels like, and what we can we
can understand it. The soul is
simply a center of integration
that integrates all of our
experiences from all of our
lifetimes and our times in
between our lifetimes. So it is
a center of integration that is
a learning system as part of a
learning system which is
continuously growing,
continuously expanding and
deepening. And if we ask, what
is the essence of what that
consciousness is? Classic
spiritual traditions have said
the essence of every individual
the soul is the essence of the
totality. Atman is Brahman. The
essence of the soul is the
essence of the Divine. For me,
the form, in my deepest
experience of the form of the
soul and the form of all reality
is light. It's light, but not
light, you know, not as we
experience it in the physical
world, a much more profound form
of light. It is light, but it is
light which is self aware and
learning over vast epics of time
and continuing to evolve as it
learns. And I think we are
coming in the time to have to a
transformation which is going to
change. I think we are actually
giving birth to the soul inside
time and space. That is usually,
we die, we expand to the soul.
We incarnate, we contract to
ego. We die, go, expand the
soul. And if we just keep that
up for a few 100,000 years,
sooner or later, I think the
soul, the integrated
consciousness we return to when
we die, manifest or wakes up
inside the individual human
being. And that's what I call
the birth of the diamond soul.
Literally wake up inside
physical existence. I think that
is the the challenge that we are
facing in this century. We no
longer have the luxury of trying
to run this planet based on the
experience of the of our the
psychological structure of
individual ego. The ego is a
magnificent entity, but it's
limited. It's cut off from each
other and from the larger
universe. We need to grow up
fast. And grow up in this case,
is to awaken to the soul that we
already are but we haven't
experienced fully inside time
and space.
Regina Meredith: Well, that's an
understatement. Yes, we do need
to wake up fast. And so now we
come to a point where you had a
session, and after that you did
not have another one for six
years. You quit for six years,
just briefly a synopsis of the
session, why you stopped for six
years, and what happened when
you picked it back up. Because
that's the fascinating part to
me.
Chris Bache: I stopped for six
years because my wife, who was
my sitter, asked me to too many
things were coming up out of my
sessions that were very novel
and disruptive, and she just
wanted the whole thing to slow
down, and she asked me to stop.
So I did, and then when I
resumed, I always knew I would
resume, and when I did resume,
six years later, I had my wife
support, and she continued to be
my sitter through all of the
remainder of my sessions. So it
was, it was kind of a husband
wife negotiation,
Regina Meredith: yes. And the
other part I found interesting
is that when you pick. Back up
six years later, you you're
being picked up at the exact
same spot you left off.
Chris Bache: That was striking,
because I was in the middle of
the ocean of suffering work. So
I was horrendous suffering six
years later, different period of
my life, different expectations
in different astrological
aspects. It my sessions began
exactly where it had stopped and
continued to deepen the ocean of
suffering for another year,
meanwhile, but in the ecstatic
portion of my sessions, when I
had stopped, I was doing this,
experiencing the whole of my
life, from start to finish.
Boom. Now I left all that
behind, and I was going into
subtle structure reality, and
being given a crash course in
cosmology, how the universe
works.
Regina Meredith: And then we
start going to lessons 2526 I
was absolutely fascinated with I
just I was trying, but I was
trying to read into it through
my own lens and filter of
understanding. And that was you
were out in the cosmos, and you
started encountering fast
beings, fast beings that were
almost like galaxies in of
themselves. And none of us have
ever seen this or felt this or
experienced this. Maybe just
give us a glimpse into what the
what seemed to be the makeup of
these beings. But the thing that
fascinated me was that you said
these beings live through
humanity, experience through
humanity, love through humanity,
Chris Bache: fill us in I've
often had kind of reservations
about that particular line in my
sessions, but I kept it in
because it's in my original
notes, when the ocean of
suffering came to a culmination
and exploded me into a deeper
level of consciousness. The
distinctive quality of this
level of consciousness is two
things. It was incredibly old,
ancient, ancient, beyond
anything I'd ever imagined
before, very, very old, and it
was more real than time and
space. So I was being catapulted
in what I eventually came to
understand as archetypal
reality, which is a level of
reality which is historically
exist before time and space
exist and contribute some of the
fundamental structures of time
and space. So the vision here is
that all of reality emerges out
of a primal one, which starts as
a void and manifest in the form
of the Big Bang. But in between
the one and even the Big Bang,
there are many gradations of
being many unfoldings that take
place of the Divine. Though I
don't like to use that word,
because we have so many
connotations of the Divine. I
want to go with but, and there
are many, many layers, and our
lower levels are sourced in the
actions of higher levels. And so
I was encountering these. I
don't know whether to call them
beings or principles, but vast,
vast beings and other people
have experienced them too,
because I think it's a universal
structure we're bumping into.
The very best my mind could do
to give it form was to see them
as galaxies, because I, you
know, watch the Hubble telescope
in the James Webb and we see
these galaxies that are billions
and billions of light years
across, so big we can hard,
can't even imagine them. And my
mind was using those images just
to give a picture to these
beings that were not galaxies,
but they have that massive
scale. And these beings were
part of the process of creation,
creating the time and space and
some of the structures within
Simon space. And far, far, far
down the line, we have human
beings. And the insight here was
that in some way, all of human
beings, and actually, all of
existence, was an expression of
the intentions of these deeper
cosmological principles and
cosmological beings. In some
way, I'm not sure that I got all
the pieces lined up correctly
there, but I do think that all
of human experience, male,
female, all versions of human
experience are aspects of a
species intelligence, and that
species intelligence is an
aspect of a planetary
intelligence, which is An aspect
of a solar system and a galactic
intelligence. And there is a way
in which this, these deeper
intelligences, manifest as our
lives, and they are experiencing
the world as as we experience
the world. And there.
Experiencing the adventures that
we are having as as we have
them.
Regina Meredith: So that would
bring us to the question then
that our experiences, and again,
we're looking at everything.
We're all watching this through
our mind, through an egoic lens,
all the filters of our past. So
each one of us is hearing this
the way we will hear it, but it
makes us wonder if we're kind of
the end toward the end result of
these vast systems of
consciousness, intelligence,
desire and creativity, how much
of what we're expressing in the
world is sovereign
Chris Bache: at all? Well, you
know, when I experience this
embeddedness in these higher
orders of creation. I never
experienced it in any way being
manipulative, and I never
experienced it as being
representing a compromise of my
individual agenda, individual
freedom. I experience this
downward flow of causation, but
as part of a profound, gracious,
compassionate, intelligent
process which was giving me and
all of us opportunities to grow
and develop that we might not
otherwise have. So it was it we
live in a conditioned universe
at levels upon levels upon
levels, and at the same time,
it's a creative universe which
is constantly manifesting new
levels, new things emerging out
of our fundamental deep
structure. And I just
experienced this as I was seeing
a complexity that had always
been there but I had not
appreciated before. So whatever
is happening has always been the
way it's happening. It's just
that we're beginning to be aware
of what's happening
Regina Meredith: that thank you
gives us, each one of us, we
could just go over this piece
over and over and try to get our
minds around the vastness of it.
Thank you for that, and also for
sharing that it was filled with
grace. I very much appreciate
that part of the story, and
another one we move on to, is
purification through
reincarnation. But we're looking
at groups of people, tribal
epoch. Periods of history are
involved when we're looking at
reincarnation, purification
through reincarnation as groups
of people throughout history.
Can you just talk about what
that looks like a little
Chris Bache: bit? Well, my focus
was not on groups of people, but
on all of humanity. When I moved
into the archetypal domain, I
moved into first and then get
counter with these cosmic
archetypes, and then I was
dropped down into what you might
call more of a Jungian level of
archetypal reality. Why I
experienced all of humanity
repeatedly as a single organism,
and I was shown, given many
lessons over the next year, that
each of our minds were like a
fractal spark within a species
mind, each of our bodies were
cells within an integrated body
of humanity. And so there was a
continuous flow back system
between from the whole of
humanity into the specificity of
each of us individually, and
then the choices that we were
making were flowing back into
the collective very similar to
Rupert sheldrake's Morphic
fields theory,
Regina Meredith: we tend to
incarnate during different
periods of history to purify a
previous period of history. But
we're doing it together, or
we're doing it as a species, you
know, and as almost soul and
tribal geographic groups.
Chris Bache: One of the things
that happened in this period is
that I began to experience, have
certain visionary experiences of
the entire human species
incarnating as a single
organism, and each of our
individual lives were cells
within that organism.
Previously, and I had written a
book on reincarnation,
previously, I had always thought
of reincarnation as the story of
the individual souls journey
towards enlightenment. But now
all of our I saw all of our
individual journeys an aspect of
its in collective journey. And
so what each of us were dealing
with was not just personal, it
was also collective. It wasn't
just this century. It was an
expression of something taking
place in a larger pattern. And I
think I was given this teaching,
which went on for a long time
years, in order to prepare me
for what was beginning to
unfold, which is this deeper
vision of where humanity is in
its evolutionary story, the
challenges we're beginning to
face, and the death and rebirth
and the birth of the next
iteration of human
consciousness, soul,
consciousness, diamond soul.
Regina Meredith: We're going to
get to the diamond soul in just
a moment. I just have one more
question I wanted to ask you
before. That, because this is a
big one for a lot of people
watching this, you had
assumptions about reincarnation,
and we all have assumptions
about everything. You were
learning, you know you're this
has been your life's path. Is
studying this, one of the things
many people watching this have
in common with what your
previous belief was, is that to
reach oneness is the end of the
road. The notion of oneness is
the end of the journey. Can you
tell us what you discovered when
you finally found that oneness?
Chris Bache: Oneness is a
profound truth. I mean, it is an
absolutely foundational,
profound truth, which is kind of
a seminal understanding that
runs through all the world's
spiritual traditions. It's kind
of a bedrock, because oneness
brings us in touch with our
essential nature, which is
underneath the variability of
our surface nature. Oneness
generates deep compassion. When
you have experienced oneness,
you are naturally going to be
gentle with everyone around you,
including yourself. You'll be
compassionate beyond measure.
And to experience oneness is a
profound step in our spiritual
journey. But I don't think it's
the end step. Sometimes the end
step is described as dissolving
into the primal void that
precedes even the manifestation
of the physical universe. But in
my experience, even that is not
the end step.
Regina Meredith: Should I give
one comment that you made? You
said it does not exhaust all
cosmological truths,
Chris Bache: yes, yeah. And
oneness is a profound stage in
our development, but the
universe has been evolving for
13 point 7 billion years. It's
going to continue to be evolving
for billions and billions and
billions of years. An individual
and a species awakening to the
truth of oneness, that's a
profound turning point for that
individual in the species life.
But evolution continues.
Challenges continue. It's not
simply that we achieve oneness.
We awake and become spiritually
realized. Then we leave the
planet, we leave the system and
go into some type of off planet
paradise. We oneness is a
profound stage in our journey. I
would start sounding like
science fiction. If I were to
try to share some of the things
that I've been shown about the
magnificent being that human,
humanity is evolving in,
Regina Meredith: please go
there. This audience is open to
science fiction, the
Chris Bache: future human, which
I think we are given the process
of giving birth to in history,
the form I've described it as
the birth of the diamond soul.
This is a the future. Human is
not simply a human being with an
open heart, a healed heart and
an expanded heart which holds
the entire world and compassion.
And it's not just an open mind
which is able to take in and
enter into deeper communion with
the intelligence of the cosmos
and incarnate that intelligence
within their own being. But it
actually transforms the
fundamental physiology of our of
our body and our sensory
experience. We have a tendency
to have a mechanistic
understanding of sensation. The
eyes, light comes in, brain
processes, senses, touch. It's
kind of very mechanical. But in
my experience, in the sessions,
it's not quite that simple. The
more conscious we are, and the
more conscious we consolidate,
and I'm talking about not
consciousness, which is
collected over experience over
1000s and 1000s of years, but
the more consciousness we
consolidate, it not only heals
our heart and opens our mind, it
enlivens our senses, so that our
eyes are in the process. Our
visual experience is in the
process of becoming hundreds of
times more sensitive than normal
today, our taste, our touch, our
sexuality, all the physical
senses are in the process of
being transformed. And if we
ask, how far can this
Regina Meredith: go? You had an
experience where you didn't
understand what was going on as
I recall when I read the book,
where you were looking at
something but it didn't look as
you normally saw it. I think you
were looking at your hands. Is
that correct?
Chris Bache: It was the very
last session. That was the 73rd
session, and I was at the end
stage of that session, about
five hours in, and I was given
an experience that I came to
call diamond vision. All of a
sudden, my vision was 1000 times
sharper than I'd ever known it
to be. I could see things. I
could discriminate colors and
shades and textures. I was
looking at my hands, and I was
able to see every pore in every
at the base of every. Every hair
follicle. I mean, it was just
amazingly detailed. I could see
dust floating in the air with
great precision. I could count
leaves on a tree. And then after
about 10 minutes, it
disappeared, and I was back to
my ordinary, perfectly focused
vision. And that's when I
understood that I was seeing
through the eyes of the future
human, that the future human is
a transformation of our physical
sensations of our entire so our
entire existence is being
polished, evoked, brought
forward into deeper forms of
manifestation by the universe.
Regina Meredith: This is so
beautiful. And that was, as I
recall a session 71 through 73
where you were shown that this
human being, this vehicle, is
designed for rapid
transformation. And please
expand on that a moment before
we come toward our close here,
Chris Bache: well in the 70th
vision, I was given what I
consider the last great vision
of my journey after that, it was
kind of wrapping it up. But in
that journey, I was taken deeply
into deep time and given three
core experiences. And one of
those experiences was an insight
into how it is that humanity is
actually built, designed for
accelerated evolution, and it's
basically we have the surface of
our being is reincarnation. We
incarnate, we learn, we grow, we
change, we make decisions. We
incarnate again, different. This
is that part. But underneath the
incarnate, our incarnating self,
there is a deeper structure
which holds all of our
incarnational memories, and is
the fundamental blueprint, in a
sense, from within which we act
and behave, so that all of
humanity is growing and
changing, growing and changing.
And there is a structure to the
collective psyche, a very
specific structure which is
accumulating and storing all
this information while we change
individually, this deeper than
individual structure is holding
it and periodically, that deeper
structure goes through a change
of a pivot. It's what I call a
shift in the plate tectonics of
the of the collective psyche. I
think it's the genius of
creation that we learn at an
individual level, but it
collects at a deeper level. And
periodically that deeper level
changes, and after that shift
takes place, all individual
experience is based on that
changed fundamental psyche, so
that after we go through the
birth of the future human all
future incarnations of all
beings, all this human beings,
will be operating out of
transform this new fundamental
collective psyche, and it's
going to continue. It doesn't
stop. So individuals learn and
grow. It's collected at a deeper
level, and that deeper level
learns and grow like Rupert
sheldrakes talks about
morphogenic fields, and it's an
ongoing, continuous evolving
process.
Regina Meredith: And you know,
I've interviewed many, many
people over the last 20 years in
this particular role, and I do
also interview people who
channel other beings from other
times and spaces. And one thing
that has come up repeatedly is
that what humanity is moving
toward, it's a total overlay
with what you're saying is to
this expansive being, this
refined being that incarnates
into the physical body who's
operating through the heart
center as the primary influence
of intelligence, and that we
this is a species that can end
up, and will end up being a
model for other species
throughout the universes. Is
that how you saw it, too, once
we can embody all of this,
Chris Bache: you know, there was
just one piece, one line in all
of the sessions that seemed to
indicate something like that. I
What i intuited was that Earth
was a hot house, growing form of
consciousness that would, in
time, be exported to other solar
systems in our galaxy. I don't
think we're the origin of all
life, and I'm sure that there is
evolution taking place in highly
developed forms in all sorts of
solar systems and other
galaxies. But at least here, we
seem to be growing something
which is destined. Seemed to me
just that one inclination seems
to be destined for more than
planet Earth.
Regina Meredith: Well, I just
wanted to say you have
validation there from other
sources who have given that
information through to us. Now
it's a while getting there. We
just have to trip through these
times again. I can't thank you
enough for the courage it took
you. We didn't talk about what
you went through, but I mean,
we're talking about life
wrecking cause. Consequences of
taking such high doses of LSD
that you say now, was really
insane to have done, but you
didn't know any better. You
lived through it, thank God,
because it really, it really
pushed you out there.
Chris Bache: Yes, truly do not,
I do not recommend. No, I'd be
much gentler if I were doing it
again, and I recommend a gentler
protocol if you're going to work
with psychedelics,
Regina Meredith: yes, yes, and
you say that repeatedly in the
book. So I recommend for people
to really dive into this. We
just touched a few places in the
book. There's so much more
connective tissue to this story
of the human, the collective
human being. And any final
thoughts you want to leave us
with today before we sign off,
Chris Bache: first, I want to
thank you for helping bring the
message from this work forward.
Psychedelics is simply a
protocol. It's a new methodology
for accessing these deep states
of consciousness, but it's
simply a modern version. We have
many protocols that have been
accessing these deep states of
consciousness. Psychedelics are
not important. They're not the
signature of this work. They're
simply an amplifier. It's
consciousness that does the
work. It's consciousness that if
we use these sessions
skillfully. It's consciousness
that really does the work that
opens us to these things. So I
would really, at the end, I
would de emphasize the
psychedelics and emphasize the
consciousness which psychedelics
amplify.
Regina Meredith: And there are
many ways to reach that. Yes,
again, Christopher, thank you so
much, and I look forward to
meeting you in the flesh in the
Gaia Studios, where we'll go
over this, but start filling in
some of the pieces we didn't
weren't able to get to today.
Chris Bache: Okay. Thank you,
Regina. I look forward to that
too. Thank you so
Regina Meredith: everybody.
Again. The title of the book is
LSD and the mind of the universe
Christopher Bache, and I can't
recommend it highly enough, it
will take you to places that you
never dreamed existed. So until
next time, thank you for joining
us here on Regina meredith.com
if you enjoyed this video, be
sure to subscribe to my YouTube
channel, and you might also want
to consider joining Patreon,
which allows me to keep all of
this content free and available
to everyone. And if you're
looking for like minded souls,
you might also enjoy my online
community called our
neighborhood. Links to join are
in the description you.