Marc Caron: Mark, Hello
everyone, and welcome to this
episode of spirit plant medicine
presents. My name is Mark Karan.
I'm happy to share that today
we're having a great
conversation with a great group
of guests in regards to Steven
Gray's new book, how
psychedelics can help save the
world, and today, we're going to
answer the question, you know,
what is the role of psychedelics
for a planet in transition? So
our first guest I'll introduce
is my friend and cohort in the
spirit plant medicine space, Mr.
Steven gray. Steven has been
traveling a spiritual and
medicine path for over 50 years
now he's a writer, educator,
conference organizer, speaker,
and he's also a facilitator for
cannabis ceremonies. Now, Steven
is the author of three books,
including the popular cannabis
and spirituality, an Explorer's
guide to the ancient plant
spirit allies. And just
recently, as I just already
mentioned, how psychedelics can
help save the world, visionary
and indigenous voices speak out.
Steven always a pleasure to see
you. Thanks, Mark, yeah, looking
forward to our conversation
today, and we also have joining
us is Belinda oraccio. I hope I
pronounce your last name, Lao
aracho, and she's of Dean a
Navajo and a she we of the
pebbles Pueblo Zuni descent. Her
maternal clan is the one who
walks around, and she was born
for the Zuni Pueblo people.
Belinda has was born and raised
in the Navajo reservation
located in Arizona in the United
States. She's a wisdom carrier,
healer and founder of kalaji,
and she's focused on culture and
traditional teachings that
impact topics such as Native
American communities. She holds
a health degrees technology and
public health. Belinda is just
well rounded in so many
different areas, and she brings
great wisdom to our community.
So we're excited to have you
here again today. Belinda, nice
to see you. Great to see you,
awesome. And of course, we have
Chris Bache. Chris Bache is a
professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he's
taught for 33 years. He's also a
junk faculty at the California
Institute of integral studies
and a fellow at the Institute of
Noetic Sciences. He's an award
winning teacher with his work
exploring the philosophical
implications of Non-ordinary
states of consciousness. Chris
has written a number of books,
and his most recent is LSD and
the minds of the universe. Great
read. If you haven't read it, go
check out that book. It's
fantastic. Welcome Chris. How
are you?
Unknown: I'm great. Welcome
everybody. It's a real honor to
be here with you today.
Marc Caron: Yeah, likewise, it's
always a pleasure to connect and
learn from you folks, because
for me, you know, this work is
really been a passion of
learning, and the things that
I've gleaned from all the talks
over the conferences of the
years has really made a
difference in my life, and it's
really exciting to be able to
share that with people around
the world. So thank you for
taking the time out of your day
to join us here, and we're going
to get started, and I'm going to
start with Steve, and basically
what we're going to do today is
we're I'm going to ask a
question of our panel, and
they're all each going to answer
for about five minutes or so,
the answer to this one specific
question. And because we're
focusing on the book How
psychedelics can help save the
world, I'm going to start with
Steven Gray, because he was the
guy who put this work together.
And we're going to start there.
So if we're ready, gang, let's
roll the question is, in your
view, Mr. Steven Gray, what is
the role of psychedelics for a
planet in transition?
Stephen Gray: Oh, thanks, Mark.
Thanks for the intro and the
lead in. And just a quick
clarification, by the way,
although you implied it in your
latest little statement there, I
am merely the editor and one of
the contributors to both the
previous cannabis book and this
one. And in this case, there are
25 contributors. So I'll, I just
wrote the intro and the outro,
as it were, and a couple of
other short things. So that's my
role. Just wanted to clarify
that, and the rest of it was cat
herding for the other 25 people
involved. But I'm delighted with
with the results. They're all
remarkable people. And. Are all
speaking in different ways, but
I would say in accord. I don't
think there would be anything in
the book that would provoke any
one of those contributors to
disagree with any of the other
contributors. So obviously
that's a big question. And I
actually think that I'm actually
more interested in what Chris
and Belinda have to say about it
than what I have to say about
it, to be honest. But so what
could I say about that issue?
Well, okay, I know I have an
answer for you, but go ahead,
Mark,
Marc Caron: yeah, what I was
going to say is maybe you can
let us know what inspired you to
put this particular book
together, and what that
inspiration was for you based
on, right?
Stephen Gray: Okay, well, I'm
going to take that question and
run down the field, maybe the
opposite direction, but we'll
see. Excuse me, so yeah. Well,
the inspiration is the potential
of psychedelics, which is
answering your question anyway,
I hope. And so here's one way of
talking about it, the role of
psychedelics for a planet in
transition. They are not silver
bullets or magic bullets. They
are fraught with the potential
for misuse, misappropriation,
misunderstanding, and in some
cases harm. They're not for
everybody. And in fact, Jamie
wheel, who's spoken at our
conference twice, had an
interesting kind of template
that he suggested. He said,
don't take it too literally. But
perhaps it might be like this.
Out of the if you take a graph
of 100% of the demographic of
the people, perhaps there's 10%
people, 10% of those people at
one end of the continuum should
never take psychedelics for a
variety of reasons, you know,
mental health, fragility, etc.
And then there are 10% of the
other end who are the dedicated,
serious Psychonauts and
explorers who are constantly
learning from the medicines. And
so those people might be taking
the medicines frequently over,
you know, accumulated number of
years. And then there are 80% in
the middle who, in Jamie's view,
perhaps should only be taking
the psychedelics for very
special occasions, perhaps three
or four times in their lives,
you know, for like a graduation,
a wedding, the birth of a first
child, something like that. So
that's just one way of looking
at, you know, who might benefit
or not from the psychedelic.
Having said that, my other sort
of favorite way to talk about
these, or put them into the
context of our current
situation, is that, you know,
there's an there's an obvious
notion that, using the more sort
of a medical metaphor, that when
the patient is in an advanced
state of illness, strong
medicines are required. So as
obviously all through, all four
of us here understand quite
clearly we are in a dire
condition on the planet, and as
Chris Bache has made so clear in
his books and talks and
different things like that, we
are heading into sorry to steal
your thunder here, Chris, but a
Death-Rebirth cycle, which is
most likely to become
increasingly more difficult on
the material level over the next
decades. We don't know how long
so things are. We're in a
crucial moment. We're in a
crucial Nexus moment. And so
what we need, as I understand
it, is we need tools that can
almost, in a sense, shock the
monkey or wake us up, do a lot
of healing work, and, you know,
awakening work. So in that
regard, the way that I like to
think of the psychedelics is as
reality medicines. They're not
about escaping into some
alternative reality,
particularly, although that's a
fraught thing to say, I suppose.
But ultimately, what they're
capable of when they're done in
the most skillful, intentional
circumstances, I think, is they
can open us up into
understandings which are real,
you know, about our who we are,
the nature of things. And that
includes, well, another way that
I like to talk about them as
well is I think of psychedelics
as having sort of two interwoven
capabilities. One is that they
are truth serums potentially so
they can show us things about
our ourselves, so that we can
see where we are blocked, where
the obstacles are, we can see
sometimes into our past and the
places we've got stuck or turned
away from ourselves, as gambor
mate might say. And then the
other side of that. It's part of
the same function, of course,
and as I say, interwoven is that
they can and. Am ideally open us
up to what my old Buddhist
teacher, chug GM Trungpa would
call unconditioned reality, the
awakened state to some degree or
another. And as people that take
psychedelics often say it these
states often feel more real than
the ones that most people live
through most of the time, so I
think I'll stop there.
Marc Caron: Well, thank you,
Steven. So before we get into
any kind of conversation, I'm
going to pass it to Belinda to
from her perspective and her
worldview, to answer really the
same question, you know, what
is, do you feel is the role of
psychedelics for our planet in
transition?
Belinda Eriacho: Thank you,
Mark. Before I get started, I do
want to do a land
acknowledgement to the people of
the Phoenix area, which are the
out on the P posh before
McDowell, you have a pie nation
and the auction people who live
in this place that they refer to
as Earth Doctor, I'm here as an
invited guest in these unceded
territories, and I share a
common history with them, and I
wanted to acknowledge them in
that way before I answer that
question. That's a That's a
loaded question mark. I you
know, in my chapter, chapter
five, that talks about turning
of the soil, I use that as a as
a metaphor for what is unfolding
in this time that we are in
right now. And to me, the way
that I look at psychedelics, I
view them more as sacred
medicines, not necessarily
psychedelics or ethnogens or
drugs, as as many people refer
to them. And I think that really
puts in perspective itself the
language that we use when we
refer to these sacred medicines.
You know, everything that we do,
we create energy, or we
transform energy, and it's
really important that we clearly
understand them and respect
them, as my friend Steven had
indicated. But I think also,
psychedelics is really an
opportunity to awaken to
ourselves. I was reading some
literature the other day about
the intellect, the intellectual
quotient and the spiritual
quotient, just, you know, on a
global level for humanity and
kind of where we are, and it
seems that we've outgrown our
intellectual selves, and now the
spiritual peace, the spiritual
aspect of ourselves, is starting
to unfold. And when my metaphor
that I talk about the turning of
the soil, what I believe is
happening with the psychedelics,
it's essentially turning
ourselves inside out. You know,
we're so used to being out in a
material world from a Western
perspective that we've forgotten
how to even be with ourselves.
And so by unfolding and taking
these different medicines, it
allows us to to go into these
places that we can eventually
heal ourselves and then resonate
that out into our families and
our communities. I also believe
that psychedelic medicines or
sacred medicines meet different
aspects in our lives. You know,
my culture, we talk about the
cycles of life. When we are born
into this physicalness, we come
in, in a spirit, physical form,
and it is not until we make our
first laugh that we embody the
physicalness as human beings.
And then we go through
adolescence, adulthood, elderly,
hood, and then we return back to
source. And I think through
those experiences, we go through
a path that I refer to as
horizon, which means the balance
of harmony in our lives. Now,
that doesn't necessarily mean
that everything is nice and
rosy, you know. Life is life,
you know, and sometimes those
difficult experiences that we go
through allow us to unfold and
to see things in a different
perspective, but also give us
some life lessons that we need
to learn. And so with that, I
think one of the things is that
in my book, I also make
reference to the prophecies of
the eagle on Condor, and I give
two examples. One is from the
Hopi people, which are located
here in Arizona, as well as the
Andean traditions, and that the
North, people of the north are
the people of the mind, and the
people of the South are the
people of the heart. And when we
can come together as one unified
community, then we can start to
heal the history that we all
share. And so I think
psychedelics allows us to to get
to that point, but also come to
a lot of other realizations
about our interconnectedness
with one another. You know the
importance of ceremony and
intention that come along with
with these sacred plant
medicines. But also there.
Realization of going to a much
deeper level in our healing
evolution, if you will. You
know, I think a lot of times
when we have an illness, we rely
on Western medicine for that
healing aspect, rather than
going to that next level deeper
within and so those are just
some of my thoughts in the way
that I view psychedelics and how
it can save the world.
Beautiful.
Marc Caron: Well, thank you so
much for sharing that. And I
just wanted to let people know
that if you want to catch
Belinda's talk from our spirit
plant medicine conference in
2022 which is titled turning of
the soil, that's available on
our YouTube channel, and it's
also available for free in our
membership portal as well at
Spirit plant medicine com. I
highly recommend going and
taking that in, because it was
just a fantastic presentation.
And as we move forward, we're
going to go to Mr. Chris Bache.
Chris again, the question is, in
your view, what do you feel is
the role of psychedelics for our
planet in transition?
Unknown: Well, first mark, I
want to affirm everything that
Steven and Belinda have said.
One of the advantages of going
last in the batting order is I
get to play off of what has
already been said. And I
certainly, absolutely agree with
it. It seems that we are living
in a different time in history,
as particularly Belinda has
pointed to. We are living in a
time when the underlying
structure of the collective
psyche is shifting. We are
shifting culturally. There are
so many cultural migrations and
integrations taking place, but
kind of at a deeper at a deep
level, the very nature of the
collective psyche seems to be
simmering, turning to the point
of boiling. One of the ways I
understand this is that we have
entered a time when the karma of
our many, many former lives, all
of us collectively, is coming
forward and pressing up inside
us, seeking resolution. I think
there's a tremendous collective
purification taking place in the
outer world and also in the
inner world. So one of the uses
of psychedelics that can be very
helpful is to helping, is to
help accelerate and deepen and
clarify this internal
purification process. I think
that's why so many people are
involved in other spiritual
practices besides psychedelic
practice of yoga and meditation,
so many different activities,
because we need to keep the
psyche open and clear, to let
this, this negative conditioning
come through us without, without
re traumatizing ourselves, to
help our system clear itself and
cleanse itself. And psychedelics
when used conscientiously in
ritual context and in
therapeutic context can deepen
and accelerate this healing
process. And I think one of the
fundamental problems that we
have been living with is our
separation from nature and our
separation from our spiritual
nature, so that the surface of
our nature is not as naturally
in tune with our deeper nature
as maybe it had been in earlier
times, simpler times. So one of
part of healing the psyche is
also sort of healing the soul at
a deeper level than just kind of
personal, therapeutic healing,
helping the soul enter into
deeper communion with its own
deep history, and with the deep
history of the planet, and with
the deep history of the
intelligence that has been
orchestrating reality in
manifesting reality For 13 point
7 billion years. So that in
addition are taking the healing
process deeper than just
personal healing, even deeper
than collective healing, it's
can be a process of reconnecting
with that core intelligence that
is manifesting life, manifesting
nature, and manifesting history
and learning from it, developing
a deeper understanding from life
itself, what is happening, what
is taking place. Why is this
century different from earlier
centuries? What is the
trajectory of our evolutionary
project? Excuse me, in this
century, so healing,
facilitating a kind of cultural
renaissance, but then also
facilitating a deeper psycho
spiritual Renaissance, so that
we can reconnect with this core
sense. Deeper understanding of
what's actually taking place in
history. So those are the those
are the points that I would just
add to what's already been said.
Marc Caron: That's fantastic,
and as we go through what
transition we're facing. But I
wanted to just take this moment
as we go into, you know, the
next question, so we can unpack
this a little bit more. Belinda,
you said something really, I
think, important and profound
that we all need to, you know,
take a look at and understand.
And this is mostly, you know,
kind of my perception, and
something that I've been picking
up because you talked about the
language and how we talk about
psychedelics, Entheogen drugs,
plant medicines and things. And,
you know, I've had the
opportunity to speak to a lot of
people in terms of interviews,
and, you know, media and things,
and everybody talks about them
as drugs. And I just want to
share my thought on this,
because when we take a look at a
natural plant and a plant
medicine, whether it's cannabis,
the mushroom, Ayahuasca, and
things of that nature. You know,
in my opinion, they're not
drugs. They're they're plants,
and plants as medicine. And when
we take a look at, you know,
other plants that we consume on
a regular basis, we don't call
them drugs. Broccoli, we don't
call a drug celery, we don't
call a drug, you know, all those
power foods and power greens, we
don't call a drug, yet, they
have different plant properties.
And when we look at, you know,
the psychedelic nature of
plants, you know, they have
different plant properties. And
that's why I think it's really
important that we don't classify
them in that stigma of being a
drug, and that we use all plants
as medicine. And it's just my
two cents on that, because it
comes up a lot where people will
call them drugs, and in my
opinion, they're really plants,
right? And many of them have
their own medicine, whether it's
a vegetable or something with
psychedelic psyche collective
properties. So
Belinda Eriacho: I think there's
one thing that's missing from
that mark. And, you know, I,
too, have been talking with many
people, and I think one of the
things that seems to be missing
is the relationship between us
and the plants and the plant
kingdom. You know, from my
culture, I refer to Ayahuasca as
grandmother, translates to
grandmother Ayahuasca. These
are, these are ancient teachers
that really have something to
pass on to us if we're willing
to listen and to open up to
those, you know, gems of wisdom.
The same thing goes with the
Mushroom Kingdom. You know,
they're not called Santa nio for
no reason at all. You know, the
holy children, you know. And so
I think it really is important
that for those of us that use
psychedelics, whether it's in
our healing or as therapeutic
modalities, is you really need
to come to that inner standing,
not understanding we're not
putting ourselves over these
plants. We're really
internalizing that and really
making that, building that
relationship with them. And I
think it's really important as
this, you know, this whole field
starts to develop. So thank you,
Mark,
Marc Caron: yeah, absolutely.
And I love that word inner
standing. I hope to use that in
the future, if you
Stephen Gray: don't mind,
awesome, not copyrighted. Yeah,
Marc Caron: fantastic, but it's
just it makes sense, and inner
standing is very different than
an intellectual understanding,
right? So, yeah, beautifully
said. So now the question is,
what is the transition you think
that we're facing? You know,
there's a lot of change in the
world right now. We're seeing it
every day. Steven, what do you
think is, you know, the biggest
part of this transition that
we're facing, what is it?
Stephen Gray: Well, hmm, yeah.
Well, again, not to belittle my
own intelligence, but I think
Chris Bache has been tapping
into what I think, if I may say
so Chris, I think it's more or
less the correct terminology
that vast intelligences of the
universe that have been saying
that, as Chris has said before,
numerous times, you know, we've
reached this kind of nexus
point. And so I think it's just
really important now, okay, so
yeah, here's, here's a good way
to talk about that, I think, as
if we think it will and is seems
to be, apparently underway
already, the stability of the
past or the status quo, such as
it is or was, is becoming less
viable, less comfortable on the
material level, and just in
general, you know, change is
happening very, very quickly on
multiple levels, as that
happens, and especially if.
Things become, well, either
rapidly or not quite so rapidly,
more difficult for many people
on the material level, like if
there become shortages of food
or clean water, if international
agreements break down, if the
climate makes makes us put like
a much greater percentage of our
financial resources into climate
change mitigation and on and on.
If those things all make our
lives more difficult and less
stable and less certain, I guess
you could say what I think is
likely to happen, and, I mean, I
don't. I'm not an authority any
more than anyone else, but it
seems to me that it's a lot of
it's already happening in terms
of its effect on the psychology
or the mentality of people. You
know, you keep hearing in the
news about how there's more
depression these days, there's
more anxiety. So I think what's
likely to happen if this
trajectory unfolds the way we
envision it, way we think it
will, or perhaps the way the
spirits are telling some people
that it is likely to there will
be more of those, you know,
problematic mind states and more
discouragement. So I think it's
really important. And this is
saying this partly because
that's the mission of the book,
is to hopefully give people, as
Dwayne Elgin, one of the
contributors to the book, says,
a believable story, a story
that's if I had it in front of
me. Actually, I could find it in
a minute, but none. I don't want
to make you wait. In his chapter
in the book, he lays out, sort
of, if the story is going to be
functional for people, it has to
have four elements, and I don't
remember what they all are now,
but one is that it has to be
simple, easy to understand,
functional, able to be, you
know, put into place,
manifested, plausible, etc. And
so Dwayne, Dwayne has a really
interesting view of this. From
my point of view. He he talks
about how, in his book choosing
earth, he actually, he actually
goes through a possible, or even
probable scenario for the next
six, seven decades. And this is
super loose, and I haven't even
read it for a while, so it's
something vaguely like this. It
looks like material conditions
are likely to continue to
deteriorate over the next
several decades. But this is
really key, if enough people get
smart or however you want to say
that, you know, wake up, do the
healing work that they need to
do we need to do so that we can
participate in intelligent,
creative solutions at multiple
levels, you know, whatever level
that is, through the arts,
through government, through
economics, whatever
environmental work, etc, etc.
But starting with that inner
understanding, or that inner
standing that Belinda and now
you are talking about Mark, then
there is the hope of, as Dwayne
calls it, the birth, or the
arising, of a mature planetary
civilization. So and Chris
again, if I you don't mind my
stealing your thunder. Chris has
said that he wasn't given any
timeline on this. Dwayne lays it
out over the next six or seven
decades as a possibility. But so
what I'm really trying to say,
in a somewhat rambly way here,
is that I feel strongly that
people need to hear messages
that things, if things look bad,
it doesn't just mean we're
heading toward doom and
destruction. It means, and this
is really a gross
oversimplification, no doubt,
but for the short term, for this
situation here it, it's, it's
connected to the things like the
prophecy of the eagle and the
Condor that Belinda was talking
about, or, or, you know, the the
hundreds of 1000s of years
accumulated karma that Chris is
talking about coming to a head.
Now, it's related to that. It's
all about that notion that we've
come to this point, and if we,
if we don't have something that
shows us a potential for the
light to come through, it's
going to be much, much harder on
people's psyches, you know? So I
think that is, I mean, maybe I'm
an idealist, you know? I'm a
dreamer, I'm a visioner in that
sense, I think we've been given
this I don't just think it. I
sense that we've been given this
absolutely incredible gift of
life on this planet to wake up
to our true, interwoven,
embedded. Interrelationship and
connection to everything and to
appreciate it and to love it and
to create within it. You know,
in this short time that each of
us has on the planet, you know,
my old Buddhist teacher,
Trungpa, you know, talked about
learning to appreciate the
redness of red and the blueness
of blue. You know, just that
really simple, like, in a sense,
surrendering or open, opening
oneself into things as they are,
and relaxing into that, right?
So we just need, I think, more
and more clear, plausible,
actionable information and
messages that there is this
potential for the birth of
individual and collective
awakening. So I guess that's one
way of talking about, you know,
whatever this transition is that
is no longer sustainable to keep
being in the state of spiritual
disconnection.
Marc Caron: I completely
understand and agree with what
you're saying there, because
there's, you know, so much going
on in the world right now that
you know we need these tools
more than ever. So Belinda, I'm
really curious about your take
of what you see from your role
in the world as an indigenous
woman, and what you see as being
the biggest transition that we
are facing as you know, global
humanity,
Belinda Eriacho: right? Thank
you so much for that question. I
was looking at rereading Chris's
chapter and then some of the
things that Steven had talked
about, but I look at things in a
different way, because I think
what's happening to us and many
indigenous cultures around the
globe. Our elders have told us
that these are just cycles that
we're going through. Everything
is evolving to that, and that's
the way that I look at things.
And so these things that may
appear as challenges to us can
really turn out to be gifts in
the end, and it's really up to
us, as, you know, as a human
species, to really think, not so
much be in our mind, but think
with our hearts. And I think
there's been already too much
thinking up here. That's why
we're in a situation that we are
in right now, and where we
really need to start moving into
is into the the mind of the
heart. And, you know, in my
book, I share a little story
about an elder that told us the
longest journey that we will
ever travel is between our mind
and our heart. And that's only
18 inches away, you know. And so
I think that that's kind of some
of the things that are coming up
for me, you know, I'm reminded
of many stories that even my my
grandparents and great
grandparents shared, and that
were passed down through our
oral traditions about how things
evolve and the way that we look
at and perceive things is really
what we create. And so, you
know, I think one of the things
that I see for myself is that
the children that are being born
in this time, they're very I
think, you know, I think Chris
calls them. Tolle calls it the
diamond. In his book makes
reference to a diamond. And I, I
think of these children as very
wise souls that are coming in
right now, they already have
this knowing that is within them
to carry on a lot of these
teachings and cultures and
traditions that we all have
forgotten about because we've
kind of been too focused on the
materialistic aspects of our
lives, and we've forgotten
everything else. And so I think,
you know, I'm a little bit more
optimistic that it's just an
evolution and a change and a
shift that we are going through
as a as humanity, there will
definitely be those that will, I
think, falter off on another
path. I think one of the things
I'm also reminded of in part of
the chapter that Chris writes
that reminds me of, is that
there are these different things
that are evolving, and
psychedelics, the sacred plant
medicines, allows us to go into
these places that are different
timelines than this physical
timeline that we are in. And we
all have our own interpretation
of what that is? You know, I
mean, I've seen the future. I've
seen the the instruments for
healing that have been shared by
our star relatives. You know, in
our my cultures, they said that
we are the star beings. We are
from the stars. Our ancestors
are from the stars. And we were
remembering those things. But
I've also seen the ancient ruins
and the dwellings crafted on
side of the walls. And many of
my my journeys, you know, and
being able to travel into time,
time frames, it's very hard to
describe these timelines that
you're able to to tap into to
have those. Connections with,
you know, deceased relatives,
and really, you know, heal those
relationships that we have with
one another so that we can
continue to evolve. I think some
of that is related to some of
the things that Chris talks
about, is about this evolution
of karma. And so one of the
things that I think that, and I
My prayer is that as each one of
us sees what's happening and
unfolding around us in the
world, whether it's geopolitical
or climate related, really start
to begin to ask ourselves, you
know, what part of that do I
own? I think there's always this
tendency to say that somebody
else's issue, but we all have,
if we really, truly believe that
we are interrelated with one
another, then we need to take
ownership of that. That's really
where the real action happens.
So thank you for that question.
Marc Caron: Absolutely my
pleasure. And you know, I think
it's I love what you said, and
I've heard it before, that the
longest journey we'll ever take
is the one from our head to our
heart. And I repeat that back,
because I think it's really
important, and I want everyone
to, you know, really think about
that for a moment and really
recognize, like, are you living
from up here? It's another quote
that I have in my world. It's
like, when you're in your head,
you're dead, when you're in your
heart, you're smart, you know.
And it's just one of those
things that when you drop into
your heart all of a sudden,
answers come, you know, undammed
and flow really well. So thank
you
Belinda Eriacho: for I might
borrow that mark, by the way,
hey, by all means,
Stephen Gray: yeah, absolutely.
Lots of trading going on. Here.
There you go. There you go.
Well,
Marc Caron: this, this is one of
the ways that psychedelics are
helping change the world, right?
We learn, we support, we get
inspired by each other, and then
we can go share what we're
doing, and all based on the
topic of psychedelics. Anyways,
Chris, again, that would be our
question for you. You know, what
is the transition you see that
we are facing as a society
today?
Unknown: Well, I only have
limited visionary, shamanic kind
of experience of the future.
When I want to turn to
specifics, I have to go to the
same sources that we all do, I
have to go to the scientist. I
have to go to the ecologist. I
was very glad, Steven that you
mentioned the work of Dwayne
Elgin, because he's been
crunching the numbers for
decades. He's been really
tracking the scientific
literature, and it seems clear,
if we do that, we are entering a
period of enormous suffering. It
is hard to overestimate how much
suffering is coming in the
decades ahead, between now and
say, just say, 50 years from
now, 2070 2075 when we look at
the melting of the ice caps,
when we look at the expanding
population when we look at
climate destabilization,
destabilization of agriculture,
likelihood of more pandemics, I
mean, realistically, we could be
looking at the death of 1/3 to
one half of the human population
of this Planet, if our carrying
capacity is somewhere around 2
billion and we're pushing 8
billion now, then the suffering
of so many of our children and
grandchildren around the world
dying is just going to be an
unspeakable agony that's going
to bring us to our knees and
give us a kind of intense
incentive, a motivation to do
things, to insist on changes
that right now we do not have
the political and social will to
do. Some do a few do, a growing
number of some do, but not
enough to make these shifts
happen. So I think we're coming
into a pain of terrible,
terrible suffering. I wish it
weren't. So I wish we could, we
could avoid it by having enough
people come to their senses
quickly enough. But I think
we're past the point in history
where we could avert this crisis
that it's coming, we might be
able to soften a touch, but it's
coming, and it's going to hit
us. It's going to hit our
children and our grandchildren,
our great grandchildren, very,
very hard. Now my visionary
experience is that this global
crisis that we are entering is a
birth process, that it is going
to be horrendously painful, but
it is not an apocalypse, in the
sense of a destruction of
everything that has come up to
this point in time. It is, it
is, in a sense, like a
Near-Death Experience, where we
come very close to death and in.
That process of coming close to
death, we break through into
different orders of
consciousness, I think Nate. And
this is not something human
beings are doing, or human
beings are in control of nature
is in control of this process.
Nature is driving this
evolutionary crisis. The this
intelligence behind nature is
driving this process. The best
we can do is be responsive in
communion with this
intelligence. Responsive with
this intelligence, and cooperate
with it in order to facilitate a
transition that it is not ours
to have designed, but nature has
designed this transition. Now,
the way I understand the long
scale of this is from within a
reincarnational perspective, and
from that perspective, the human
beings who are entering this
crisis are not human beings the
way we ordinarily think of them.
They're not 100 year old beings.
They're 10s of 1000s, hundreds
of 1000s of year old beings.
They have layers and layers and
layers of the history inside of
each one of us, and this history
comes from different cultures
and different places around the
world and different places in
society, different colors,
different religious traditions,
all these aspects of our global
complex picture are all woven
into the fiber of our being. We
have been growing for hundreds
of 1000s of years as souls
making some progress here, maybe
making some step backwards
there, but overall, we've been
growing, but collectively the
psychological level of our
collective maturation is still
basically egoic. It's still
rooted in our individual
consciousness. And the world
that is falling apart around our
ears is a world that was built
by ego and as and I don't just
disparage ego. Ego is beautiful.
I mean it, it's just, it's an
extra, ordinarily beautiful
phenomenon, but it is still
fundamentally cut off from the
deeper fabric of life, from the
deeper fabric of our
interconnectedness, from the
deeper fabric of our spiritual
connectedness. And basically
it's it because of its limited
awareness, it designs a world
which works for some and doesn't
work for others. It elevates the
condition of life for some at
the cost of disparaging the
quality of life of other beings.
And we can just we know how this
happens. We know how this works.
We know what's been happening.
And basically this is a world
that works for some and doesn't
work for others, and it's a
world the limitations of this
view are basically leading to a
global destruction, a global
catastrophe of unmitigated
suffering. I don't think we can
survive as a species living out
of the level of consciousness
that we have been living out of
up to this point in time. For
all its beauty, the ego is still
too small a consciousness to
basically solve the global
problems, to solve the social
problems that that are becoming
paramount right now. We either
need to, we will either grow up
or we're going to die, and that
makes this death process a
tremendously powerful
evolutionary accelerator. Now,
what growing up means, I think,
is shifting from an egoic
perspective to a soul
perspective. Basically, I think
we are in a time when all of our
former lives and all of this
history and all of this work
that each one of us has been
doing, and collectively we've
been doing. I think what's
happening is, just as the world
is coming together as one, our
psyches are coming together as
one, the prophecies that Belinda
refers to as East West culture,
north south culture, but the
psyche is coming together as
one. And when this, when we
reach critical mass, not only
will the world give birth to a
new culture, but the core of
this culture, I think, is that
it will be operating out of a
different level of
consciousness, out of a higher
level of consciousness. And I
think the most immediate way of
understanding this is out of
soul consciousness, and this is
what, in my visions, comes
through as the birth of the
diamond soul, which is simply
all of our history integrated
into a single consciousness,
which is transparent to each
other at a very deep level and
transparent to the Divine at a
very deep level. And once we
collectively make this
transition, it's not going to
work if only a few people here
or there make this transition.
Nature doesn't think small.
Nature only thinks in large,
large movements. The entire
species is being taken through
this transition. And. I don't
know how we're going to make
this transition. I don't know
whether it's going to come
slowly or fast, or how we're
going to do it, but the visions
which have been poured into me
in my years of psychedelic work
is that we do make this
transition. We do come out of
this crisis a different kind of
species, not only improved a
little bit around the edges, but
with a fundamental change taking
place at the very core of the
collective unconscious, so that
every human being born after
this transition takes place is
operating out of a different
foundation of consciousness, a
different more spiritually
informed form of consciousness.
And just as any mother, when she
goes into labor is in a day
filled with pain, but at the end
of the day, when she gives birth
to her child, that pain is worth
it, because of the beauty of the
child is being born. I think it
will be that way for us too. We
are giving birth to a new form
of humanity, a more enlightened
form, a more compassionate form,
a more spiritually awakened form
of humanity, historically
unprecedented. And as this
transition takes place, we will
look back at this century of
crisis, and we will say it was
worth it to give birth to
something so beautiful. It was
worth it.
Stephen Gray: Mark, can I add a
little icing on that cake?
Marc Caron: Absolutely you can.
Steven, thanks. Well,
Stephen Gray: that was
incredible, Chris, by the way,
mind blowing, really. And and I
just like to throw in one of my
favorite sayings, necessity is
the mother of invention. And I
think that the intelligence, I
don't think I'm sure the
intelligence capabilities of
humanity, often, as you've just
implied, I think Chris in
concert with each other are all
but limitless. And so from my
point of view, the optimistic
side of this, what you're
talking about, Chris, is a
potentially extremely difficult,
painful period of dissolution
before there's enough of a gap
for the new vision to come in is
going to be in some way tempered
by increasing intelligence. You
know that it's like life is
getting real on the planet, you
know. And as things get real,
our deeper capabilities start to
come out more and more. So I
think that's really important to
understand, frankly, and and
goes along with what I was
saying earlier about the need
for sort of plausible,
understandable, actionable
visions and and messages for
people so that people don't so
that as many people as possible
don't just fall into despair and
hopelessness as material
conditions deteriorate, if
that's what's going to happen.
So, yeah, I just wanted to add
that, you know, let us not
underestimate, and this is, I'm
not saying this in contradiction
to anything you've said, Chris,
but let us not underestimate the
almost unlimited potential for
creativity that is going to
become increasingly needed as
time goes on and will come out,
you know, as we move out of the
sort of the you know, Herman,
Hess last book, The Glass Bead
game, Magister Ludy takes place
About 500 years in the future,
and he refers back to, or those
people refer back to this time
as the age of feyoton. And I'm
not sure if I'm pronouncing it
correctly, but it means paper,
like it's like plastic or
insubstantial or something. So
there's a kind of a
frivolousness that dominates
those parts of the world that
can afford to be frivolous at
this time, which I think is
likely to crumble, and more and
more people are going to get
real. You know, I don't want to
ramble too long, but I just want
to say, as a music person
myself, music has been treated
in such shabby ways in recent
history, and I think it's going
to play an important role in the
future, as it as this reality
process deep, or this reality
kind of, you know, trajectory
deepens, and people will start
to increasingly discover that,
that there's incredible
potential in music that a lot of
people already know, but a lot
of people have no idea, because
of the fact that it's, you know,
oftentimes people put it on they
don't even barely listen to it,
or it's piped into elevators and
grocery stores and all that. And
just treat it as a kind of a
cheapo commodity to influence
the mood of a situation, buy
more or whatever. You know, we
certainly know that with songs
like the Peyote prayer. Songs
and their capability, and the
Icaros of the Ayahuasca world
and their capability and such.
Enough from me.
Marc Caron: Thanks for adding
that in, Steven and and Chris,
you said something that I
thought was so beautifully, said
the and it was really the
metaphor of a mother giving
birth and that pain that turns
into, you know, great pleasure,
right? And it just reminded me
of something that, you know,
it's one thing I always live by.
And you know, we see great
change coming, and one of our,
you know, care ways of dealing
with change is a lot of people
resist change, you know, and I
want to encourage everybody to
embrace the change, because
change is automatic growth, not
necessarily, but when change can
happen and we can grow and help
others grow and transform
through the pain air, quoting
the Pain of change versus, you
know, the the ability to embrace
it as an opportunity, because,
you know, it's going to suck,
it's going to hurt. It happens
when change is happening. Meta
Morphic is, I gotta believe, you
know, isn't always, you know,
isn't painless to the
caterpillar in that sense. And
that, you know, we do anything
when the change comes. You know,
let's embrace the change and
grow with it, based on some of
the things that we've been
talking about here. And Belinda,
I just want to reach, you know,
touch in with you. Is there
something you wanted to add to
what Chris and Steven may have
said there?
Belinda Eriacho: Yes, I think
one of the things that's really
important to me, and one of the
things that I continue to see in
this space is that we forget
about the importance of
spirituality in this space, you
know, either because we don't
understand it, and especially in
circles of science, it's very
difficult for them to talk about
that when we're talking about
healing. For many indigenous
cultures, spirituality is
actually the number one
component that actually helps to
bring healing and wholeness to
an individual. So I think that's
one of the things I also wanted
to add. And as we start to move
forward in this movement that we
be mindful of that,
Marc Caron: yeah, it's really
goes hand in hand with our
disconnection to nature, right?
Unknown: If I could add a
footnote to what Steven had
said, I think in my visionary
experience, one of the messages
has come through over and over
and over again is the pace of
the future is the pace of the
past is irrelevant to the pace
of the future, these things are
going to happen much faster than
we could possibly imagine, much
faster, faster, faster. And one
of the ways it was unfolded, for
me is a vision of the entire
collective psyche, the species
mind that underlies all of our
individual minds is a field, is
a unified field, and then under
the pressure of this time in
history, this field is going to
become hyper stimulated, through
all the angst and all the
suffering and all the
uncertainty, it's going to
become hyper simulated. And when
it becomes hyper stimulated,
it'll begin to function in what
chaos thinkers would call a non
linear system, it'll become a
non linear system, or a far from
equilibrium system. Non linear
systems are capable of doing
things that linear systems
cannot do, and one of the things
they can do is change rapidly.
Change quickly. Small
fluctuations of input can
produce dramatic outputs. The
butterfly flaps its wings and
China can produce a hurricane
across the world. So that means
that under the pressure of the
future, the contribution of
individuals, the influence of
individuals, will not be
diminishing, it'll be
increasing, so that individuals
can affect the outcome of this
evolutionary transition more in
the future than they were in the
past, and it's just through this
and through many other ways, the
speed with which things can
change the creativity and when
non linear systems evoke from
deeper within its Nature, latent
forms of creativity that are
part of the natural fabric, but
had not been actualized up to
that point in time. So I think
Steven's absolutely right. The
creativity of the universe is
going to be manifesting the
collectivity, the
interconnectivity of our beings,
of our hearts and of our minds.
I think we're entering into the
time. One of the ways of
thinking about where we're
coming we're coming into is
we're entering into the period
of the one heart, where humanity
will have will experience the
one heart. And once we know the
one heart in our essence, then
we won't hurt each other, we
won't satisfy we won't. Let
anybody be diminished in their
opportunities of life. And I
think we are awakening into the
one heart. And I think that
you're talking about making the
journey from mind to heart is a
very powerful mentioning this.
Marc Caron: May I mark you. May
Steven,
Stephen Gray: thank you. Oh,
Chris, another beautiful
statement. Thanks so much. Yeah,
I want to add in another thing
on the sort of optimism side you
might say, excuse me. And this
is another one of those little
aphorisms which has come to me
in a variety of ways, but this
particular aphorism is there? I
think it's Victor Hugo said that
there, there is nothing as
powerful as an idea whose time
has come and canucault little
fish, a road man from the Native
American church that I sat up in
meetings with perhaps two dozen
times or more over a 12 year
period. Others have said this
too, probably many actually. But
what Ken said to me one time, or
canuca said to me one time, was
that he and some others had been
having a vision that as the
stability, or, you know,
believable believability,
plausibility of the current,
spiritually disconnected, as
Chris says, egoic, dominated
system becomes less and less
plausible, less and less viable,
then that will create a gap that
is creating a gap, but the gap
will widen or become big enough
for this new vision to come in,
and that new vision will make
sense. You know, as Terence
McKenna, who, I think, borrowed
this from William Blake, or
somebody ultimately, and
reworded it for modern times,
was, if the truth can be told so
as to be understood, it will be
believed, which is essentially
what Dwayne is saying Elgin is
saying in his chapter as well.
So I think it's, again, from the
sort of like giving people hope
perspective, it's important to
realize, again, that we're not
just looking at destruction.
It's the birth, it's the
Death-Rebirth part of it, right?
That's so important.
Marc Caron: Yeah, great. Well,
thank you for adding on to that,
Steven. Now we are getting near
a time we want to be mindful,
because sometimes people don't
like the the long episodes of
things. So if there's one thing
I like to do is I always like to
give people something tangible
or a call to action. And I know
we've talked about a lot of
great ideas and things that
people can do, but I'd like to
ask each of you specifically
that if there was one thing
someone can do to help this
transition along for humanity as
a call to action as an
individual, what would you
suggest or think that might be
the most you know bear the most
fruit? What do you think the
most important action for all of
us to do is moving forward.
Whoever wants to go first? Go
Stephen Gray: ahead. Go first. I
gotta quote canucas Little Fish
again, who said to us in the
teepee a couple of times,
relatives, stay behind the
medicine. So it's a metaphor,
essentially Steven Howard Bunner
in his book plant intelligence
and the imaginal realm, used as
the phrase following the golden
thread, which you and I have
been having fun with the last
couple of years mark. So that's
the getting in front of the
medicine as a as in a reality,
in reality, but also as a
metaphor, is the ego getting in
the way and enforcing its agenda
and its needs onto the
situation, staying behind the
medicine, as I understand it is,
has to do with quieting the
mind, calming the mind, being
humbling oneself, dropping down
into the heart. As people have
said so beautifully, Belinda and
Chris today, dropping down into
the heart and experiencing
through that way and just
following the golden thread, I
think it's a very optimistic, in
a sense, way of looking at our
potential so or to put it into
more sort of a fun way, excuse
me, the wonderful novelist Tom
Robbins In his book fierce
invalids home from hot climates.
Told a story about a friend of
his who had a like a parakeet or
some large, you know, bird. That
was the first thing any visitor
to the place always saw when the
person walked in the door.
Here's this thing sitting on a
stand, and it said to everybody,
the parrot's name was sailor. By
the way, Sailor the parrot, and
everyone who came in through the
store, it said, People of Sea
World relax. So if there's one
sort of simple message, it's
like, relax, pay attention and
trust and stay behind the
medicine. And then I think, you
know, at least I'd like to
believe that things unfold in
and of themselves, and we then
know the next intelligent,
skillful step to take, Mark
before we go, are you going to
is one of us going to say
something about the book launch?
Oh, not there yet. Okay, okay.
Didn't mean to jump
Marc Caron: the gun. Always jump
in the gun. Oh, well, I
Stephen Gray: didn't know if
this was my last time to say
anything for the day or not.
It's
Marc Caron: never your last
time. Oh yes, always just one
more thing. Okay. Anyway,
Steven, that's that's fantastic.
I completely can relate to what
you're saying. And Belinda, what
do you think you know for people
to do one thing leave here from
this conversation and do one
thing that can make a difference
in this world. What Yeah, that
to be.
Belinda Eriacho: Thank you for
that question mark. You know,
one of the things at the very
end of my chapter, I end with a
prayer for healing of humanity.
And I think one of the best
things that we each can do is
look internal to ourselves and
do the work that we are being
called to. Because with that,
then it resonates out into our
families, our communities, and
then globally, just like, you
know, Chris had talked a little
bit about, it's just like that
pebble in the pond to really get
out there and do something, you
know, get involved, look for
practice sacred activism. You
know, look for those
opportunities where you can help
your neighbors, you can help
your community. I think with all
of that said and done, you know,
it helps to for us to evolve
into a better place.
Marc Caron: Very well said. And
I like that you talked about,
you know that the contribution
and volunteerism, because I
think that that's just a
powerful way that people can get
outside of themselves, and, you
know, serve the greater good. So
thank you for bringing that to
the surface, Belinda. I think
it's really important. And
Chris, you're
Unknown: up. Alright. Well, in
addition to doing our inner work
that Belinda referred to in
addressing the shadow and taking
responsibility for our own
shadow, I'd like to sort of
broaden the perspective. Now. I
think Steven's right that music
is going to play a very
important role in the time that
we're coming into and not just
musicians, but artists,
politicians, scientists, every
it's going to take all of us
working in concert to bring
about this social
transformation, and it's to help
us make this shift. So I would
just invite us to remember that
before we were born and before
our children were born, every
one of us knew what we were
getting into before we were
born. We all made a conscious
choice to be born in this time
and to this place in this
particular form, in this
particular sex, in this
particular culture we were born,
and we chose to become an active
participant in this historical
process. And no matter what I
might recommend in terms of the
good thing for someone to do or
a core thing for someone to do,
inevitably, I would reflect my
own limitations, of my own spot
in the world. And I think what's
important is for each one of us
to remember that we have already
buried around us, all the help
that we need, all the
information we need, all the
resources that we need to do our
particular piece in contributing
to this transformation that we
are a part of. The question is
not, what do we need to do? The
question is, I think, will we
have the courage to do what is
ours to do. You will know what
is ours to do. Will we have the
courage to do it? If everybody
has the courage to do their
particular part, then we're
going to make it through this
thing.
Marc Caron: I really like that
that that courage to to push
through that, Chris, I think
it's, you know, so spot on as so
many people kind of stand on the
sidelines, never playing the
game. They're just watching it
right? And I think it's really
important. And if there's one
thing I wanted to add in terms
of just a call to action from
from my perspective, and I think
about a conversation I had with
Donnie Blakey, who I know Steven
knows quite well. I don't know
Belinda, if you knew Donnie
before he passed, but he was
just a brilliant guy. And he
said something to me, and
without the huge story of where
he you know what it was, but the
most important thing he says was
it was about having. Or others,
you know, having your best
interest at heart, not our
interest, kind of like what
Steven was saying about being
behind the medicine and put
other people's best interest in
your heart as well, not what you
can get out of them or do and
really, respect, appreciate,
understand the other person's
world, because so many people
are going through, you know,
trials and tribulations of life
right now, and what we need is
more understanding, you know,
compassion, non judgment, where
we can actually put other
people's best interest at heart
and not our own. And I think
that, you know, that has a huge
potential to change the way
people interact in this world
and where they're at. So, you
know, that's really, you know,
you don't know where other
people are at. So who are we to?
You know, Judge, complain,
criticize, condemn, any of those
things. And when we step back in
a position of love, acceptance,
appreciation of where we are all
at on our journey, it can really
make a difference. Because I
know there's people out there
that don't hear kind words very
often, and we have the ability
to impact people with our words
and our actions
Belinda Eriacho: so and I think
Mark, you meant understanding,
not understanding.
Marc Caron: Yes, yes. Thank you.
Belinda, that's a good one. I'm
going to have to get used to
using that one, because it's
super powerful. Well, I want to
thank you, all three of you, for
being part of our conversation
today. It's always an honor. I
learned so much, and I get
inspired as well. And I know
that you know, Steven's book is
out, it's available, and we're
actually having a book launch
here at St James Hall in
Vancouver, so maybe Steven, you
can talk a little bit about
that. We're pretty excited.
We're getting close,
Stephen Gray: sure. So anyone
who can walk, drive, bicycle,
train, boat or fly to Vancouver,
we'd love to have you with us on
the evening of April 7, which
is, by the way, we didn't know
this when we set this date with
St James Hall, but it happens to
be good Friday, which is an
interesting coincidence, you
might say, or perhaps
synchronicity. So at the very
least it's going to be a small
g, Good Friday. Good Friday.
Excuse me, and we've been mark
you and I have been talking
about it, not book launch,
almost sounds a little bit, I
don't know, academic or library
like or dry or something like
that. But really, we're painting
it as a as an empowering
celebration that Ian, you know,
in my highest ideal, idealized
vision of what this could be, we
bring people together. We talk.
We don't talk a lot. Dennis
McKenna has volunteered to come
in and say a few words. I've
been trying to talk Belinda into
coming up, but it's a long way,
and she's got other things to
do. And, you know, I'd love to
have some more of the
contributors around, but they're
all far flung, so Dennis is our
is our more local person who has
consented. But we're not going
to talk long, and then we're
going to go directly into one of
our frequently done in the past,
cannabis friendly Well, call it
a cannabis ceremony, but we like
to call it a cannabis friendly
ceremony, because you're
certainly not required to, you
know, imbibe any cannabis, and
the ceremony itself will be
equally, maybe not equally, but,
you know, quite decently
powerful and effective as a
meditation ceremony, whether
you, you know, imbibe any
cannabis or not. And then we
will follow that. Well, I'll
hang out in a corner and sign
some books if people want me to.
But other than that, our
wonderful world musician Chene
Edgar in his and his incredibly
talented multi instrumental
percussionist Curtis Andrews,
are going to do an hour or so of
dance music, which, you know,
it's almost impossible not to
dance to the shines music. You
really have to be stuck in your
chair to get to not want to
dance to shine. So what I'm
hoping to do cannabis in that
way, you know, and we haven't
talked about cannabis as part of
this discussion, particularly,
but you know, if we had more
time in an or in another
context, I would want to talk
about how cannabis has an
important role to play in all
this because of its sort of
gentle ubiquity. And when
understood properly, it can be
considered the sacrament of
peace, but it allows people to
have visions and deepening of
experience in a way that's quite
functional in a situation like
150 people at St James Hall. You
know, you don't want to be
handing out two dried grams of
mushrooms to 150 people in that
kind of circumstance, right? But
cannabis, you can do quite
safely, especially with the kind
of guidance that we give them in
the container that we hold for
them. So my vision, my hope, is
that that is an empowering thing
as well as a celebratory thing.
So we highly and strongly
encourage people to come and
join us for that. And so there's
some Mark. You want to talk
about how they can get info and
details Absolutely.
Marc Caron: But I just want to
add to that is like, shine and
Curtis are incredible. And I
know Chris Bache, you know that.
And Belinda, if you were there
on Saturday night at the
conference, Oh, you missed out
on a special treat. I'll get you
some music for it there, but Oh,
my God, incredible, incredible
experience. So just grateful for
that. And yeah, you can get, if
you go to spirit, plant,
medicine, com, slash events,
you'll see a link there where
you can get register your
tickets, because all sorts of
information. There's a couple of
little videos and music you can
sample on and right now until
April, what is its 14 March 17.
Till March 17. March 17, we're
offering a 30% discount for
anybody who wants to join us in
early bird ticket, and that's
going for another few days. So
if you're watching live or after
the fact, now is the time to
save on that. And we look
forward to really having a great
evening of, you know, community
connection ceremony, some
medicine for those who are
interested, and, of course, some
epic music and dance with curves
and shine. It's just really
incredible. So if there's any
last words anybody would like to
share before we wrap it up,
because I'm going to play a
little video. Little video of
the event that's a minute as we
close off. But Belinda and
Chris, if there's anything you'd
like to add, we'd love to to
just have you send us off. No.
Belinda Eriacho: Thank you.
Thank you for this conversation.
It's been really beautiful.
Thank you.
Unknown: And likewise. Thank you
and Steven, thank you for your
vision to bring together all the
voices that you brought together
in the book, and for everything
that you do, and you and Mark do
to facilitate community around
the awakening of our time in
history. Thank you very much.
Stephen Gray: Okay, well, and I
would like to thank, well, mark
for, you know, Mark for you
being so supportive of all this,
you know, for one thing, and
Belinda and Chris for being so
generous and giving your time
for this as well. And really,
I'm not exaggerating both of
both of you, the things that
you've said today have just
really touched me. They're been
really brilliant. So thanks a
lot for that, and
Marc Caron: thank you for your
kind words, everyone. And
Steven, you know, it's just one
way of me just sharing the
message I'm all about. How do we
transform our lives? What are
the tools? What Works and the
medicine brought me to this, and
so I'm just here to help you
know, these great, visionary and
indigenous voices speak out.
It's what I want to be part of
supporting for a change in the
world, and this is one of the
vehicles that I believe is very
powerful to do that. So I'm just
honored to be able to share
space, share time, and help
everybody share their message.
So thank you so much. And with
that being said, I'm going to
play a little video here as we
sign off, just a little bit
about the event and what's going
on, and you'll get to sample a
little bit of music. So here we
go. Thanks again, everyone.
Stephen Gray: Please do not
underestimate how deep we can go
individually and collectively
with this. And I say that from
experience. You
Marc Caron: this all awesome.
Well, thank you all for joining
us. That's just a little teaser
and a taste, but if you go to
the website and take a look,
there's a 10 minute version of
that whole soundtrack that shine
and Curtis were playing that you
can go enjoy, because it's
really quite epic. So thanks
again, everyone until next.
Belinda Eriacho: Great day.
Everyone bye. Thank you again.