Chris Bache: Eventually, I came
to understand that the many
deaths that one endures in this
process are actually that death
is actually a symptom of
purification. The form that you
are can die. The structures of
your life can be shattered, but
the inner essence of your being
cannot die. And I began to
realize that death, what we
experience as death, is actually
a deep form of purification,
which is letting go of the small
in order to welcome and be
welcomed by that which is
larger.
Tami Simon: Hello, friends.
Welcome. I'm so happy that
you're here with us for insights
at the edge. Live in this
episode of insights at the edge.
My guest is Christopher M Bache,
PhD. Let me tell you a little
bit about Chris. He's professor
emeritus in the Department of
Philosophy and Religious Studies
at Youngstown State University,
where he taught for 33 years.
He's also adjunct faculty at the
California Institute of integral
studies, Emeritus fellow at the
Institute of Noetic Sciences,
and he's on the Advisory Council
of Grof legacy training. He's
written several books, including
dark night, early dawn, the
living classroom, and a book
that got my attention. Some
friends of mine said, I'm
reading this book. It's called
LSD and the mind of the
universe. You've got to read it.
It's so engrossing. It's a page
turner. It will actually
introduce you what the mind of
the universe? What's that? And
you know, if there was ever a
moment where I think it's
appropriate to say this
conversation is a conversation
that truly will be filled with
insights at the edge, it's this
conversation with Chris Bache.
Chris welcome.
Chris Bache: Hi, Tammy. It's a
pleasure to be here with you
this evening.
Tami Simon: Tell us a little bit
right here at the beginning,
what prompted you to engage
ready for this over 20 years in
73 high dose LSD sessions that
were structured in a specific
way for the purpose of deep
spiritual awakening and
exploring the nature of the
cosmos. What inspired you to
engage in such what we'll learn
was really an arduous
undertaking.
Chris Bache: Well, I had just
finished graduate school. I got
my PhD from Brown University in
philosophy of religion. I had
published my dissertation in a
series of articles, and was
looking for where to take my
work next. And at that point in
my life, I met the work of Ian
Stevenson in reincarnation
research at Virginia, and, more
importantly, of Stan Grof. And
as soon as I read realms of the
human unconscious, which had
just been published, this was in
78 when I started, I immediately
saw the profound implications
for Stan's work for philosophy
of religion, not just for
psychology, and I knew I wanted
to get involved in doing this
work. So even though LSD had
been made illegal, by that time
this is had been made illegal,
1970 I chose to conscientiously
break the law and to begin a
series of rigorously structured
following stands protocol of LSD
sessions, and I chose, after
three medium dose sessions to
work at high doses. This is a
protocol I don't recommend
today. I would be much gentler
on myself if I were doing it
over again, but at the time I
did, this is what I was doing to
explore to accelerate my own
spiritual development. And then
quickly it evolved into engaging
the deep structures of human
evolution and trying to support
humanity's spiritual
development, and then exploring
this marvelous universe that we
are part of.
Tami Simon: You write towards
the beginning of the book. In
the end, what's important is not
the method of exploration used,
but what this method shows us
about the extraordinary universe
we live in, and that's what I
want to focus on in our
conversation, is really the
discoveries that you made. And
why don't we start off with. The
title of the book, LSD, and here
we go. The mind of the universe.
I'm not sure everyone even can
track with you there, the
universe has a mind. Tell us
what you discovered about this.
Chris Bache: Well, as I came to
experience it, I experience
consciousness as like an
infinite ocean, and when we open
ourselves in deep psychedelic
states, it's like our mind is a
seed catalyst that we drop into
this ocean, and it crystallizes
a set of experiences out of this
infinite potential. And by
absorbing these experiences and
internalizing them and learning
what we are being offered. We're
being being taught. We're
changed, we're purified, we're
we're we're changed inwardly.
And then when we drop that
changed mind into this infinite
potential, it triggers an even
deeper set of experiences out of
out of its infinity. And I
always experienced myself as
engaging an intelligence, a
consciousness, that was
directing my sessions. I mean, I
never did not control what was
unfolding in my sessions. I was
always yielding and following a
lead that came from conscious,
deeper levels of consciousness,
and as the journey continued,
the levels of consciousness that
I was entering deepen several
times, multiple times. And so
what do we call this infinite
consciousness? It's been called
many things in the world's
mystical traditions. I hesitate
to call it God, though. I do
refer to it as the divine,
because God has so many layers
of historical, historical
overlay, which I wouldn't want
to affirm. So just to give him
some sense of the approximation
of the vast scale and scope of
this consciousness, I call it
the mind of the universe. Just
as the universe has a body. It
has a mind. And you can our mind
is as our body is a product of
our universe. Our mind is also a
product of the universe. And
when we sink deeply into our
consciousness, we come out into
a vast consciousness, which you
can think of as the divine
consciousness, or you can think
of it as the mind of the
universe.
Tami Simon: Now you use this
word purification, and I
referred to the 73 journeys that
you went on as having a quality
of arduousness to at least it
read that way to me, as you
include much of the descriptions
of what you went through in each
one of these journeys. I mean,
in the beginning, you know what
you're writing about is
seizures, vomiting, convulsions,
it sounded really rough. Why was
that? Do you think now, in
retrospect, as you look back,
why was all of that physical and
energetic purification
necessary?
Chris Bache: Well, there are
many levels of answers to that,
but basically, if we want to
move into deeper intimacy with
the consciousness of the
universe. We're moving into
states of consciousness which
are large, which are vast, and
operate at a much higher level
of much higher frequency, much
higher energy level, and our
egoic consciousness, the
consciousness which is surrounds
our body in a sense, and which
is the consciousness that we are
operationalizing as egoic
consciousness is just too small.
We have to let go of that
consciousness. And some people
find that easier and more
difficult, but letting go of
that consciousness and dying as
an at the egoic level and
entering into spiritual reality,
I found is actually the first of
many cycles of death and
rebirth, because the universe
has many levels and many
dimensions to it. In order to
enter each successive deeper
level, we have to go through a
deeper level of surrender, and
that often involves very intense
purification, confrontations.
And every step deeper into the
universe is a step into a higher
bandwidth of energy, if you
will. We have to literally learn
to become a being who can live,
can live at that level, become
operational that level for hours
and hours at a time. And that
takes that takes work. It takes
a lot of work.
Tami Simon: You write in the
context of a psychedelic
session, pain is something we
learn to embrace. One learns to
reverse one's instinct to avoid
suffering and to. Open to it
instead, not because we like to
suffer, but because of what lies
on the other side of suffering.
Yes, and I wanted to understand
more about what you learned
about embracing pain, and I
asked this question, Chris,
because in the midst of our
lives, there's so much pain we
need to embrace and so much
letting go that we have to do,
and I don't think that many of
us are that good at it.
Chris Bache: Well, I want to be
careful. I don't want to over
generalize that the insights or
truths that emerge in a
psychedelic session and apply
them to circumstances in our
everyday life. So we'd have to
make some necessary adjustments
to it. But in a psychedelic
session, when we hyper amplify
consciousness, consciousness
begins to clean itself. It
begins to transform itself, and
as it purifies itself, and as it
goes through these first we
encounter unfinished business,
you know, things we'd rather not
face, things we're scared of,
things that frighten us. But
that's only early layers.
Eventually we're going through
layers in which we're sloughing
off not only our personal
identity, but we're sloughing
off our identity as a human
being per se, and then our
identity as a time space being
as we're moving beyond a linear
time and beyond three
dimensional space. All of these
adjustments to move into these
deeper states of consciousness
involve again when you're
working with high doses of a
psychedelic like LSD, it
intensifies and accelerates this
purification process. If you
took an ice cube and put it next
to a candle, meaning analogy for
a gentler spiritual practice,
the candle would melt the ice
cube very gently, and it would
weep and it would dissolve. But
if you threw the same ice cube
on a hot skillet, it would bump
around, jump around and snap,
crackle and pop as the molecules
exploded. And psychedelic
sessions are kind of like the
latter. You're doing the same
process that you do in deep,
long, contemplative retreat
context, but you're doing it
faster, and because you're doing
it faster, there's more of a
kind of a convulsive quality to
it. There's more intense quality
to it. But essentially, it is
the same as traditional
spiritual practitioners undergo
in the dark night of the soul,
in these processes. It's the
same process, eventually, I came
to understand that the many
deaths that one endures in this
process are actually that death
is actually a symptom of
purification. Once you've died
several times and been reborn on
the other side of that process,
you realize you can't die. It's
impossible to die. The form that
you are can die. The structures
of your life can be shattered,
but the inner essence of your
being cannot die. So that death
itself begins to lose its
categories. It becomes to be a
non functional category. And I
began to realize that death,
what we experience as death, is
actually a deep form of
purification, which is letting
go of the small in order to
welcome and be welcomed by that
which is larger.
Tami Simon: Which brings me to
wanting to make sure that we
carefully parse out but I still
want to address here in the
midst of our lives, not in the
midst of psychedelic sessions.
What did you learn about what it
takes to die before we die?
That's really what I want to
understand. Yeah,
Chris Bache: I want to be
careful, because I don't want to
frame my work in terms of the
dynamics of spiritual awakening.
And that phrasing, to die before
we die, so that we do not die
when we die, is kind of really
oriented around the dynamics of
spiritual awakening in my sense,
in my work, even though I began
this work with a sort of an
awakening, a spiritual awakening
agenda. It became much more than
that. It became an adventure of
exploring the deep structure of
the universe itself. And so
death changes as one goes, as
one pivots from spiritual
awakening as a project to
cosmological exploration as a
project. But what I learned, if
I were to try to summarize it in
some way, first, I have no fear
of death whatsoever. I have no
fear of dying. I feel like I've
died many times in that process
and in that process of dying.
Before you die physically.
There. Is a great relaxation
that settles in an abiding
communion with the universe or
with the divine, which begins to
saturate one's physical
existence, so that the boundary
line between here and there,
between being physically alive
and spiritually alive and
cosmologically alive, it gets
very thin in the process. So I
guess I've learned to trust life
more, to recognize that anything
that's coming at me, which is
challenging and difficult, is to
be embraced head on,
straightforward, to not back
away from anything to see
everything to its root, and
that's a major lesson in
psychedelic work. If you run
from the hard stuff, it only
gets worse. But if you embrace
the challenges and let the
universe take you where it wants
to take you, then eventually you
will come to a breaking point,
and when you go through that eye
of that needle, you will open up
into a magnificent landscape a
different level of being you.