Aviv Shahar: Central to the
portals project is the inquiry
about the future and the
evolutionary change underway. We
seek to perceive what is
emerging at the edge of the
human experience, to de code and
integrate insights about how we
humans are evolving through this
liminal transition. Chris Bache
is a professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he
taught for 33 years a fellow at
the Institute of Noetic
Sciences. Chris is the author of
the living classroom teaching
and collective consciousness,
and of dark night, early dawn,
Steps to a deep ecology of mind.
And his third book, LSD and the
mind of the universe, diamonds
from heaven, where Chris
describes his 20 years of
intensive work through 73 LSD
sessions in the interest of
transparency, I have never
touched LSD and never touched
any psychedelic or any mushroom.
My own 42 years of Journey to
unlock the universal human
potential was centered on the
premise that the human brain,
when we are open to the blessing
realms, is the most advanced
chemistry and pharmaceutical
production unit in the universe.
And I've applied my spiritual
and development search in ways
that promote naturally arising
states and inner conductivity.
So we are not here to recommend
that you should do anything.
I've invited Chris because Chris
of your rigor and Focused
Inquiry, which are profound, and
your account where you frame
insights and perspectives that
are of great interest as we seek
to appreciate what is emerging
at the edge of human
consciousness. Chris, welcome.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Aviv,
it's a real pleasure to be here
with you today.
Aviv Shahar: So you have already
lived several lifetimes in this
one life, you've had a full
academic career. You published
three books. You've raised a
family and three children, and
alongside all of this, you've
done this intense 20 years
research work. So let me first
ask, what is the portal you are
in right now? What is the
inquiry you're working on at
this time.
Chris Bache: Well, when I
published LSD in the mind of the
universe, or, as I prefer to
call it, diamonds from heaven,
that's its name for me, when I
published that, I felt like I
had accomplished my life's work.
I mean, after a long career of
teaching as a philosopher of
religion, this was my most
important gift to the history of
philosophical inquiry into the
deep structure of existence. And
that brought with it a
tremendous sense of closure and
relaxation. And since the book
has come out into the world
three years ago, now, just about
three years, I've just been
content to follow the book out
into the world and to follow
into conversations that people
want to have around the issues
that have come up with the book.
I don't have any agenda. I don't
have any felt need to achieve
anything. I have moved to North
Carolina in the last three
years, and so I've been doing a
lot of yard work. My hands are
in the soil, and all those basic
things. I have children and
grandchildren that I love to
stay in touch with as often as I
can. They live farther away.
They're not close by, so that
takes some work. So I'm kind of
growing old in a comfortable
place. I am cultivating a form
of a way of spiritual practice
that builds upon the systematic
remembering of the experiences
that I had on the 73 days
covered in my book. And those
are living memories for me, and
I'm experimenting with how to
use those memories. Memories to
more deeply absorb and integrate
the realities that I touched
very intimately on those session
days.
Aviv Shahar: So we will pick up
this thread, which is
fascinating. You're describing a
condition where a memory is not
frozen in time, it's a living
stream of intelligence that
continues to inform you, even
into into the here and now, and
we will pick this up as we
unfold the conversation in his
forward to your book. Irwin
Laszlo writes this is one of the
most insightful and significant
books I have ever read. But to
understand its significance, one
must be willing to entertain
three premises. A, there is an
intelligence behind the things
that exist in the universe. B,
that there is purpose exhibited
by this intelligence, and see
that it is humanly possible to
access some elements of this
intelligence and learn some
aspects of its purpose. So I'm
interested, given the way you're
describing where you are, how is
this deliberation unfolding for
you in terms of your belief,
your feeling about these three
premises, a that the universe is
an intelligent place, that there
is an inherent or latent
purpose, and that we actually
have, as humans, the capacity to
unpack or to connect or to de
code. Both
Chris Bache: those premises are
absolutely foundational to my
lived reality these days, the
worldview that I was educated in
in graduate school is the
scientific worldview, or the
early 20th century scientific
worldview, that the world is
basically a fantastic machine.
It has no innate intelligence.
Intelligence is lucky accident
that sprung up somewhere along
the way, that our existence is
accidental. It's not purposive,
and that when we die, when our
brain ceases to function
correctly, then our
consciousness disappears, and we
so there is no existential
meaning or significance to our
lives. And all of those
assumptions have been overturned
in my psychedelic work, what I
found is that by dissolving into
the deeper levels of my own
mind, I opened beyond my own
personal existence into the mind
of the universe itself. And in
that process, repeatedly, over
and over again, through many
years, came into communion with
an intelligence that was
profound, just extraordinarily
brilliant and vast beyond
imagination and compassionate
beyond measure. And so returning
to that intelligence and
drinking from it and being
willing to undergo very
challenging processes of
initiation, but always being
rewarded with deeper intimacy
with this intelligence that the
universe I now live in is
saturated with intelligence at
all the levels I can see and at
levels I can't see. The world I
live in, intellectually and
emotionally, is a world of
genius unfolding itself
systematically over vast epics
of time, and it's also a world
in which humanity's
participation in this creative
endeavor is not a participation
that's limited to 100 year
lifetime or one single lifetime,
but it's a participation that
continues lifetime after
lifetime after lifetime through
the process that we classically
have known as reincarnation. But
it's larger than that. It's that
our entire species and the
development of this planet and
this solar system in this
galaxy, is all part of an
exquisite, purposeful,
systematic unfolding of the
creative power of this creative
intelligence. And I hesitate to
call it God or call it the
divine, because as a professor
of religious studies, I know how
that word has been used, and I
know what it has come to mean in
different cultures around the
world. And while part of it is
good and beautiful, so many
other parts of it are limiting.
So I prefer to speak in terms of
the creative intelligence of the
universe, the intelligence that
is behind existence and the.
Intelligence that is inside
existence, expressing itself in
the complexity of life.
Aviv Shahar: So in many ways,
you have just given us the
condensed preview version of the
the everything we are about to
unfold in the next hour and so
on, which is beautiful. It's
exactly what, what I was hoping
we can do give, give the people
that join us a sense on the
front end of what we are about
to unfold in, in the way you
just described that. You were
again describing three layers
there as as you talked about,
first making contact with this
intelligence, appreciating this
intelligence, and then you're
describing that as you engage
with that intelligence, there is
an aspect of communion, a fuller
whole person experience, and
then the deeper inside that you
discover the sense of compassion
and intimacy. So and you say
that the universe is interested
in our experience of it. What do
you believe about why that is
the case?
Chris Bache: Well, first of all,
part of my experience has been
the classic teaching in some of
the Eastern traditions that the
essence of the individual is the
same as the essence of the
totality that Atman is Brahman,
that our our nature is the
nature of the Divine, which is
the nature of reality itself. So
it's not completely true to
think of this in terms of a
duality between me and it at a
deeper level, my being is a
fractal emanation, manifestation
of its reality, of its truth. So
our relationship is, it's deeply
essential and mutually
participating right from the
start, but in terms of function,
in terms of Chris Bache, his
actual function, I am so small
and it is so vast, that
relatively speaking, there's a
relative duality involved. And
of course, it's not just the
small bit and the totality, but
between the totality and my
little small bit, there's layers
and layers and layers and
layers. It's a very, very
complex, organic system of
massive scale. So my to get to
the focus of your question, my
experience has been that as I
went through my spiritual work,
and went through my spiritual
practice, psychedelic practice,
and went through the initiations
and the cycles of death and
rebirth that I'm sure we'll talk
to later, and opened into
periods where I would spend
hours absorbed in communion and
dialog or with this
intelligence, and then, as I
would begin to get smaller and
come back into my normal shape
and size, so there was a window
that would open and stay open
for hours, and then a window
that would close, I repeatedly
had the sense of that This
intelligence was so pleased to
have this opportunity to share,
to commune, to convey it, not
just not with me, but with
humanity as a whole, that we are
just getting after 13 point 7
billion years, we are just
getting able to begin to
embrace, to open Up to the scale
of the intelligence of the
universe, so that for 13 point 7
billion years, this intelligence
has been creating this universe,
this magnificent garden, and
holding it while we evolve
slowly to the point where we can
just begin to become aware of
what it has been doing, and it
seems to be so pleased to be
able to share consciously, what
it has previously been
constructing unconsciously,
Aviv Shahar: the idea of seeing
ourselves as a fractal of the
whole inside a nested reality
that is interpenetrating.
Carries some some powerful
propositions and ideas that we
will unfold and you unfold in
your book. Because what it says
is that as I change in myself as
you change in yourself, because
we are a fractal of the whole
we, in some way, facilitate and
catalyze a bigger change. So we
are participant to this
unfolding, gigantic story that
you are describing.
Chris Bache: Absolutely we are
participants. We are an
expression of the creative
process. We are continuance of
the creative process, and we are
learning to be generators, more
and more conscious generators of
the creative process.
Aviv Shahar: Yes. So would it be
right to say that when you
suggest and when we contemplate
that the universe is interested
in us, in humanity, that it's a
form of the universe, interest
in itself, in its own evolution,
that it comes to experience
through its beloved human I
Chris Bache: think so. I think
that's, you know, that's widely
viewed insight in many of the
mystical traditions of the
world, that there's a deep
collaboration. And the in this
intelligence is interested in
its expansion, and we are, in
some ways, at this point in
time, one of the cutting edges
of its expansion, its learning
Aviv Shahar: well, so let's
begin to explore a little into
and through the journey. Just
there to pick up on your
description that we are at the
leading edge of something that's
evolving through this universe,
and you describe in Session Six,
the vast community of explorers.
And you write, I experienced
explorers in different fields of
learning as part of a vast
cooperative enterprise. What do
you believe about and how did
you experience then and when you
reflect now on this community of
explorers, and I get the visual
sense of people who are in
different spaces and domains
right at the edge, the cutting
edge of discovery.
Chris Bache: Well, you know, as
I was first trained as an
historian, and then as in
philosophy of religion. And so I
spent, you know, years and years
and years studying some of the
great thinkers in history in
these fields. And so I had a
real sense of great beings and
great autobiographies who have
contributed systematically to
the tapestry of learning that I
was an inheritor of in various
ways, and this session was
really about it was helping
liberate me from a felt sense of
responsibility to The
intellectual lineages that I had
been educated into. It was as if
I was above the earth, and I was
watching these beings through
time, through history, do make
their great contributions to art
and literature and science and
philosophy and theology, and
usually I would be just
intimidated by, you know,
genius, you know how great they
were. But here I felt myself as
a young learner, entering the
company of older learners and
entering into the fellowship of
learning. But then the next step
was I came to see I was given a
survey of all the knowledge that
I had acquired through all the
years of college and graduate
school, and I was given a series
of lessons which taught me the
incompleteness of this
knowledge. And then I was shown
a new way of doing philosophy
that was opening in my life with
this work, and I believe that
psychedelics represent a
revolution in the way of doing
philosophy, not just certain
insights into consciousness, but
how philosophy can be done and
and this new way is to first
systematic, systematically
expand the boundaries of
experience to enter into
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, which, of course,
humanity has been doing for
1000s and 1000s of years through
meditation, yoga, Transcendence,
and also psychedelics, but
moving into non ordinary state
of consciousness, in my case
with psychedelics, paying very
careful and critical attention
to what happens in those
experiences, come back and
record them very precisely, as
exactly as possible, within 24
hours, and then to reflect on
them, to integrate them, To
integrate them with bodies of
knowledge and other disciplines,
and to compare them to the
experiences that other people
are having in these states, and
by systematically expanding and
contracting consciousness in
this way, but not just having
interesting experiences, but
intellectually digesting the.
Experiences, internalizing those
experiences. What I think we're
able to do is that we can begin
to think about things and to
understand things and talk about
things that previously most
human beings could never talk
about, could never envision,
only the most sophisticated
mystics in the most esoteric
traditions could have access to
some of these domains, but with
psychedelics, if they are
handled responsibly and
conscientiously, even a modest a
person of modest means can have
access to this reality, these
realities, and begin to
understand some of the workings
of the universe that are
revealed through these states.
Because as our as our mind,
changes its sensitivity, we
begin to be able to experience
different aspects of the cosmos.
So it's like the color spectrum.
We see a certain portion of the
visible spectrum, but when we
could slide our our awareness to
a different portion of the
spectrum, A Different World of
Color opens to us the same way
with consciousness. So what I
what this session gave me, was
intellectual permission to not
try to prove everything to the
satisfaction of my peers, but to
rather begin a new methodology
in philosophy that may not be
recognized for generations and
it would take the rest of my
life to really carry out, and
that's why I did this work for
20 years of psychedelic
exploration, and then I spent
another 20 years thinking about
and digesting those experiences
before publishing diamonds from
heaven.
Aviv Shahar: Would it be correct
to say that so in any of the
pathways to altered states that
whatever we come into contact
with, whether you view it as a
stream of intelligence, or
whatever way you frame this,
that it depends still on the
frame of reference that you have
cultivated before. So in your
case, your various studies and
research and work in Philosophy
and Religion provided, in a way,
inner scaffolds, inner
structures for the experience
that you were going through by
way of translation. That is to
say, if somebody else showed up
adjacent through an adjacent
experience, but with different
scaffolds, with different inner
topography, they would be
interpreting their experience
possibly differently. Would you
how would you restate what I'm
trying to get to and sense there
Chris Bache: good point and
really an important thing to
consider. It's not just the
question is not just whether
they would interpret their
experiences differently, but
would they actually be having
different experiences because
their conditioning was different
going into the experiences? This
is a discussion that I've had
with Ken ring, one of the
founders of near death episode
research, and the author of a
number of books, and he and I
published our dialog around this
particular point in an article
called are deep psychedelic
experiences trustable? Do they
simply reflect the conditioning
of the personal psyche or the
even the collective psyche, or
do they actually go beyond one's
conditioning and give us access
to something truly veridical
about the universe? And I want
to be I want to honor both sides
of this discussion, because I
subscribe to what some have
called a participatory model of
spiritual experience, which
means these experiences are not
like apples hanging on the
cosmic tree that you just reach
up and pluck and they're just
there for the taking, and
anybody can reach up and pluck
them, and it's there for the
taking. It's a much more complex
dynamic that's involved, but,
and I'll explain that in a
minute, but first, I want to say
that my conditioning was
shattered again and again and
again as I took this journey.
And I think that's true for
people who work systematically
with these states, that in the
beginning, our conditioning has
a strong coloring and shaping
the role, and simply our
personal history has a shaping
role, but very quickly, after
several years, you reach a point
where you get past all the
conditioning that you've had,
even. From birth forward, and
you're you're you literally your
entire physical existence
collapses, and in that collapse,
one moves beyond territory that
you've ever known intellectually
are the I think my My academic
background helped me understand
what I was experiencing, but did
not structure what I was
experiencing. I was often wished
that I had PhDs in in physics
and astrophysics, and
particularly to better
understand some of the phenomena
that I was being shown. But
instead of picking an apple from
a tree, I think it's something
like this, as I have experienced
it, the mind of the cosmos. The
mind of the universe is an
infinite lake of infinite
potential capable of giving us
infinite variety of experiences.
And our mind acts like a seed
catalyst that we drop it into
this infinite potential, and it
catalyzes a certain response, a
certain set of experiences which
reflect that seed crystal. As we
internalize those experiences,
we go through a process of
purification and transformation,
which changes the nature of our
individual consciousness, so
that later, when we return to
that infinite lake where the
seed crystal that we drop into
it has been changed, expanded,
and it precipitates a different
set of experiences out of its
infinite potential. This is what
I mean by it's a participatory
cosmology, a participatory
model. And it's not that our our
consciousness, creates or
dictates what emerges. It's just
that there is a complicated
feedback process that's going
and the more we go into this,
the more we do it, the more new
and new and new frontiers begin
to open that are far beyond
anything we could imagine,
beyond anything, even against
many of the things that we've
been taught. It's just it's new
territory, and then comes the
task of trying to make sense of
what it was that you experience.
And these experiences are kind
of sequential. It's like
exploring new territory. So one
experience leads to another,
which leads to another, which
leads to another in a complex,
overlapping manner. So in the
end, you have to examine the
structure of the whole
trajectory of experiences,
because it's like a giant jigsaw
puzzle to puzzle.
Aviv Shahar: Yeah, there is a
potent way you describe the very
thing you just painted for us
when you talk about the
foundation of teaching that
finds you in session 16, which
you call self generating fields
of experience. And you write, we
are self generating fields of
energy in a living universe. We
generate energy by making
choices, and the universe
responds to this energy. That's
what you were just describing
with a lake in complex and
subtle ways. We are always
creating our own experience. And
then you add, we control the
flow of energy out from and back
into our lives. What comes to us
from without originates from
within. The more one moves
towards one's center and engages
the deeper levels of one's
conditioning, the more one
becomes conscious of being the
source of one's experience. I
suppose that's what you were
describing now in in the way
that insight continues to evolve
with you. It's a powerful
synthesizing of the human
journey, whether you do any
psychedelics or not, because
that insight is true in the in
the normal day to day
consciousness, you don't need to
be in an altered state to
realize it and or you can
discover the edge of your own
experience and realize that you
actually are the catalyst of
what it is that the universe
brings to you
Chris Bache: absolutely this.
I'd like to I really hope that
what I've shared in this book is
used by and is useful to people
who never take a psychedelic
whatsoever, because, in the end,
psychedelics are not critical.
My understanding is that
psychedelics, and particularly
the psychedelic that I used in
my work, LSD, is an amplifier of
consciousness. It does not give
you any. Specific experiences.
It's not a hallucinogen. It
doesn't give you false visions.
It amplifies consciousness. It's
all it does, how you use that
amplified consciousness, how you
care, take it, how you protect
it, isolate it, internalize it,
meditate with it, and engage
your mind during those hours of
hypersensitivity is what
determines the quality of the
perception that emerges from
that dialog. So many people have
written me and they said, I've
never taken a psychedelic in my
life. I've been meditating for
40 years. I understand what
you're writing about. It really
parallels my own experience and
my own spiritual practice. And I
say yes, because it's not about
psychedelics. What we're
exploring is the nature of
consciousness to reveal the
deeper truths of its own being
and of the universe. And so this
idea that we are self generating
fields of experience is an
ancient idea. I mean, it really
is at the core of the belief in
karma and rebirth that we are,
it's we are a learning system.
We are born in circumstances of
our choosing, of our destiny. We
make choices in response to
those circumstances. We learn in
response to those circumstances
and and in that process, we are
changed. And when we die, that
process doesn't end, but it
continues. And so what I was
experiencing was simply an L, an
escalated and intensified vision
of that ancient teaching.
Aviv Shahar: You then describe,
later a cosmic tour, and you say
that for several hours, the
consciousness that accompanied
you took you on a tour of the
universe to show you its work,
and that it brought an
overwhelming sense of
Homecoming. What did you
discover about the universe
through this tour, and what was
the sense of Homecoming?
Chris Bache: Well, this was my
19th session, so by this time, I
was about 334, years into the
work, and I had gone through ego
death, and I had entered into
what in the book I described as
the ocean of suffering, kind of
a the hell realms of of the
collective psyche, the where the
collective psyche stores, it's,
it's, it's, most torturous
memories of the history of the
species. And I had navigated
that, and as almost a the gift
or the grace of because I had
volunteered to participate in a
in a healing of some aspect of
the collective psyche. The
universe gave me this gift, many
gifts at that time, and one of
them was this cosmic tour where
it would take me. This is where
I wish I had degrees in physics
so I would be able to concretize
or conceptualize some of the
things it was showing me, but
over and over again, it took me
and showed me some aspect of our
cosmic reality and overwhelm. I
was overwhelmed repeatedly by
the genius of it, by the
intelligence of it, by the
intentionality of it. It taught
me a lot about reincarnation. It
taught me about the
reincarnation patterns of our
species, not just individuals,
but of the dynamics of
collective reincarnation. It
took me into some of the
formation structures of
galaxies. And then I'm not, not
sure whether it was this, this
particular part, or in the
immediately next it it took me,
I would go through a succession
of death and rebirth processes
internal to this tour. And it
took me into deeper and deeper
levels of ontological
simplicity, and I began to
experience a deeper and deeper
Quiet, quiet beyond any quiet I
had ever imagined. And
saturating the silence was a
sense of Homecoming, deeper and
deeper levels of Homecoming. And
at one particular transition, I
went into this extraordinary
piece, extraordinary homecoming.
And I was overwhelmed by how sad
it was that we had lost contact
with this innate quality of our
own being at this cosmic level
of. Yeah. And I asked what, what
had happened? And it said this
voice that was accom, that the
consciousness I was with said we
had left time. We left time. And
then it said we never intended
so many to get caught in time.
It was as if linear time was
simply one of the experiments
that the universe was having. So
somehow moving deeper into home
also meant moving beyond the
conditions of space and time. So
this was a universe, a tour, not
only of the physical universe,
but it was a tour of the levels
of reality behind the universe
that kind of give birth to space
and time itself. And we come
from these realities. Our
substance is made from these
realities. So we participate
inside the divine creation of
space and time as a spiritual
being who was rooted in these
spiritual realities,
Aviv Shahar: and we will get
further to both the divine
reality and the various cycles
of death and rebirth. But just
to pick where you started, there
the sense of suffering that you
were describing. What do you
understand? Stepping back and
looking at the way you interpret
the experience, what do you
understand to be the
significance of suffering in the
place of suffering in the
evolutionary process? Why is
suffering part of the
evolutionary process?
Chris Bache: That really is a
core question, isn't it? It's a
deep question, and it's a hard
question to answer without
preparing the ground well, and
preparing the ground well would
take much longer than we have
room for here, so I'm going to
have to take shortcuts, and I'm
going to have to ask the
indulgence of your listener,
during the same period of the
cosmic tour, During the same
year, when I was being given a
crash course in cosmology, 101,
I was taken back to what
appeared to be the beginning of
creation itself, the Beginning
of Time and Space, and I
experienced an overwhelming
love, just completely saturating
me and just overwhelming me. It
was a cosmic love. And then I
experienced all of evolution,
the birth of space and time, and
all the evolution of space and
time taking place inside this
love, and this love was holding
it and guiding it. And I,
because of experiences that I
had had, I knew that evolution
involved tremendous suffering,
terrible suffering, not just for
the human race, but for species
up and down the evolutionary
line. But let's just focus on
the human race. I knew history,
and I knew how much harm we had
done to each other and how much
harm the planet had done to us,
and how much suffering was
involved. And in this
experience, I experienced all of
this suffering as something that
humanity had taken on, as by
free choice, and by free choice
motivated by the Divine Love of
creation that lies Behind
creation, so that the suffering
that is inevitable in an
evolutionary project which is
stretched across billions of
years, was not something which
was being done to us, it was not
a punishment. It was not being
inflicted on us. It was not the
work of demonic forces, but it
literally was a burden that we
had consciously chosen in order
to participate in this creative
project. Now, why is there so
much suffering? There are layers
and layers of a response to
this. One of them is we make
choices. Sometimes we make good
choices, sometimes we make bad
choices. We learn by inheriting
the consequences of those of our
choices. And sometimes we
inherit bad consequences from
bad choices. But I think the
answer is much deeper. Goes much
deeper than that. In order to
understand why human beings
suffer, we have to have some
understanding of what a human
being is, and, more importantly,
what a human being is becoming.
We are not finished as a
species. We are just beginning.
We only develop sufficient
consciousness to to reach our
minds down to the source of our
own mind. About 5000 years ago,
you. We're going to be evolving
for millions and billions of
years. Yet we are not finished.
We are just getting started.
Much of the suffering inherent
in human existence has to do
with the unfinished nature of
our own evolutionary process.
There will come a time I'm sure
that we will have sufficient
consciousness and sufficient
self control that we will be
able to wash disease out of our
body through complete control of
our mind. But we're not there
yet. We will be capable of so
many things that we are not
capable of now, but that all of
the things we are going through
now are part of not only the
learning exercise, but the
building exercise of building a
form of human being much more
advanced than the form of human
being we are today, just as Homo
sapiens is more advanced than
Homo erectus, which is more
advanced than our ancient
ancestors in the primate
kingdom. So I think the core,
the deepest level of the answer
to your question, what is the
role of suffering in evolution?
The deepest level is that it's
simply a burden that we take on
voluntarily to participate in
the joy of creating the
universe, of creating our
species in the universe, and
that in the end, it benefits us.
It's in some ways, like the
suffering that a woman takes on
when she gives birth. She knows
it's coming. She does it
voluntarily. It's absolutely
terrible. It's really
horrendous. But when she holds
her child, it's worth it. And I
think that's true for evolution
too. There will come a time when
we will have evolved to a point
where we will look back on the
entire history of all that pain,
without diluting it, without
denying it, and we will say it
was worth it in order to become
what we have become today.
Aviv Shahar: So central ethos in
this is recognizing that we are
involved in an unfinished
project. As you say, Evolution
The universe is an evolving
unfinished project, and you're
making, right there in in your
journey, some potent points
about the cost of existence and
of the physical universe, and in
that context, as you just framed
it now, and this entire
appreciation of the visible
universe as it contains only
small parts of the universe, so
which for us, for all intents
and purposes, the dimensions
that you are describing that you
said you wish you had
astrophysics in your degrees in
education, some of those
dimensions is what scientists
today describe as dark energy
and and dark matter, which I
Intuit we can anticipate is a
very crude, primitive definition
of the so much more that is
going to be discovered once we
are prepared to reintegrate the
greater realities of
consciousness and human
possibility and escape this idea
that The universe is a is a
machine that just reproduced the
same but as you describe the and
just painted the sense of the
physical universe, you're making
a very important point, which is
that the universe is not
physical. Universe is not a
trap, not a punishment that we
have fallen into of or from, and
that there is this purpose
inherent in the totality of
life, which you describe as the
continual transformation, the
continual growth. So for me,
what you are describing, there
is a lucid and beautiful
distinction about the project,
the evolutionary project, which
you just narrated again. What
else must we whether you choose
to do any psychedelic or any
other expedition to altered
states. What? What else must we
understand about that
relationship of the universe at
large, the physical universe,
and us as agents of the cutting
edge, the leading edge of this
process?
Chris Bache: Boy, you're asking
good questions. Let me. Let me
step back and put this in the
context all of the religions of
the last 5000 years, the what I
call the Axial Age, religions
all came into existence, you
know, five 3000 years ago, when
we first began to get underneath
our individual consciousness
and. Tap into spiritual
consciousness, tap into the
consciousness of the universe,
or the consciousness of the
Divine all of the religions of
this era, both Western and
Eastern religions, are examples
of what I would call an up and
out cosmology, and I understand
their intention when you begin
to experientially touch your
divine essence. It is so much so
ecstatic fill, so bliss filled,
so much more satisfying than
physical existence, that how
could you not but think that you
belong there more than here? And
so all the theologies that were
given birth to in this period
are theologies of return, which
basically say we don't belong on
Earth. We belong in heaven,
somehow, through some mishap or
some misfortune or punishment,
we've here. But what we want to
do is get out of here and get
back to there, and whether it's
by Western concepts of
salvation, being saved by faith
are Eastern concepts of
reincarnation, where you evolve,
evolve, evolve, until you wake
up spiritually. And when you
wake up, the Hindus say they
call that Moksha escape, because
you escape back to spiritual
paradise. So the whole agenda of
the Axial Age religions is to
achieve some type of catharsis
which allows you to abandon time
and space and to return home.
But that leaves open the
fundamental question, what is
the purpose of time and space?
What is the purpose of the
entire created order. When we
were thinking that the universe
might be only 6000 years old, as
many of we did in ancient times,
you might justify an up and out
cosmology. But now that we
understand much more how big our
universe is, how old it is, and
how brilliant it is, and how
filled with genius, the idea
that spiritual awakeness,
spiritual fruition should result
in leaving the physical universe
just doesn't ring true as
powerful. It doesn't have the
same appeal. And I think what's
happening is we are now growing
up enough to recognize the to
understand that first vision,
but to see that it's actually a
very incomplete cosmology,
because now we're beginning to
understand that the the next
step after waking up, or the
step of waking up To the reality
of one's divine nature and the
CO participation, the
coexistence of divinity and
physicality, and physicality
itself as an aspect of divinity.
Then that opens up the
possibility of waking up and
then bringing heaven to earth,
bringing truly the ecstatic
experience, the ecstatic
experience of heavenly
consciousness inside, into time,
space, reality and building and
truly shaping the physical world
In a way to be a reflection and
an embodiment of spiritual
Paradise, and that's where we
find the importance of emergent
spirituality, of a of a embodied
spirituality, this theme which
is becoming more and more
prevalent. It's not an escapist
spirituality, it's an embodied
spirituality. And psychedelics,
if they give us a sensitivity,
it's not about getting up and
out. It's really about getting
more and more deeply within, to
open up, to bring it in deeper
and deeper and deeper within.
And so then the question
becomes, okay, now, if we
understand that if that speaks
truth to us, if we feel that
that's true, how can we do this?
And then the question becomes,
well, now we're talking
practicalities.
Aviv Shahar: Yes, well, so
before we transition to that,
this axial vision that you
describe of the two worlds
described in different religious
texts in variety of different
ways. So you're really narrating
in your experience and updating
of that theological cosmological
view when you describe the sense
of two cosmic beings, one that
had the nature of a of a he, and
one that had the nature of a
she. And you describe the the
feminine cosmic being, if, if I
get that correctly, as the one
that devoted itself to the Qi.
Creation of time and space and
the physical manifestation. And
it's partnering intelligence in
he holding that other part of
that compassionate communion of
love, describe, describe what
that insight was and how it
builds on what you were just
narrating, that that the this
next phase of evolution in what
you were proposing is actually
those two parts of the of the
cosmic process, getting
integrated and interpenetrating
into each other, such that they
liberate each other of their
loneliness.
Chris Bache: I want to be
careful, and I want to remind us
that a finite mind does as best
as it can to give cognitive
structure to transcendent
experiences. So what I'm about
to describe is in terms of, just
as you summarized it, a
splitting of the Divine
Principle into two halves, a
male half that stays outside of
time and space in a transcendent
position, and a female half that
begins the process of
manifesting time and space in
the entire physical cosmos. Now
I don't literally think in terms
of male female in this way, but
this is the best my mind could
come up with to understand. So
it's the principle that's
important. The principle is that
not all of the creative
intelligence manifest as
physical reality. Some of it
stays and holds the position
outside physical reality. So
there is a spiritual reality
which gives birth to physical
reality. My experience was now,
as we are growing up through
1000s and 1000s of years,
millions of years of evolution,
we finally have reached the
point where physical reality is
sufficiently conscious that it
can return to transcendent
reality and not merge, but enter
into communion, into con to
consummate a return. And this
return doesn't lead to an up and
out exit, but this return leads
to the Divine wedding, the
divine marriage, the infusion,
deeper and deeper infusion of
the transcendent divine and the
eminent divine. I think of this
as kind of like white light, the
transcendent divine and the
immanent Divine is kind of green
light, green energy. So when the
white energy and the green
energy fuse, we have awakened
resplendent physical existence
with a consciousness that far
Transcendence, what we have
known up to this point in time.
And I think we see this in the
lives of the great mystics, the
lives of the great spiritual
teachers. They are living a
absolutely grounded physical
life, and yet they are also
living a profoundly spiritual
life simultaneously. And from
that perspective, the Buddhists
say nirvana is Samsara. Samsara
the world of form and Nirvana,
the world of Transcendence.
Those are not two separate
realities. Those are now co
existent realities in our lives
that is embodied spirituality.
Aviv Shahar: And I would say
that one of the ways for us to
describe this is to that we are
engaged in the project of
spiritualizing this world. We
don't need to go to another
world to gain the spiritual
experience we are in the
physical form to help
spiritualize this world. Part of
the report from these journeys
that you're offering us is the
validation that indeed we have
entered a time where you don't
need to be high Lama or just a
special priest. It actually is
an invitation for humanity at
large to each in our own way,
become participant in what you
called earlier, the fellowship
of learning, and then become
involved in the in the
evolutionary project. So I want
here now to start to make the
next transition for you to
describe the realization of the
relationship between the
personal awakening and the
collective awakening and how.
How you have gone through these
different cycles of death and
rebirth through this experience
and the significance of these
and how do they facilitate
collective awakening?
Chris Bache: Well, first, what
I'm going to describe is my
variation on an ancient teaching
in Buddhism, for example, when
one sits down to meditate or do
some form of spiritual practice,
the first thing they do is
cultivate what is called
bodhicitta. And bodhichitta is
the wish to save all sentient
beings. So you do this practice
not for your personal benefit.
You do it to nourish the
uplifting of the whole of
creation. The last thing you do
at the end of your practice is
what's called distribution of
the merit. You give all the
blessings you've acquired. You
don't try to hold them to
yourself. You give them away. So
everything you're doing in in
mature spiritual practice is not
for your personal benefit. It's
for the benefit of the whole
these ideas show up in the
spiritual traditions up and down
the line. So the way this showed
up in my practice, in my
psychedelic practice, I began my
psychedelic practice thinking
that this was part of a personal
transformation. So I would, I
would go through some
purification process, some
Death-Rebirth process, that
would result in my personal
healing and my personal
liberation, perhaps, or
something. But it was always
sort of personally referenced.
But what happened was, after
about two years after I had gone
through a lot of personal
cleansing and had relived my own
birth and gone through a
Death-Rebirth process and had my
earth identity shattered, I
entered into a new cycle of
very, very intense purification
processes. But they were not
personal. They were collective.
They systematically got larger
and larger for two years until
they were they included the
experiences of hundreds millions
of human beings over 1000s of
years, and there were periods of
just intense agony and suffering
and violence. And at first I
thought this must be some form
of a deeper ego death. But it
went on for so long and it
involved so many beings that
eventually I came to a new way
of thinking about it, and it was
very challenging. It took me
years to even admit this
possibility, but what I came to
eventually was the conviction
that in these sessions, I was
not working to heal or transform
my individual being, but I was
being used cooperatively to heal
and transform my entire human
family, that the pain that I was
engaging was not part of my
personal pain or even my
reincarnational soul pain, but
it was, it was part of the pain
of humanity's history itself,
that this pain of history was
lodged in the collective psyche,
just as My personal pain might
be lodged in my personal psyche.
Humanity's collective pain was
lodged and stuck in the
collective psyche. And somehow,
by becoming as large as these
sessions allowed me to become, I
was able to take on this
suffering and to digest it just
as at an earlier time, I had
taken on and digested my
personal suffering as a result
of making this choice, of
allowing this to happen, the
universe began to not only take
me deeper into its pain, which
lasted about two years. And then
there was a crescendo, and then
it was finished. I was not taken
back into this territory
anymore. I went beyond. But the
universe took me deeply into a
spiritual awakening process,
which was again, not personal,
it was collective. It began to
take me into the future, into
what I came to call deep time.
And it took me there, not as an
individual, but as a field of
energy, somehow encompassing
large swaths of the of the
collective psyche. And I had
repeatedly this experience that
there is no ultimate membrane
between the individual and the
collective, between the
individual and the species.
Everything that the individual
is is a distillation of
something that's going on in the
species, and the species is the
collection. Of everything that's
going on in its individual
manners, pick any problem, any
issue that anybody is working on
in their life, and they would
not have that issue if it
weren't for some pattern of this
issue that's really touching the
lives of many, many people in
the human family. So that I
learned over and over again in
many different settings and
context that the work of
spiritual transformation of the
individual and the work of
collective as a whole are all
intertwined, and there are no
absolute boundaries. There are
relative boundaries, but there
are no absolute boundaries. So
that my book, this my book dark
night, early dawn, I describe
this in terms of the dark night
of the soul. And the dark night
of the soul is a very, very
intense period of spiritual
purification that takes place
before the individual mystic
awakens into spiritual
realization. But here I was
talking about the dark night of
our collective soul, that
humanity as a whole was going
through a dark night, a period
of profound purification, which
I think, by analogy, is a period
which is leading up to a
profound spiritual awakening for
humanity as a whole. I don't
many people have said this. We
are past the age of individuals
enlightenment. Now. We either
become enlightened as a species,
we either wake up as a species,
or we're going to lose this
planet. So my work has been
about collective transformation,
not personal transformation, so
much
Aviv Shahar: and implicit inside
this, this insight is also the
idea that anybody you can choose
to work on your individual
struggle or on your individual
healing, and when you work on
the individual, you can choose
devotionally or by sentiment or
by a frame of mind. Recognize
that your work on yourself is
part of your contribution to the
whole, and if you make that
internal inclusion and
integration, you become part of
the fellowship of learning and
healing, and essentially you you
opt in to the evolutionary
project.
Chris Bache: Yeah, now you are
in the you evolutionary project,
whether or not you recognize it.
Whether or not you opt in, you
are part in it. You are hard
wired into it. But if you
recognize it, then you can
consciously participate, and
that deepens and enriches that
process.
Aviv Shahar: And then, as the
journey continued, you moved
from the personal to the
collective and to the archetypal
and to the higher archetypal
dimension describe what these
realms and these cycles of death
and rebirth meant for you in
this discovery.
Chris Bache: Well, after two
years of working in what I came
to call this collective
suffering, the ocean of
suffering and experiencing the
blessings of insights that were
also coming in a chapter I
called the initiation into the
universe, where I was given
these teachings of cosmology,
101, the suffering kind of
reached a culmination. It's hard
to describe, but it was kind of
a collective breakthrough, and
then it spun me into a level of
reality that was stunningly old.
It was ancient, and for the next
year and a half it kept bringing
me back. Now it's always
progressive, so it take me back
to that level of reality. And
every time I entered that
reality, what was stunning about
it was it was ancient and it was
more real than physical time
space was, and that's very
disorienting, you know, to think
that there is a reality which is
more real than physical reality,
it just completely shattered me.
But it was such a consistent
part I had to no chance but to
choice, but to yield and give
into that.
Aviv Shahar: So part of your
struggle, part of your struggle
in the journey, must have been
the how do you stabilize these
insights and awarenesses when
you need to come back to teach
in the classroom and and be a
family man and all the rest of
that?
Chris Bache: Wherever I was on
Saturday, in my inner work, on
Monday, I was back in the
classroom teaching my courses,
which is part of the very
grounding. It's really, really
important if you're going to go
deep, you have to be grounded.
You have to lifestyle of
commitment to grounded practice.
And for me, that grounding was
provided by my family and by my
teaching, my students always but
it is difficult. And there's one
thing I'll mention that Eric.
Every time you break through to
a new level of reality, it's
cognitively very confusing. You
don't understand what you're
experiencing at first, and when
you write up your description,
it has gaps and fragments. But
if you go back again and again
to that level of reality,
eventually your mind learns to
adapt to it, and you begin to be
more capable of having more
coherent experiences there. So
in the beginning, your your
write ups maybe have holes in
them, but with repetition, those
holes are filled in, and you
have more complete pictures. And
this is part of what I mean by
cultivating the philosophical
discipline that's required to
have coherent, sustained
experiences of deeper levels of
reality, the second part that's
required is, and this is a
again, this applies at multiple
levels of of the adventure,
higher levels of reality are
deeper levels, let's say of
reality are higher levels of
energy. Every deeper level of
reality functions at a higher
level of energy. So when I made
the transition into archetypal
reality, I went through huge
purification processes in which
I was dissolved into white hot
lava, plunged into burning suns,
just tremendous fields of energy
that just burning more and more
out of me. And if I hadn't gone
through that, I wouldn't have
been able to have coherent
consciousness. Because you
literally, you have to become a
being that can live at that
level for hours at a time, even
only temporarily, in order to
have coherent cognition at that
level. So to enter into
archetype of reality, yeah, it
takes
Aviv Shahar: us to capture the
principle you're describing
there, because that would be the
case, not just in the
psychedelic experience, but in
any developmental journey.
Because if you are to embrace
larger and more potent realms,
then there are several processes
that will have to take place for
a start, what you're describing
is you're being rewired on the
inside, because there are
different circuitries in your
brain and in the energy field
that you are that get activated,
get switched on in the process,
and then secondarily, once
you're engaging with higher
level of potency, the what you
describe as purification
process, your system need to
cleanse, need to actually
release any of the residue of
the previous infrastructure that
you were part of. Because what
you're describing that the
universe is a compassionate,
loving actuality, but it's not
socialistic environment. Rather,
it is a gradient. It has levels
and dimensions, and those can
sometimes interpenetrate. But
there are also containers that
for the sanctity of their and
the fidelity of the process,
they must be retained, and if
you are as a human vessel to
enter these realms, your system,
your physical system, need to be
rewired and updated to be able
to manage that. And the 51% of
the work is actually stabilizing
the work that you got exposed
to. That's how I would translate
what you just shared through my
lens of of of non psychedelic
experience, but engaged on on
the cutting edge of the
spiritual and developmental
journey.
Chris Bache: Absolutely And all
we're seeing is a particular
variation of a universal pattern
that if you want to open to
deeper truths and to a deeper
participatory relationship with
the universe, you have to empty
yourself of everything which is
keeping you small. You have to
empty yourself of old ways of
thinking, old ways of feeling,
and all of these thoughts and
Feeling patterns have biological
correlates. So you go through a
detoxification process which is
physical as well as mental and
emotional, when a when a monk in
Tibetan Buddhism wants to
receive higher levels of
teaching, teachings which are
capable of generating awakening
or enlightenment, They must
first do what's called NDR the
preparatory practices, which of
the 500 preparatory practices
are five practices you do
100,000 times each. And one of
those practices is doing full
body prostrations while reciting
prayerful mantras. So you're
you're going on the ground,
you're lying down, you're
getting up, you're praying,
you're. Going on the ground.
You're lying up, and you're not
only retuning your mind with
these mantras and you're
retuning your heart with the
devotion of these mantras, but
you literally are working your
body and working your body to
purify your body, while you are
purifying your mind and your
heart. And this is way it is for
all spiritual practice, isn't
it? We always are having to
purify ourselves. And if, if
psychedelics push you into a
higher state of consciousness
kind of quickly, you then have
to purify after you go into that
state of consciousness.
Aviv Shahar: You either, you
either need to do the you either
need to pay on the front end or
during or after
Chris Bache: now or pay me
later, but you have to pay Yeah.
Aviv Shahar: The one distinction
I'd make, and I'm interested in
your comment, is so some of
those Buddhist practices, they
emerged in ancient times. What
we're describing is that
humanity has now entered an
environment, a universal
environment, where you may be
able to go through an
accelerated journey, not just in
the way you have done that
journey, but because in in
metaphoric terms or in actual
terms, we can say the universe
has come, has drawn nearer to
the human realm. That's part of
the epochal shift that we are
experiencing at this time, such
that, because of what you're
describing, that we have entered
the phase of collective
awakening. We may be in one
lifetime go through, we may be
able to go through an
accelerated journey, especially
when we engage with the with the
exercise, not through the lens
of the individual, but as part
of the bigger project of the
humanity participating in the
evolutionary process.
Chris Bache: Yeah. And so if you
open your individual life,
whether it's spiritual practice
or psychological transformation,
or even as you engage diseases
in your physical body to this
larger collective landscape
landscape, then I think you
participate in this evolutionary
project in a new and Intense
fashion. Also, if you are
engaged in social
transformation, if you are
trying to bring working for
social justice, working for true
equality in our healthcare
delivery systems and so on and
so forth, with a conscious
understanding that this is the
time we must change our culture.
We must change our historical
practices. We must let go of the
divisions of the history. We
must lay a foundation for a
future that works for all of its
citizens, not just for some of
its citizens. Then that too,
even if you're not meditating,
even if you're not doing those
internal practices, if you're
social activist, then that too
is part of this larger, deep
transformation. And I think
you're right. I think what we're
finding is in many spiritual
practitioners and visionaries in
many different lineages are
coming to the same conclusion
that everything is speeding up,
that our evolution is speeding
up, and humanity is coming to a
critical pivot point, a
bifurcation point, a point of
critical instability that we are
we either grow up or we probably
go extinct. We cannot continue
to manage the planet with the
lower level of consciousness
that we have been operating out
of in the past, we have to
achieve a breakthrough of depth
and breadth in order to grow up
to the species that's been
growing inside of us for 1000s
of years. And I understand this
in terms of reincarnation. It's
like we've been reincarnating
and reincarnating and
reincarnating. We've been
learning bits and pieces,
learning and learning and
learning. And I think what's
happening is, as the world is
trying to become an integrated
whole as a planet, we're dealing
with problems the magnitude of
which we cannot solve at a local
level. They have to be solved at
a global level. Likewise,
individually, intra psychically,
we are bringing together all of
the lives and all of the karma
from all of our previous lives.
We have lived in every race. We
have been every race on the
planet. We have been every
religion. We have been every
nationality. We have all these
lives inside of us, and now,
whereas in the past, we would
the world has torn itself apart,
nation against nation, race
against race, likewise, all
these divisions are inside of
us, and as we become one and
whole. So we fuse that history
into one integrated being, and
in that process, we support
humanity that is fusing its past
into one integrated being, and
that's giving birth to what I
call the diamond soul. Will
fully awaken soul consciousness
Aviv Shahar: just before we get
to the diamond revelation and
experience, what bridging Will
you offer? I mean, what you just
framed there is that a way to
view the meta crisis unfolding
in just any and every aspect of
of life on the planet. Right
now, we can choose to view it as
the living crucible, the
initiatory crucible of this
evolutionary project, in a way,
forcing us to realize that we
can't do it on our own. We have
to come together. So what
bridging comment will you offer
about that journey where you
appreciate the archetype, and
earlier on, and through that you
you come to some vision of the
birth of the future human, that
new species that that's arising.
What else? What other scaffolds
you want to put there before we
explore the sense of diamond
Luminosity?
Chris Bache: Well, what I share
with you now doesn't come from
an intellectual basis. It
doesn't come from books I've
read, and I wish I could give it
that and give you footnotes, and
you know that type of
documentation that academics
love to give, but I I have to
speak to you only out of my
spiritual experiences, only out
of my psychedelic experiences.
And over the course of this long
journey, I was plunged into a
series of initiations and
initiation visionary
experiences. And what I shared
in that last statement is
basically simply what was given
to me, what was shown me with
consistency, that humanity is
coming into a critical time, a
critically in stable time, a
bifurcation time, bifurcation
point that the world was
entering into a global crisis
that seemed to be driven by a
cascading series of ecological
crises, that these ecological
crises were hitting us again And
again, causing a profound
breakdown, a breakdown that
already many people see it
coming, and it is so severe,
many very wise people think that
it's an extinction event. We are
really going extinct as a
species. We will not be able to
survive what's coming. My
experience as a visionary in the
psychedelic condition is that
that is not what's going to
happen, that we are coming into
a time of acute suffering, acute
dismantling, a surrendering of
the past, but in that process,
we will give birth to something
extraordinary, not simply a new
civilization or a new culture,
and not simply a new economics
or a new industrial production,
a green production, we are
literally giving birth to the
next form of the human being,
the future human. And I couldn't
have dreamed this up. I couldn't
have made this up and but it's
been a it's been to me a vision
which was given me, starting in
the late night, early 90s,
culminating in 1995 and it was
given to me not as A visionary
experience of what will be, but
at great after great work, well,
I was taken into what I call
deep time and taken into the
future, taken into whole time,
and was experienced This
transformation that humanity is
undergoing as what has happened,
not all simultaneously what will
happen, but also what has
happened
Aviv Shahar: with time, where
time is non linear, so you could
be in those different positions
and experiences concurrently.
Yes.
Chris Bache: And so for me, it
is out of that basis that I say
this is an initiatory event. It
is not an extinction event. It
is a process that we will go
through now. We can go through
it kind of clumsily and
awkwardly and dragging our
heels, or we. And go through it
cooperatively with vision and
foresight, and we can accelerate
our way through it, or we can
fight it and make it'll become
worse, right? That's our choice.
I mean, you said you all, we all
grow. We either go, we drag, get
dragged through, or we walk
through with elegance. And
that's our choice. Now, do we go
forward with vision, or do we
try to hold on to the past, or
try to go back to some time in
history when things were easier,
they made sense? Or do we forge
ahead into a new future?
Aviv Shahar: So this must have
been and in many ways you
describe that sense, the
realization of that, the
feeling, experience, communion
of that, and the calling that
makes that became a driving
issue, just stabilizing that and
operating in life was, I
imagine, a challenge by itself.
When you speak of it now, it
leaves in you as as powerfully
and as passionately, all while
you you communicate that this is
a an experience and a set of
insights that you must contain,
because it's it's not about
jumping on rooftops and
screaming. It actually is about
containing and giving birth to
the realization of these
extraordinary shape shifting
events that are unfolding right
as we speak on the global stage,
and that these are theaters of
experience through which the
individual, the collective, the
archetypal consciousness that
the human experience represents
can be transformed to become
participatory in in the
evolutionary process.
Chris Bache: Yes, exactly when I
first had the this kind of
culminating breakthrough, after
years of these visions and I
experienced the death and
rebirth of humanity. It took me
about a year to recover. It was
such a powerful experience. It
was like, as I say in the book,
it was like walking around
Hiroshima a week before the bomb
was dropped, and I had such
profound compassion and such
deep respect for every person
that I was seeing, because my
understanding was that each one
of us chose to incarnate at this
time in history, knowing what we
were getting into, knowing that
it was going to be hard, knowing
that it was going to be very,
very difficult. But there are no
victims here. There are only
saints, there are only
volunteers who have chosen to
participate in this and that
every person here, whether or
not I agree with them
politically or whether you know
whatever, whatever our
differences may be, every person
here deserves my complete
respect because they are a soul
who has chosen to participate in
this historic transformation,
Aviv Shahar: and then you will
let later into the diamond
Luminosity and its discovery,
describe that transition,
please.
Chris Bache: Well, I have to
back up just a little bit,
because I described going into
archetypal reality, and I
haven't described too much about
what went on there, but let's
just kind of jump over that. And
then I went through another
death and rebirth process. And
then I entered what I came to
call causal mind, or the
universe, experienced in a
condition of consciousness where
everything is one, all the
diversity of life pulses as a
single life form, just a single
totality, an overwhelming,
absorbing experience in the
fundamental oneness of life,
where My boundaries dissolved
completely, not only my personal
boundaries, but I saw that there
were no boundaries. From this
perspective throughout the
entire universe, that we all
were aspects of this fundamental
oneness. And I experienced what
the Buddhists call Shunyata,
emptiness, emptiness of self,
transparency. There was another
session where I was taken into
the cosmic void, into the
fertile void, out of which the
universe emerged, an experience
of overwhelming cosmic love. And
that went on for a year. I just
was absorbed in extraordinary
blessings, and I was completely
satisfied. As a philosopher, I
was totally satisfied. And then
I went through yet another
Death-Rebirth experience, a very
intense Death-Rebirth
experience. And when I came
through it, i. Taken into a
consciousness of clear, clear
light, just I had known light
many times before. Light had
shown up in many Death-Rebirth
processes, but this was
different. This was an
exceptionally hyper, clear
Luminosity, and I came to call
it the diamond light, the
diamond Luminosity. And when I
looked at other sources in the
spiritual literature, again,
Buddhism is one of the ones I
know the best. And when I
studied the Buddhist literature,
I think this is what they call
Dharmakaya, the clear light of
absolute reality. It is a light
so clear that it eventually
becomes invisible. But it's just
crystalline, clear, and in that
clarity, there is an ecstasy
that goes beyond bliss, beyond
any of the ecstasy associated
with form, because this is pure
formlessness. Once I touched
this, then the only thing I
wanted to do was get back to it.
I mean, once you touch this kind
of diamond Luminosity,
everything else becomes
insignificant. And over the next
four years and 26 sessions, I
only went back into the diamond
Luminosity four times, about
once a year. And in between
those four sessions, there was
sessions of intense
purification. More purification,
you know, more so on so forth.
In the middle of that cycle, I
had the experience of the Great
Awakening, the experience of the
death and rebirth of humanity.
So the diamond Luminosity work
started developed. Then I had
the experience of the future
awakening of humanity. And then
I went back into two more years
of work with two more
initiations into the diamond
Luminosity. In the first two
sessions, I went deeper and
deeper into the diamond
Luminosity. And then in the last
two the diamond Luminosity
crunched itself deeper and
deeper into my physical body
into my mind, and I experienced
it kind of remaking me, almost
at a cellular I don't understand
the process, but it was infused.
It was entering into my body so
that eventually it changed not
only how I think and how I feel.
It gave me a brief glimpse in my
very, very last session of a
change in my vision. I had an
experience of seeing 100 times
clear, 100 times more refined
than I had ever seen in my
ordinary consciousness. And it
wasn't a hallucination. It was
what I came to call diamond
vision, and I and then after
about 10 minutes, it
disappeared, and I was back to
my ordinary, clear vision. And
that's when I began to
understand that the future human
that we are giving birth to is
not only a human being with a
healed and expansive heart, and
not only a human being with an
open mind open to deeper
communion with the universe, but
it's a human being which lives
physically differently. All of
our senses are not simply
biomechanical processes. They
are functions of a level of
consciousness we hold within the
body. And so our vision is
capable of infinitely more
refinement than in our hearing
and our tastes and our touches.
So when we talk about bringing
heaven to earth, it's not simply
like, you know, a social, nice,
Harmony social we're talking
about weaving divine
consciousness, activating Divine
Consciousness inside our body,
so that our body becomes
profoundly satisfying, capable
of much, much more refined
sensory experience, not just
emotional and physics and what
Aviv Shahar: you're describing,
what you're describing there,
building on everything you said
earlier, is the universe is
interested not just in altered
human consciousness. It wants
that consciousness to permeate
all the levels of physical
reality such that the universe
can experience through us the
sensory portal and the mental
portal and the embodied
experience all at a richer,
higher fidelity, higher quality,
kind of a way,
Chris Bache: yes, and I would
say the way I think of this is
not. So much that it can
experience though, I'm I'm sure
that's true, but I think it's
actually sharing with us the
gift of its capacity. It's,
it's, it's literally kind of
cloning itself. It's sharing,
it's sharing the gift of how it
experiences life with us, and
it's growing us and growing us
to allow us to incarnate and
embody its experience of life at
deeper and deeper levels. And
that means it's an act of
generosity.
Aviv Shahar: Well, Chris, this
has been a fascinating
exploration, and I so much
appreciate that you're able to
both narrate your experience,
integrate into it, your teaching
and spiritual practice and and
also talk to it from the
extemporaneous experience of
this moment in time of being a
conscious being On this
tormented planet as humanity is
going through these very
difficult transitional events,
but what makes the whole
difference? I mean, the teaching
from Viktor, frankly, is if when
you're in the most difficult
circumstance, if you carry with
you a different logo, therapy, a
different reason, a different
purpose, a different awareness,
a different recognition and
insight about what it is that
you are undergoing, whether it's
illness, whether it's pain,
about the greater planetary
situation, there is a
difference, because do we
experience what We experience
merely personally, or do we
experience the personal
dimension when we are merged
inside that greater actuality
and that search, that inquiry,
that struggle, is actually part
of the spiritual work of this
time, which you discovered
through psychedelics? My
experience is it's accessible in
the day to day tasking of life,
of being a parent and a spouse
and a teacher and a leader, and
working through the day to day
struggles of life and asking,
How can I make the higher
choices, how can I be the better
version of myself? How can I
find resources to transcend the
moment of conflict, to
metabolize and transmogrify the
moment of being triggered to
instead of acting out on being
triggered, to use it as a
trampoline to engage with a
higher, cosmic, universal
dimension of life. That's the
invitation that I hear in your
narrative.
Chris Bache: Yeah, absolutely,
there's psychedelics are totally
incidental. They're simply how I
encountered these principles.
And one can encounter these
principles in so many different
forms, in so many contexts, as
we enter this dark night of our
collective soul, which I think
has begun, and it's going to get
worse, but as we enter it, we're
going to hear people say all
sorts of things. They're going
to offer all sorts of
interpretations that we're being
punished, or this is the end of
time, and this is that we're
being plagued by demons. And are
this we were this is a
punishment that is owed to us.
And I think it's very important
that we have a deep vision of
what is being produced, what is
taking place in history, a
vision of the future human that
we are in the process of giving
birth to inside ourselves and
collectively. If imagine a woman
who's giving birth and she
doesn't know that she's pregnant
and she doesn't know anything
about labor or what's actually
taking place, what a horrible
day it would be. But if she
understands that she's giving
birth to a new life, then it all
kind of coheres to to see the
intelligence of the universe and
the compassion of the universe,
you have to look very, very
deep, because on the surface,
the universe does not appear to
be very compassionate, and it
doesn't appear to Be very
intelligent, it appears to be a
really brutal being to see that
compassion. You have to
understand existence at a very,
very deep level. And as we enter
this time in history,
particularly this century, we
have to be capable of looking
very, very deeply. And when we
look deeply, then we cooperate
with that process of
transformation. It doesn't
require psychedelics at all, but
when we record, when we
participate and cooperate with
the challenges that we are
living in our immediate life, in
our immediate circumstances, and
we find our way to the highest
good, the highest. Highest
choices, the greatest good for
the greatest number, then we,
then we feed into good outcome
for the delivery of this future
human, both in our own life and
in the lives of our children and
our grandchildren and to future
generations.
Aviv Shahar: Thank you for your
commitment to the inquiry and
for your generosity, this has
been an extraordinary journey
with you today. Thank you
Chris Bache: and ADIVA, thank
you for your work. Thank you for
the work you're doing in the
world. This is really noble and
important work. Thank you for
our conversation. You foreign
Aviv Shahar: along with our
website at portals of
perception.org, portals is also
available on YouTube and on all
podcast platforms as well as
social media, you can become an
active member and join the
conversation in community
events, and you can help us get
the word out by liking this
content and by sharing it with
your friends at.