Rachel Fleming: Hmm, diamonds
from heaven. It was LSD in the
mind of the universe. Was that?
Was that the title?
Chris Bache: Yes, that was the
publisher's title, but my title,
while I was writing the book,
was always diamonds from
Rachel Fleming: heaven. Okay,
beautiful. Absolutely, I've been
a fan of your books. Actually,
Colin, and I talk about you
regularly about your books, I've
been a fan. Reincarnation was
wonderful, and then the one in
the middle, and then then the
LSD books been fabulous. So a
lot of the people here do not
know your research methods. So
kind of, what I would describe
you as, kind of, is an explorer
of the outer reaches of the
cosmos, really kind of in search
of the truth of reality, and
really what it means to be kind
of human in this reality. And
your research method is deeply
interesting. And I would love if
we you could start us off by
telling us about about what that
is and what your work has been.
Chris Bache: Well, what we all
share in the animistic community
is the belief that nature is
infused with consciousness, is
fused with mind and soul. And of
course, now we know how vast the
physical universe is, and the
question becomes, how large is
the mind of the universe? How
deep is it? And so I was just
out of graduate school in 1978
in my finish in philosophy of
religion, and I met the work of
Stanislav Grof, who many of you
know, one of the foremost
thinkers in the Transpersonal
psychology community, in the
psychedelic community, and I
read his book, realms of the
human unconscious, and my life
pivoted with that book, because
I immediately saw that his
research was relevant, not only
to clinical psychology, but also
to philosophy that it would he
was offering a method to
actually safely and
systematically explore the
deepest levels of consciousness,
wherein lay the answers to the
philosophical questions that I
was carrying coming out of a
training in religious studies.
So in 1979 I began what became a
20 year journey, working with
LSD. And it was 1979 LSD is what
Stan had done his research with,
and that's what I chose to
continue with. If I were doing
it today, I would have a more
diversified cocktail of
Ayahuasca, Psilocybin, more, but
I worked with LSD, and I chose
to work with very high doses,
for reasons that are too
complicated to go into now, but
that had a profound impact on
the work, because it not only
changed how deep the went work
the work went, but It changed
how wide it went. The field of
consciousness that I took in
these transformational exercises
expanded with the power of the
state of consciousness that I
was entering to enter into these
exercises. So basically, I did
this work in standard grafian
protocol, totally isolated from
the world with the sitter, a
trained clinical psychologist.
Sitter, I did it at home, in a
controlled environment, totally
internally focused, not in any
with any contact of the outside
world, amplifying the states of
awareness with carefully
selected music designed to
empower the states of
consciousness in which you
basically just Shatter your
mind. In essentially working at
these levels, you just Shatter
your mind, and your mind
dissolves out into subtler and
subtler forms or aspects of
reality, and it became a
systematic exploration of what I
think of as the mind of the
universe. I hesitate to call it
the divine, though sometimes I
do. It's just because the divine
has so many culturally infused
qualities in history that I'd
rather avoid. So I think of it
as the mind of the universe. And
I did this work for 20 years,
always keeping very careful
records and whatnot and and then
i i digested those experiences
for another 20 years, because
this is these are not
immediately transparent
experiences. They're very
complex and interwoven, and they
involve many levels of reality
being orchestrated in the same
kind of title, surges of these
states. And there was a
systematic instruction I found
that one session more or less
started where the other session
stopped. When you work in this
system. Systematic fashion,
there was a progressive
deepening and deepening and
deepening. And so it just took
years for me to understand what
the universe was showing me and
where it was taking me and I was
being shown things. I mean, I
always had a sense of a
systematic encounter with an
intelligence that was
orchestrating my experience in
dialog with me, not taking any
form, never taking any any deity
form or any archetypal form, but
always when pressed dissolving
into deeper and deeper layers of
infinity. Anyway. So that is,
cumulatively, the story that I'm
telling in LSD, in the mind of
the universe.
Rachel Fleming: And would you
say, Chris, that this is an
objective reality, that if
anybody that did a similar
method, I mean, I think, I think
what you did was incredibly
brave. But would would everybody
kind of reach this unfolding
that you did using that method?
Or is that not possible to say?
Chris Bache: No, I think, I
think it is possible to say I
think Stan Grof work allows us
to say it, and where he's
dealing with integrating the
experiences of 1000s of people,
and I'm only talking integrating
my experiences, but my
experiences fit comfortably
within the larger matrix that
Grof is work has explored, and
it's a complicated answer,
because on the one hand I want
to say yes, and on the other
hand, I have to qualify that
immediately, because when you
begin this work, these
substances only amplify
consciousness. They don't give
you an experience, they don't
take you a particular place.
They amplify your mind. And
because each of us has a
different life story, then the
mind which is amplified is
different, and we therefore,
when an amplified mind engages
the deeper mind of the universe,
what comes forward will be, in
the beginning, somewhat unique
and will reflect our individual
history. And that's why these
substances are very helpful for
healing. They evoke our
unconscious, and therefore they
evoke our problems. And it's an
individual experience. But if
you keep going farther, if you
press to the limits of of your
time, space, identity. If you
press to the limits of what your
individual history can hold and
go through this transformation
we call ego death, then you
begin to open into spiritual
reality, farther removed from
your own personal history. And
that's when the experiences
begin to overlap. That's when
they begin to converge. Now, my
understanding is that spiritual
reality is not simply something
you enter and pluck fruit from,
like plucking an apple from a
tree. It's interactive. It's
always interactive. So there's a
participatory quality to our
experiences. So the mind that we
bring to the encounter acts as a
seed catalyst. It crystallizes a
certain set of experiences from
the infinite potential of the
mind of the universe. And then
as we internalize those
experiences and are purified by
those experiences, it changes
the seed bind, and then we it
catalyzes an even deeper level
of secrets from the universe. So
it's a both and situation,
participatory. But once you
understand the cycle of
participation, then I think the
universe that we discover is
coherent and consistent. My
universe is the same universe
that is discovered by
contemplative monks, the
mystical traditions, the near
death episode traditions. There
are degrees of depth, and then
we have to be careful, because
you can reach a point where you
think, Oh, this is what the
reality is. And it turns out,
well, no, this is what reality
is at this level of reality, but
you can pop that and go into a
deeper level of reality, and
things change a bit.
Rachel Fleming: One thing that I
find really exciting about your
work is that we talk about
practices. You know that finding
the right practices, to find the
cracks kind of in ourselves, to
get back to a much more porous,
expanded way of being, and yet
these practices take repetition
and tenaciousness and
everything, and you have used a
different method. Here. You've
used what, what one might kind
of think of as a fast track to
some of these experiences. I
mean, it's a very difficult
method, and I'm sure not one
that you would kind of recommend
to a lot of people, but that
that feels for me, where the
excitement of your work is as
you fast tracked a lot of sleep.
Lower practices and possibly got
to the edge of the map that a
lot of these contemplative
practices have got to. I feel as
though you've managed to go
further than than much that I've
seen before on kind of what the
underlying nature of reality is.
Would you say that's
Chris Bache: true, it is a fast
track, except it's a fast track
that doesn't allow any
bypassing. So the fact that it's
a fast track means it's a much
more intensely concentrated
track. So purification, which in
the conventional spiritual path
would be drawn out over years,
can take place within days. And
as any woman who's given birth
knows, a short labor is not
necessarily an easier labor,
it's just much, much more
intense. And this is true for
this type of practice, true the
purification that one goes
through in order to acclimate to
these subtler and cleaner and
clearer states of reality, those
purifications and
detoxifications are extremely
intense. I mean, they send you
in convulsions across the floor,
in throwing up, constantly
coming and going, and they
require a systematic
purification of your lifestyle,
just as any traditional
spiritual practice does, and I
want to emphasize that the
states of consciousness that I
touched for hours at a time, we
usually only learn about these
realities from the work of
contemplative mystics who have a
certain sense of they abide in
these realities. And I emphasize
that this is a practice, not of
abiding. It's a it's a temporary
access. It's only temporary
immersion in these states. And I
don't want to confuse temporary
immersion from abiding immersion
all honor to the Great Ones who
abide in these realities. You
know, this is different. This is
temporary access, very, very
intense purification. But you
don't come away with permanent
access, embedded in your nature,
to these realities. What you
come away with are seeds of
Transcendence, or seed
experiences, which you then have
to nurture within your your
daily spiritual practice. You
have to nurture them within your
embodied, physical existence.
And I also want to mention that
these practices in the earlier
times in history have tended to
be associated with a
dissociative spirituality. So
the goal was to get up into
Transcendence and get away from
Earth, you know. So these are
the up and out cosmologies of
the last five Axial Age,
religions of the last 5000
years. The cosmology that
emerged in my work is very
different. It wasn't about
getting Transcendence. There was
Transcendence in service of
incarnation. Transcendence and
service of deeper integration.
It was about opening up and
letting in as much of the
universe as possible, and then
going through the
transformations that would allow
this energy to live in the
historical body, and giving me,
at one point, insights into
where the evolutionary
intelligence was taking the
human family as a whole. I began
this work thinking in terms of a
personal model of
transformation, but things
happen that just shattered that
model, and I began to understand
that I was had been drawn into a
collective transformation, and
that my my so called individual
work, was part of a collective
process, which then naturally
lead, yielded some Insights into
our collective family, human
family, evolutionary trajectory,
fantastic.
Rachel Fleming: And I want to
ask you about that in great
depth in a minute, because for
me, that's kind of the exciting
thing that you discovered, if
you like. But first of all, I'd
love to ask you about the
aliveness and intelligence in
the universe. Then we are
talking about the aliveness and
intelligence in everything
around us, you know, in humans
being just one load of that, but
just kind of as is everything an
animate world and animate
universe. I just wondered if you
could summarize your
understandings of the aliveness
in the universe and how layered
that is, and how deep that goes,
how big it is, yes, what did you
What have you mean?
Chris Bache: Well, you're asking
a lot because it, you know, the
universe is so vast, and the
mind of the universe. Has so
many layers to it, and those
layers are, of course, all
complexly interwoven, and it's
all alive, and it's all
intelligent, and it's it's
everywhere we dig into the
universe, of course, we discover
aliveness and intelligence.
We're finding that we can't dig
in anywhere and not encounter
this intelligence, this living
intelligence. So when you dig
into the mind of the universe,
you find layers of intelligence
operating there. There are
layers of intelligence operating
in the biosphere, operating in
the incarnational rhythms of a
planet I began to experience at
one point, for example,
reincarnation, the I had gone
into, sorry to cut so many
corners here, but there's no way
to do it except jump into it, go
into states of consciousness in
which time was radically
dilated, not eternity, not
timelessness, but radical
dilations of time and dilations
of personal boundaries, so
dissolving into my human family,
becoming the human family, and
from that perspective,
experiencing reincarnation, the
pulse of reincarnation, taking
place, all of us together as a
single organism, incarnating
generation by generation. And I
experienced whole lifetimes,
incarnating in generations,
living their lives, dying and
returning into the spiritual
reality. And there was an
intelligence to this entire
process so that all of our, what
I had previously thought of as
individual karma, individual
challenging, individual
transformation, all of our
individual karma was part of a
vast network of exquisitely
tuned collective karma, and our
and history was expressing the
rhythms of collective
transformation through the
medium of our individual
transformation, just one
example, and then going deeper,
beginning to experience the the
pulse of the entire universe as
A single living organism. And
when you when you dissolve it
into that level of oneness. You
know, the Buddhists have a word
for it. They talk about Nirvana,
blown out. Self is blown out. Or
Shunyata, emptiness of self when
you experience the world as one
in any scale, then you
experience that there are no
permanent boundaries between
yourself and the world. So
literally, there is no private
self. And so the self kind of
pops and life runs through you.
You run through life, and the
whole of life breathes as one.
It breathes together, as platoon
has said, So everywhere you
touch it, the world is
intelligent. At the very end of
my journey, after in the 70th
session out of 73 I did 73
sessions. In the 70th session, I
was taken deep, deep, deep into
what I call deep time, farther
into time than I had ever been
taken before and given a series
of visions. And one of those
visions had to do with
experiencing in some way, from
my perspective and my history,
the large story of what was
happening in the universe. And I
experienced reincarnation. I was
experiencing the same deep
pattern, and I experienced stars
of light shooting out of time
and space, shooting into the
universe. And I understood that
these were what I call diamond
souls. These were the fruition
of a reincarnation process
creating a diamond pure, a soul
that could explore the spiritual
world in dimensions previously
unavailable to it, that time and
space was creating diamond souls
over vast periods of time, so
layers and layers and layers of
intelligence operating at
different levels.
Rachel Fleming: So when I read
your book, Chris, I mean, it's
literally mind blowing. I mean,
it's kind of it feels as though
it's science fiction, or it's in
the realms of science fiction.
And yet, for me, there was
nothing in there that didn't
sound right. You know, it just
kind of has that feeling of, ah,
yes, I understand this, and it
feels right to me. And I. Love
to talk to you about the
evolutionary process. You
touched on it a bit there, but
let's go into that in more
detail. But first of all
reincarnation, because that is
something that obviously we
don't all feel is true. But you
did earlier work on the subject
of reincarnation, and just
before we go on to the
evolutionary story that you've
seen, could you talk about a
little bit about reincarnation
and your work on it, and why you
believe that that is what's
happening?
Chris Bache: Well, I did. I
wrote my first book on
reincarnation because I thought
it was such an essential
principle, because our
philosophical roads divide. If
you think we only are on earth
one time, or we're on Earth
multiple times, those lead to
different visions of reality.
And today, I think we have
overwhelming empirical evidence
that reincarnation is simply
true. It's a fact of life. I
think Ian Stevenson at the
University of Virginia and his
study of young children around
the world who have spontaneous
memories of their most immediate
life. He's just documented
hundreds and hundreds and
hundreds of these children, and
his research has been
challenged, but it's still, it's
holding up. And I think he is
the Charles Darwin of
reincarnation studies. And then
we have past life therapies,
people coming in, highly
qualified people healing using
past life access to past life
memories to heal present life
traumas. This, to me, is just an
empirical fact of life. So after
living it takes a long time to
sort of live in a reincarnation
universe to understand the
implications of the fact that
there's this pulse of life, and
that all of us have been here
multiple times, and all of us
have deeper histories with
place, with people, with
projects, and that we're always
starting something and we're
continuing something in one
lifetime, and we're doing
something that's Going To be
continued in another lifetime
that this overlapping complexity
so that I don't see little
children as little anymore, and
I don't see old people as old
anymore. Sometimes little
children are deeply old in soul,
and old people are sometimes
very young in soul. And so it's
you just tune to a different
level. Now I had that in the
early stages of my psychedelic
work. And in the early stages of
my psychedelic work, I was taken
into some of the nuts and bolts
of reincarnation and karma, and
then that became kind of ground
one as I began to be taken into
the human family and to
experience the human family
evolving and growing through
reincarnation. This, to me,
reincarnation is simply the
higher octave of evolution. It's
the cutting edge of evolution in
our particular species, where
evolution ch was trying to
change whole species.
Reincarnation is evolving
individuals within certain
species. And I don't think just
human species. I think somewhere
lower down the line,
reincarnation begins to turn and
gestate, and then the question
becomes, well, where is
reincarnation taking us, if we
are reincarnating so many times,
where are we going? What's
going? What's the whole project
of it? What's the purpose of it?
And to determine to answer the
question, what's the purpose of
a reincarnating species is
complicated, because once you
understand that every human
being on the planet is
reincarnating with a purpose,
its specific purpose, then you
realize the full breadth of the
living experience of human
being, the breath of what's
being learned, that what
humanity is learning is just
enormous. And when we try to
say, well, this is the purpose
of life, we have a tendency to
sort of take a purpose that we
can identify with and maybe over
generalize it to encompass all
purposes. So we really have to
look at the whole of the human
family and gestate the whole of
the things that people are
learning to even begin to come
up with some generality that
encompasses them all. You see
what I mean. So, so in some
cases, we can be learning love,
we can be learning generosity,
we can be learning strength of
self. We can be learning
physical defense. We can be
learning surrendering physical
defense, what one person is
growing into in one lifetime,
another person may be growing
out of, and both of them are
living in. Their truth at a
process level. Most of the
Eastern religions basically say,
Yes, you grow, you activate the
chakras, you bring higher and
higher levels of consciousness
online. But when your
consciousness opens up to divine
essence, when it opens up to the
you that is more real than any
of your individual, private
incarnational use, the divine.
You, the essential you. When you
open up to that, then you reach
enlightenment, what the Hindus
call moksha, means you can
escape, you can leave. So once
you wake up, then let's get out
of here. There's better places
to be than Earth, so that's an
up and out cosmology. But what
happened in my sessions was
different than that. I reached a
point about halfway on my
journey when all of my former
lives began to come into me. I
was in a again, a kind of a
pregnant time, reality of deep
time. And my former lives were
coming in and were coming in,
and it was like wrapping a
filament of kite string around a
spool. But that's string was
human experience. It was whole
human lifetimes. And they kept
coming together, and they
reached a critical mass, and
when they reached a critical
mass, they fused into one. And
when that happened, there was a
tremendous explosion of energy,
and a diamond Luminosity
exploded from my chest. And
that's when I began to
understand, and was shown, that
we make progress incrementally,
lifetime by lifetime, as we
incarnate. But the goal is not
simply to make incremental
progress. The goal eventually is
that all of our lives come
infused into one and we become,
on earth, a being who has
100,000 hundreds of 1000s of
years of history in it, awakened
within it, and empowered within
it. That is the being that we
are becoming, and that is a
different kind of being than an
egoic being. It's the vast depth
of its heart is deep is bigger.
The breath of its mind is
bigger. The texture of its
social relationships is bigger,
and its relationship to nature
is different because it knows
that the world we leave is the
world we inherit. It has a
deeper, embodied texture of its
relationship with nature. And my
discovery was that this is not
simply a path of individuals.
This is simply a story of
individual spiritual awakening
that we are all going into this
transition. We are all giving
birth to the diamond soul. The
entire species is at a point in
its history where it can no
longer afford the luxury of
trying to live on this planet in
the fragmented egoic state. When
a world order is created by
egos, it leads to a fragmented
order that serves some and not
others, but when the soul wakes
up to the with the profound
compassion of its history, the
soul lives on this planet
differently than the ego does,
and I think we are coming into a
very profound, tumultuous period
of history, which I think of as
A birth process. It will feel
like a death process. And it is
a death process. It's basically
destroying the culture that was
built by the ego, and destroying
the ego which built that
culture, and in that process of
dying to that which is small,
giving birth to something new,
giving birth literally to a new
stage in the human story, not a
new body politic and New
Economics, and a shift I think,
is taking place at the depths of
the collective unconscious. The
plate tectonics of the
collective psyche are shifting
in that Jungian sense deep, deep
down inside the human psyche.
This transformation is taking
place so that all human beings
who are born after this
transition will be living their
individual life within the
matrix of a different collective
psyche that I think, is the work
of the hour. That's what we are
working to. And part of this to
actualize, and part of this is
reawakening to the divine
presence which we've stripped
out of nature tried to
unsuccessfully, but reawakening
to this common ground that. We
have with nature to this
intelligence that surrounds us
and saturates us.
Rachel Fleming: Wow, Chris. I
mean, I'm imagining that people
hearing this for the first time,
it's kind of difficult to get
your head around it. And I'm I
want to bring Colin in in a
minute. So to summarize, in my
kind of terms, and what you're
talking about, really, is the
evolution of the human species,
individuals and collectively,
towards a position where we can
remember our entire history. So
if we take reincarnation as a
given, then we're evolving
towards a place where we can
remember past, our past
incarnations on this earth. And
you know, Colin, can I bring you
in here? Because there's
something that you talk about.
You know, in reanimating
ourselves, we need to have a
completely new cognitive
framework. You know, the that
the the the way of connecting to
the intelligence in the universe
is so foreign to us now that we
need a whole different framework
to kind of be able to wrestle
with with that kind of
information. What's your feeling
about what Chris is talking
about. I know you've read the
book too, and I know you love
it. So biased question here, but
yeah, from your perspective.
Colin Campbell: Thanks, Rachel.
Well, first of all, I really
wanted to say how much of an
honor it is to meet you, Chris.
I have to say, you know the
encounter with your books, and
the first one I encountered was
dark, night, early dawn. Was was
really well, tectonic in nature.
For me, it was, and I'm filled
with questions. And was, and
have been all the way through
reading your books and re
reading them and reading them
again, thinking about it and
brewing on it, and a lot of the
questions I really want to ask,
I have no idea how I would even
articulate. I can feel them and
I can sense them, but how, and
I, you know, so, I mean, I can
see, feel myself at the sort of
edges, you know, of my, what I
call my present cognition,
because, you know, I was, I was
lucky enough to be born into and
brought up within a traditional
indigenous culture here in
southern Africa. And through,
through my childhood, lived in
wilderness and among people who
had a very, very particular
relationship with wilderness and
a cosmology that came out of
that. And subsequently, I find
myself, you know, in in the
worlds of post industrial world,
trying to reconcile that part of
me with the part of me I find
myself in now, and finding that
there's it's very difficult to
bring it feels like, in a
certain sense, that there are
two cognitive frameworks within
me at some level, and that
somehow I'm tasked with trying
to reconcile these two parts of
myself and reading, reading
through your books, I you know
where I found myself, find
myself pulled back into the
cognitive system, really, that I
grew up in, and that forms a
kind of an under structure
within my experience now and but
I mean within that, then I have,
I have questions. I mean loads
of them, which, which your books
really, really brought up in me.
And among them, among the most
difficult to articulate our
questions around time and and
the notion that somehow, rather,
you know, so reincarnation is
not something that really comes
into the cosmology is here in
southern Africa, and yet it
does. It's implicit in certain
terms. But I'm really so as we
look at this idea of
reincarnation and the cognitive
framework that I would perceive
it from here as we speak about
it relies on a sequence of time
that speaks of a past from which
we come and a future to which we
go. But what happens if we take
that out, if, in fact, if in
fact, that's merely my present
cognitive framework. But you
know, how would we understand
reincarnation and the notion of
a trajectory towards something,
if time in its kind of sequence
from beginning to seeming
culmination, or some such thing?
If that wasn't the case? Yeah.
Yeah, I don't know if I'm making
any sense.
Chris Bache: It's a good
question. If you if we eliminate
the arrow of time, then
reincarnation begins to look
like multi incarnation, not
reincarnation. Some people have
conceptualize this. We're living
all of our lives simultaneously
in a and we're interacting all
these lives are active and
interacting in a way that
befuddles the logic of linear
development, and it requires a
different kind of logic. And
I've tried to think in that
world multiple times, and I
basically keep coming down to I
can't do it. I mean, I literally
cannot live in a world where
Multi incarnation makes sense. I
can't make it make sense. Now,
another little thread, Robert
Monroe, from the Monroe
Institute of Applied Science,
out of body guy you know, has
been wrote three wonderful books
in the out of body state,
exploring the universe daily
from the out of body state. He
says, You reach a point in your
spiritual development where you
discover that you can incarnate
in any time period you wish. So
soul forward does not mean time
forward, right? So you can
incarnate in the 10th century
BC, and next you could incarnate
in the 20th century. AD, so
permeability of time. You see
how that continues the concept
of linear development, but it
flexes on the concept of Time's
absolute linearity. For myself,
I've gone through so many
permutations of time, moving
into deep time where you can I
experienced my entire life in
the early stages, birth to
death, simultaneously present,
absolutely I was experiencing
the whole of my life, the end
and the Beginning and all of its
development as a simultaneous
whole. Later, I was taken into
periods of time where 100,000
years were being lived out as if
it were one minute. It's
convinced me that the universe
has many modalities of time
built into it, that when we move
into deeper dimensional of
reality, there are different
modalities of time that are
available. There all that would
you would think, and it does
make me receptive to the idea of
letting go of a concept of
linear time and linear
development. And somehow I try
to reconcile the fact that from
the universe's perspective,
there are multiple modalities of
time, so that the universe can
show me the future from its time
which is and can give me the
experience of knowing the future
as something which has already
happened and simultaneously
which is yet to happen, and at
the same time, at the same time,
hold on to some notion of the
value and the challenge of
something approximating Linear
development. And I think my best
take is that life chops its its
challenges to is chops learning
into bits and pieces. And we
can't learn it all in one
lifetime. We can't do it all
simultaneously. It's easier if
it's just broken down into bits
and pieces. And if this, if this
challenge of linear development,
is coming to a fruition, and is
coming to a diamond soul, a an
awareness that holds all of its
time moments in its present
consciousness on Earth, this, of
course, is not the end of the
developmental story, of the
linear story, because in a
million years will be farther.
In a billion years will be
farther still. The universe is
just getting warmed up. You
know, if that we have no reason
for thinking that the universe
is is in anywhere near the end
of its evolutionary story, we
know it's really at the early
stages of its story. So I think
of time is one of the great
gifts of evolution.
Individuality is one of the
great gifts of the physical
universe. Time is one of the
gifts of the physical universe.
Behind that lay lies
permutations of metaphysics that
put that are more fluid with
respect to time, but inside
space time, I think there is a
an approximate linear arrow of
time which serves the soul's
purpose, which serves some
deeper kind. Cosmic Web. And
yet, at the same time, when we
are in the linear development,
if we open up to the universe,
if we open up to the universe's
sense of time, we often get
these flashes of more than, more
than the present. You know, more
parallel dimensions of time. So
your question makes a lot of
sense, and it's it's a
substantive question.
Rachel Fleming: Can I ask one
Colin, or do you want to come
back on that? Okay, so
Colin Campbell: yeah, great.
Rachel Fleming: This is the
problem with your work, Chris.
We need to keep trying to we're
out in kind of like inarticulate
ball terrain, aren't we, when we
get to that you what you call
the diamond soul, then when
there's this moment of
remembering what? What are the
other attributes? What are the
other kind of what does that
bring, other than remembering
and wholeness? You know, did you
have an experience of what else?
Chris Bache: Well, first of all,
I think soul consciousness is
what we return to when we die.
So while we are in the Bardo
Earth, Bardo Earth kind of stage
when we die, we return to whole
consciousness. So it's not
something we're unfamiliar with.
It's something we are familiar
with. And then we precipitate
out of whole consciousness into
part consciousness, egoic
consciousness, and we return. So
it's a it's a constant
accordion. Kind of effect, we
die as we get large. We're born.
We get small, we die. We get
large. We're born, we get small
sooner or later, if we just keep
up for a few 1000 years, 100
million years, sooner or later,
large wakes up inside physical
consciousness, and so it's
simply a consolidation of what's
taking place naturally and
normally. It's just a stage in
this process, the times that
I've been carried into deep time
and experience temporarily my
diamond soul, and then the
diamond stole the soul that's
emerging as an archetypal
imprint, an archetypal form.
I It's hard to describe because
of the enormity and the beauty
and the joy we're looking we're
talking about a human being
that's completely healed, of all
the wounds of history. That's
healed of all the terrible
things we've done to each other,
men and women, and wars and
violence, that's healed all of
those scars. Healed a tremendous
breath of communion with the
natural world, an intimacy with
all life forms, not only then a
breath of companionship with all
life and with other human beings
and with human community and
with natural nature's community,
but an openness of the mind,
able to take in more directly,
enter into deeper communion with
the intelligence of the
universe. I mean, the genius of
the universe has all the answers
to all the technological limit
questions we want to have
answers to, and we just are not
able to download all that
knowledge. And the diamond soul
is a more complete and higher
potency of human being that can
enter into deeper downloads from
the divine intelligence. But
it's not only an expansion of
heart and an expansion of mind,
our physical senses are also
amplified by orders of magnitude
in the very, very last session,
after 73 sessions, the very last
session, the universe gave me an
experience of what I call
diamond vision. Suddenly, in a
kind of a late, late session,
wind down, clear space. My
vision became 1000s of times
more cute and sharper than it
had ever been before. I could
see things, details, gradients
of color, sharpness and
precision of form. I could just
see I was. Me is that I ever had
accepted this fuzzy stuff as
real seeing. This was diamond
clarity seeing. And then after
10 minutes, it went away, and I
was seeing the way I normally
see. And that's when I
discovered, I realized what I
was being shown is that we tend
to think of sensation as kind of
a biomechanical process, but
it's actually a conscious
process, and the more
consciousness which is is
present in this body, this body
has built into it the capacity
for infinitely higher levels of
sensate, experience, touch,
hearing, seeing, sensitivities
of all manner of physical
sensations. So it truly is. It's
heaven on earth in the body, so
that the body participates in
the qualities of heaven without
having to leave the physical
existence. This is why, I mean,
it's not an up and out
cosmology. It's bringing it in
deeper and deeper and deeper,
changing, literally, the
physiology of the body to allow
it to operate in this ecstatic
state, which becomes the normal
state. Yeah, that is a child I
think, is worth the labor that
we're going into to give birth
to. And we are going in a
terribly, terribly severe labor.
Our past is being stripped away.
Will be stripped away. We will
lose all capacities that we
associate with normal and
minimal existence. This is what
happens in all mystical
traditions, in all psychedelic
traditions, literally, the small
has to be broken ground to dust,
stripped and dismembered in
order for the new to awaken
within us, and this is happening
now historically, where we're
entering into what I think of as
the dark night of our collective
soul. The Dark Night is an image
often used for a hard time, but
it's not a hard time in John of
the Cross. The Dark Night of
self is a hard time. The Dark
Night of the Soul is a very,
very intense purification time
which immediately precedes the
awakening of full illumination.
And a dark night of the of the
collective soul is a time of
intense purification, intense
loss of reality as we have known
it up to this point in time. And
I think out of the out of the
pain and suffering that's
coming, it's going to crack US
Open and break us down to our
center and in this ordeal, we
will not survive, but we will
give birth to that in us which
is more beautiful, more
ecstatic, more competent, more
plugged in. I think we truly are
becoming a species of Buddhas, a
species of Christ and prophets.
These are the models we've had
trying to give us some for
vision of what's happening. In
the early years, we could not
imagine an ordinary human being
reaching that level of
excellence. But now we're
beginning to understand through
reincarnation, over and over and
over and over again, slowly, we
grow into that level of
excellence, which is simply a
level of transparency to the
essential condition which in
which we experience life. The
irony is, we experience what's
always been happening all the
way along. It's always been this
way. The universe has always
been one. The universe has
always been filled with
intelligence. We have always
been empty of self. But somehow
we distracted ourselves from
thinking that that's not there.
It's always been there. So we're
waking up to the paradise that
the universe already is. We've
just been missing it.
Rachel Fleming: Wow, Chris, I
just find your experience and
your vision just such a hopeful
one as we move into what we see
as ecological crisis and
societal crisis, and I just
again, as I felt quite
emotional. Said at the
beginning, it was just one of
the most inspiring books, or the
most inspiring book last year,
but what one of the most of my
lifetime? You know, I. It, and
I'm sure Colin would agree with
me on that. So it's so wonderful
to hear.