Marc Caron: Hello and welcome to
conscious living. My name is
Mark Caron, and today I'm coming
here live from the beautiful I'm
awake Foundation Center where
they do consciousness research
and a lot of really interesting
work in the field of
spirituality, medicines,
consciousness and
transformation. I was blessed to
be invited, and I'm actually
broadcasting live from here
today in this episode of
conscious living radio where
it's going to be another Spira
plant medicine focused program,
and I'm happy to invite my good
friend and partner of the
conference, Steven gray. And
Steven always a pleasure to have
you here. We're going to be
airing our program today on
100.5 cfro FM in Vancouver, Co
Op radio. We're happy to have
been running that program for
over 15 years now locally. And
Steven, you've been a guest many
times and really a co host in
many programs. So thank you for
joining me in what's I'm sure,
going to be a really, really
great conversation with our
guests today,
Stephen Gray: absolutely.
Marc Caron: Well, Steven, I
guess you know you're a man of
many words today. Why don't you
introduce our guest? You've done
it many times, that's for sure.
Stephen Gray: Yeah, happy to
Well, that's partly because I
have a big heart feeling toward
Chris, but also an immense
amount of respect for him as a
person and for the work that
he's done on behalf of the rest
of us in elucidating central
issues of our time. So Chris, I
could ask you for a very brief
synopsis of that 20 year
journey, but maybe you'd allow
me to stumble through it, and
then you can sit back and smile
and see if I got it right. So
welcome to the people who are
alive and those who are going to
join us later. Chris Bache, the
story I know about Chris is that
he is now a retired professor of
religion and philosophy, or
religious studies and
philosophy, from Ohio State
University and Youngstown, Ohio.
And early in his career, he
Well, he he was always
interested in mysticism and deep
spiritual exploration, and he
came upon the work of the
legendary excuse me psychiatrist
Stanislav Grof, who pioneered a
protocol for working with high
doses of LSD in particular. And
Chris undertook what amounted to
what turned out to be a 20 year
journey of 73 high dose LSD
sessions following the Stan Grof
protocol. Those were sessions
using 500 to 600 micrograms of
LSD, which, for any of you who
are not familiar with that kind
of calculation, that's a high
dose. And that protocol involves
at home or in a, you know, safe,
quiet space with headphones on
and a carefully curated
playlist, excuse me, eyeshades
to keep block out the light so
that inner visions are not
obstructed or mitigated, and a
qualified sitter. The person
that he had, in this case, is a
therapist, was a therapist, and
so knew what she was doing with
the situation and the following
day. So he generally did this on
a Saturday, and then the
following day, again, following
the Grof protocol, he spent
basically the whole day, as far
as I recall, with those
headphones on again to kind of
trigger memories of what was
playing on the music when he had
certain kinds of experiences and
visions, and then meticulously
transcribing all that. So Chris
is the author of several books,
including a book that I long
before I ever met him, from 20
years ago or so called dark
night, early dawn, which was
really a really impressive book.
I really liked it. Stand Out
book. I still have it in my
shelves back here the living
classroom, which I have not
read, and hope to because
there's a new edition coming
out, I believe, right. Chris,
Yep, yeah. And the incredible
LSD in the mind of the universe,
subtitled diamonds from heaven,
which many people have read now.
So excuse me. I just want to add
a little bit more about how I
understand what happened in that
20 year journey. Mind you, this
would be like an all day
description. I. If it were to do
justice to what happened. But
the very, very short version is,
and again, please correct the
nuances of this if I didn't
quite remember it correctly,
Chris, in each one of those 73
journeys the first two hours
was, as you described it in the
book. I believe Chris at one
point, sometimes exquisitely
painful as you had to go through
the difficult process, which
most of us probably would never
want to go through, actually, of
ego dissolution and beyond, in a
sense, beyond ego, personal, ego
dissolution, but letting go of
any kind of identity, even as a
human as I recall. And then what
happened? And again, please
correct my language if I haven't
got it quite right, Chris. But
as I recall, and in my language,
you broke out into what you have
called in various ways, but one
way is the vast intelligences of
the universe. And believe me,
folks, I this is no
exaggeration. The kind of
material that Chris, you might
say, downloaded or brought back,
is absolutely stunning and
absolutely relevant to what's
going on on the planet. One of
the things that's most in my
mind, anyway important and
absolutely central about the
things that Chris downloaded, as
it were, is that, especially in
the in the, I believe, the
latter third or so of the 20
years, he started to get
increasingly clear, and I would
say, or interpret it as
confident messages that we are,
well, he had already heard, I
guess, that we've been we are
going through, as a species, a a
death and rebirth trajectory or
process that has been coming
toward us for perhaps hundreds
of 1000 years or whatever. And
excuse me, but the confidence
that I just mentioned implied
that in the later years, as I
recall Chris, these voices or
this intelligence started
indicating a greater likelihood
that we would indeed somehow get
through this and and that we
will come out into what you
might call a natural state of
being on this planet, you've
labeled it the birth of the
future human. So there are so
many questions we could ask you
about that, but let me ask you a
two part question to start with.
First of all, correct me on
anything that I didn't quite get
right. And secondly, I've been
thinking a lot about this, off
and on. It's central to, you
know, my life and where my mind
wants to go. And so one thing
that I'm wondering about is you
have, I think you first said you
thought this process might take
hundreds of years before
something you know, the light
might shine again, so to speak.
But I think it was in a either
an email or a phone conversation
in the last few months, you said
you might have had to correct
that to say 1000s of years, or
more than 1000 years. So I'm
trying to keep this simple and
turn it over to you, but the
context of that question that
I'm going to put to you is that
one of the things that I and I
think Mark also is really tuned
into, and probably you is that
there's an incredible amount of
energy going on right now on the
planet to try to re correct that
dis spiritual disconnection. So,
you know, I guess the question
is, is it really going to be a
complete, you know, emptying and
dying off over the next decades?
Or might there be a cross fade
where things start to lighten
up, or, you know, the light
starts to shine in more to
counterbalance that dissolution,
so to speak, species dissolution
over the next decades. For
example, pardon me one more
little thing, because you know
this, you're the person who
turned Dwayne Elgin onto me for
my book how psychedelics can
help save the world. And he laid
out sort of a possible scenario
over the next six or seven
decades that might result in
what he called the birth of a
mature planetary civilization.
So how are you seeing all that
now, timelines and all that?
Chris Bache: Yeah, first Steven,
thank you, buddy for that very
nice and warm introduction. I
really appreciate our
friendship, and I appreciate the
what you what you're doing with
the conference, and mark you
too. This is a great conference.
It's my favorite psychedelic
conference to participate in,
and I always find it such a
rich, rich setting and audience
and soup to ask and answer, to
address these types of
questions, so to focus
specifically in. Question you
ask, I would strengthen the
visionary component. It was
really less like messages
downloading as deep and profound
immersion into transtemporal
states of consciousness, going
into what I call deep time,
letting go, moving outside
linear time, and also these,
these visions started coming
into me when I was a good 1214,
years into my process. So a lot
of things that happened before
then, ego death, of entering
into this collective suffering,
of entering into what I think is
some dimension of the collective
unconscious of humanity, which
stores all of its pain and
suffering that humanity has
experienced, just as an
individual, stores their
individual trauma, going through
that and going into archetypal
reality. And when I was in
archetype of reality beginning
this work, I began to be
download a series of visionary
encounters, which kept on
showing me the same basic story
that humanity was coming to a
pivot point in its evolutionary
journey, that this was that
we're like the karmic streams of
history were entering a canyon.
We were about to go through a
revolutionary pivot that would
be retro. We would see it in
time as a before and after,
transformational event, of an
event that was so powerful it
was going to literally trigger a
shift in the collective psyche
of humanity, so that all beings
born after this shift had taken
place would be operating out of
a different inner landscape, a
different collective psychic
landscape. And this was ra I
just was completely unprepared
for this, because I had begun
this work thinking that this was
about personal transformation,
and then thinking it was about
maybe personal awakening,
spiritual awakening. But then I
enter these profound collective
territories, and then I began to
have these visionary downloads
about where the where the
creative intelligence of the
universe, or where the divine
intelligence was taking
humanity, where all this was
going. And so there's these,
these deep experiences of
extraordinary spiritual
awakening taking place at a
collective level, extreme
transformation, a deep
intelligence working inside
nature, inside history,
underneath us all, bringing this
about. And then, but it didn't
show me how this was ever going
to take place. It didn't show me
the how of it. And then, in 1995
which look how long ago. This is
almost 30 years ago. I went
through a very deep experience
in which I was dissolved well
beyond egoic identity, dissolved
into the human species, became
one with the human family, and
in that condition, experienced a
the death and rebirth of
humanity, a profound unraveling,
a loss of control. It was a
global systems crisis that
seemed to be triggered by a
cascading series of eco crises.
It was, it was excruciating to
experience, and it kept building
in intensity. And I experienced
this not as a human being, not
as an individual human being,
but I experienced this as the
species. And then it seemed to
be getting deeper and deeper. We
were all forced into survival
mode, and just when it was at
its worst, the peak passed, and
the dangers began to recede, and
we began to pick ourselves up
and to put the pieces back
together. And when we did, we
were changed. We found that
something had been unleashed
enough, something had been
tapped into, something had been
broken open at the very deep
level of our being, so that when
we began to build after this
crisis, all of our work, all of
our being, all of our
relationships, were filled with
new insights, new values, new
understandings of the Human
Project, and there was a
creative contagion that where
the work of individuals and
collectives fed back into each
other, that was just spiraling
us into very quickly, in a into
a new condition. I think now
that's. Basic outline, and
that's clear, but like Black Elk
in the visions that he received
as a young boy about the future
of his people, the my visions
did not come with dates and it
did not come with a lot of
detail. There were in a lot of
attention paid to the mechanisms
involved, but not to the
specific pattern of causation
other than this escalating
global eco crisis, also, it did
not come with dates, so I don't
really have a sense of, Well, of
from the visionary perspective,
when this will happen, how long
it will last. So in order to
fill in all that information, I
have to turn to the scientist in
terms of their calculations for
the depth and the speed with
which the Eco crisis is moving.
I turn to people like Dwayne
Elgin, who has been processing
all this information for
decades. And I've come to first.
I've been surprised that the
crisis is coming at us as fast
as it has. I thought we had more
time, but it's coming out as
fast. It's coming out as hard.
We're still in the early stages,
and I think Dwayne is right. The
next 50 years are going to be
absolutely pivotal in terms of
the intensity of the ecological
forces that will be bearing down
on us that will have to be
responding to. I don't think we
have 1000 years if we don't
address this. I don't think I
think of this as kind of and
again, I don't say this as a
Psychonaut or as a visionary. I
say this just as a person trying
to understand historical
information. I think this thing
may take three or four
generations, and if we don't
make the pivot within that time
frame, we may lose the planet. I
think the 21st Century is the
critical century that is going
to bring us to our knees and
force us to make choices that
we're not willing to make now
for a variety of different
reasons. And then, and I think
this is going to be such a deep
pivot, it's going to be result
in a shift in what I might call
the plate tectonics of the
collective psyche, a shift at
the very, very core of our
being. And in other ways. I
think this represents a
culmination of a reincarnational
process which has been building
for 1000s, 10s of 1000s,
hundreds of 1000s of years. I
think we've been gestating the
next iteration of the human
condition for all this time.
We've been reincarnating
learning, learning, exploring,
growing, becoming more gestation
is long. Labor is short and
intense, life threatening. I
think we've been in gestation
for a long time, and we are
entering into labor, which is
it's going to be a volatile and
very dangerous period. And I
think we will give birth to this
new human, this future human,
many people have these are
having this vision. They call it
different things, Homo
spiritualis, homo noeticus. But
basically, there is this common
intuition that something new is
coming up underneath us. It's
coming into expression
underneath us, and it's being
driven by the same intelligence
that drove the creation of
galaxies, the creation of the
planet, the emergence of life on
the planet, the emergence of
conscious awareness on the
planet. This is being driven
from deep inside the process.
Now, I think that we classically
say there are no certain
outcomes. Everybody has to exert
full and complete exertion for
us to get through this like
labor. It's potentially life
threatening, and mothers dying
labor. Children die in labor all
the time. I understand that. I
really endorse that. And at the
same time,
the entire trajectory of my
psychedelic experience,
particularly those in the last
five years or so, took me so
deep into the future with such
realistic perception, and gave
me experiences of what this
future human will be like, and
those touches of the future of
humanity just bring me to my
knees. They're so
extraordinarily beautiful. It's,
it's our deepest dreams come
true, and I experienced this
pivot as something which was yet
to be accomplished, but also had
already been accomplished. So
that from deep time, I
experienced this as an actuality
that had taken place, and yet,
from my linear time, it's an
actuality which is yet. Be take
place. And so in my heart, I
don't doubt that humanity will
make it through this transition.
My concern is how many of our
children, how many of the
world's children will have to
die before we come to our
spiritual senses?
Stephen Gray: So that definitely
leaves it open for, as you say,
incredible exertion, which is
something that's really
important to people like Mark
and I very
Chris Bache: important. Oh,
yeah, you mentioned in that
context. One of the thing, one
of the things that this series,
visionary series, showed me, is
that as we enter deeper into
crisis, the whole foundation of
the psyche and our culture will
be shifting into what chaos
theoreticians would call
nonlinear systems. Would there
be so much energy, so much
engagement to high energy
engagement, that we would be
shifting out of a linear dynamic
of history into a nonlinear and
in nonlinear, we know something
about how nonlinear systems
behave, and some of the
characteristics, and one of the
important characteristics is in
a nonlinear condition, systems
are particularly susceptible to
small influences, small
perturbations, and that means,
as we go into this crisis, the
actions of individuals will have
proportionately greater impact
than they would have had at
earlier, more quiet periods of
history, so the individual
becomes a more dynamic player
moving forward than individuals
have been In the past.
Stephen Gray: That's an
incredibly important message for
people. Go ahead, Mark, I see
your mouth moving.
Marc Caron: Well, you did partly
answer what I was thinking a
little bit, Chris, because, you
know, there's so much you said
there and then my question is,
is, what can we do as
individuals, as groups, as
collective society. And you
know, it's hard enough to
organize important stuff in the
world for a lot of people. How
do you suggest that we move
forward from starting as Me to
We, to the many what, what do
you think is a good approach for
that?
Chris Bache: Yeah, you know, I
think they're probably people
who are better qualified and
more skilled at filling in that
particular place. Piece of, how
can we respond? I mean, I know
Dwayne Elgin is really good at
that. Other people are really
focused on, how can we move
forward, dynamically, creatively
in this process, and so I'd
rather not Barbara Marx Hubbard
was great. Remember on her wheel
and all the different
professions, I think it's going
to take all of us to get through
this. Take all the scientists,
all the educators, all the
politicians, all the artists.
It's going to take every one of
us and all the skills that we
bring to our various livelihoods
to move into this. What I would
offer is the metaphysical
perspective that comes from
reincarnation research and
without going into the data
supporting us, but the basic
vision is, when we incarnate, we
choose our incarnation. We
choose the time and place and
circumstances of our birth. And
therefore it's it's an axiom of
my thought that all the human
beings on the planet right now
knew what they were getting into
when they chose to incarnate in
this century under these very
demanding circumstances, and
they chose to incarnate with a
specific kind of karmic agenda,
with a specific sense of how to
contribute. So I think each one
of us needs. All we need to do
is look deeply, look under our
feet, to look at where we are,
who we are, how we are
positioned. And the question is
not really, I think, how do we
find the right thing to do? I
think the deeper question is,
will we have the courage? Where
do we find the courage to do
what we discover that we can do
absolutely. The essence of this
pivot is a pivot into oneness,
an awakening of oneness
underneath our feet, which will
completely change technology,
how we apply technology,
international conflict, social
relationships, organization of
society that fundamental
awakening in the human heart,
the healing of the human heart,
and awakening, awakening into a
true, deep, vivid, mystical
experience of the fundamental
oneness of all life. And that
means that's an inclusive
vision. And so. So as we move
toward that time in history and
back into ecological balance, of
course, a oneness that includes
all living species on the
planet, the more we become the
human being that is trying, that
the Earth needs right now, that
culture needs right now, the
more we accelerate the
transformation of this, this
transformational change in our
own role in it, we must become
the future being that Earth
needs, and as we do, we enter
into synergistic relationship
with other beings who are also
working to become what the
planet needs right now. Yeah,
beautiful, that's not very most
specifics. There are other
people who are better with
specifics,
Stephen Gray: right? Well, I I
agree with you, you know, I
mean, in the sense that we don't
know what people need to do. And
if I may dare, a bit of a
provisional answer about that,
I've got Mark interested in this
term that I got from Steve and
her at Buhner, which I believe
he translated from William
Blake, which is follow the
golden thread. And so, you know,
obviously, I mean, think we all
know as a it's almost a
platitude in some ways, that the
inner work is the foundation for
moving out into the outer work,
and that one would hope that if
the inner work is being done
properly effectively, then you
can follow the golden thread,
or, as they sometimes say, let
go and let God, and then it's
like, that's, I think, another
central component of this
revision that we're dealing with
is we're moving hopefully, we
need to move from sort of head
based calculation of how to move
through the world to heart
based, or intuitive based, you
know, through that. And then
I'll just add one more thing
before tossing it back to you,
if I may, Chris, one of our
other speakers, Mary Sanders,
just sent me the title of her
talk for the spirit plant
matters conference, conference
for this year, and it's
reimagining collective care as a
path to liberation. And seems to
me that's another central
component of it. You know, you
talk about us moving toward
oneness, so the recognition of
the power of connection and
shared vision and shared prayer.
You might even say, shared
manifestation seems to me
central to this movement
forward.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think
Marc Caron: I just wanted to add
one more thing, if I could,
gentlemen, because Steven, you
said something about, you know,
you mentioned the head and you
mentioned the heart. And I think
we have so much wisdom and
knowledge, you know, education
type knowledge, that it's when
we lead that with our heart is
so much more powerful because,
you know, we can just repeat
what we hear, what we read and
what we learn, but it's a in my
experience, you know, in terms
of when I share, I know when I'm
in my head and I'm in my heart,
and the difference that it makes
in rapport and relating, and
same as when somebody's
presenting or you're working
with someone, you know the
difference between that and it
kind of reminds me of a quote
that I always loved hearing that
made a lot of sense was the
longest journey you'll ever take
is the one between your head and
your heart.
Chris Bache: Yeah, now I would
add the third piece, and that is
the body of the body's wisdom.
And of course, this is the
context within head and heart
meet. And of course, one of the
reasons we're in so much trouble
in terms of the planet is we're
just our theologies and
philosophies had tended to aim
us away from the body, away from
physical embodiment, away from
the Earth, and ignoring the
messages that we've been getting
from the earth. And so it the an
opening of the heart at that
level, an opening of the mind at
a level, and an opening of our
body to our body as a cell in
the body of the planet. So lots
of levels going on all at the
same time. Yeah, very
interesting,
Marc Caron: yeah. And to add to
that, if I may, because the
body, of course, is the
connector between spirit and and
the planet, with the importance
of of food and what we put in
our body. So you know, our
conference called Spirit plant
medicine, all plants have
spirit, whether it be broccoli,
cannabis, Iboga, mushrooms,
whatever it is. And the
importance, I think, for us to
get back to clean, nutritious
food that isn't contaminated in
the same way lets our body work
in a much better way. And when
we acknowledge this, plants the
spirit. Of the plants, whether
it be a psychedelic medicine or
something psychoactive, to
something that's just something
to nurture our body for
nutrition and health and
vitamins and all the things that
we need. In a good way, makes
that connection even more
powerful. And I feel that, you
know, in so many ways, when we
look at the mass population of,
you know, just say, North
America. You know, the quality
of our store bought food is, you
know, really beautiful we all
need to become aware of,
Stephen Gray: yeah. So no more
beer and pizza mark, no.
Marc Caron: Well, everything in
moderation. I have to believe
it's like, you know, every now
and again you have to have a zag
or not, but you understand what
I'm saying. It's just what you
put in is,
Stephen Gray: of course, no,
that's really important. When I
think, you know, Chris, you
might have things to say about
that, but I'd like to try
leading you in another
direction, if I may, just before
my no Mark's going to want to
turn it to questions soon. You
know, you've spoken, obviously
about the birth of the future
human. And there's a, there's a
kind of humorous saying from the
famous baseball catcher and
pitcher from the Yankees, from
way back when Yogi Berra, who
was prone to these sort of
malapropisms that ended up kind
of making sense anyway, and one
of them was something like, If
you don't know where you're
going, you might end up
somewhere else. So it's a sort
of like a two part question.
It's like, and I don't even know
if you can answer this, I don't
want, I know you don't want to
step beyond the bands, bounds of
your knowledge. But what you
know, we've talked about this
before. How would you describe
what the awakened human looks
like, in terms of how they move
in the world and so on, and what
might be the kinds of signs of
awakening that people might look
for? And it's on this principle,
if you don't know where you're
going, kind of idea, right?
Like, I think it is helpful and
correct me anyone if I'm wrong,
but to have some kind of
signpost is, what is the natural
human being looking like? What
is the birth of the future
human, or with a future human
looking like?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, I think
our spiritual traditions have
been giving us insights into
what's emerging, I think all of
the great saints and sages that
were responsible for
establishing or starting seeding
the religions of the Axial Age,
one of the things that drew us
to them, Drew humanity to them
is because we could feel a deep
resonance with them. And they
were kind of the prototypes,
archetypal prototypes of what we
were becoming, and they invited
us to become what they had
become. And in that way, I
think, in the Buddhas and the
prophets and the Christ and the
great saints of all the deepest
spiritual traditions, we can see
the prototypes of what's coming
so and the difference is, I
think that some people have
said, and I agree, that the age
of individual enlightenment is
over. Now it's collective
enlightenment or death. You
know, it's a collective game. So
the dynamic that's so unusual is
the entire that nature seems, at
least in my experience,
visionary experience, nature
seems intent on awakening the
entire species to really and the
entire species is going to go
through what individual mystics
have gone through in their
individual awakening. The
individual mystic goes through
the dark night of the soul, a
period of intense purification,
offloading past karma, past
negativity or behavior, en route
to entering into a clear state
of awareness, which we would
call spiritual awakening, or
enlightenment, or something
along those lines. I think
humanity as a whole was going is
going through, or will be going
through, is beginning to go
through a collective dark night
of the soul, a period of
profound purification of
confronting what we might think
of as the sins of our fathers,
which are our sins, because we
are our own fathers in this way,
but going through a tremendous
kind of purification process in
order to clear out our basement,
so to speak, in order To make us
more receptive to increasing
energies entering us at this
from the spiritual dimension at
this time in history. Now,
another way of putting this, and
it ran through my sessions, is,
I think the future human. I
think we're coming to a pivot
point in our reincarnational
story. Story. We've been
reincarnating. We die. We expand
to soul. We incarnate. We
contract into ego. We expand to
soul. We contract into ego. And
we just keep this up for 1000s
and 1000s and 1000s of years.
And we're learning and we're
growing. And sometimes we step
back, and mostly we step
forward, but we keep on learning
and growing. And enlightenment
is the Eastern traditions have
tended to see enlightenment,
this culminating in
enlightenment. But if we really
look at what that means and and
often they think, they've tended
to place it in a context, you
become enlightened, and then you
can leave you leave time and
space. You leave Samsara, who
wants to be in time and space
when you can be in the bliss of
eternity. But I think that's a
short sighted understanding of
what's taking place. Now that we
have a better understanding of
how big the universe is, how old
it is, and how complex it is, it
doesn't really make much sense
to think that after all these
hundreds of 1000s of years of
evolving humanity the point of
individuated consciousness, and
about just 5000 years ago,
humanity begins to sink down at
that depth layer where they
begin to tap into that dimension
of their own mind, which is one
with the mind of all living
things, just at that point, 5000
years after we've developed
writing, then when we achieve
spiritual awakening, then we
leave, we just leave it all
behind. I don't think that's
what's happening. I think now
we're beginning to have a deeper
understanding, and that is,
we've been reincarnating,
reincarnating, reincarnating.
And I think we are at a time
when all of our former lives are
beginning to come together.
They're they're beginning to
come to us. And as they come
together, they bring forward, of
course, all their unfinished
business, which becomes our
unfinished business. And this is
happening collectively. And when
this process reaches critical
stage, at least, this is how it
unfolded in my session. So I
just, I asked the listeners
indulgence. There was a time
when all my former lives started
coming into me fast and furious,
and they were fusing. And I've
done a lot of past life therapy
work, so I'm familiar with a lot
of them, but they were just
coming in, coming in, and then
they seemed to fuse. They hit a
critical mass. And when they hit
a critical mass, there was an
explosion of diamond light out
of my chest, and it catapulted
me into a state of consciousness
where I was an individual, but
an individual beyond any frame
of reference that I had ever
imagined before. And I think
what I was being shown or taken
into was what happens to an
individual when they reach this
turning point in their
evolutionary journey where all
of our former lives come
together and fuse, and a new
identity is born. And this
identity, I think, is the
identity of the soul. But it's
not the soul that we encounter
after we die. It is that, but
it's the soul in a human
incarnation, in the earth, in
the body. And this is what I
call the birth of the diamond
soul. That is, I think, the
future human will be a human
being, where the operating
identity will not be any
individual, private identity,
not 100 year old identity, but
it'll be 100,000 year old
identity. We will have a sense
of ourselves, a living,
conscious memory of ourselves as
a being that's been living in
and out of time for 1000s and
1000s of years, and a s any
being who is just larger has a
deeper sense of themselves, a
deeper sense of relationships
with other human beings, because
if they remember their former
lives, they remember their
relationships that they're they
were all involved in. And as we
have been male female, we've
been every race imaginable,
every religion imaginable, and
all of these differences are
coming together and fusing to
produce an individuality that
holds all of that as an
integrated, harmonious
singularity, okay, that I think
is, is the best take I have on
the future human. And I can tell
you that when I was taken toward
the end of my journeys into the
deep time and was given the
grace of experiencing this new
archetype, this future human, it
just it moved me to tears. Was
so beautiful. So I mean, picture
a humanity completely healed of
all the wounds of history,
completely healed of all the
divisions that we've etched in
history, a humanity with an
open, expansive, compassionate
heart like the best of the
saints through history, humanity
with their consciousness open
into deep communion with the
creative intelligence of the
universe, with fewer interfering
Bardo echoes, shadows in the in
the way, and a human being who
is deeply committed to being in
the body, not trying To get out
of time and space, but living
increasingly strong, focused,
intentional life, an integration
of spirit and matter inside
their physical existence. That's
kind of the bit. That's what has
been coming into me. That's what
I have to offer.
Stephen Gray: That was
absolutely beautiful. Chris, you
know, I think I'm going to play
this back to myself with
headphones on, just before
bedtime for a beautiful bedtime
story, and before a beautiful
Chris Bache: story, we really
are. It is ordinary, hard times
ahead, but deep beauty.
Stephen Gray: We need that kind
of encouragement. Chris, this is
such a gift that you offer to
people. You know, it puts me in
mind of something Bishop Desmond
Tutu once said, that is the
problem with most people, is
they don't believe in the
possibility of possibility. We
need people to take heart. We
need people to believe that what
they do, as you say, matters
more than ever, right? Yeah.
Anyway, I'm guessing, Mark you'd
like to open it up to some
questions,
Marc Caron: yeah, and just a
second. I just wanted to add to
that, because I believe that,
you know, as human beings, we
can do so much more than that.
We think we can do. We have such
an ability to push through, to
persevere, to, you know, I don't
mean work hard, as in, you know,
crazy, but we can do more than
we think we can do, and it's by
pushing that limit, by pushing
ourselves. Is, you know, how we
build the muscles? You don't go
to the gym. Build Muscle, you
know, light and few reps, you've
got to push through the pain,
and, you know, the challenging,
the things that are making it
build. And I think it's
something that you know, in some
cases, and I can speak for
myself personally, that we
sometimes you get a little soft,
you know, and to remember that
we have the ability to be able
to have that strength to push
through. So before we go to two
questions, I have one question
that some people may be
thinking, I don't know if
anybody will ask, and I know
I've asked this question of you
before, Chris, but you've done
such an amazing work on 72 high
dose journeys, and as a
professor of religious studies,
most people would think that's
not what a professor of
religious studies would be
doing, because you know the
stigma of what LSD might be seen
as, what Made you what inspired
you to choose that direction or
that path for this deep dive
philosophical work. And what
would you say to anybody who,
after hearing what you've done
and experienced, is there
anything that you would say to
them in terms of, you know, some
sage advice,
Chris Bache: starting at Vienna,
my advice is, please don't do
it. Don't do it the way I did
it. I was young and foolish. I
know I understand much more now
than I did then. I would advise
a different protocol. But how I
got into this is a simple story.
I came out of graduate school
kind of an atheistically
inclined agnostic in philosophy
of religion, but I've had a
long, lifelong, passionate
desire to ask the big questions
and to seek the big answers. I
mean, I really wanted to
understand how life works,
what's going on, what's Why is
life filled with so much
suffering? What's is there an
intelligence inside the universe
expressing itself? I really
wanted to answer those questions
if I could. And right after I
finished graduate school, I met
the work of Stan Grof and his
work, realms of the human
unconscious changed my life, and
very quickly, was followed in
1980 BY HIS Manual LSD
psychotherapy. And I just, I
knew I wanted, I wanted to do
this work. I needed to do this
work. I don't like breaking the
law, but I would. I went
underground, basically in part
of the transitional underground
generation that did this work,
and I started doing the high
dose work. First. Us a matter of
efficiency. That is, I was still
thinking it was a personal
model, and I knew the sessions
would be more intense, but it
would turn up more of my psyche,
and I would, if I could manage
the intensity, I would clean up
my shit faster, and I'd get to
enlightenment faster. Turns out
all my assumptions were wrong.
Is not about personal and and
when you work with high high
doses, you activate a larger
piece of the fabric of
existence, and your what may
begin is your individual
transformational process becomes
part and parcel of humanity's
larger collective
transformational process. But
then when, when I began to
understand some of this, three
or four years into the process,
I found that I had developed a
taste for working with high
doses. I was able my
constitution was wired such that
I seemed to have the ability to
get very large and spacious, and
very importantly, I had the
ability to contract safely at
the end. And this is, you know,
not everybody, you know, a lot
of people shouldn't work with
psychedelics at all, and a lot
of people should not work with
high doses of a powerful
psychedelic like LSD. So this
is, you know, and I would do it
differently, even if you have a
natural aptitude, even if you
have the capacity, even if you
have the strong social setting
that supports you. In this work,
I would be much gentler. I would
be a Gen take a gentler way in
I'd work with more lower doses.
I would balance the occasional
high dose with integrating lower
doses. I'd work with not only
LSD, but I'd balance it with
working with Psilocybin or
Ayahuasca, the vegetative
psychedelics. So there's just a
lot of things I would do
differently, yeah,
Stephen Gray: but, but, you
know, you can't answer this
question, of course, because
it's the road not taken. But you
know, just speculatively, would
you have been able to bring back
such deep and powerful
information had you not put
yourself through this fire?
Unknown: It? I It,
Chris Bache: it, I found that it
takes a lot of work and a lot of
discipline in order. When you go
very deep in the universe, and
you transcend so many levels of
time and space and identity and
species identity and into
archetypal and beyond archetype
reality, you're breaking into so
many layers of new territory
that it's very hard to stay
conscious at those levels, and
often people only bring back
pieces. But if you work
consistently and with
discipline, you can learn how to
stay conscious at those levels,
and you can bring back more and
more, but it's a discipline.
It's really, for me, it's a
philosophical discipline to
really, not only engage and
break into new territory, but to
bring the experiences back and
get them down in writing or art
or music, different people in
different modalities, but to
bring them inside one's being to
learn to live by the insights
that they give you. So I may not
have gone out as far as I ended
up going out, but I also learned
that going out is not everything
that I thought it was going to
be in the early stages. I
thought that the farther out you
went, the more profound the
impact would have and allow you
to hold and change your life,
and you'd become an enlightened
being and and so depth was
related to, if you if you did it
right, was related to
stabilizing the impact of these
deep immersions. What I learned
is that it's a much more
complicated process than I had
initially thought. The process
of retaining and holding on to
those experiences is much bigger
than simply remembering them. To
integrate a journey is different
than integrating individual
sessions, and I found that the
task of integrating such a
radical journey, it will take me
lifetimes. I think, integrate
where I went, and I don't think
I could ever integrate them in
that sense of being able to hold
them, enter them, live from
them. During my current
lifetime, this just the universe
is too big, and it took me in
too deeply to sort of hold it
well.
Stephen Gray: I thank you.
Deeply. The for having done that
work for us anyway. I know you
wouldn't start out to do it for
quote, us, but it turned out
that way.
Chris Bache: Turned out that
way. Yeah,
Marc Caron: I like the comment
on efficiency. So we have
comment here in the chat.
Melanie White says, Thank you,
Chris. She loved the book LSD in
the mind of the universe. And
thank you for sharing your
insights with us tonight. And I
think that'd be a great segue
for those of you watching
online, maybe just the live
streams, after the factor even
live right now, we have a studio
audience here in our zoom where
we're going to take some
questions. We do have a question
here from Jacob. Michael, if you
can bring Jacob in, we'll unmute
him and we'll hear what he has
to ask. Welcome to the program,
Jacob. Thanks for for joining us
and asking a question.
Unknown: Yeah, thank you. It's
going to be my first spirit
plant medicine conference this
year. So very exciting to kind
of join you beforehand. I was
deeply struck by the book
Christopher and it articulated a
process that I seem to find
myself in some of the early
stages of not to presuppose that
it would go in the same
direction, but certainly I'd
never encountered anybody who
had been dropping into those
collective levels. And yeah,
much, much more to say about the
richness of the work. But the
question I wanted to put to you
is really whether you'd really
encountered like, how does this
process and journey for you
relate to Christology, or did
you have kind of Christ avatar
experiences, and how does that
kind of map On to the process
for you?
Chris Bache: Yeah, interesting
question, Jacob, there have been
two religious traditions, or
spiritual traditions, that have
had the largest influence on my
life. The first was
Christianity, and the second is
Buddhism. And I also taught
world religions for decades, and
so I spent semester after
semester, going around the
planet, in my mind, with my
students doing a huge, you know,
Huston Smith kind of journey in
and out of the world religions.
And I, they just all became,
they became passionate lovers
for me. And each one of them
taught me so much. And while I
started, in a sense, within the
Christian framework, I also
began to understand over time
that Christ is the fruition of a
spiritual impulse in the Middle
East that parallels in certain
seminal ways, the fruition of
the Spiritual impulse in India,
the fruition in Africa, the
fruition in South America, that
I began to see larger patterns.
So for me, if Christology is the
study of the Christ archetype,
for me, that archetype is bigger
than Jesus, but it kind of, it's
a larger dynamic of profound
awakening of the human heart,
profound awakening of the of the
mind, of the Spirit. So I just,
kind of, I live and breathe in
in kind of the Universalist
waters, which, on the one hand,
recognizes the distinctness of
each of the lineages, but also
recognize the or the overlapping
common ground. Now, I, you know,
I didn't have a lot of
experiences of Avatar kind of
beings or angelic beings, or
even spirit guys. I didn't have,
you know, the machine elves
encounter that people do at the
DMT and I didn't have a lot of
experience of individuated
beings in my journey. And I know
that a lot of people do, and so
I don't question that there the
universe is filled with beings
that we often counter in
psychedelic sessions. My sense
is that the nature of the work I
did. My sense is that maybe this
is a hypothesis. You have to be
a being, to experience beings,
you have to be a self to
experience cells in the
universe. And if your work
grinds you fine, just grinds you
repeatedly into dust. Then when
that dust goes out into the
universe, it sort of takes you
into the fabric of life. Rather
than putting you into individual
dialog with individual pieces of
life, even deeply spiritual,
large pieces of life, so I was
drawn into archetypal dynamics,
archetypal dimensions I was
drawn into, and I always was in.
There was a consciousness
guiding my sessions. I always
felt in the hands of some
massive consciousness. But this
consciousness never appeared to
me in any kind of concrete,
physical, this type of form. I
felt it as a presence. It guided
me deeper and deeper and deeper.
It was open ended and infinite,
but didn't distill itself into
particular forms. So was that.
You see how that kind of gets
complicated around Christology,
on the one hand, it affirms the
deep essence of it. On the other
hand, it it doesn't get
concretized into our
historically specific
expressions.
Stephen Gray: Yeah, was there a
visual component to these
journeys?
Chris Bache: Very strong visual
components, not hallucinatory. I
mean, I could pull off my eye
shades in the middle of the
journey, and I was not
hallucinating, but very, very
deep visual components, yes, but
I never saw the intelligence
that I was experiencing so
intimately. I mean, this
intelligence would draw me into
it would purify me and beat me
up and crush me and destroy me
again and again. And then, when
I'd gone through the
purification process, it would
receive me and take me and
educate me and take me through
things over and over again until
it was sure that I understood
what it wanted me to know. And
then it would take me on deeper
but it never adopted a form that
I could identify as such? Wow,
Unknown: could I do a brief,
brief follow up question?
Marc Caron: Sure nobody else has
their hands up, so go for it
cool.
Unknown: Your work also
resonated a lot for me with that
of Pierre Tolle, hard de
Chardin, and I wondered if
you're like to what, how did,
how do you feel his work kind of
mapping with your sense of this
kind of as an EPO birth period?
Yeah, I just assuming you're
familiar with his realms.
Chris Bache: And isn't it
striking, the overlap, I mean,
really the profound insights
that he had to humanity coming
to a turning point and the news
sphere. And, you know, he was
trained as a geologist, and so
he had this large historical
landscape, and with his deep
natural spirituality and his
deep Christian faith, he saw so
much, and I think there is an
overlap. And I had read, you
know, Chardin in graduate
school, and I had read many
spiritual teachers and many, but
I don't think they, I mean, just
to sort of anticipate a question
that some readers might have, I
don't think it shaped my
experience of what actually
happened in the sessions. It
helped me understand and
interpret what happened in the
sessions. But the Sessions had
their own generative power,
which seemed to be drawing from
a different kind of source, but
that sardin saw as much as he
sell all on his own in his non
amplified capacity. Just
awesome. Just awesome.
Marc Caron: Yeah. Well, thank
you so much for the question
Jacob. And if anybody else has
any questions for Chris, now is
the time if you want to raise
your digital can turn your
camera on, we'd be happy to take
your question. Looks like we're
good, or you can raise your
physical hand, oh, there we go.
Jackie, are you good? There we
go. We'll ask you to unmute
here.
Unknown: Awesome. Hi, Chris, Hi,
Jackie,
so this is maybe, like you had
said, in terms of, like, the
movement of the planet and all
the urgency and what direction
we move into that there are
people better suited, maybe, to
fill in the details, but I'm
thinking about like, what are
the things that might be
happening now in terms of
accelerating shifts in
consciousness, like, are there
things is, are psychedelics part
of that, you know, Stevens book,
can psychedelics help change the
world? How do we stabilize those
things? And I'm, I'm thinking
about, like, I know. There are
groups of meditators, deep
meditators, for example, who are
working with low dose five Meo
as a kind of ally for achieving
nature of mind meditation, or a
kind of idea that somehow these
excursions can help us
restructure so that we can
contain more or have more
capacity for these shifts in
consciousness. So I'm just
curious your thoughts on that
like, not that I know, of
course, you can't advocate that
everybody go do psychedelics,
but just what your thoughts are
like if you had a workshop, what
would you train people to do?
Chris Bache: Well, first I just
want to a big yes to everything
you're saying. I think we're all
hardwired into the collective
psyche. I mean, it's we are
truly embedded our individual
life is a cell within the life
of our species, physically at a
physical, biological level, and
also at a mental level,
spiritual level. So everything
we do registers in the
collective psyche, and the
collective psyche shapes
everything that we do. I mean,
it creates the structures and
the territory. So an extreme
example is, I think when I die,
I take my psychedelic
experiences with me, but I also
think that the species mind will
keeps it too, because I was a
human being when I had these
experiences, so they become part
of the human family of
experience, and therefore they
continue to even if I never
reincarnated again, these
experiences would be alive
within the human family, and
this is true for all of us.
Everything we're doing continues
to live. So the harm that we
bring into life registers in the
human family, the healing that
we bring into life, the insights
that we bring, the care and
compassion that we bring, all
kind of infuse the network of
life that is the human family
and beyond the human family. So,
yeah, I think that when we work
as the spiritual traditions tell
us there is no such thing as
private spiritual practice. So
you know, the first thing you do
in Buddhist tradition, when you
do a practice is you cultivate
bodhichitta, or the desire to
save or to in to help all
sentient beings. The last thing
you do at the end of the
practice is you distribute the
merit to all levels of being,
all six levels of the Bardo, to
all levels. So you're constantly
the trap that we can get caught
in is to think that it's all
about some personal
enlightenment or personal
exercise, and the spiritual
traditions are telling us just
the opposite. It's not about You
dummy, it's all of us. It's all
of us. So open your heart, open
your mind, let the pain in,
bring the healing out, and when
we do that, I think we can just
trust that everything we're
doing is being conserved and
used by the other beings who are
alive at this point in time. In
fact, that's one of the things
I'm going to be talking about at
the conference, because in my
life, I was an academic. I had
to keep all this work completely
hidden. I never let my students
knew know what I was doing. I
was always, you know, that was a
private part of my life, but I
found that my students began to
be activated by my psychedelic
work, and they there was a
certain transparency opening
between their mind and my mind,
and I began to understand it was
as if my students were showing
me that what I had experienced
about the nature of
consciousness, that ultimately
it's all one integrated
consciousness. It was as if what
was happening in my classroom
was demonstrating that this is
true, and eventually it forced
me to learn an entirely new way
of teaching that was respectful
of these quantum fields that
were emerging in our work
together. So there is no such
thing as private practice. There
is no such thing, you know,
we're all in this together.
We're arm in arm. Everything we
do serves everyone in the
process.
Unknown: Beautiful. Thank you.
Marc Caron: Thank you. Thank you
for that question. Jackie was
coming in from Philadelphia.
It's really great to see people
coming in from different parts
of the world. We have another
one person joining us from
Salisbury, UK, different parts
of Well, here's Albuquerque, New
Mexico. Albuquerque. Technology,
all right. Michael K, Michael K,
has a question. I'll unmute you
here. Michael, there we go. Oh,
you're muted. You're not at your
you'll have to, there you go.
You'll have to put the request.
Unknown: There you are. Hello,
everyone. You. Hello. Yeah, I'm
calling from Lake, Lake Geneva,
Wisconsin, and Chris, I wanted
to focus on your experience in
the collective of the human
species and relating that to
individual efforts today. And
you mentioned that you carry
hope for the future. You were
that we will come through this
birthing process. But could you
expand a little bit more on the
relationship between the
individual and collective and de
with what you just said? And the
final comments on the last
question, do you think that the
right inspiration from the right
individual will spread much
faster in the future into the
collective consciousness, with
acceptance, far faster than it
has been in the past.
Chris Bache: Yeah, where if we,
if we just look at what's going
on around us right now, you
know, America's in a
presidential election, and we
see a deeply divided country,
and we couldn't have candidates
more polar opposites than the
candidates we have in such deep
polarization of political of the
political spectrum, and we see
this in so many different areas
of discourse. So it is
extraordinary, very turbulent,
choppy, uncertain times, and I
it's not just the truth that
catalyzes connections with
greater truth, but also lying
catalyzes lying, you know, and
darkness catalyzes darkness. So
the collective this dynamic
between the individual and the
collective is not simply a sunny
side of the street dynamic. It
also applies to the darker side
of the street, and we see this
in in shamanic cultures, where
they are dealing not just with
healing, but they're also
dealing with dark forces and
managing them or controlling
them. I think, however, that
Carl Jung is right that nature
tilts towards growth. I think it
tilts towards us becoming more
than we are, larger than we are,
wiser than we are more
intelligent than we are. Nature
tilts towards growth. And I
think that if nature is trying
to bring about this pivot
towards this higher form of
consciousness, emerging even
though we are experiencing
tremendous upheaval from the at
the collective level,
politically, socially,
culturally, I think the deeper
movement is towards higher,
better, truer, clearer, better,
good, More good. And so I think
that if nature favors growth,
that individuals who have made
the transition in their own
being, that humanity is trying
to make collectively, I think of
those individuals as becoming
kind of seed catalyst. Their
very presence helps catalyze
what's trying to emerge out
underneath our feet at a
collective level. So I do think
that individuals have tremendous
power to influence, not just
physically, not just by physical
contact, but all the spiritual
traditions have recognized that
there is a subtler form of
influence that radiates around
people when they do deep
spiritual practice. That's why
the Chinese traditions always
valued having a contemplative
practicing in their community
outside of town. The Christian
monasteries and nunneries have
always understood that their
work, their spiritual practice
had a beneficent influence on
the surrounding communities, so
I think that's going to be
increasing as we move forward.
Beautiful.
Marc Caron: Great question.
Thank you for that, Michael. And
I think unless anybody else
raises her hand in the next you
know, half a second or so,
we'll, we'll start wrapping up
our program. And Chris, I first
I want to just thank you for you
know, the work that you do, and
let you know how much I
appreciate you. I've got to know
you over the past number of
years, as you've been a great
supporter of their spirit, plant
medicine, conference and your
graciousness, your wisdom, your
energy, and that of your
beautiful wife, Christina, as
well. You know it's just it's so
beautiful to be in your presence
and to hear your words and bring
take that in. So I just want to
let you. How grateful I am for
you and the work that you do,
and I'm going to have to pay you
later when you get up here,
Chris, you know, at the
beginning, you said it's one of
the best psychedelic conferences
ever. So thank you for that.
Which leads into a segment that
I just wanted to share with
people that you know, if you're
here in the Zoom Room and you're
watching, and you're thinking
about coming to the conference,
or you're not sure, or you're
watching online, one of the
things that we do is bring in
this virtual aspect, so that we
can be live in person, maybe not
in person, but we have a virtual
community where you can connect
with each other, you can have
questions and answers with the
speakers in the room as well. We
bring in. Chris was one of our
surprise guests last year who
came in and talked to some folks
in the room. And, you know, just
have that different way of
connecting and being able to
participate, because not
everybody we understand can come
and join us physically. There's
always limitations and time
frames, but if you can join us
in person, we'd love to see you
there, and we love to see you in
the virtual room. And the bonus
of the virtual stuff too is you
get replays, and you can come
back into the membership and you
can catch up on it, instead of
just getting that one hit from
the room in a physical presence.
So thank you so much for your
work, Chris, I really appreciate
the support of you and your
beautiful wife with our
conference. And I got a shirt
for you because I know the ones
you like,
Chris Bache: Ah, good, yeah,
I've worn the other ones so much
they're getting worn out. So a
new shirt is
Marc Caron: good. You know, the
only one is a fun side note, but
it's true. I was at the unicorn
Music Festival, for those who
don't know, and John, and John
Stockton is he's a beautiful
soul, and he's a lawyer from the
days of cannabis and everything
else. I had seen him for a
while. And he comes up to our,
our tent and stuff at the at the
conference, and he's wearing the
same shirt, the green tree
shirt, and like you said, Chris,
it was all worn out. He loved
it. It it was one of his
favorite shirts, so he had to
set him up with another just a
funny story as a sidebar for
that. But if there's anything
that you want to add, Steven or
Chris before we wrap it up, that
would be great.
Stephen Gray: Well, excuse me,
I'm assuming you'll say a little
bit more about ways that people
can join the conference mark.
But also, I have a particular
question for a friend of mine
who lives in Switzerland and
wanted to catch this interview,
but it'll be 2am there right
now, or when this started. And
so how can he see this later?
Because, and the other thing I
want to say to anyone who's
still with us now, plus anyone
who sees this later, is if you,
if you heard the things that
Chris said, said today, along
with perhaps other information
that he has shared, this is
absolutely important for our
planet right now to hear these
things that Chris is saying
absolutely central and at the
very least, I mean, you know,
the basic ground of that, in a
sense, is the encouragement and
sort of upliftingness that's
going to be needed as we go
through these, you know,
increasingly challenging times
on the material level. I mean,
there's going to be no doubt you
know what's already happened,
and it will increase further is
deeper levels of anxiety and
depression and confusion and
tendencies to grasp on to, you
know, unreasonable hopes, such
as, you know what's going on in
the Maga movement, for example,
etc, etc. So I my my dream, my
hope, is that 1000s and 1000s of
people will watch this
interview. And so starting with
my friend Craig in Switzerland,
how can he tune into it?
Marc Caron: Mark, well, what a
great question. Steven, thanks
for asking. It's really simple.
First off, for anybody who
signed up, we're going to send
out an email with the link,
direct link. But you can check
out our spirit plant medicine
YouTube channel. It's streaming
there live as we speak. You can
check out our Facebook page as
well. It's streaming live there
as we speak. And so they're
always there for replays after
the fact. And if you're inspired
or moved by what you're hearing,
please. Please share it with
your friends. Share it far and
wide, and that helps the
algorithms as well in the social
media platforms to, you know,
start showing it more and more.
So it's really important that if
there's something here that
moved you, please, you know,
find those and share them far
and wide, so it's easy to find,
and we'll send out some email
reminders.
Stephen Gray: And I would like
to put in one final pitch for
people to attend the conference,
because of the, again, the kinds
of things that Chris has been
sharing is that we are moving
into a collective journey. And
quite honestly, this is not
really a sales pitch. I don't
see it that way. It's a, it's a,
it's a call to a gathering. I've
been I've been tending to think
of the conference as an
empowerment hub, now that we can
support and empower and
encourage each other by meeting,
whether it be, you know, they
can only make it virtually or
even better. Of course, in
person, it's, it's, it's part of
the collective journey that
we're working with here.
Marc Caron: Yeah, yeah. And I
Chris Bache: can jump in and
just heartfelt plug for the
conference, because, I mean,
truly, I just love going to the
conference. It's an intimate
conference. It's not like, god
bless maps. You know, it's not
like the 13,000 mega
conferences. This is a group of
dedicated practitioners working
with many therapeutic
modalities, with many substances
as opportunities for
conversations and a lot of new
things get open there. I release
diamonds, LSD in the mind of the
universe in 2019 I think it was
right. We got it early release
there. And now at this
conference, I'm going to be
releasing, as part of my
presentation, the new edition of
the living classroom, which is
the first time that I'm able to
really tell the story of the
role of psychedelics that
psychedelic played in the the
ideas that I wrote about in the
original version of 2000 in of
the living classroom in 2008
where I thought it was best to
keep psychedelics out of the
story. So there's just, there's
new material that comes forward,
new ideas, and there's just
nothing like the contagious
quality of being in the room
with like minded people and the
interactions and exchanges that
take place. It's just, it's just
a really, a wonderful, wonderful
place to be.
Stephen Gray: Hey, Chris, have
you been talking to Colin at all
about getting that book in time
for the conference, yes.
Chris Bache: Oh, good. I think
we're going to have it in time.
It's going to be an advanced
release. I don't know whether
we'll have the paperback. I
don't think the paperback is
going to be out. And so that
means it's going to be a bit
pricey, because it'll be the
hard back, you know, and it's
SUNY press, State University of
New York Press and but, yeah, we
will have copies there. I wish
we were going to have the
paperback, but that won't be out
for another year.
Stephen Gray: Hey, Mark, maybe
we could offer a slight special
discount ticket price if they
purchase the book at the same
time.
Marc Caron: Well, that's a good
one. I'm not sure how I would
rip that out of my mind right
now.
Chris Bache: Warn you, it's a
pricey I don't remember exactly
what it is, but it's, it's aimed
at libraries. You know, the
heart of that challenge is,
yeah, it was the
Marc Caron: publisher.
Definitely share it. Share it
out there, far and wide for
those interested as well through
our community. And you know,
it's thank you for your kind
words, Chris in it is the, let
me just get the marbles out of
my mouth. It's not really a
conference. We just call it a
conference. It's a ceremony, and
then we kind of put a conference
inside of it, right? So it
certainly is, is a community
based gathering. And you know,
I'm blessed to be here today at
the I am awake Foundation. And
this is a story about Chris and
Jen and the work that they're
doing in consciousness, research
and exploration. And they met at
the Spira plant medicine
conference in 2019 and their
work grew from there. So they've
been doing this beautiful work
for five years. We've met so
many people who have met and,
you know, created relationships.
And you know, doing business and
working together and just
connecting that, that we've seen
is a great connecting
opportunity, and even if you're
not in person, you still have
that ability in the virtual
world as well, because you have
the ability to connect and chat
with like minded people. So if
you're interested, by all means,
please join us. There's many
ways to do so, and we'd love to
see you there, whether
virtually, and of course, in
person, there's always room. So
that being said, I just want to
thank you again, Chris for the
work you do. I look forward to
seeing you and Christina again
in the very near future. And
Steven, thank you as well for
being my partner and co host and
everything that we do together.
It's always, always a pleasure.
And I also want to give a big
shout out to Michael Krause, who
is behind the scenes. He's just
a beautiful soul who does a lot
of great work with unify the
world peace movement and many,
many different things regarding
spirituality of consciousness.
There he is, there, Michael,
thank you for your support
always, as we do these programs
so we can I.
Unknown: You can, can? I can't
raise my hand because of the
technology behind it.
Marc Caron: Well, you've got,
you've got all the power,
really, man.
Unknown: And I just wanted to
deeply, deeply express my
gratitude to you, specifically,
Chris, for your wisdom, for your
knowledge, and having done the
work for all of us, and, and
what I really got from you and
and, and really feeling into
your energy, and you said
presence early on, is where
you've arrived in that deepest,
deepest level of the of the
gentleness of your heart. And
that, to me, that is what we
need to cultivate across the
planet if we want to move into
that new transformation. And I,
I I would want to get emotional
almost because I can, I can feel
the presence of you and and I, I
just deeply one about you, for
your work, for your wisdom, for
your knowledge and and, and the
beauty of your soul and and
thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
And it What an honor to be
supporting this through the
technology here in the in the
background and and also, thank
you, Steve, and thank you, Mark,
the beauty that shines through
you is and the commitment is is
unparalleled. So
Marc Caron: thank you for that,
Michael. And you know, as a
segue, hey, Steven, next this
Thursday, two days from now,
we've got a great series coming
up in the in the next month of
pre conference events and
conversations. This Thursday,
four o'clock, Marco Sanchez and
acashia Lewis will be joining
us,
Stephen Gray: and they're both
absolutely brilliant. They were,
in my humble opinion, no offense
to any of the other speakers
last year, they were the two
strongest, and for me
personally, they're both
brilliant and have a lot of
really relevant things to say.
And Hey, Michael, if you're
still listening, I'm lucky for
you, Chris has gone beyond the
level of spiritual realization
where he's seduced by flattery.
Marc Caron: And then lastly,
hey, next a week from today,
Rick Doblin from Matt, and then
I think the following Thursday
after we have soy, keen,
Stephen Gray: soy, Ken a Yeah,
actually, we have to talk about
that
Marc Caron: the time. Let's just
talk about who's joining us next
Thursday, and we'll talk about
that.
Stephen Gray: No part of that
Mark is we might possibly have
to switch that to Wednesday for
Anya, but we'll have to talk
about it.
Marc Caron: Okay. Well, next
week, stay tuned. We got lots
coming. Just check your emails
and make sure you confirm that
so you get everything. We'll be
posting that. We just want to
let everybody know. So with that
being said, I just want to wrap
up with a nice little closing
for conscious living on Co Op
radio. My name is Mark Kuhn,
joined by Steven gray and our
special guest Chris Bache here
on 100.5 cfro FM in Vancouver,
until next time, take care of
each other. Thank you,
Unknown: everybody.
Marc Caron: All right, we are
completing.