Unknown: Okay, okay.
Dottie Koontz: So welcome
everybody. This is the Vancouver
ions community group, and our
speaker tonight is, I'm very
excited to have Chris Bache PhD
back to talk about another of
his areas of contemplation,
which we wrote about in his
book, life cycles, a study of
reincarnation. Reincarnation is
a topic that I'm sure people
have different ideas about,
either believing, disbelieving
or curious based on my own
contemplation in my younger
years and subsequent personal
experiences, including a past
life regression in my 20s, I'm
in the believer camp. Chris, who
was our speaker a couple of
years ago, was just wonderful.
And as we've said in our check
ins, that everyone, a lot of
people, have read his book and
been very appreciative of the
the work that he did and and the
in the work that he wrote about.
Chris is a professor emeritus in
the Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he
taught for 33 years. He's also
adjunct faculty at the
California Institute of integral
studies, Emeritus fellow at the
Institute of Noetic Sciences, on
the board of the Grof legacy
training an award winning
teacher and international
speaker, Chris has written four
books, life cycles, about
reincarnation, dark night, early
dawn, about pioneering work in
psychedelic philosophy, the
living classroom, and
exploration of collective fields
of consciousness in teaching and
LSD in the mind of the universe,
the story of his 20 year journey
with LSD, which is a fabulous
book. Chris lives in
Weaverville, North Carolina with
his wife, Christina Hardy, a
professional astrologer and past
life therapist. So Chris take it
away and thank you for being
here.
Chris Bache: Hi everybody. Sure
it's nice to see you. And thank
you for all of your warm
greetings. It really touched my
heart, and I hope we have a lot
of fun today. I'm looking
forward today, and because many
of you know my work, I just want
to show you something which I
think you'd like to see. You
know, in 19, in 2008 I wrote the
living classroom. I talked about
fields of consciousness, the
transmission, energetic
transmission. I never meant. I
never mentioned psychedelics.
Didn't I didn't mention anything
about my psychedelic work. Now,
Sunni is bringing out that book
in a new edition. So this is the
new edition just out this coming
month, and it's in expensive and
hardback, but ebook. It's out in
ebook and it'll be in paperback
in a year. This is the true
edition of the living classroom.
This time they gave me
permission to talk about
psychedelics. So this time I'm
actually saying I was a
university professor for 20
years. I was taking these large
doses of LSD in a therapeutic
setting, and this is what
happened with my students, and
this is the theory of classrooms
and fields of consciousness that
came out of it. So just to share
that with you, because this a
special joy, and it kind of
deepens the final puts the final
stitch into bringing back
together the two halves of my
life that I had to separate in
order to do the psychedelic
work, in order to stay a
university professor in the
world, but to do this work, I
had to let them separate. Now
they're coming back together
again late in my life. But
before I published in
psychedelics, I tackled what I
thought was really a really
important fundamental question
dividing world philosophies, and
that is reincarnation. If you
believe this is the only life we
got, you're going to go down a
certain direction. If you
believe we have multiple
lifetimes, you're going to go
down a different direction. Seem
to be a fundamental thing. And
the amazing thing is, after I
got out of graduate school, and
after I started teaching and I
started to read around more, I
found that we had amazing body
of evidence that documents that
this is a a true and legitimate
part of life. None of my
graduate courses had taken
reincarnation seriously, you
know, not this, not the Western
religions that I studied, not
the scientific traditions that
had displaced those traditions
in my mind. And here was Ian
Stevenson at University of
Virginia proving that
reincarnation is a fact of life,
I had to race my entire
intellectual Blackboard and
start over again, because if
reincarnation is a fact of
nature, then we're living in a
much different universe than I
had thought we were living in
before. So my entire life has
kind of been un. Folding an
understanding of what it's like,
just like we see, we see plate
tectonics now, and we see
galaxies giving birth to stars,
and we see planets terraforming
now, there is this understanding
that reincarnation is part of
how nature has carried forward
and advanced the learning of
individuals within certain
species. Up to that point in
time, evolution is carrying
forward the learning of entire
groups, forward into more groups
and more groups, but eventually,
there reaches a point where
individuality matures and nature
has found a way to fold
individual learning forward into
cascading accumulations of
knowledge and wisdom and
experience. Okay, so my first
sabbatical, I wrote life cycles,
and it starts with a chapter on
the evidence for reincarnation,
and then it goes on to look at
say, so what if reincarnation is
true? What does it say about our
relationships? What does it say
about family? What does it say
about larger patterns? So, so
what I'd like to do tonight is
share with you this lecture on
gathering together the
scientific evidence for
reincarnation. Now, it turns out
I gave a good lecture on this
topic at an internet European
gathering, World Congress on
consciousness, and it's 35
minutes long. So what I'd like
to do is play that and let that
carry the water for taking you
through the evidence. I can't
say it better than I said it
here. And I was younger, had
more energy. Was a stage, and it
worked well. And then after 35
minutes, I'll catch it, finish
it out, and then we've got all
the time remaining for
questions, question and answers,
okay, all right, so let's hope
the technology gods are with us.
Fingers crossed, everybody.
I hope you're seeing what I'm
seeing, which is, all right,
large screen, and I hope the
sound works.
Unknown: There we go. Okay,
okay,
Chris Bache: now if I can make
this,
if the most important
philosophical question one can
ask in life is, do we survive
the death of our body, which Dr
Van Lommel is asking, I think
the second most important
question is, do we live once, or
do we live more than once? And
it all hinges on time. The
problem the significances of
time. As a teacher, if I give a
quiz, I have a right to expect a
certain performance from the
students. If I give an hour
exam, I have a right to expect a
higher level of performance. And
if I give a take home research
paper, I expect a higher level
of performance because they have
more time if this universe, if
this magnificent universe that
we are in, has a purpose. And as
a philosopher, we can, we have
to measure the purpose of the
universe proportionate to the
time. We have to fulfill that
purpose if we only live one
time, then we might extrapolate
or estimate or calculate the
purpose of existence to be
Unknown: but if we live 100
Chris Bache: times, if we live
1000 times, if we Live 10,000
times, if our participation in
this magnificent universe is
truly open ended, then we have a
very different relationship with
the universe, and then we have a
reason to think about the
possible purpose of existence in
a completely different framework
and the religions of the last
4000 years have had a tendency
to not value physical existence.
They've had a tendency to say,
well, you achieve realization,
you achieve enlightenment, and
then you leave Nirvana, Samsara,
you escape. Samsara, moksha,
escape or you achieve salvation,
and then you leave. But that
leaves the fundamental question,
what is the purpose of the
universe unanswered? What is the
purpose of my physical existence
in the universe? But if we come
back, if we come back to this
life many times, then we have a
different story that begins to
unfold, and it doesn't. I think
it. I. I think our understanding
of reincarnation is completely
incomplete at this point, just
as we've begun to understand the
true depth and breadth of the
universe that we are part of,
likewise, when we begin to
understand that we participate,
we're dancing with this universe
for extended period of time,
then we have a deeper
understanding of what the
universe might actually be
trying to accomplish in us, and
what might be our gift to the
universe in the continual
refinement and compounding of
our talent over time. So what
I'd like to do today is talk
about the evidence for
reincarnation, and I've been
thinking about this and been in
this game for a long time. The
first book I wrote, it was, is
life cycles. And notice how long
ago I wrote it. It was the first
book I wrote as an academic, and
that is a signal of how
important I think this topic is,
and that there is good, critical
empirical evidence that allows
us to decide this topic. If
there weren't critical evidence,
then it would just be a wasted
exercise. And I think this
evidence did not exist 50 years
ago, and the theologians used to
debate about reincarnation go
round and round, but today we
have a different body of
physical of empirical evidence
on reincarnation that has moved
the topic from the theologians
table to the psychologist table
to the philosopher's table to
the to the psychiatrist table.
And that's what I'd like to take
you through some today. Now when
looking at the evidence for
reincarnation, we can either
look at go small or go large. We
either look at the detailed
cases in or we look at the
larger body of literature. The
Beauty and the real joy is in
the detailed cases. But in 45
minutes, I've chosen to go
large. What I would really like
to do is encourage you today to
read one book on reincarnation
that you haven't read yet, and
so I want to take you into some
of the literature on
reincarnation and show you some
of the patterns that are
emerging in the literature and
rebirth. Okay, ready to go.
Let's go 20 cases suggestive of
reincarnation, by Ian Stevenson.
This is a book that changed my
life, because, like many people,
when I finished graduate school
in 1978 I was an atheistically
inclined agnostic. I was trained
in philosophy of religion, but
all that training basically made
me an atheist. But when I
encountered this book right
after finishing graduate school,
he turned my life around because
he convinced me that there was
evidence that we live on life
more than once. He is the Ah,
okay. Oh, good. Steven Stevenson
is the Carlson professor. Was
the Carlson Professor the
University of Virginia between
1967 and 2001 he has written 11
books on reincarnation. Some of
the most important are these
cases of reincarnation type
written over a seven year period
from 73 to 84 unlearn language.
The language is by children
about children who have an
ability to speak a language
which no one in their family
speaks, no one in their entire
town speaks, sometimes an
ancient language, children who
remember previous lives. And his
last book, his monumobus, a 1000
page, two volume work, a study
of 187 cases of children who not
only have detailed memories of
their most previous of their
immediate life, but actually
carry the scars in their body
which relate to the death wounds
of the body in their previous
personality. And that, of
course, really upsets academics.
I mean, it's one thing to have
continuity of memory that's bad
enough, but to suggest that a
wound of death can actually be
transferred into the physical
body of a subsequent personality
that drives my colleagues right
up a wall. But 187 cases, well
documented case histories. It's
a magnificent book. What are we
looking at with Stevenson? We're
looking at cases of children
from around the world who have
detailed recall of their most
immediate recent life. They know
their way around towns that
they've never been in before.
They can recognize persons when
they're brought into the life
place of the previous
personality. They can recognize
persons. Persons that they have
never met before. They know the
personal history, their personal
history with that person. They
have the appropriate emotional
responses with that person.
Husbands. For wives, children.
You have cases of a five year
old child who is showing all the
feelings of the husband of a 35
year old woman with all the
emotional responses. There is
one case of a child called
parmed When he was reunited with
the family of the previous
personality. He was very shy
around the wife of the previous
personality. He wouldn't
identify her until she left the
room, but then he identified
her, and then later, he took her
aside, and he said two things to
her. He said, I've come but
you've not fixed bindi, which is
the spot that Indian women wear
on their Ford, is an indication
that they're married. And he
also criticized her for wearing
a white saree instead of a
colorful saree. In the tradition
in India is when you become a
widow, you don't wear color.
From the rest of your life, you
wear only white. Essentially,
this five year old boy was
saying to this 35 year old
woman, I've come but you're
acting like you're not married.
They know the inner architecture
of homes that they've never been
in. They know people who owed
them money when they died and
the debt had not been collected.
In one case, this little child
was brought back to the home of
the previous personality, and
the wife of the previous
personality said, Okay, if
you're my husband, where did you
put the will. We couldn't find
the will. The little boy walked
over to a floorboard in the
kitchen, pulled up the
floorboard and pulled the will
out of this little secret place
that only he knew about in the
floor of the kitchen. Cases like
that drive by philosophical
colleagues at the University
right up a wall. They don't know
what to do with it. It's hard
for them deny it, but there it
is, some patterns in the data.
The average time interval
between the death of the first
personality and the birth of the
second personality Stevens binds
about two and a half years the
average distance between the
life place of the first
personality and the life place
of the second personality, 50
miles. And these children tend
to lose their memories around
the year, around eight years
old, when they become begins to
get into school and in a more
complex social environment, they
basically forget. They lose
their memory. So we're looking
at a small time window from
research, from about three years
old to eight years old, a five
minute time window to get to
these children and document
their memories. The remaining
90% forget them by the time
they're eight. The remaining 10%
the vast majority of those,
forget them when they hit
puberty, when they hit puberty,
you know, all hell breaks loose,
and they forget their subtle
traces of their former lives.
Stevenson asked, why do these
children remember what most of
us forget? And his answer is, he
doesn't know we need more
research. Saul research, he has
a hypothesis. He points out that
about 60% of these children died
violently in their previous
life. The remaining 40% died
either early, suddenly or with
an acute sense of unfinished
business, like a mother who dies
shortly after the birth of her
baby,
his hypothesis is, maybe there's
something about the trauma of
being wrenched from life
violently suddenly with an acute
sense of unfinished business
that encodes The consciousness
in a way that draws them back
faster than usual and closer
than usual, because this time, I
don't have time to give all the
evidence, but this two and a
half and 52 and a half years 50
miles, is faster than the
population at Large and closer
to home than the population at
large.
In reviewing 20 cases suggestive
of reincarnation, the Journal of
American Medical Association,
wrote, Stevenson has
painstakingly and unemotionally
collected a detailed series of
cases in which the evidence for
reincarnation is difficult to
understand on other grounds. Two
years later, the Journal of
Nervous and Mental disease, a
major psychiatric journal in the
United States, published an
entire journal devoted to
Stevenson's cases, and that it
was such an unusual move that
they published an editorial to
justify or. Explain their
rationale, and in the editorial
they wrote, Our decision to
publish this material recognizes
the legitimacy of his research
methods and the conformity of
his reasoning to the usual
canons of rational thought.
That's the way an academic
qualifies their endorsement. Now
the philosophical institution,
the guardians of Orthodoxy, are
not going to let Stevenson get
away with this, not without a
fight. And he has had his
critics, and the most important
critic is a man named Paul
Edwards. And I promise you, this
is the best picture I could find
of Paul Edwards online his book
reincarnation with critical
examination. Paul Edwards was a
major American philosopher. He
taught at the New School for
Social Research. He's best known
for having been the editor in
chief of the eight volume
Encyclopedia of Philosophy. So
he's a major heavyweight in the
philosophical tradition. He
wrote a series of articles in
1986 to 87 a four part article
on reincarnation. And eventually
he published these articles in a
later form. In this book
reincarnation, in his he is the
harshest critic of Stevenson. He
accuses Stevenson of fraud. He
accuses Stevenson of not being
sufficiently rigorous in his
analysis of the data. He accuses
Stevenson of not actually
verifying that he thinks that
there could have been contact
between the two families as
Stevenson isn't really critical
in proving that these families,
the first and second
personality, have never had
contact. But there's actually a
deeper you know, to to accuse
someone of bad research and to
prove that research two
different things. And if you go
through Stevenson's arguments
very carefully, I'm sorry,
Edwards arguments very
carefully, you see that there's
kind of a deeper logic operating
in his work. He says
reincarnation would represent a
crucifixion of our
understanding. And by our
understanding, he means secular
humanism, the philosophical
scientific tradition, the
Newtonian, Cartesian
philosophical tradition. He
says, If you believe in
reincarnation, you must accept
what he calls six collateral
assumptions. And these
collateral assumptions are that
materialism is false, that that
mind is not reducible to brain,
that our identity is more than
our personality, that there is a
domain other than space time,
that Death is an illusion, that
there may be a deeper logic to
our lives. Edward says these
assumptions are surely
fantastic, if not indeed
nonsense, and even in the
absence of a demonstration of
specific flaws, a rational
person will conclude either that
Stevenson's reports are
seriously defective or that his
alleged facts can be explained
without bringing in
reincarnation. Well, I won't go
over Edwards arguments more
carefully, because Robert Robert
almeter has done this for us.
Robert almiter is another major
American philosopher. He is
Professor Emeritus at Georgia
State University. He has
authored, or co authored 24
books. He wrote this book in
which he is evaluating five
categories of evidence for
survival of death. The major
analysis he's doing in this book
is the debate between Stevenson
and Edwards, and what he shows
by analyzing Edwards argument is
that Edwards does not refute
Stevenson's argument. What he
does is refuse to even look at
it seriously, because he is so
convinced that it must be false,
he says his argument constitutes
a blatant bit of question
begging, because he always
assumes precisely what is in
contention. What is in
contention is, Can consciousness
exist without a brain? And
because he believes that science
has proven that consciousness
can exist without a brain,
therefore we know that there
must be something wrong with the
evidence. Albert says if you
have a very commanding argument
that you can that you cannot
refute, then not to accept. The
argument is to act irrationally.
Stevenson's tradition continues,
even though he's passed on, he's
now looking from the bleacher
seats, watching us from there.
This book by Tom Schroeder, old
souls. Tom Schroeder wins the
definitely wins for having the
award for having the worst cover
of any book in reincarnation
research. But Tom Schroeder is
an interesting guy. He's a
reporter. He's a Pulitzer Prize
winning reporter. He's also one
of the editors for The
Washington Post, a major
American newspaper, and he was
interested in whether
Stevenson's research could stand
up to a critical reporter's eye.
So he went with Stevenson on one
of his trips around the world
studying these small children.
He looked over his shoulder, and
he came away convinced, as the
subtitle shows, compelling
evidence from children who
remember past lives, convinced
that this Stevenson's methods
were good, the data would stand
up. These children were real.
This is a compelling case for
reincarnation, and at the
University of Virginia,
Stevenson's work continues in
the person of Jim Tucker, who
has now inherited Stevenson's
chair. This book is a wonderful
book. This is very much in the
Stevenson tradition, continuing
to look in detail the detail
cases, and explaining why these
cases cannot be attributed to
weaker hypotheses like super psi
or something like this. I might
mention that Jim Tucker's book
is a lot easier to read than
Stevenson's book. Stevenson
writes and thinks like a lawyer.
It's very good, but it's very,
very detailed, very dry. Jim
Tucker brings a little more life
to the subject matter. Now
everything we've been looking at
so far has to do with what I
would call the evidence from
spontaneous memories, just
children who spontaneously have
memories of previous life. But
there's another body of evidence
you have to approach it with the
different framework. It's evoked
memories, memories which have
been evoked in some way,
different techniques, even
massage, can evoke a former life
memory. But the most common one
that we're familiar with is
hypnotherapy, some type of
hypnosis. The following cases,
following books, are
representative titles of people
who have worked in the field of
past life therapy. My favorite
book, written by a single
therapist who has worked in the
area of past life therapy and
has thought about it a great
deal, is this book by Roger
Wilber. Notice the date an
earlier book, other lives, other
cells, started as a Jung Ian
ended up in past life therapy,
doing past life's work, even
though Carl Jung, I don't know
whether you probably know, he
himself believed in
reincarnation towards the later
years of his life, but he kind
of kept it quiet. This is a
wonderful book, intellectually,
totally competent, a wonderful
review of detailed cases and a
discussion of the implications
of these cases. Past life
therapy began to really explode
in the 70s, 80s, and there were
a lot of therapists who were
concerned that there was not a
graduate school, there was no
curriculum, there was no agreed
upon curriculum for how to
establish the credentials for
people who wanted to do past
life therapy. And this task was
taken on by Winifred Lucas, who
wrote a magnificent two volume
anthology, which is a compendium
of essays and articles of the
best of the best of the people
working at that time in past
life therapy. So if you wanted
to read a single book, I would
read Wilbers book by one author.
But if you wanted to see an
overview of multiple people
writing in the field, I would go
to Winifred Lucas's book
regression therapy, a handbook
for professionals.
Carol Bowman
was a social worker. She wasn't
interested in past life therapy.
She got into it because her son
started having nightmares. He
started waking up with very
disturbing nightmares, and she
approached him. She tried to
work with him, took him to
therapist, tried to do
conventional things, but it
didn't work. And then she began
to do her homework. She began to
look into past life therapy. She
began to learn the field, and
she began to help her own child
solve his own trauma carried
over from a previous life that
was. Is both spontaneously
bubbling up in his life, she
began to attract other people
with other children who are also
having problems, and eventually
she wrote this beautiful book,
specifically a therapeutic book
for parents who have children
who are having traumatic memory
surface that they're having
difficulty dealing with, was
very successful, very
persuasive. It really made had a
lot of impact. She got more
business coming in. She wrote a
second book. She gets the award
for the second worst title cover
on reincarnation book, return
from heaven. She's looking
specifically at relatives who
have been reincarnated within
their own families. Now, as a
philosopher, that's a weaker
body of evidence, right? Because
there's so much potential for
contamination if you're
remembering your grandfather.
But as a father, this is
interesting. It's interesting
because reincarnation simply
doesn't happen where it works
well for the researchers, across
great distances and great
families, but inside families is
a very common occurrence, and
therefore it deserves to be
looked at and next. Michael
Newton, two wonderful books, and
I must confess a special
partiality if you want to read
some, if you wanted to just pick
out one or two books out of this
entire list, I can't help but
wish that you would read Michael
Newton's work. Michael Newton
was a hypnotherapist who got
into past life therapy and was
doing past life therapy, and
then he accidentally discovered
that his clients in deep
hypnosis had the ability not
only to remember their previous
life, but to remember what
happened to them after they
died. They could remember.
Basically, his clients were
beginning to describe the
afterlife, and he thought, he
didn't think this was possible,
but he followed his clients,
good therapist that he is, and
he took hundreds of people into
deep hypnotic regressions, and
he followed them when they would
go through their former life,
and they would go through the
death experience. He would
follow them into their memories,
continuing on, and then he would
ask them questions. And he kept
detailed notes. He would ask
questions about, what was this,
what was going on, what was it
like? And what he found was,
regardless of what background
people came from, whatever their
cultural enculturation was,
fundamentalist, Baptist, Karl,
Marxist, atheist, hardcore
scientific reductionist,
whatever their background was,
people were describing the same
fundamental reality in the after
death state. They were
describing a world that had
order, that had structure, that
had logic. There was actually a
social structure. It was a world
in which older learners taught
younger learners. And it was
also a world where people made
the choice to reincarnate as a
conscious, careful decision.
It's one of the most important
choices you make, if you go to
college, what courses you sign
up for, that's an important
choice, because once you sign up
for a course, you're committed
for the entire semester, when
you incarnate, what life you
take on is an important choice.
And Michael Newton found that,
in fact, in the spiritual world,
the choice of what life to take
is a consciously taken choice,
made under the guidance of your
spiritual helpers and made in
cooperation with the other
persons that you're going to be
incarnating with. So before we
knew, before we were born, when
we knew more than we know now,
when we were aware of more than
we are aware now, we chose the
life that we are living now,
that fact alone just bears deep
Meditation. Two last examples,
not from professionals, they're
from amateurs, but that's what
makes them interesting. The
first is this book looking for
Carol Beckwith, and what makes
it interesting is the man who
wrote it, Robert snow. Because
Robert snow is the commander of
the homicide division of the
Indianapolis Police Department.
All right, so he's chief of
detectives, of he investigates
murders. His opinion is very
important. It must stand up in
court. He would be the last
person that you would think
would be doing research on a
former life. But it happened
that he kind of, he did a hypno,
a hypnotic session not oriented
towards past lives. He just. On
a lark, he did the hypnotic
session, and in this hypnotic
session, he was hit in the face
with a life that appeared to be
his life, but it was, it scared
him to death, and he literally
ran out of the room. But he was
curious, and so he brought all
of his detective skills to the
systematic search to see if he
could identify and track down
whether there was such a person.
And the story of his experience
and the story of his detective
work is told in this short book,
looking for Carol Beckwith. And
lastly, this book, Soul
Survivor, which you may have
seen it because they did some
news clips, decent news clips on
it, written by Bruce and Andrew
leninga about their son, James.
And this is a case of a child,
three years old, two years old,
who started having spontaneous
memories and trauma, waking up
crying in the middle of the
night, spontaneous memories of
appear, apparently dying in
World War Two as an airplane
pilot over the over the coast of
Japan. And his father was a
fundamentalist Baptist, and he
was absolutely, vehemently
opposed to his son.
Reincarnating mother was a
little more receptive. So they
got involved in first they
wanted to help their son, but he
got involved in the the inquiry
because he wanted to disprove
reincarnation, whatever was
going on with James. He wanted
to disprove reincarnation to
protect his faith. In the end,
they tracked down this pilot.
They tracked down the story.
They were able to reunite James
with the people at a military
reunion, with the people who had
served with this pilot. And
James was able to identify
people onto this group. The
father became convinced that, in
fact, his son was a
reincarnation of this pilot, and
reincarnation is true. Now I'd
like to just finish with two,
two observations. Quick
observation says, lunch awaits.
I'd like to emphasize what we
don't know about reincarnation.
The evidence for reincarnation
may be compelling. However, we
don't really know a lot about
how reincarnation takes place,
or what the physics of rebirth
is. We're still beginners in
this at this point, we can't say
what the soul is or what it's
made of. How does it come and go
from the physical body? How does
it interface with our biology
and our genetic makeup? How does
it encode its previous learning
into our present body? And how
does it leave with its learning
intact after we die. These
things right now are beyond our
present grasp. I'm sure we'll
make progress in the future, but
before we do, we're going to
have to start we're going to
have to stop reducing mind to
brain, and we're going to be
have to approach this research
with a more multi dimensional
metaphysical cosmology. And
lastly, I'd like to point to a
certain paradox in the evidence.
And to do this paradox, I need
to really go back to Ian
Stevenson, Stevenson's evidence,
I think, is the most powerful
evidence for reincarnation, and
his evidence liberates our
thinking at one level, but it
also constricts our thinking at
another, because the strongest
evidence for reincarnation comes
from lives that show the
tightest connection, the
tightest correlation. But the
correlation can be so tight it
can lead, if you just study
Stevenson's evidence, it can
lead to a
anemic an under developed vision
of what life is like when we
die, when most of us die. In
that respect, we must remember
that Stevenson's cases are not
typical cases. These children
are coming back very fast and
very close to home. Most people
spend much more quote time in
the timeless condition of the
spirit world. They have a much
wider breadth of experiences. So
Stevenson's evidence liberates
us to thinking about the soul
and thinking about our lives and
thinking about our existence in
a much larger, expanded
framework, but in order to
actually fill in that Canvas, in
order to actually explore more
deeply what happens to us when
we die, and what the larger
circle of life is like, from
expanded consciousness to
contracted conscious. And back
into expanded consciousness, we
need to look at other bodies of
data. I think Michael Newton's
work is an important body of
data that gives us a larger
vision. And this afternoon, when
I talk about psychedelic
research, I'll look at another
body of data, which I think can
give us an expanded vision of
our life in this universe. Thank
you very much.
Okay, that brings us back.
Brings us back.
Dottie Koontz: Excellent.
Chris Bache: I sure had fun
sharing this with you. It brings
back a lot of memories for me. I
had a good time with this group
of people giving this material,
and now you have to picture
yourself. We've just finished
this talk. I'm walking around on
stage with a microphone, waiting
for the questions or
contributions you'd like to make
in the wake of this
presentation, I will just say
that my thinking of
reincarnation has evolved beyond
where it was when I wrote life
cycles. I opened up a deeper
level of reincarnation thinking
in dark net early dawn, when I
began to bring in the
psychedelic experience, and then
in LSD, in the mind of the
universe, I give the most
complete expanded understanding
of reincarnation with the birth
of the diamond soul, with the
concept of the birth of the
diamond soul in history. So but
where it all begins is, do we
have good evidence? Do we have
good, reliable evidence that any
good, hard, no skeptic should
endorse whether or not they do
or not. So that's some of the
literature, and Dottie has a
core bibliography that she's
going to hopefully send out to
everybody afterwards. So all the
names and places and books that
I mentioned are there, plus
more, so you'll get those. So
now the floor is open,
Unknown: yeah. So if
Dottie Koontz: you'd like to ask
a question, use the little hand
raised thing down at the bottom.
Let's see which one is it react
raise your hand, and we'll call
on you. Victoria, you're the
first. Wow.
Victoria: That was very lovely.
And you, you actually answered.
One of my questions was, how is
your understanding evolved? But
the two, two questions, you talk
about species reincarnation,
which I'd love to hear more
about that, especially given our
current situation. And I also
would like to understand more
what you mean when you talk in
the book about purification and
detoxification, because that
also seems very relevant. And
what does that mean for us,
individually and collectively?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, when I
began my psychedelic work, I
thought it was about personal
transformation, personal even
maybe personal enlightenment, if
I got lucky. But then, of
course, what happened is that I
dissolved the method I was using
was so powerful. It dissolved me
so deeply into collective
consciousness and the collective
species mind again and again
again, that it began to activate
dynamics at a species level. And
one of the very powerful ones
way down the road was actually
experiencing, it was like I was
in deep space, and I was
experiencing the pulse of life
on our planet. And it was a
pulse that kind of pulsed every
100 years more or less, but it
was a pulse of reincarnation.
And I was experiencing all of
human beings as cells in a super
organism. And the super organism
was evolving itself through
their individual life task. It
was just, it was the most
magnificent thing, and it was
beautiful, but it deep, in my
sense, that everything we're
doing is part of a larger
collective dynamic, an
evolutionary dynamic. Everything
we're doing is every what we
think of as a private is not
private. Everything is wired
into a collective network. And
that's true of reincarnation in
general, and then in specific
things about when I went into
the ocean of suffering, the
things we get involved in, in
deep spiritual work, some of
it's our personal, some of it's
former life. Some of it's not
personal at all. Some of it's
just it's larger, cleaning the
bayou. Now we know from studying
mystical. Autobiographies, when
an individual is opening to
deeper, pure, more
comprehensive, unitive states of
consciousness, those states of
consciousness are incredibly
powerful and pure, and they tend
to churn up the psyche and bring
to the surface all the things
that are distorting their
natural ability to enter into
this awareness. So all the
bruises and all the Chee little
things and all the little,
sneaky little things and
whatever, whatever that kind of
mucking us up, comes to the
surface. Well, if that's and
then we process them, and as we
process them, we clear them out,
we let them go. And then our
whole psychic system gets
cleaner and cleaner, and we're
able to not only heal, but to go
into deeper spiritual states of
awareness. So we know mystics do
this. We know meditators do
this. We know people in
psychotherapy do this. Turns out
that this is also true for the
entire species. The entire
species carries the wounds of
its history in its collective
memory banks. The entire species
has lived all these years of
war, has died in all these
terrible deaths of plague. Have
all the mothers who have died in
childbirth, anything which isn't
processed out by the present or
future life of that soul stream
is still in this collective
psyche, and it still holds
humanity's back, if you will. It
still scares humanity. It still
keeps us focused. And if
humanity is as I think it is, in
the process of growing up into a
deeper existential level of
awareness, it has to offload all
these things which are keeping
it small, which means it has to
purify itself, sweat out all the
mean the first all their pain
that we're carrying as a
collective, all the pain and
suffering, all the vicious
wounding of other being, this is
coming to the surface in us,
collectively and as well As
individually. And if you begin
to look like that, then there
are certain things that you can
see happening in a culture which
seem to be maybe less as we
thought of them before, as a lot
of individuals manifesting this
thing and kind of more as the
pulse of a deeper process. So I
think we are entering a time in
history of exponential growth.
But exponential growth, watch
out. It requires exponential
purification, exponential
detoxification. But this is
simply how complex systems
evolve themselves, how we grow.
So it's it's a very exciting
time, very challenging time,
time of exponential growth. But
for that same reason, time that
calls on the Warrior Within us,
the warrior is within us going
to be hard times.
Victoria: Well, just briefly.
Well, I imagine it can be brief.
So for me, this brings up so
much emotion. It feels like
patriarchy needs to be within,
that I needs to be let go of.
And that seems huge. It feels
like you kind of alluded to the
wrong leaders. Who knows? But it
feels like it's being brought
up. And so can you just give an
example of what, what does that
mean that that's huge, but
minute to minute, or what, what
does that mean to do?
Chris Bache: We just went
through this election. Now, I'm
pretty sure I'm in a safe room,
but if I apologize, if I step on
people's political tolls, I
apologize. But we had a choice
between a man and a woman and a
particular kind of man with a
particular worldview and a woman
with a particular kind of woman
a particular worldview, and
collectively, we chose, I think,
the worst of the choice. We
chose regressively. We chose
looking backwards. We try. We
chose trying to hold on to what
we had, instead of facing the
uncertainty of the future with
vision and courage. And so this
is going to hurt us for years
and years, decisions will be
made, things will get worse. I
don't know whether that's a bad
thing or a good thing, that
things are going to get worse
faster than if we had had wisdom
at the leadership level. I don't
know, but I think we're going to
find. It will be years before we
begin to recognize and recover
from the political decisions
that will be enacted over the
next decade under the influence
of this election. So I see it as
we have choice points in this
process. We have choice points
of whether to be wise or whether
to be dumb. I'm afraid we didn't
pass this, this intelligence
choice in our country. So
fingers crossed and hands
folded, yeah.
Victoria: So just so for me
individually, keep a focus on
the kind of person I want to be
is that, rather than going into
judgment or grief or
Chris Bache: outrage, one of the
things about reincarnation is
that it gives everybody
permission to be at the level of
spiritual development that they
are at, and You kind of lose the
habit of judging other people
because you can't judge other
people because you don't know
what their calling was, what
their challenge was, you don't
you just don't know. You don't
know how old they are. They
could be babies, they could be
graduate students. You just
don't know. So it leads me to be
kind of respectfully distant in
that way. So my focus is do the
best I can help the people who
see what I see do the best they
can together. I think we will
make a difference. And by the
way, I think as we go into
hotter and hotter, and I don't
mean that temperature wise, but
more and more intense
destabilization in the future,
the in the individual can have a
significantly greater impact.
This is we've learned from
nonlinear systems and chaos
theory. The more intense, the
more nonlinear a system S has
been giant, generating in
instability because it's
absorbing more and more energy.
It becomes unstable at those
highly energized states,
individuals can have a
disproportionate impact. You
know, butterfly flaps at Wings,
hurricane in China. So there's
an interconnection of the web as
we go into this crisis, each
individual will have a greater
impact than they might have had
100 years ago, because the whole
foundation is going to be
energized. Victoria, thank you
very much. Thank you for your
good questions. Thank you,
Dottie Koontz: jonai, you're
next. Okay.
Jonai: This has all been
wonderful. Everything I just
I've so enjoyed listening to you
to that that whole presentation
that you did, and Victoria's
questions and your answers and
everything and past lifetimes
has been so interesting to me,
and I have asked for lifetimes
with certain people. I've been
wounded, I've been actually
killed. I've been, you know, set
out to die all kinds of things.
But right now I am get, I've
been for the last three or four
years, preparing myself to write
quote memoir, but it's not going
to be the usual type of memoir
book. It'll be in three parts.
In the first 56 and a half
years, of course, will be the
first part, and that'll probably
be the least amount, but I have
to write that without judgment,
without blame, clear and and so
on. And so the things that
you're saying in terms of what
we have to do for ourselves are
so it's home to me, to me so
much. And I'm, I'm close to
that, and I have been close to
that for a while, but I just had
to figure it out in my mind, how
to say it, how to be it, how to,
you know, present it. And the
second part is all of the all of
the esoteric studies, ancient
wisdom techniques, all of that
kind of thing, past life, stuff
and everything. And the third
part is now.
Dottie Koontz: Jonay, sorry to
interrupt, but do you have a
question?
Christopher: I uh, I think I, I
wish I had a question. I can't.
I can't. I'm working with all
the answers right now, and the I
guess my question would be, I
want to make a difference.
Somehow I feel I can do it with
my writing, with the way that I
write, the things that I write
about, and and it's a big, big
task, and I am wondering, you
know, how do I Oh. Build that.
How do I? How do I keep that
focus in spite of what's going
on around us?
Chris Bache: Yeah, the life of a
writer is a is a different kind
of life, isn't it? It's like
climb the mountain, close the
door, open the windows, but it's
a deep inner focus, and you hold
that focus for a long time. It
took me five years at the
computer to write LSD in the
mind of the universe. It took me
three years just to get myself
in the position of letting
people in as deeply as I was
going to let them in. And then
it took decades, 20 years, just
to gather the experiences which
I put into that book. And so it
is, it's it's a very intense
process, and I'd encourage you
just trust your calling. Trust
your calling. If you feel that
that writing is your calling,
it's your contribution, it's
what you can give. Then buckle
in, take it as far, take it as
deep, bring it as deeply into
forward as possible, and then
share it with world. Throw it
out there, let it go and dump it
attachment to the results. You
do the best you can. You let it
go where it will go. And that's
a great that's, that's a great
gift.
Christopher: Yeah, I set a very
high intention, and the other
part of that is to not be
attached to the outcome. That's
the other part of the intention.
But I don't have a long time to
do this. I'm 83 years old. This
is something that I'm doing
okay, for a legacy for my
family, for one thing, but also
I, I want, I want the world to
understand so many things that
they're missing right now. And,
of course, we just came up with
a huge challenge in this
election, a huge, huge
challenge. So this is my way of
trying to, you know, address all
of that
Chris Bache: pressure cooker is
on, amazing things. Cannot when
the pressure is on, huh?
Christopher: Yes, yeah, it's an
I can do it. I know all of this
is happening around me, but I
can do this, but I gotta let go
of all that other stuff.
Chris Bache: Good luck to you.
Fingers crossed. Looking forward
to seeing what you produce.
Thank you.
Christopher: And I did read your
life, your life, life cycles.
But if I had read this stuff
sooner, my life would have been
totally different. But I don't
know that I would have wanted it
that way, because part of what I
was doing all those 56 and a
half years was it was, it was my
purpose. It was what I had to do
to move on.
Dottie Koontz: Thank you. John,
a so our next question is,
Christopher,
Christopher: there we go. Thank
you, Tony. Tremendous
presentation. Thank you. Thank
you for sharing that. It's, it's
an honor, and I wish I, I wanted
to go on and hear the rest of
your lecture as well. And I
don't know if you still do in
person events or not, but it
would be wonderful. So moving
forward with the with the
question, so as a child, I was
taught that I had seen and
therefore I had debt. Later in
life, I moved on, you know, more
sophisticated I thought, and
then I had karma and again,
debt, right? So here we are
again. Then, you know, the idea
with it, reincarnation and karma
became entwined, right? And it
was the idea that since you have
karma, you know, you have to
reincarnate to keep working on
this Wheel of Karma, this
reincarnation. So I'd be
interested in your thoughts
about is karma really entwined
with reincarnation? Certainly,
you know, for those who have had
the experience of meeting Divine
Presence and source and the
incredible love. You know, life
becomes a an honor. You know,
tremendous honor to be here.
Unknown: So
Janine: is it, you know, is it
acts of honor and giving back,
or is it is reincarnation bound
to karma. Yeah. And the second
part of that being more
recently, I've heard people
saying our karma is being
lessened and going down, and
perhaps we're, you know, if that
theory is correct, that we're
paying that off, and maybe in
the future, we're reincarnating,
because we don't have karma
anymore. Show thoughts
Chris Bache: lot of questions
rolled into those couple of
questions, yes, I think of karma
back. I think karma cause and
effect is just. Part of the
process is the physical universe
has a lot of cause and effects
running. The spiritual,
conscious universe has a lot of
cause and effect coming. But the
question is, how we interpret
that cause and effect pattern?
And I think we've been kind of
interpreting it in too narrow a
way for a long time in the if
you listen to past life therapy,
if you read aloud past life
therapy, you basically could
justifiably come away with
inclusion, that life is
basically about healing, that we
fuck up a lot. We get a lot of
fix up to do, and you could kind
of have a negative perception of
what carries over from the past.
There's so much mess up and so
much cleanup that's needed when,
in fact, I think most people,
they pass their karmic test.
Most of the kids in the school
systems, they graduate, they go
to the next level. Most people
pass their karmic test, and that
means we're bringing into our
next life, not just liabilities.
We're bringing in assets, we're
bringing in skills, we're
bringing in relationships that
have matured. So if you but the
people who don't go to
therapists to celebrate their
victories, they go to therapists
to heal their wounds. So it's
okay. It's perfectly okay, but
we just have to remember there's
a larger pattern here, and so we
have to make sure that the story
which emerges is not just a
story of healing, but a story of
investing in human development
and human growth, challenging
ourselves, Developing arts,
talented knowledge, just the
enriching of the human spirit.
That is certainly the larger
share of what's happening in
reincarnation than simply these
picking over the bones of a
grudge here or grudge there. Now
if you look at religion, I think
there's been a similar kind of
damping down in that the
religions of the last 4000
years, the Axial Age, they
reflected an intensification of
our getting access to spiritual
reality, yoga, meditation, we
were just getting deeper and
deeper first takes in the
spiritual reality. And if you do
have a deep experience of
spiritual reality. How could you
not but think we belong there
more than here? Somehow, there's
been an accident that we got
marooned here. The job is to get
back to there, right? Christ
will come and save me from my
sins. I am stuck in the mud. Get
me back to there. I'll become
enlightened. I'll become
awakened. So when I can awake, I
can go there, because who wants
to be here? When you can go
there? Okay, I understand that.
I feel the compassion in that.
But now that we're beginning to
understand how big here is, how
huge it is, how old it is, that
we measure it in light years, in
distances of 6 million, million
miles a year, in one light year,
and we're measuring billions of
light years across, and it's so
old, it doesn't really make
sense to really say, Oh, yeah.
And after all of this
evolutionary thrust, just after
5000 years, when we began to be
conscious, just as we begin to
sink down into that
consciousness, which we share
with all of life, and we
discover, oh, my God, my life is
one with all of life. Just then
we leave the system, and the
system has served its purpose.
No, I don't think so. At least
what came through in my work,
and I find so many people
affirming it, and that is, it is
about incarnating deeper and
deeper and deeper, not just
patching up our history, but
incarnating the power of spirit,
incarnating Heaven into our
physical bodies, heaven into our
social relationships. It's about
giving birth to this deeper
consciousness inside our
incarnations. I think we're
giving birth so that the ego,
beautiful thing as it is, the
consciousness that holds our
lifetime, is giving birth to the
soul consciousness in the body,
the diamond soul, the whole the
consciousness that holds all of
our lifetimes, not as fragments,
but unified as one, fused in
one. When all of our lifetimes,
all those 1000s of years, come
together and fuse into a
singularity, it gives birth to a
consciousness that is more than
just an enlightened
consciousness. It gives birth to
a magnitude of consciousness
which is different. It's 100,000
year old consciousness, and that
is becoming the new operational
consciousness of humanity.
Society to get there, we have to
let go of all the divisions that
we've invoked, all the racism,
all the political divisions, all
the national divisions, all the
class divisions, all that stuff
which we've kept used to keep
separate from each other. This
has gotta. We gotta sweat that
stuff out of our out of our
pores, we have to sweat it out.
And I don't know how long it's
going to take. I don't know how
many generations, but as it is a
multi generational task, isn't
it? It's a multi generational
task where somewhere along the
way, we go through gradually,
probably a transformation, where
we do something like the
mystics. Do we go through a
death and rebirth? We go through
a complete collapse, a surrender
to forces beyond our control. We
let go of self interest. We
begin to take on, into our
hearts, the needs of other
beings in this crisis where we
will all become refugees at one
way or another, the human heart,
I think, is going to be opened,
purified, touched, and the human
heart that emerges from this
time in History is going to be
massive, beautiful, ecstatic,
enlightened, prophetic, Christ
consciousness, Buddha
consciousness, profit
consciousness, different order
of time. And I think all of us
knew what we were getting into
when we chose to incarnate in
this part of the century. We
chose to be part of it. We chose
to align ourselves with this
silver movement, not just for
our own benefit. It speeds up
our evolution, but it also helps
our children, helps our
grandchildren through this.
We're all in this together. So I
think karma is part of the web
work. But here's another thing,
those when we are privileged to
touch the infinite, the Infinite
is like Ali, Ali, income, free
infant is like infinite joy, no
judgment, infinite capacity to
transform karma and wrap it up
and throw it away. So this, on
the one hand, we learn, we have
to learn. On the other hand, we
can learn and let go much faster
than we think we can. We let go
these old, stupid, narrow
concepts of God which keep us so
imprisoned in our fear and
uncertainty. Let that go. I
think this is an extraordinary,
powerful time. And I do think
you're right. Yeah, I'll tell
you Robert Monroe, his book,
Monroe is the Monroe Institute.
His book four journeys. He was
taken into the future. He thinks
somewhere around mid 3000
something. AD, and in that
future, when he looked up and
saw the Bardo, there was no
Bardo anymore. There were no
souls in the intermediate state.
It was physical reality, purely
open into the Luminosity of
diamond light. And I think what
it teaches us is that the Bardo
our lives that are unresolved,
unfinished, and it's individual,
but also collective. I think we
are processing our former lives.
We're processing our karma.
We're growing up. We're facing
ourselves in history, and when
that happens, we will be much
more transparent to the divine
intelligence, to the Divine
Love, to the Divine information
that can help us. When we have
this kind of access, there'll be
no technical problem that we
can't solve, there'll be no
social problem that we can't
heal, can't solve, right? That's
what I think we're working
towards. So, yeah, thank you.
Thanks for the great question.
Christopher, yeah,
Dottie Koontz: beautiful answer.
So Janine, you're the next
Unknown: questioner. Thank you.
Janine: Thank you so much,
Chris. Let's see. I guess maybe
if I put it on gallery, then I
won't feel strange.
Unknown: Yeah, thank you so
much. I actually like I have so
much in my thoughts right now
that I'm going to try to connect
to them. One is, I said to a
friend who used to not have,
like spiritual, expansive
connections, and then her
husband died. And then, you
know, she had experiences, and
she had sort of judged me
before. From my experiences, and
what popped out of my mouth is
one person's experience is
another person's Woo, yeah,
yeah, you know. And so I think
that's important to me, because
I find myself like not wanting
to prove anything to anybody,
just because I come from a
different world, right, but
simply to experience and share
when that feels appropriate and
wow that last response, one of
the things that reminded me of
was having a soul retrieval at a
time that I was like at the
lowest time in my life and
completely overwhelmed and
really having a hard time
functioning. And in the two day
process. I went from being in
that state to so expansive, so
joyful, so so much ease. And so
when you're talking about where
we're going, you know I I'm
like, I'm not going to assume
that we know how it's going to
go, and it may be very different
for different people, but things
can happen really fast.
Dottie Koontz: So Janine, do you
have a question?
Unknown: Yeah, I guess, I guess
I was saying these things to
hear responses to them. But one
question, yeah, go ahead.
Chris Bache: I think you're very
much right. Soul Retrieval and
what's happening in an
historical situation is very
similar. In soul retrieval, we
retrieve alienated split off
portions of our soul, and to do
that, we have to heal those
portions and integrate them,
welcome them back into the
unity. I think the same thing is
happening in our historical
process, too. We are retrieving
our souls during the whole
period of history when we
thought we were egos and we made
decisions based on our private,
separate existence. Now we have
to retrieve all those pieces of
injured and what we did to other
people so that we can now grow
into a full, manifesting soul.
Yeah, hmm.
Unknown: Other quick question,
and thank you so much.
Appreciate that. I'm curious
whether you've looked at the
work of Nassim Haramein, the
unified field physicist, because
I think there's some alignment,
you know, different worlds, yet
some real connections.
Chris Bache: Sounds like it,
doesn't it mean unified theory.
I'm up for all for unified
theory. But here's the one of
the advantages of being retired
and getting old is I don't have
to keep up with the literature
anymore. So I did. I'm really
behind on, you know, the
literature as such, but the and
you know, Irvin Laszlo work,
Akashic field, field theory,
chaos theory, the work in
fields, yeah, absolutely, yeah.
Fertile Ground.
Unknown: Great. Thank you so
much for all that you're sharing
with us.
Appreciate it. Thank you.
Dottie Koontz: Thank you, Dean,
oops,
Norma: Norma, you're, you're up
next. What's your question? I
don't exactly have a question,
but I'm, I have been studying
myself getting old, and I, I'm
going through a process, and I'm
losing my identity. I'm not who
I was each decade, I'm a
different person, and now I'm
losing my identity, and I
realized I've, I've been an ego,
and my ego was all that identity
and now, and also what you said,
Oh, then I said, where, where do
people? I think I'm headed,
maybe toward peoplelessness,
people and I'm wondering if, oh,
maybe this is a question, yeah,
uh, because what I saw when you
were describing the golden
something is Dust, is dust, and
the possibility that humans as
that I will not be human, but I
will be dust, dust to dust and
dust to dust, or whatever it is.
So that is kind of bringing and
I do appreciate dropping in and
getting. Excited about more
information, so I'll go to the
library and find you.
Chris Bache: Well, you know,
Nora, your experience of getting
lighter and lighter and kind of
disappearing that that speaks to
me. That's my experience, too. I
find that the older I get, and
I'm 75 now, so you may have a
couple years on me, but I'm
right behind you. The thinner my
arms get and the weaker my
skeleton gets, it's like it's
falling off. It gets soft and
it's falling off. And as it
falls off, the memories
associated with get loose and
they can fall off. And I find it
much easier to move into egoless
places than I used to, just
because my my skin is wrapped a
little loose, you know, my mind.
And I think we get older, it
gets easier to step into that in
between place. And that's,
that's, that's just kind of and
it just when, when we get to the
very end, it's a big release,
and we go light to light,
Norma: light. That's, that's
what I'm feeling, too, is I'm
getting lighter. You know,
everything is getting lighter.
And I'm excited about the last
breath. I'm hoping I can be
conscious with my last breath.
Chris Bache: You know, all my
life I've been telling my
children when they're every
little little bit of kids, I
said, it's a great life, and in
the end, you get to die. Death
is something to look forward to.
Death is graduation. Death is
coming home. If there, if there
were one thing I wish I could
give to people, it's give up
your fear of death. If you have
a fear of death, you've got your
entire metaphysics upside down.
Birth is when the hard stuff
begins. You should warn the
child, they're beginning first
grade. Death is graduation.
Death is joy and celebration.
All of our mythology that makes
death hard difficult goes deep,
nonsense. 99.9% of the people,
it's a spontaneous into the arms
of the Divine rushing home. And
so if you're clear, I mean, if
you're really clear on what
birth is and what death is, then
death is something you take into
your heart and celebrate. This
is a life coming to fruition.
You're bringing your soul in
everything you've learned, back
to your core soul. You're
bringing all of your decisions
back to your core soul. And
that's that's like, wow, that's
Paul: graduation. May not be joy
and sorrow. It may not be joy
and sorrow, it may be something
whole,
Chris Bache: yeah, bigger than
that, bigger than joy and
sorrow, yeah, yeah, yeah. Thank
you. You bet. Yeah. Thank you.
Dottie Koontz: Thank you, Norma.
I guess it's my turn, because
Paul here has a question.
Paul: My question was from, as
you've talked about, and you've
talked about the word
reincarnation. Is reincarnation,
from your perspective, strictly
related to humanity on Earth, or
does it serve a different role
or a greater role in the broader
universe?
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah, good
question. And you know in my
writing, you know that my work
really focuses on human
consciousness. And people have
asked me, How come you don't get
really deep into animal
consciousness and plant
consciousness, like a lot of
other shamans and whatnot? And
that's a really good question,
because I know there are fields
of consciousness related to
plant kingdoms and animal
kingdoms, and I think the reason
is because, for me, humanity
represents the greatest threat
to all life on the planet. And
so my work has been really
trying to work with human
consciousness in the belief that
if we can heal humanity, all the
other forms of life will be
safer, will be safe from us.
Interesting. The cultures that
believe in reincarnation, they
all tend to agree on one thing.
It doesn't begin with human
beings. So they all look to
higher mammalian forms, higher
life forms among the animal
kingdoms, as a bridge over into
human consciousness. So there's
a sense of learning, the basics.
So my sense of it is
individuality is the seed kernel
that makes reincarnation
possible. So I don't look at a
field of grass and say, Hmm,
there's 10,000 individuals
there. They all pretty much it's
a collective identity. Somewhere
along the way, these complex
collective identities. To give
birth to more and more
individual awareness, self
awareness. In it my dog, I tend
to think that my dog's pretty
individuated, you know. So
somewhere along the way,
reincarnation begins as a
learning following, a learning
and following, and it begins
before human beings, I think.
But nobody knows exactly where,
and nobody knows exactly how,
but it's just an organic,
natural developmental process
from humans. And I also think
once you come to certain
thresholds, there's not much
point in incarnating at a lower
level. General rule of thumb,
once you can function as a human
being, not much point in
functioning coming back as a
dog, because the you're at a
quantum jump higher now that I
don't want to make it make rigid
rules here, but basically it's
kind of like college. Once you
can do once you can do calculus,
we will not give you a course to
go back and take a course in
algebra, because algebra, assume
calculus, assumes the knowledge
of algebra. You can do it if you
want. But we won't give you
credit for like. It's like that
with, you know, with an
incarnation, we sort of go
through certain developmental
stages, and once you can
function at that stage, then
naturally you want to function
at that stage and higher, that
stage and higher?
Unknown: Yeah.
Dottie Koontz: Thank you. Thank
you. I have one more question
related to that. Is, of all the
books I've read on on
reincarnation and past lives,
I've not seen one where there
was a reincarnation from or to
another planet or star system.
Do you have anything to say
about that?
Chris Bache: Well, I'd say, why
not? I mean, like, once you
understand that the dynamic
principles of evolution are
being are carrying themselves
out, playing themselves out in
other solar systems, in other
galaxies, and you run the
numbers, it's kind of like
there's got to be, there's got
to be intelligent life out
there, and if we can incarnate,
then they can incarnate. And
distance is immaterial. And
there are some people who have
conscious recall of having been
a life form in another planet,
and I can't remember her name,
but there's a woman who does
past life therapy, and this is
her major focus, helping people
who integrate incarnations that
which are aware from another
lifetime. So if you do a little
digging around, and I'm sorry, I
just can't remember her name at
present, so I just say, Sure.
Why not I? I personally don't
have conscious recall of such,
though. I will say I was at a a
spiritual workshop. Met a person
there, one of the teachers
there, and he had recall of he I
and one other person there, in
another planetary system, in
another incarnation. So I'd say,
Okay,
Dottie Koontz: why not great. So
we have time for one last
question. If anyone, unless you
would like to say, have a last
say.
Chris Bache: Chris, well, let me
just maybe drop, draw some
things together, unless great,
clearly, reincarnation is not
doesn't end all your all the
questions to me, reincarnation
just begins a whole rich vein of
questions. It opens up
possibilities because it
relieves us from the terrible
burden of time. Now, when we ask
ourselves, what do we want to
be? What do we want to become?
We should be thinking in terms
of 10,000 year increments, not
100 year increments. Do you want
to become Beethoven? Do you want
to become a Mozart? Do you want
to become a great poet, a great
artist? Now we have unlimited
time. The universe wants us to
develop all the talents that are
latent within this human form.
So and the diamond soul is going
to function at a much, much
higher level of sensory
experience, vision, much more
refined, intense, clarified all
the physical senses. It's not
just an open heart, it's not
just an open mind, but the
entire physical body animated
into higher orders of Self
Realization, the Divine is
shoving together, kind of, I
think of it as green reality,
earth and then light, pure
light, spiritual reality. And
we're just forging more and more
and more and more into each
other until we become green.
Spiritual Beings filled with
light, radiating with light.
It's going to take time, but the
pace is picking up and and I
think when the child is born,
when we succeed in bringing this
new, awakened consciousness,
transform consciousness into the
world, like every mother and
every mother, they will look at
that child, and we will say, it
was worth it. It was worth it to
give birth to this magnificent
being, this Christ Child, this
Buddha awakened child to
humanity, not just here and
there, not just for some special
people here and there, for all
of humanity everywhere. And boy,
don't you know, the women have
to. I think the women are the
key to getting us through this
crisis. Men have had their
chance. We have screwed it up.
We've had our chance women have
to exercise a greater and
greater share of power to
reclaim the power that they've
been denied, to bring it fully
forward, and any man worth his
salt will be so glad when that
happens, because we'll know that
half of us is now showing up
fully, and we are stronger when
we're all together, and that's
basically the message of
reincarnation. We are constantly
growing deeper community, not
just deeper individuals. We're
growing deeper community. We
have blended all the races in
our body. We've blended all the
different cultures, all the
different religions in our body.
They're all here. We are the
living consciousness that
incorporates the future human,
which is transnational, trans
racial, trans religious. We're
just there's so many false
identities which are going to
fall away quickly as we make
this and as we make this
transition. Here's one of the
sweet things my last thought to
share with you, we're going to
find that 99% of the work has
already been done. We are just
waking up. The fetus isn't
gestated in the day of labor.
Labor has been long. Most of the
work has already been done. It's
just the last bit, the last
waking up, the last time around,
opening up and letting this
birth take place. I think if
this is the century, it'll
happen this century. It has to.
We don't have time. Not have
time. Yeah. Thank you very much
for giving it such a big slice
of your day and having this time
for us to spend together.
Really, it's such wonderful
experience to know and hope that
you take the work and take it
out among your friends and share
the book, share the work. It's a
real honor. Thank you.
Dottie Koontz: Thank you, Chris.
That was That was fabulous. I'm
going to put it on gallery view,
and if you want to unmute
yourself and say goodbye to
Chris and everyone else, thank
you all for coming. This has
been fabulous, wonderful. Thank
you.
Jonai: Thank you so much. Thank
you so much. Thank you so much.
Unknown: Thank you, Chris and
thank you. Dottie,
Dottie Koontz: beautiful. Rest
of your day. Yeah, Chris, I have
one
Unknown: question, can you say
your last name?
Chris Bache: Thank you. Thank
you. Bye.