Chris Bache: And eventually you
come out with a certain
understanding, at least, of the
large structure, the nature of
reality. We're not simply
creating a new society or a
better society or a new economy
or a new ecology. We are
actually giving birth to a new
form of the human species. I
never expected anything like
this to emerge in the work. I
didn't know that this was even
possible. At the subtle level of
consciousness, you open up to
different levels of collective
consciousness, and so when your
individual identity pops. I have
had the experience many times of
opening up to my species
identity, to the collective
psyche.
Well, I'm always hesitant to
jump into this, because my
experiences are based upon
shamanic, you know, rigorous use
of LSD. And when everyone hears
LSD, they think, Oh, the 60s.
They think hallucinations. They
think, you know, and this is
very far from this. This is
really within a therapeutic
tradition. It's within Stan Grof
tradition. It's the systematic,
the systematic use of these very
hyper, intense states of
awareness. And when you engage
these states, there is cycles of
tremendous purification,
tremendous death and reborn, and
death and reborn. But if you go
through it often enough, deeply
enough, there is a progressive
initiation into deeper and
deeper levels of reality, and
eventually you come out with a
certain understanding, at least,
of the large structure, the
nature of reality. And it's not
easy to summarize, but I mean,
I've tried to do it in this
book. I'm just finishing
diamonds from heaven to describe
the progression one of the
qualities of that come out of
this vision of cosmology is that
there are many, many levels to
the cosmos. The physical world
is simply kind of like a dense
level. Of course, there are
layers and layers and layers
within the physical world, as we
get into the quantum level, but
as you build out into non
physical or extra physical
dimensions, there are levels,
layers and layers, and it's a
repeated experience that the
lower levels are sourced in the
higher levels, the higher
levels, or The deeper levels,
are more intelligent, more
intense, energetically, and they
are more conscious. So the
experience going out into them
is you're going into a more
conscious, more powerful, more
source dimension of existence,
until eventually, you know, you
leave behind time space. And
then there are dimensions which
echo time space, the bar what
the Tibetans call the Bardo, you
know, the intermediate
dimensions. And one can go
eventually even beyond all the
echoes of time and space, and
enter what some of the spiritual
traditions would call extra
samsaric reality, or reality
beyond all the cycles of death
and rebirth, and enter in the
domain of just pure light, just
just pure light. And the quantum
physicists say everything, all
molecules are ultimately really
rooted in light. You know,
photons are light. And I find
that's true when in the domain
of consciousness and the
universe that one perceives, is
that ultimately all physical
reality is sourced in an ocean
of light, an ocean of radiance.
You can't take your ego into
that reality and have an
experience of that reality. You
can only enter those realities
by surrendering what you were in
the lower realities. And it's
not that these lower realities
are inferior or bad or evil, or
anything like that. It's just
that they are more specific
manifestation of progressively
individualized manifestation of
this larger reality. So that you
reverse the process when you go
out into that reality, you have
to de couple, let go of, you
know, a deeper level, so that
you literally become, for hours
at a time, a citizen of that
level of reality. You have to
stop being Chris Bache. You have
to stop being a human being. You
have to stop being a time space
being at all you literally live
in. Breathe the nature of that
existence. There is a sense
always of profound homecoming,
of profound return. You know
that we came all existence comes
from this reality. So there's
that tremendous sense of of
stillness, calm, reunion, being
restored to your primal
wholeness. And one gets a sense
that these levels are constantly
infusing and informing this
reality. We have a theory of
evolution which our theories of
evolution are partly right and
partly deeply incomplete. We
think it's all happening by
chance, screened by necessity.
You know, it's all but my
experience is it's not being
driven by chance. I mean, chance
has a factor is, but there is a
tremendous intelligence
manifesting itself in the self
emergent quality of time and
space. So there is a there is an
intelligence manifesting. It's
not a god outside manipulating,
and it's not even like creative
design, kind of manipulating,
but it's a self arising
intelligence, a self emerging
intelligence that's manifesting
ever more complex forms of life,
and it's evolving and it's
changing. One of the other
things that comes when you move
into these deep dimensions. You
move beyond linear time as we
conventionally know it, into
deep dimensions of time, and
sometimes even beyond any time,
sense of time whatsoever. But
when you're coming in and out of
these different states, you get
a perspective of that this
reality is changing. We know
this it's changing, but you get
a sense of where it's changing
to what the next phase of human
evolution might be, where we
seem to be going, and we're
going somewhere, and there is an
intelligence expressing itself
in this process. And so the end
result, there's a sense in which
I trust you just learn to trust
where you are, that there isn't
a wisdom in where you are doing
what you're doing, and somehow
each one of our works contribute
to the larger pattern of the
creative intelligence
manifesting itself inside time
and space. I was totally,
completely surprised. I never
expected anything like this to
emerge in the work. I didn't
know that this was even
possible. I had never seen it
addressed in the psychedelic
literature. But when you, when
you pop, the ball, the bubble of
the ego, when when you pop, you
don't simply Drip, drop into
unit of consciousness, or
ONENESS consciousness. But you
open up into different at the
subtle level of consciousness.
You open up to different levels
of collective consciousness. And
so when your individual identity
pops you, I have had the
experience many times of opening
up to my species identity,
opening up to the collective
psyche, to and I found that that
species consciousness is
coherent. Carl Jung was right,
and there is a coherent species
mind. And as the shamanic
traditions that when you touch
the species mind in deep states
of consciousness, it's only
natural, but insights into what
the evolutionary progression of
the growth process of this
species is, and I over many
years, I had repeated
experiences doing taking me
deeper and deeper, and teaching
me there was a consciousness,
teaching me what's what, what's
happening, and showing me that
the visions that came just
report, the visions for whatever
was that humanity was coming
into a time of tremendous
fruition that we had been
developing for hundreds of 1000s
of years, and we were coming to
a pinnacle, a tremendous, great
Awakening, an opening of a new
level of consciousness in
humanity, and that this was a
pivot point. Everything we had
accomplished would kind of
quickly become passe as we
pivoted into this new platform
of consciousness. But for there
to be a great awakening, the
birth of a new consciousness.
There must first take place a
great death. As the mystics go
through a dark night of the soul
to awaken into divine
consciousness, humanity was
going to have to go through a
great, dark night of the soul,
of our collective soul, in order
to purge, purge. Change the
karmic residue of all of its
egoic driven competitions,
hostility, violence, the things
we do to each other, the things
we can't take that this world we
live in is a world built by ego.
We are moving into a larger
reality, and we have to, we have
to let go of all those old
restrictive poisons. And I think
we're coming into a time of
great crisis. The visions show
me that we're coming into a dark
night of purification. I don't
know the details of it. I just
have experienced it. I think
it's going to be starting in the
21st Century. I don't know how
long it will last. I don't know
how long we'll go through, but
it's a time of loss of control,
of breaking down, of
destructuring, of life as we
know it.
But coming out of it, we're not
simply creating a new society or
a better society, or a new
economy or a new ecology, we are
actually giving birth to a new
form of the human species. We're
we're the fundamental
architecture of the collective
psyche is pivoting, and as it
pivots, we will. We are giving
birth to a new blueprint for
humanity. And the way I've seen
it manifesting is in in the
visions and in my psychedelic
experience and other
experiences, reincarnation is
just accepted, as a matter of
fact. So we die, we going we're
born. We die, we're born. Keeps
going up, keep going on, and
lifetime by lifetime, we rewind.
We're collecting more and more
experiences. And in my sessions,
that reached a point where I was
reintegrating all my former
lives were coming together like
winding kite string around a
spool, and it hit a critical
mass, and it exploded into the
most brilliant, luminous diamond
light in my heart. It just
exploded in me. And I think what
I saw in this experience, what I
was being shown, was where
reincarnation is taking us.
We're not just going through
class from the first grade to
the second grade to the third
grade. We're not simply adding
incremental improvements in our
life, but sooner or later, we
come to a fusion point where all
of our souls, all of our lives,
all of our experiences, hit a
critical mass and are fused. And
when that happens, the soul
awakens inside the human body.
When we die, we return to the
soul, the mega consciousness
that holds us all. But this is
an awakening of the soul inside
time and space, and I think
that's the future human that
we're birthing. We've been
gestating this consciousness for
hundreds of 1000s of years.
We're giving birth to it now,
but most of the work has been
done. Most of the work has been
done in history, but now it's
time for all of this inner
development to manifest. And I
think when we awaken as souls,
when we when our deep
consciousness awakens, it will
change life on our planet,
because it will make our mind
safe, because our heart will be
open, and we will no longer
represent a danger to each other
and to other species on the
planet, and there'll be a much
easier communion with the deeper
creative consciousness of the
universe, so that a period a
time of tremendous creativity,
acceleration of creativity. And
in my very end of this long 20
year journey, the very last
sessions, I was put through a
tremendous strip down process
and thrown deep into the future,
I don't know how far, but deep
into the future, and allowed to
experience it felt like I tried.
I was allowed to try on that
form and the most beautiful,
beautiful being, just
extraordinary being. And it's
really important for us to
understand that we are giving
birth to something magnificent,
because if we don't have a
vision of what's happening in
history, we will get swallowed
by the pain of the purification
that's coming. And we must hold
firm. We must stand firm and not
get, not yield to despair. A
mother giving birth is in
terrible pain, but she knows
what she's doing. We are giving
birth. We have to understand
what we're doing. I mean, we
have a tendency. In our
theologies and in our stories
that we tell to explain our
existence, to think very
statically of human nature,
because it doesn't seem to be
changing too fast. So we think
of static human nature, static
human nature. But when you when
you expand the horizon, even
intellectually or with
imagination or experientially,
when you expand the time
horizon, at least, what I was
given to experience was that
humanity is built for speed, and
it has to do with each of our
learning cycles, or 100 years,
100 years, 100 years, 100 years.
But the universe does not think
in 100 year increments. The
Universe thinks in billions and
trillions of your increments.
And from that perspective,
humanity, it seems to be
designed for accelerated
evolution. So that, you know, in
the long scale, we're moving
very fast through time, so all
of our history, all of our all
the pains we've done, the
mistakes we've made, the things
we've done, we're carrying them
in our person, but we can shed
them if our concentration, if
our awareness is intensified, as
I think, they will be
intensified in the trials that
are coming. If we pay attention
and do our work well and live
very deeply, we can shed that
past very quickly. And as we
shed that past, we can enact the
soul in history. He had that. He
tells his story in four journeys
of being taken into the not
great distant future. He later
said it was about 1000 years out
where, when he was taken into
that future and looked back that
all of the Bardo was empty, all
of the all the souls in the
Bardo were emptied. And there
was a much cleaner and clearer
communion between physical
beings and consciousness,
spiritual consciousness. And
there was a it was easier to
kind of do a temporary visit, to
kind of come into share a
physical life form, leave it
alone, come back into spiritual
reality. And I think that's kind
of simple. That's another way of
describing what we're going to
because the Bardo is this
layered reality surrounding time
and space, where it's filled
with soul fragments,
unintegrated pieces of
experiences at different levels.
And as we become more
integrated, as we become more
coherent, we're emptying the
Bardo. And as we empty the
Bardo, the communion between
deep spiritual reality and
physical reality becomes easier,
becomes clearer. We've seen it
happen for individuals. There
are great saints who are
translucent to this reality, but
I think they are foreshadowing
what's happening for the whole
species, and we're going into
that direction as an entire
species. I think we have an
extraordinary future ahead. We
have to, we have to some hard
work. But underneath, yeah, and,
you know, the thing that has
come through my sessions is that
the Divine is very happy with us
and everything that everything
is right on time. I mean, we
have we make so many mistakes,
we do so many things badly. But
in the long view, the sense I
get is that we're working hard
and we're doing a pretty good
job, and it's going to be more
hard work, but overall, the
Divine is very pleased. And
again, I hate to use the word
the divine, but the creative
consciousness of the universe is
very happy with what's
happening.
Unknown: Space, oh,
Sarah clay,
you.