Unknown: ANNOUNCER.
Welcome to what is going on for
new thought from the edge of ohm
each week on ohm times, flagship
radio show, veteran broadcaster,
author and media consultant
Sandy sedgbeer conducts thought
provoking interviews with
inspirational authors, artists,
musicians, scientists, speakers
and filmmakers who are working
at the point where spirituality
and science meet consciousness
at the very edge of OM here is
your host, Sandy sedgbeer,
Sandy Sedgbeer: hello and
welcome. Today, we're going to
be talking about life after
death, Heaven and Hell and
reincarnation. Christopher Bache
is professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, adjunct
faculty at the California
Institute of integral studies,
Emeritus fellow at the Institute
of Noetic Sciences, and he's on
the Advisory Council of Grof
legacy training, an award
winning teacher and
international speaker. He is the
author of four books, including
one that I rate as one of my
favorite of all time, LSD and
the mind of the universe,
diamonds from heaven, which
chronicles his 20 year
psychedelic journey exploring
consciousness. And the other
book which we're going to be
discussing today is life cycles,
reincarnation and the web of
life, which combines scientist
testimonies about reincarnation
with the synthesis of findings
from consciousness research and
near death studies. Christopher
Bache, welcome back to the show.
Chris Bache: Hi Sandy. It's a
pleasure to be with you today.
Sandy Sedgbeer: You too. So life
cycles has been hailed as the
first book to both describe the
dynamics of rebirth and explore
the ramifications of adopting a
reincarnationist perspective.
Now, this was published, what,
Chris Bache: years ago? There
abouts Yeah, so that
Sandy Sedgbeer: was right after
you had started your journey
with LSD. How many years into
that journey, and how did that
journey inspire this?
Chris Bache: Well, I started my
psychedelic work the after one
year, my first year of being an
academic, and I worked for four
years, and then I stopped for
six years, and during that six
year interval, I did three years
of past life therapy, uncovering
and working with my own former
lives, and I wrote life cycles.
So my psychedelic work, by that
time, had reached deeply enough
that I had been given many
personal insights into karma,
the deeper cause and effect that
underlies our lives. But at that
time, I had not had personal
experiences of my former lives
in a psychedelic context. I had
in a hypnotherapy context, but
not a psychedelic context, but
it really was my study of Ian
Stevenson and then later, other
pioneers in the research
documenting children and adults
with validated, verified past
lives, memories that really
became the foundation for my
work and life cycles. Yeah.
Sandy Sedgbeer: I mean, you
shared a few of those stories,
which I have, you know, read
before, and they're absolutely
fascinating, because the whole
circumstance is there's just so
much evidence there that, you
know, you really can't question
it. One of them that really
interested me was the child who
you mentioned, Dr Helen Wambach,
who had a patient, a five year
old girl who rejected human
contact and withdrew into
childhood autism, but somehow
she demonstrated mathematical
and reading skills which she had
not been taught, but she would
not communicate. But then, over
the period of their work
together, she showed Dr Wambach
that how she felt, what she was
feeling by force feeding her
with, you know, a baby bottle,
because she felt totally,
totally, you know, like she was
being treated like a helpless
infant, yeah, and when and when
the doctor, you know, understood
that, then the child started
coming into herself, yeah, but
she lost the reading and she
lost the mathematics. I mean,
stories like that are just, you
know, what do you make of them?
Chris Bache: Well, what I make
of. Them is that life is much
long, our lives, our personal
lives, let's say our individual
lives are much longer than we
presently. Tend to think that
they are and that they're always
beginning and starting, and
there are overlaps. And once you
understand the larger life of
the soul, then this kind of
continuity of qualities,
knowledge, learning, attitudes,
traumas, of virtues that are
kind of blending from one life
into the start of another life,
where we pick up and continue to
the learning. I'm making it over
simple, overly linear and overly
simple, but that basic idea that
there is a blending, we don't
start our lives a tabula rasa.
We don't start our lives blank.
We start our lives with a
history which is a specific
history, which we can see very
clearly when we begin to look at
children with fresh eyes.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Why is it the
last? It's always the last life,
you know that they seem to talk
Chris Bache: about? Well, it's
not always the left last life.
Actually, in the literature,
Stevenson's research focuses on
children who have an active
recall of their most immediate
former life, their last life.
But remember, the Stevenson's
research is addressing a very
unusual population, children who
have spontaneous memories of
their former lives. Most people
do not have spontaneous memories
of their farmer lives. His
children are reincarnating very
quickly compared to the
population at large, only an
average of two and a half years
and very close to their life
circumstance of their previous
life, 50 years. Studies which
look at larger people, larger
populations of people who don't
have spontaneous recall,
indicate a longer time frame
between lifetimes and a much
broader geographical radius. So
it's, it's, so it's, it's, that
is a little bit of a distortion
from the research protocol. When
we look at therapy, people come
to the therapeutic literature.
People come to therapy because
of pain, and sometimes this pain
is grounded in something that
happened to them in their recent
past, their recent incarnational
past, but not always. Sometimes
it comes from several lifetimes
before. So the way I think of it
is our former lives are like a
deck of playing cards. We may
have had 52 lives, but only a
handful of those cards are
active in this present life, and
those, let's say five cards,
come from different centuries
and only weave together certain
elements of those five lives
into the composite that makes up
the present life. So when we,
when we kind of develop a more
textured understanding. We begin
to understand that it's not a
linear development from life to
lifetime, is that we go back to
the soul. The soul holds all of
our former lives, and then the
soul decides which of those
former lives in which
combination it's going to
incarnate into as the next
incarnation.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Yeah, you
mentioned the word soul. But in
the book you make, you know,
distinction between soul and
over soul, yeah. So what is the
difference?
Chris Bache: Well, and then at
the end of the book, I dissolve
that distinction. But the soul,
the distinction is that for
Westerners who are accustomed to
thinking of the soul as the
spiritual essence of this
present lifetime, we need a
larger concept of soul to
include all of our former
lifetimes. And for that, I use
the concept of the oversoul,
borrowing that term from other
other people at the end, in the
end of the book, I say it gets
increasingly cumbersome to
maintain this division. And for
me, the word the soul and I
usually differentiate it by
capital S. Soul with a capital S
is what I mean by the oversoul,
the consciousness that holds all
of our lifetimes. Soul with the
small s is the consciousness
that's integrating all my
experiences in this incarnation.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So the over soul
is what some people would call
the higher self, the part of
them that you know continues
forever.
Chris Bache: Yes, I think so.
Yeah,
Sandy Sedgbeer: so I was doing
some research today, and I came
across this article on
psychology today by Dr Alex
lickerman, who is a Buddhist,
but he doesn't believe in
reincarnation, but he said that
the real. Question at the heart
of reincarnation is not one of
evidence, but one of identity.
Chris Bache: Yeah, good point. I
haven't read that article. I'd
be interested in seeing what he
says. Yeah, I think once you
move into a reincarnational
worldview, the concept of
identity, shifts and expands
because I accept this body and
my personality as my current
identity. And you know, if I
have deep, mystical experiences
of oneness with the universe,
that I would accept a universal
cosmic principle as my deeper
identity. The concept of the
soul is kind of intermediate
position, isn't it? Because it's
on the one hand, it's
individual, it's an IT, because
my soul and your soul are
different in that they reflect
different histories and they
have an individuated quality.
But if you ask the question,
what is the essence of the soul?
What is the essence of that
spiritual identity? Then it
comes back down to the same
mystical insights. The essence
of one is the essence of all.
The essence is the essence of
the Divine. Some would say of
the cosmic intelligence, the
cosmic principle. But it is the
question of identities is really
quite critical. Shifting into a
reincarnation worldview doesn't
undermine the value or the
integrity of this identity, but
it recontextualizes that
identity within the soul's
identity, which is the meta
consciousness, which holds the
100,000 years, say, of identity,
of all of our lifetime
experiences.
Sandy Sedgbeer: It's, you know,
it's very hard to believe that
you have a different identity,
that you are not, you know, this
thing that you've lived with for
so many years, it's even harder
to think that actually, you know
the over soul, or that essence
of you is infinite. It's lived
forever and it will live
forever. I mean, that's a hard
one to get your head around.
Chris Bache: Well, it's hard in
the beginning, but it gets
easier with practice, both
intellectual practice, but
particularly with experiential
practice and experiential
access. It's one thing to be
intellectually convinced by the
evidence that reincarnation is a
principle operating in life, and
then when you begin to look at
life through that lens, a lot of
things begin to make sense which
didn't make sense before, and
that deepens one sense of
opening to that. But when you
actually sort of turn within and
follow your awareness deeper
within your own consciousness,
so deep that eventually it taps
into levels of your own self
awareness which predates your
physical body, and you learn the
stories of that self awareness
that come from another life, and
those experiences of that former
life have a distinct quality of
being you while being other than
you, but you know that they are
you. And if you encounter
several such lives and you
dialog with them and you work
with them, then it kind of has
causes a dilation within your
not only in your thinking, but
within your heart that it
becomes easier to accept this
transcendent, though
individuated, but transcendent
dimension to your identity. It
just and eventually it becomes
it hard to think smaller than
that, it actually becomes hard
to take this as your only
identity that just
Sandy Sedgbeer: I'm going to ask
you some questions, some of the
most common questions that come
up with this subject. And you
know, the first one is, why do
we reincarnate?
Chris Bache: Well, to learn, to
grow, to become more than we
are. And that really kind of
gets down to the very basic
question, what is the purpose of
existence? If we think we don't
reincarnate, if we only live one
lifetime, then if there is a
purpose to existence, it must be
something that can be realized
within however many years we
have in one lifetime, but if we
live an open ended number of
lives, then it invites us to
expand our understanding of what
the universe is doing in us,
with us, with all that time. And
so it opens up an open ended
development. Possibility we now
have an understanding of the
universe's time frame for the
creation of galaxies and planets
and systems and so on, but we've
been excluded from that because
we haven't had a sufficiently
expansive understanding of
ourselves. Reincarnation invites
us to open up into an expansive
understanding of our individual
participation in the cosmic
unfolding. And so we have all
these lives in order to learn
more, to become more, to
actualize more. And it's not
simply a matter of becoming
enlightened, though that's a
noble gold unto itself. It's
enlightenment. Is simply a stage
on in an evolutionary
progression which extends far
beyond enlightenment. I mean, if
you just think ahead, what will
what could we become if we had a
million years more or billion
years more.
Sandy Sedgbeer: I only have a
problem with this because if we
are sparks of God, yeah, if we
know everything, when we leave,
and many people say, suddenly
they understand everything, and
you know, they're in a whole
other kind of it, you know,
their awareness is so expanded.
Why do we need to learn more?
How much more is there to learn?
Aren't we complete when we're
there, but then we actually, you
know, kind of regress when we
come here. And I don't
understand the point of that
Chris Bache: well, that would be
like asking to a real good
question, when the infinite
before creation, before
manifesting the physical
universe, why would the creative
principle manifest the physical
universe, which almost is
inherently less self aware, less
knowledgeable? And I think it's
not so much we do expand our
knowledge much, much more when
we are when we die. Whether it
it seems like it is infinite
knowledge, maybe it is, but
maybe there's even more than
what we think of as infinite
knowledge. But the real question
becomes, if God were to come to
us and say, Would you help me
grow this universe? Would you
bring as much knowledge as you
can into your person and help me
grow this universe into a higher
form of physical manifestation
of our spiritual nature? So it's
not simply what happens to us
when we die? I think we get a
glimpse, we expand, we get a
contact. The question is, who
would turn down the invitation
to actually participate in a
creative process which will
produce higher and higher and
higher, deeper and deeper and
deeper forms of humanity, in
evolution, in history, so that
truly we will eventually be able
to make heaven on earth. We
won't simply be imprisoned and
dumb and stupid when we
incarnate. We will be
enlightened. We will be
infinitely aware in our physical
incarnation. I think this is the
trajectory that we're on. So
it's becoming more and more and
participating in the dance of
creation.
Sandy Sedgbeer: You know, I can,
I can follow that some of the
way I, you know, yeah, I'd be
there saying, Yeah, I'll
participate. But the fact is,
you know, to then come here and
forget everything, and to really
be living like you're starting
all over again, you know, all
the knowledge, all the wisdom
that you've gathered over all of
those years. What happens to it?
Chris Bache: But we don't forget
everything, do we? Because we we
we may lose a fair amount of our
conscious recall, but what we
have known is built into our
unconscious recall, just like
these children, who may not
remember how they acquired that
mathematical knowledge or other
kinds of knowledge, but it's
there we not may not remember
how we develop the capacities
that are now natural to us, but
there is a history behind
everything that we are. So we
don't really forget it all. We
just forget some of it, but we
bring a lot of it into our very
being, and then we we express
that knowledge in our life and
we develop so that by the time
we finish, we have become more
we have incarnated more
completely some of that
knowledge than we were at the
beginning of our lifetime.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So many you
know, we've all seen media.
Teams who bring loved ones, you
know, how is it that if somebody
has passed over and they're
either in the Bardo or they're
reincarnated, or they've, you
know, they're doing whatever
they're doing, how is it that
they come back? You know, they
can reconnect to that identity
in that moment, to give that,
you know, yeah, believed loved
one, whatever message they need.
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, now
we're getting into the nuts and
bolts of the soul. It's a good
question, and I'm going to give
a short answer to a long, a long
question. Um, uh, this is an
ideal scenario, but a not
uncommon scenario. I think, when
we die, we return to the soul,
and after a transitional period
where we evaluate our current,
la past life, and we evaluate
what went right, what went
wrong, and we assimilate that
learning, we return to the soul,
and we begin to naturally
exchange what we might think of
as our small identity for our
large identity, our 100 Year
identity for 100,000 year
identity, so that Chris Bache no
longer lives Just as Chris
Bache, but is restored to the
total knowledge of my soul. Now
let's say my father died when I
was 18. Okay, so when I die, I
may want to see my dad, and if I
want, if I get the opportunity
to see my dad, whether or not
his soul has incarnated an
aspect of him in a subsequent
incarnation. I think it works
something like this, when my
being wants to meet my dad, his
soul comes to me, but
manifesting the front image of
that soul would be the being
that I had known him as, which
would be my father. So Chris
Bache would meet his father, but
soon, before too long, it would
it would be a matter of soul to
soul. So Chris Bache his soul
would be meeting my father's
soul, and we would be having a
much deeper conversation than
simply Chris Bache speaking to
his father. Now we're having a
cosmic conversation. Now I think
the mediums can contact people
who are discarded, but that we
should be careful before we
infer that the form in which the
medium encounters them is the
form in which they are truly
existing in their post death
state. I think a lot of our
fascination and compulsion, even
to communicate with those who
have died in the form in which
we knew them, reflects a limited
understanding of what happens to
us when we die, and it tends to
reflect a Western understanding
that when we die, we are judged,
and we go to heaven or hell or
purgatory or some level of the
Bardo. And it's a pretty short
term concept I am not
particularly interested in
communicating to my father as I
knew him, when there's so much
more could take place in our
exchange.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So in a sense,
you know, the the soul of the
person that comes through for
somebody is, in a way, doing
something with compassion, and
they're just stepping into,
Chris Bache: yeah, they're
wearing the wearing the
compassion, the presence of that
that this person had known them
as, and communicating to that
person through that persona. But
that persona isn't necessarily
who they truly are now.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Yeah, another
common question is, until I read
this book, I didn't know how to
answer it is, well, how, you
know, how can there be
reincarnation? There's far more
people on the planet now than
there were, you know, 1000 years
ago, yeah, yeah.
Chris Bache: Well, you know,
I'll answer with an analogy.
Start there. If you were at a
university, and the university
had 6000 students, and you never
left campus. You lived on
campus, and there was a rhythm.
Every semester there were fewer
people, they went home, and then
every semester they came back.
But over a few years, you would
notice that the population of
the campus is getting bigger.
And you might wonder where all
these extra people coming from?
But of course, they're coming
from a town outside of campus,
which is a much, much larger
town than the number of people
on campus. And I think it's like
that in the. Three incarnation,
we have no reason for believing
that the number of souls
available to incarnate is
finite, or that it's small and
that all of them were present at
some early point in Earth's
evolutionary history, and
therefore we have to explain
where all the extra souls are
coming from. Perhaps there are
billions of souls in line
waiting to take up positions as
positions become available in
the earth school. We have no
reason for believing that the
number of souls is finite, or
that they were all present on
earth in the beginning. So we
just have to, well, the
invitation here is to open up to
understanding that the spiritual
universe is many, many times
larger than the physical
universe. Robert Monroe is
working out of body work in the
Monroe Institute emphasizes over
and over the physical universe
is a small slice of reality.
Most of reality is spiritual,
Sandy Sedgbeer: but wasn't it?
Robert Monroe, who also said
that some humans involved
evolved from higher animals.
Chris Bache: Yeah, actually,
that's the that is the common
view of most reincarnation
societies. That is, if we look,
if we follow the line back and
ask, where does reincarnation
begin, they generally think that
it doesn't begin with human
consciousness. It begins farther
back in our animal pedigree. So
reincarnation seems to be a
dynamic that is correlated with
the birth of individuality
grass. Hard to see grass as
individual, but sooner or later,
we have individuated
consciousness emerging within
the animal kingdom.
Reincarnation seems to be a
function of that individuated
consciousness, exploring and
empowering and expanding itself,
and that starts before human
beings.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Now we're
actually getting, I think it's
Dr Linda Brackman, who does past
life regression, who was trained
with Michael Newton, and he told
her that the time would come
when many people's the lives
they accessed were not lived on
this planet. And that's actually
happening. She said, I mean, her
books are full of stories of,
you know, people's experiences
that they connect with previous
life somewhere else entirely.
Chris Bache: Well, we'd have to
ask, at least on a theoretical
level, why not if we just look
up at the universe and look
through the Hubble telescope and
all wonderful images that are
coming to us, and we see life
burgeoning and stars and
planets, why shouldn't there be
evolved life on those forms? And
if reincarnation is possible,
then why should it be only be
restricted to one star system?
Why might not there be some type
of interplanetary crossovers? I
don't have any personal
experience of that myself, but I
know that she does, and so I
think, well, that's interesting.
Sandy Sedgbeer: It is
interesting. It is. We're going
to take a short break now.
You're listening to what is
going on. I'm Sandy sedgby, and
my guest today is professor
emeritus in the Department of
Philosophy and Religious Studies
at young town State University,
and I won't read the rest of
what you do other than you're an
international speaker, a teacher
and an author, Christopher
Bache, and we're discussing the
compelling research and the
tantalizing questions raised in
his book, life cycles,
reincarnation and the web of
life still to come. What happens
to those identities that we once
thought were us. Why was
reincarnation removed from the
scriptures? Why is our time
between lives as important to
our development as our earthly
phase and more? Stay tuned.
Unknown: Times TV.
Sandy Sedgbeer: I Hello. I'm
Sandy sedgbeer, host of modern
times flagship radio show what
is going on, and as an author,
editor and 13 times book judge
who's read 1000s of books and
interviewed hundreds of authors,
I'm constantly asked what's
really worth reading and what's
not so, I created the no BS
spiritual book club to help you
save time and money by picking
the brains of discerning names
who have walked this path before
you. There's no catch, no fees
and no BS, just an ever growing
library of 10 Best spiritual
book lists from some of your
favorite authors and teachers,
Pastor. E book excerpts, audios
and video interviews with people
like Don Miguel, Ruiz Jr, David
G, Lee Harris, Mark Nepo and Mon
from well known classics to
hidden gems you've never heard
of. It's the only no BS guide to
the best spiritual books to
enlighten your journey of self
discovery. So why not join the
Club? Get inspired and save
money at the no BS spiritual
book club.com
Unknown: imagine becoming a
super influencer, reinvent
yourself, invest in your brand
and then manifest your success
with a robust spheric approach.
Own times media and broadcasting
offers a unique and multi
faceted way to become the
spiritual and conscious
influencer you deserve to be by
putting your message across our
powerful platform with its
proven record of integrity and
excellence, through our produced
shows own times, offers the
opportunity to become a Social
media TV personality, a radio
show host, an OM Times magazine
columnist and a syndicated
podcaster all in one shot by
live streaming your show on
omtimes TV and broadcasting it
across the extensive ohm times
radio and TV networks, you
become more than a host. You
become an ambassador and a force
for positive change own times.
Open yourself to the
possibilities.
Everything that we do, we can do
in a contemplative manner.
Through the art of
contemplation, you can use the
gene keys in a really powerful
way. Gene keys is basically the
Code Book of Life in the gene
keys, the book is made up of
these three levels, shadows,
gifts and cities. And the
journey is from is through those
three levels, kind of unpicking
of the shadow states, the
releasing of the gifts and then
the embodying of this higher
consciousness called the city.
And the cities are very exalted
words, and it's not like we kind
of suddenly are all these
exalted Christ like beings, but
we have flashes and
illuminations along the journey,
and the more we get stuck into
the journey, the more
illumination comes to us,
because the more we're releasing
the light from in these codes
inside our DNA. So all those
revelations are inside us. So
the contemplative way is the
inner way.
There are 16 million children
struggling with hunger in
America. That's one in five
daughters, sons, neighbors and
classmates who don't know where
their next meal is coming from,
yet, billions of pounds of good
food go to waste every year.
It's time we do something about
it. Feeding America is a
nationwide network of food banks
that helps provide meals to
millions of kids and families in
need. Visit feedingamerica.org
to help them feed even more
together, we can solve hunger
together. We're Feeding America.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Welcome back.
Christopher Bache, so I'm rather
attached to this, you know,
person, personality, the thought
that it might disappear at some
point, you know, like an actor
just shedding a role that
they've played, take off the
costume and never to be seen or
heard from again, you know,
Chris Bache: never to be heard
and seen from again.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Well, in that
form, oh, in that form, well, in
that form, you know, it's, I
don't like that idea. I mean,
I'd like to know that, you know,
maybe I could connect with her
sometime. Maybe I could even
bring her back, yeah, and be
that character again. Do you
think any of that is possible?
Chris Bache: Well, I think the
the the essence and the system
of our lives is preserved
beautifully intact when we die,
we take with us not only all of
our memories, but we take with
us a living and vivid version of
the experiences that we had on
Earth in Technicolor and stereo
as the near death episode
experiences have shown us when
they have when they relive their
life, they relive it in much,
much more detail than they were
ever remember having it in the
first place. So not only do we
continue perfectly intact, but
we continue in this super
saturated version of ourselves.
And all of that is taken
forward, all of that is brought
into the soul. And the soul can
crystallize its larger
consciousness in any of its
forms, or it can actualize all
of their integrated
consciousness into a singular,
integrated form, and in the end,
a. I'm only willing to give
this, this 100 years, if that
you know, it's just, it's just
too limited. I mean, why ride a
bicycle when you can have a
spaceship? Just, it's so much.
So there's no sense of
sacrifice. I think there's,
there's a sense maybe, of
trading up.
Sandy Sedgbeer: You know,
sometimes I think that I'm, I'm
not very um, elevated in my
consciousness, you know. And if
I have been alive for millennia,
then I'm really not doing a very
good job, you know, after all of
that time, that I'd be further
on. You know, I tend to look at
things like people or beings,
like spirit guides and angels
and ascended masters as they
were once, you know, just as
human as me, enjoyed a human
life, perhaps, and have reached
such an elevated state. I mean,
is it conceivable that I could
be one of them one day?
Chris Bache: Well, yes, of
course, it's conceivable,
because your essential nature
already is one of those beings.
But let me just kind of flip
this a little bit at first. I
just, I've been teaching this
stuff for years, and I had just
generations and generations of
students come through my
courses. And one of the things
I've learned is you can't judge
you can't read a book by looking
at the cover. You can't judge a
person's soul development by
looking at what they're dealing
with. And it's kind of like at a
university, somebody can have
developed a great deal of
expertise in music, for example,
but then they decide to start
developing an expertise in their
art. And so they let go of their
expertise in music in order to
start a whole new course regimen
in art. And if you were to look
at only what they do in art, you
might think, oh, this person is
a freshman, when really they're
very sophisticated senior with
all these other skills. And I
think it's also that way for the
soul too. So I mean, I mean,
look at what you do. You're an
enormous influencer. You're
you're hosting one spiritual
dialog after another. You you're
touching 1000s and 1000s of
people's lives. What, how could
your soul, if your soul were in
the Bardo, say, in a pre
incarnated state, and you were
given the opportunity to bring
down some sense of what, you
know, some aspiration, some
capacity and enthusiasm for
exploring spiritual knowledge,
but not by yourself in a
monastic context, but in a
platform that reaches out into
the world at a time in history
when the world needs this type
of knowledge. So my basic sense
is, Don't sell yourself short. I
mean, I think there are many
more Bodhisattvas in the world
than we think.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Um, yeah, I'm
sure you're right. Okay, so
another question, white light,
several spiritual teachers are
of the opinion that we should
not go towards the light, as we
will be trapped in cycles of
reincarnation. They say, they
say you can bypass that and go
somewhere else. What do you
think of that one?
Chris Bache: Well, it doesn't
make any sense to me. It doesn't
compute for me. To me, the white
light, just at a simple level,
when we separate from our body,
the white light is our homing
beacon, taking us back home,
taking us back to the our
essential nature, our deeper
spirit, our deeper divine
nature. Now the basic classic
idea is people instinctively
move towards the light, and they
move as far towards the light as
they feel comfortable, and at
some point to one along the way,
for various reasons, people feel
less comfortable, or they feel
sort of it's more natural just
to stop and drop a drop off, and
that that they're at that level
of spiritual development, that
they feel most comfortable in
the 1000s and 1000s of levels of
the Bardo and so the the
admission, the admonition for
and from that level they will
eventually go through a process
in which they will make the
choice to incarnate again, the
admit, admonition in Most
spiritual traditions is to do a
kind of training that allows you
to be comfortable with the
light, so that you can follow
the light all the way home, all
the way through all the levels
of the Bardo, all the way to the
most intense form of that light,
which resides within what the
Buddhists call Extra. Samsara
reality, so a reality which is
outside the entire reincarnating
universe altogether. So to me,
whether our journey into the
light takes us back to our own
natural level of peak spiritual
realization, or whether it takes
us all the way back beyond all
those intermediate levels to the
highest level. It doesn't make
any much difference to me. It
makes most sense to follow the
light all the way as far as you
can.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Yeah. Well,
you've seen that, haven't you?
Chris Bache: I have, and it
touched me in a way that has
affected the entire rest of my
life.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Yeah, so why was
reincarnation taken out of
Christianity? I mean, for the
first 500 years of Christianity,
it was a vital commitment, and
then Justin Ian removed it.
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, that's
a complex story. And that I was
first an historian of early
Christianity, that was my first
academic love in the search for
the historical Jesus. Was my
first I did my masters at
Cambridge in the search for the
historical Jesus, and it's it's
a complex process, and I don't
think the definitive story has
yet been written. Did Jesus
teach reincarnation? It
certainly is present in some of
the Gnostic Gospels. But do
those Gnostic Gospels reflect
the actual teaching of the
historical Jesus, and if Jesus
did teach reincarnation, then we
have to explain why it was
filtered out. Or if he did teach
reincarnation, why isn't it more
thoroughly saturating the
earliest level of the scriptural
tradition. However we answer
those, and we don't have the
time to answer those today, it
clearly is the case that there
were multiple variations of
Christianity in the early
centuries, and some of those
variations taught reincarnation,
and they also taught the
empowerment of women, that women
should have clerical capacities
and responsibilities, so on, so
forth. And both of those
elements were filtered out of
the tradition. It is Geddes
McGregor, who is a Christian.
Was Christian theologian. Wrote
numerous books on early
Christian thought around
reincarnation. He was of, he's
of the opinion that there is
nothing inherently contradictory
to the belief in reincarnation
and the teachings of the
essential Jesus, kind of the or
early, early core teachings of
Jesus. But it it gives an
individual too much autonomy for
their spiritual welfare. In the
historical context of the
collapse of the Roman Empire,
the emergence of the Catholic of
highly centralized authority,
the church saw this highly
centralized network of priests,
bishops, Cardinals, the Pope, as
essential to the salvation of
the salvation of the church, and
therefore to all whom the church
served. So I would give them the
benefit of the doubt and say
that they thought they were
doing a good thing by really
creating this system that made
individuals contingent upon the
intermediate clear clergy and
the authority of the Church now,
from a reincarnation
perspective, they didn't do a
good thing. It took us a long
time to uncover this deeper
teaching that where each one of
us is responsible for our
relationship with the divine.
The Church may help us, but the
end, in the end, the church is
not essential to the maturing of
our relationship to the divine.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Well, I have
another question about that. I
mean you, you devoted, you know,
chapter six to the question of
whether there's room for
reincarnation in Christian
thought, yeah, 35 years ago, you
know, I'd like to know in a
minute if your view on that has
changed. But before we do that,
I want to make sure we get this
one in talk about the hidden
phase of life, the time between
lives, which you say is just as
important to our development,
Chris Bache: yeah, and that's
actually why I named the book
life cycles. I wish I had named
it a little bit differently,
because it became acutely
significant to me that if you
look at the cycle of life as
only. Taking place between birth
and death. You're missing half
of the cycle. We miss what
happens between death and birth.
And you have to look at the
whole cycle to understand the
rhythm of the soul, the rhythm
of human consciousness. And so
there are, just as there are
kind of standardized gradations
of what happens when a child is
born there, there's a
standardized process of what
happens when we die. And I think
Michael Newton's work is the
some of the best work I've seen,
explaining what happens in the
minutes, hours, years, relative,
you know, using time in a non
time universe after we die, the
integration, the introspection,
the review of our most recent
life, looking at it deeply from
within a spiritual perspective,
looking at our relationships and
Our challenges and from a
relation, from a deeper
spiritual perspective,
integrating all of our successes
and failures, really
internalizing them, entering
into the civilization of
spiritual beings in this
civilization and In the
community of fellow Soul
Travelers in enjoying the the
recess, the the return to a more
complete spiritual awareness of
existence, and then in time, a
gradual focusing into the next
challenge that we set for
ourselves, because it's like a
university. You finish a
semester, you take your exams,
you digest and rest for a bit,
but you make then choices for
what you're going to take next
semester. And mutant mutant
shows that these choices are
done not by ourselves, but under
the guidance and tutelage of our
guides, our Senior kind of more
senior spiritual beings, till
and we have some insight into
the lives that we're choosing,
we have options, and we we make
a choice that this particular
set of challenges suits my
particular needs where I am in
my development, or it gives me
an opportunity to be of service
in ways that I haven't
experienced before. And then we
make those choices, and then
we've engaged the incarnational
process, and we wake up kicking
and screaming as a newborn
child. If you understand the
whole of the cycle, then you
have a much the beginnings of a
much deeper understanding of
what makes life tick in a human
psyche than if you only pay
attention from birth to death.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So I was doing
some research on statistics, and
I discovered that it seems, you
know, very obviously rough
numbers, but something like over
57% of people in the world
believe in life after death,
between 12 and 44% depending on
you know, which country you're
looking at, believe in
reincarnation. 75% believe in
heaven and hell. You know, which
makes me wonder, because if you
know, only 57 believe in life
after death. Where's that extra
where do they think heaven and
hell is? I don't know. Yeah.
What do you have to say about
Chris Bache: heaven and hell?
And 25% of American Protestants
and about the same percentage of
American Catholics believe in
reincarnation. That's the one of
the statistics that that really
blows my mind, Heaven and Hell.
You know, I think in some ways,
the Buddhists get closest to it,
and their basic vision of is,
when we die, we enter in a
universe, a stage of our life
where what we are is mirrored
back to us in our in our
experience. So if we've done
good in life, if we've been
generous and kind and
thoughtful, then that is
mirrored back to us in the
experience of heaven or the
heavenly beings. If we've done
harm and injury and selfish and
stingy things and hurt people,
then that is simply mirrored
back to us, not out of
punishment, but to educate us.
And this is the experience of
hell. So from this perspective,
hell is the experience of our
shortcomings, heaven is the
experience of our joys. And I
think that works and Newton his
cause. Cosmology seems to
integrate that, but this is
would be mistakenly and could be
mistakenly interpreted as a
cosmological absolute, when
really it's simply a stage in
our debriefing. It's a stage
that we go through. I think the
deeper reality is that there is
a heaven of heavens. There is a
heaven beyond the heaven of our
feedback to our own goodness.
There is a heaven of heavens, a
reality of infinite love,
infinite knowledge, infinite
bliss, within which the entire
human evolutionary saga is just
a small piece and should not be
taken as defining the limits of
the universe. Is there,
similarly, a hell of hells? Is
there an eternal hell? And I
absolutely do not believe there
is it has not been so in my
experience at all, that is
simply a theological mistake, a
mistaken interpretation. Now, I
think there is accountability.
There is we are responsible for
the actions that we take, and
there is an accountability.
Nobody gets out scot free. But
that accountability does not
include this loathsome idea of
eternal damnation or eternal
punishment. No mother or father
would do that to their child for
making mistakes, and likewise,
the supreme intelligence of the
universe would not do that to
human beings. Now, having said
that, let me step into something
different, as you know, from my
book, you know, LSD, in the mind
of the universe, I have entered
and spent many years and days in
hell realms, in experiencing
extreme torture of that looks
like a hell realm, and my
understanding, eventually of
this is this, just as my
individual psyche retains all my
individual memories, both good
ones and traumatic ones, there
is a consciousness of the human
species which retains all of its
memories and processes, all of
those memories in a central
medicine psychological
condition, what Jung called the
collective un psych unconscious.
And that means all the terrible
things that human beings have
done to each other, all the
wars, all the horrors and all
the injustices and all the rapes
and the pillaging, to the extent
that those have not been
clarified or healed or removed,
they become part of the
collective torment, the
collective shadow of humanity.
So you might say that within the
human psyche, there are clusters
of memories that have a hellish
quality. But that doesn't mean
that there is a cosmological
state of being of hell, because
just as individuals have bad
experiences that they can then
clear from their system, the
human species can have terrible
trauma, which it is in the
process of clearing from its
system. Okay, and I think that
in the early church, maybe some
of the people who had contact
with these collective hellish
realms mistakenly interpreted
them to as a cosmological
principle of eternal hell.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Well, just we've
got about four minutes left less
than that quickly. Go back to
this question whether there is
room for reincarnation in
Christian thought. You say that
it would only take a small
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think, of
course, traditional Christianity
would say, No, there's no room
for it whatsoever. One life,
eternal hell. But I think there
are many Christianity has
committed itself that if
anything can be demonstrated as
a fact, then we'll find out how
it works, and work it into
Christian theology. And if
reincarnation is demonstrated as
a fact, which I think it has
been and is being, then
Christianity will find out how
to how it works and how it
makes, how to make room for it.
All we have to do incorporate
reincarnation within a Christian
framework is expand the notion
of the age of the soul. We can
even give Jesus a unique role in
salvation history. If we want
to, we may choose to expand to
see Jesus as part of a whole
brotherhood and sisterhood of
awakened beings helping
humanity. But even if we wanted
to make Jesus the. Unique savior
of Christianity. All we have to
do is open up the notion that
the journey of the soul is a
journey of maturation that takes
place over many lifetimes. It's
not finished in one lifetime,
and all of a sudden the
inadequacies that have been
foisted on Christianity by this
terribly short sighted
assumption that we only have one
lifetime. So if you only live
six days and you die, there's a
consequence to that. Or if you
are a bad person, or you do
something bad in the first 10
years of your life, you could go
to hell for the rest of your
life, these terrible
consequences, the kindness of
the universe, the compassion of
Jesus, has much more room to
grow in a world which
understands that he's talking to
souls. He's not simply talking
to personalities. He's talking
to souls in his teaching.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Last question,
very quickly. You end the book
by talking about the web of
life, understanding the rhythms
about life as an ongoing dialog,
which is you've kind of covered
in what you've just said, more
or less. Is there anything that
you want to add to that
Chris Bache: I've lived in the
reincarnational worldview so
long, and I've taught it and
talked with people and listened
to their stories and processes
people's life experience that it
is so natural to me to
understand the uniqueness of
every soul and the uniqueness of
every incarnation and the
complex background web between
lives and circumstances that to
see life in the old way, what I
used to see it in this kind of
silo way, is completely
unnatural, intellectually and
spiritually untenable and
spiritually unnourishing. So to
me, reincarnation doesn't answer
all our questions, but it is the
beginning of deeper and deeper
and deeper questions and deeper
answers which brings a true
richness and deep satisfaction
to the life process. It takes
out this terrible horror of a
good God,
Sandy Sedgbeer: I'm gonna have
to cut you there. It looks like
we've gone over time. I'm so
sorry, but that's okay. What can
I say? You know, talking to you
is always fascinating. Thank you
so much for joining us today.
Thank you Sandy. So life cycles,
reincarnation and the web of
life is still available in
paperback format. And for more
information about LSD and the
mind of the universe and Chris's
other books, articles and
events, visit his website. Chris
bache.com, that's it for this
week. I'll be back at the same
time next week with another what
is going on till then, it's
goodbye from me and thank you
again. To Chris Bache, Thank
you, Sandy, you.