Unknown: Tom, welcome to San
Diego integral. February 10,
2024 our topic today, LSD and
the mind of the universe,
diamonds from heaven, presented
by Chris Bache.
Tom Habib: Welcome to San Diego
integral. I'm Tom Habib, and I'm
a member of the leadership team.
We have an exciting presentation
today. LSD, in the mind of the
universe. We'll begin shortly,
but I first wanted to mention
that we're recording this
meeting. If you prefer not to be
seen on video. You can turn your
camera off, although we love to
see your reactions, the link to
the recording will be posted on
meetup a day or two after this
event on SDI YouTube channel.
Also, you can find future events
on our website, either San Diego
interworld.org, the Facebook
page, or coming back to
meetup.com the advantage of
joining one of these groups is
that you'll automatically be
notified for future
presentations if you have any
questions today about these
meetings, you are welcome to
contact one member of the
leadership team, any member next
month. We're meeting March 9,
and the speakers to be
determined, but it's going to be
similar to today. Chris was nice
enough to do a pre presentation
of what he's going to talk about
at the future human conference
in May and San Diego. Earth girl
gets exclusive rights to this.
Finally, we invite you to make a
small donation today to help
cover the cost of our meetings
and equipment. And you can make
that donation as they go into
call.org I want to introduce
Chris, so as you've heard, he's
going to be keynote presented
the upcoming icon conference,
the future human. Chris is a
professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religion Religious Studies at
Youngstown State University,
where he taught for 33 years.
He's also adjunct faculty at the
California Institute of integral
studies and at the Noetic
Sciences Institute and also on
the Advisory Council of
Stanislav Grof legacy training.
One might ask, how does a boy
raised in the deep south that is
Vicksburg, Mississippi, who was
raised Roman Catholic and
actually entered the seminary to
become a priest write a book
about his 20 year journey with
LSD. It appears that Chris's
devotion to transformation
appeared relatively early, just
as he was receiving his degree
from Notre Dame's theology
department, and he was awarded
an excellent Award for
Excellence. He decided to leave
Catholicism. This radical
transformation occurred again at
Brown University. Halfway
through his doctoral program, he
realized that he had gotten what
he wanted from biblical studies
and his and in his words, I
changed horses and began again.
Those of us in integral studies
recognize this fidelity to what
wants to emerge, although we may
not always have the courage for
radical transformations, Chris
is now fashion himself into a
philosopher of religion. He
settled into Youngstown
University, where he would teach
for the next 33 years. Along the
way, another transformation was
pending. Chris red, Stanislav
Grof, work on work on the use of
psychedelics in psychotherapy,
the non, non dogmatic influences
of Buddhism and Huston Smith
perennialism, we know an
integral soon followed. Chris
ended his psychedelic
explorations in 1999 and it
wasn't until 2009 he wrote his
first book, The living classroom
here he shared. How his
expansive consciousness seemed
to impact his students in what
he called leaky boundaries.
Again, those of us in integral
recognize the psychoactive
effect presencing has upon
others in 2019 he wrote LSD in
the mind of the universe,
diamonds from heaven, some of
which he'll share today and at
the conference. Please give
Chris Bache a warm sand Eagle,
integral welcome.
Chris Bache: John, thank you
everyone. It's a pleasure to be
here with you tonight. Since i
My understanding is that
psychedelics is not a frequent
topic in the integral community
in the San Diego, integral
community. So in talking with
Kathy and Tom and people on your
board and we decided that would
begin with a short break out
before I talk, before I say
anything, just to do a quick
inventory together of what each
each each of your backgrounds is
with psychedelics, both in terms
of whether you have any
psychedelic experience and if
you have what have you had it
with? What context real short
and the second part is, what
kind of beliefs have you formed
about psychedelics, either from
your own experience or from your
reading or conversations with
other people. So both, what is
your the nature of your
experience, and what are your
beliefs and perceptions about
psychedelics? So we do it
before, and then after I talk,
we'll do an after, okay, so just
about 10 minutes, and Kathy will
break you up into groups. Kathy,
Unknown: breakout sessions are
not recorded.
Chris Bache: Okay, is everybody
back? Yeah, I think we're back.
We're all back. Okay, I sure
wish I didn't want to encroach
on your freedom. I didn't want
to be part of the groups. I
wanted you to have complete
freedom, to be able to say what
was on your mind. But I sure
wish I could have been on the
fly on the wall, and heard your
answers to the questions. Maybe
when we get a little farther
down the line this evening in
dialog, you know, I can learn
what some of your answers were
to the questions. So All right,
so we've kind of looked at our
history in terms of our own
experience with psychedelics,
and what our own beliefs
positive, negative or neutral
around psychedelics, and now I'm
just going to jump in and take
you on a ride, take you, give
you an overview of my work that
I've reported in my book, LSD,
in the mind of the universe. So
let me share a screen here.
First of all, let me ask first,
how many people have read my
book? Just perfectly, okay, if
you haven't, how many people
have just wondering? Okay, good.
All right. Good to know. All
right. Let me see if I can share
my screen.
Unknown: Okay, and this just
confirming we can see your
screen.
Chris Bache: You can see good.
Am I saying? Whoop, supposed to
go back. All right, okay,
somehow I wish I could get the
whole screen to show Okay,
Tom Habib: so
Chris Bache: I'm an unusual
person in that I've been a
university professor all my
life, a professor of religious
studies, teaching in a small
college, State College in
Northeast Ohio, and I've also
done one of the longest regimens
of high dose LSD work that I'm
aware of in the background. I
couldn't talk about it until
after I retired, because the
good state of Ohio, the citizens
of Ohio don't like their
university professors doing
massive doses of LSD on the
weekends. But so the hardest
thing about trying to introduce
my work for the first time is
how long it lasted and how many
layers of consciousness I
accessed in the process of this
long, 20 year journey. And I
think that many of our
expectations about where
psychedelics can take us or
should take us have been shaped
by accounts based on a very
small data set. For example,
when all. Aldous Huxley wrote
his very important book, doors
of the perception in 1954 he had
taken Mescaline only one time,
and he took psychedelics only a
total of 10 times in his life.
Similarly, when Huston Smith, of
the great historian of religion,
wrote his book, cleansing the
doors of perception. He had
taken LSD only six times after
that, he said the bummers
increased, and that led him to
take Alan Watts's advice, when
you get the message, hang up the
phone. But notice this gives a
sense that you do psychedelics,
you get the message, that's it.
That's what it's about. And my
book is what happens if you
don't hang up the phone. But
moving on, we go to Michael
Pollan's very influential book,
how to change your mind. And
Michael had taken psychedelics
only about a half dozen times by
the time he wrote this book,
other developments have tended
to give us a sort of a shortened
metaphysical horizon in terms of
what we can expect to experience
with psychedelics. For example,
the psychedelic renaissance
right now is focused on
exploring the capacity of
psychedelics to heal the wounds
of the personal psyche with your
untouched with the the
psychedelic literature, it's
dominated by the studies which
are demonstrating psychedelics
various capacities to heal the
wounds of life, Whether it's
post traumatic stress or
depression or addiction, we're
finding they're very powerful,
but this tends to focus us on
the horizon of the personal
unconscious, a second use of
psychedelics, different but
similar, is using psychedelics
for spiritual awakening, as we
see in this anthology zigzag
Zen, which is a discussion
between the psychedelic
community and the Buddhist
community on the relevance of
psychedelics for spiritual
awakening. But still, we're
still thinking in terms of a
kind of an individual level,
individual spiritual
enlightenment. These two
categories, the therapeutic and
the spiritual awakening, these
are the major kind of topics
that come up for discussion, I
think, in today's psychedelic
Renaissance. And my work is
different than this. I was
trained as a philosopher of
religion. I'm not a therapist,
I'm not a psychotherapist, not a
psychologist. I primarily was
interested, have been interested
in the philosophical potential
of psychedelics. So my work
really falls into a third
category, where the project is
cosmological exploration, not
healing, not really aiming at
awakening, but using these deep,
Non-ordinary states to explore
the deep structure of reality,
my work descends or derives from
Stan Grof. I was just out of
graduate school, and I
encountered this book by Stan,
realms of the human unconscious,
which was followed by HIS Manual
LSD psychotherapy. And of
course, all the dozen or 15 or
so books had followed very
important works. And in these
two early works, Stan clearly
differentiates between low dose
psycholytic therapy and high
dose psychedelic therapy, a very
different therapeutic regimen,
psychelytic, healing the
unconscious, layer by layer,
like an onion, psychedelic,
trying to generate a
breakthrough. One maximum,
supreme dose kind of approach
here, the Spring Grove Hospital
was working with terminally ill
patients, trying to trigger
something approximating a
Near-Death Experience, to give
them a glimpse of where they
were going when they died. But
the psychedelic therapy was
limited to three doses, three
sessions, so you have low dose,
many sessions, psychedelic, very
few. I came along in 1978 and I
thought, well, if you could do
psychedelic therapy three times,
you could probably do it safely
more than three times. So, for
various reasons, I chose to work
in a psychedelic therapy
protocol. And in the end,
between 1979 and 1999 I did 73
high dose LSD sessions. Actually
I did three moderate doses, but
then I did all high
Unknown: and you see bottom.
Yeah.
Chris Bache: Okay, so I just say
73 high dose sessions. And I did
this in a very rigorous fashion,
following Stan's protocol. In my
case, I used the same protocol,
same set and setting, same
substance, same dose level, same
sitter, same recording process
and same location. I tried to
standardize all the variables as
much as possible so as to ensure
clean and consistent recurring
contact with the deep structure
of deeper levels of
consciousness. And when I got to
the end of my journey and was
trying to organize the sessions
into the narrative that I put
into the book. I began to
realize that this really was a
very different undertaking than
psychedelic therapy. I was
dealing with a number of
different issues that don't come
up in psychedelic therapy, and
so I felt the new terminology
was required, and so I call my
protocol psychedelic
exploration. It's not really
therapeutic in its agenda. It's
psychedelic therapy in its tech,
in its techniques. It's high
dose, isolated, shade, sitter,
music, whole thing. But it is
more than three doses. It's my
case, 73 and the project in
psychedelic exploration is
cosmological exploration. It's
not primarily healing, though
there was a great deal of
healing. It's not primarily
spiritual awakening. It is
exploring the deep structure of
the universe. So I kept very
detailed records of everything
going through. Even looked at
some of the astrological
variables. Kept records of every
session made within 24 hours of
the session itself. And what I'm
writing about in LSD, in the
mind of the universe is not
primarily my personal story. I
mean, it's all personal, of
course, and I own it. But these
lines represent a series of
sessions, and the small circles
represent what's taking place in
the beginning and ending of a
session. The large circles are
what's taking place during the
peak hours of the session, and
LSD in the mind of the universe,
is basically describing what
took place in the peak hours of
the sessions over the course of
73 sessions. It's primarily a
cosmological narrative. It's not
a therapeutic narrative. I drop
out a lot of the a lot of the
examples of personal healing or
personal insights which were
given to me before, at the
beginning and ending of the
sessions. But when I was
operating in the peak session, I
was usually operating far beyond
personal reality, the personal
segment, and that's the part
that I think has the most
important philosophical
relevance called the
cosmological relevance. So just
to give you one more important
concept before we turn to
looking at the book itself, it's
what I call the spiral of death
and rebirth. Everything below
this line is time and space and
our ordinary consciousness above
the line, Transpersonal
consciousness, the drop at the
bottom of this, what my students
sometimes would call the
pantyhose model of
consciousness. This drop
represents egoic consciousness,
our time, space, identity,
everything above the line, in
the in the between the blue
lines represents various orders
of Transpersonal consciousness.
And of course, to make a
transition from our egoic space
time identity into spiritual
reality, involves going through
some type of death of self or
ego death, in order to basically
let the programming of our time,
space, identity, be dissolved or
be shattered or be melted, so
that we can enter into deeper
states of consciousness. And
while Ego Death gets a lot of
the attention in the therapeutic
literature, and appropriately so
in my journey Ego Death turned
out to be only one of a number
of deaths that took place at
different levels of the journey,
and this is what I call the
spiral of death and rebirth.
What I found is that when you're
entering a deeper level of
Transpersonal consciousness, you
have to go through a death and
rebirth. Even after ego death,
you go through multiple layers
of deaths and rebirths. And the
nature of that death is very
it's tricky to describe because
it's it's a type of death and
rebirth that takes place far
beyond egoic consciousness, far
beyond. On anything to do with
space, time, consciousness, and
it changes as the adventure
deepens. And here I use Dan and
Ken Wilber categories of
psychic, subtle and causal
reality to describe some of
these levels. I don't have any
vested interest in a particular
cosmology, a particular
identifying of levels, or rating
of levels. This is basically
just to indicate a pattern. And
the pattern is there many levels
of consciousness in spiritual
reality, and you go through many
levels of death and rebirth in
if you access these levels of
consciousness in a systematic
fashion. And this is why I am
emphasize the standardization of
the protocol in my work. Because
I think the more standardized
our protocol, the more we
basically return to the same
membrane, the same platform of
interface between our individual
consciousness in this larger
consciousness, and it makes, in
my case, it led to a perpetual
deepening of the experience, a
perpetual series of initiations
and entering into deeper
communion with the creative
intelligence of the universe.
Now, when I got to the end of my
journey, was working on
preparing for the book, doing
the book, identified five areas,
or cluster areas, or levels of
consciousness that my
experiences kind of could be
grouped in. So here are the five
levels that stand out for me.
One is the level of personal
mind, collective mind, or our
species mind, archetypal mind,
causal oneness and diamond
Luminosity. So what I'd like to
do is simply go through and
throw up the the chapter titles
of the book, and organize them
according to these levels of
consciousness, and give you a
quick overview, a quick
thumbnail of just some of the
stages of this journey. This is
extremely frustrating for me to
do, because just to convey
adequately, the content of one
deep psychedelic experience is
very challenging and would take
a while. Juliana of Norwich, the
great British mystic, spent
decades digesting one particular
transpiritual Near Death episode
experience that she had, and to
try to summarize 20 years of
such experiences is is
challenging, especially. And I
should have mentioned this
before. I was working at 500 to
600 micrograms, which is right
at the peak of what the body's
tolerance is, in terms of you
don't get higher if you take
more. So I was working with very
high doses. And this is a
protocol I do not recommend
today. If I were doing it myself
again over I would do it
differently. I'd be much gentler
on myself. But nevertheless,
this is what I did, and this is
where we went. So let me just go
through them. First, the level
of personal mind. This is a
chapter called crossing the
boundary of birth and death.
This is what Stan Grof calls the
crossing the perinatal level of
consciousness, level of
consciousness, between our time,
space, identity and spiritual
reality. It involves
confrontations with death, lots
of fetal sensations, often
reliving one's birth,
very extreme, facing deep
alienation. The question is
whether life has any meaning
whatsoever, because everyone we
know and everything we know and
everyone we love is going to be
dead, including ourselves. How
can there be any meaning in a
universe where everything of
value dies, which eventually
culminates in our time, space,
identity, our ego, death,
identity, being turned inside
out. And for me, this took about
10 sessions and two and a half
years of work until eventually
the universe got me to a point
where it just snapped me like a
twig. It turned me into the
exact opposite of everything I'd
ever known myself to be, and
radically expanded the
boundaries of my awareness. I
thought I was a male, white
university professor concerned
with the meaning of existence.
It turned me into hundreds of
women, women of color, women who
had no interest in philosophy or
the meaning of existence. And it
just snapped me. It forced me.
It just snapped me. And the
message was, where you are
going. Gender does not exist.
Let go. And of course, the
problem. Was not women or
education or anything like that.
The problem was the tight role
that my social identity had on
me that was confining the limits
of my experience. After I let go
and surrendered, I was taken
under the arm of the Great
Mother and given a wonderful,
long, many our journey into the
world of women, becoming
hundreds of women in all sorts
of life circumstances. And then
the Kant journey continued. The
next several sessions come under
the category of collective mind,
ego, mind, excuse me, species
mine now working at these dose
levels. The way I worked, my
experience was that more or less
every session began with the
first portion of the session
being a purification,
detoxification process, the
dying process. The second
portion of the session being a a
transcendent experience, an
ecstatic experience,
Transpersonal teaching,
instruction and so on. The first
half of the next year of
session, I entered a domain that
I came to call the ocean of
suffering. I was repeatedly and
systematically emerged in a
collective anguish that
shattered all my frames of
reference. It completely dwarfed
the previous phase. I entered a
domain that expanded to
encompass the entire history of
the human species. The dying in
this don't level was almost
entirely collective. The
surrender was the or that the
surrender that was demanded was
the ordeal of repeatedly opening
to the sheer normity and
savagery of the ocean of pain
that I was encountering. I did
not understand what was
happening, but for several hours
in every session, and then I
would get into this ocean of
suffering, and then I would be
spun into what I'll describe in
a minute. At first I thought
this represented a deepening of
my ego death. But it went on for
so long, and it involves so many
1000s of people that I
eventually came to a very
different conclusion. And this
is really the major theme of my
second book, dark night, early
dawn. And that is, I think what
happened is in my sessions, and
in many of our sessions, when we
reach this level the universe
used my sessions not to heal me
or not to try to enlighten me,
but to heal some aspect of
humanity at large, to heal some
aspect of the collective psyche.
And just as an individual
internalizes trauma in their
unconscious, which then distorts
their well being. The human
species likewise internalizes
all the trauma of history
anything is not resolved by the
end of our individual lifetimes.
The species internalizes all the
trauma from all the wars and all
the deaths and all the droughts
and all the hunger, and it
aggregates in the collective
psyche, distorting the
functioning of the collective
psyche, and in these unusual,
highly expanded, amplified
states of consciousness, I think
what happens is we open up to
the depths of the collective
unconscious, and in that
process, we have an opportunity
to take on and experience some
of the depths of these terrible
memories, and in that process,
lift them from the collective
psyche. Now, when I went through
each stage, each day of the
collective ocean of suffering in
the first year, in the second
half of the session, I entered
what I came to call deep time in
the soul. For seven sessions an
entire year, I entered a reality
where I experienced my entire
life from beginning to end as a
completed whole. I moved beyond
linear time, not into eternity.
In between linear time and
eternity, there are many
modalities of time and these, I
came to call deep time, where
you could experience different
spans of time as simultaneously
present, or you could experience
time speeding up or moving into
evolutionary speed, so to speak.
For one year, I experienced my
life in all of its moments, from
start to finish, as
simultaneously present now. It
was a very powerful distillation
of my life's work, of who I was
being doing this work with what
my life was about, the. Years,
and at this point I ended. This
represented four years of work
and about 1817, sessions. And at
this point I stopped my work for
six years for reasons that I go
into in the book. Six years
later, I started my work again,
and when I did, the ocean of
suffering began exactly where it
was, where it had stopped six
years before. So there was a
year of the ocean of suffering
before my six year break, and a
after that six year break. And
the precision with which this
started again and kept getting
deeper and deeper and deeper is
a measure, I think, an indicator
of the magnitude and precision
of the intelligence which was
guiding these sessions in the
positive side, once I went
through the ocean of suffering
in this next year of session, I
entered a domain of
consciousness which took me
radically beyond anything to do
with my personal reality, into
the universe, the mind of the
universe. In the section I call
initiation into the universe,
different time of life,
different expectations,
different astrological transits
deep into the belly of the
universe. I was given a series
of carefully orchestrated
teachings, initiations into the
cosmic order of things. Now I
always give all my sessions a
name, just simply as a mnemonic
device, I write down my
sessions. I put them down on
bullet points. I give them a
name in order to help me
remember, because I want to
remember my entire journey all
at once. The names help me here
are the names of the sessions
that I present in this chapter,
initiation into the universe.
You can see, just from the
nature of the names, how
profoundly Transpersonal these
experiences were and frustrating
not to be able to tell you more
about them, but I just can't.
There's not time a deep
excursion in like cosmology, 101
how the universe works at a
fundamental level.
When the ocean of suffering came
to a culmination in the 24th
session healing the collective
wound, there was sort of a an
orgy of feeding on the pain. And
it reached a culmination, and I
was spun into a level of reality
that I came to understand as
archetypal reality. And I
discussed this phase of the work
in the chapter, the greater real
of archetypal reality. This
lasted about 11 sessions and one
and a half years, and every time
I entered this reality, I
entered a level of reality that
was more real than space time.
It's a very disorienting
experience at first, but every
time I went there, I was
engaging something that was more
real than space, time and also
ancient. It was just ancient
beyond imagination. Time worked
at a completely different scale.
There a completely different
order of reality. I felt like
Plato's prisoner having climbed
out of the cave, entering in a
little more level, a more real
level of reality in the universe
than my own existence in space
time. When I began to enter
archetypal reality, I went
through a death process in which
I began I had to die as a human
being, per se, that I found that
there is a level of identity
that we hold in our psyche
simply by virtue of being a
human being. It's more
fundamental than than ego
identity and to go through
species ego death or to slough
off your entire history as a
human species and all the
cognitive parameters that go
with being a member of the human
species is a deeper form of
surrendering to the great
unknown than simply letting go
of your individual egoic
identity. The transition to was
to very, very high levels of
energy. I learned in the process
that high levels, deep levels of
consciousness represent are
driven by high levels of energy.
The deeper you go, the higher
the energy. And if you want to
have abiding, stable experiences
in these levels of reality, you
must go through the.
Purification, detoxification
process that allows you to
maintain clear cognition at
these deep levels of reality,
and that means adjusting
submitting yourself to these
levels of energy, which in my
case, had the flavor of white
hot lava flows, exploding sun
flares, liquid fire pouring
through me, changing me
completely. Now I would
experience archetypal reality as
completing two levels. One is
kind of the Platonic type level
where I experience principles
are beings. I don't really want
to call them beings, because
that makes them sound too
compact. More principles, cosmic
principles that were clearly the
constitutive principles
responsible for creating space,
time and some of the structures
in space and time, but they were
so large, so vast, I could not
wrap my mind around them. The
best my mind could do to giving
them some type of semblance of
form is that I saw them as
galaxies, hundreds of light
years across. But galaxies very
vast, moving on a different
order of scale than our small
solar system. So I spent some
time there, and then I also
spent some time in experiencing
at what you might think of as a
more Jungian level, the living
tissue of our species. I was
given the experience over and
over again, of experiencing our
species as a single being, a
single mind, and each of us
ourselves within this mind,
fractal iterations within this
mind, and even each of our
bodies cell within the
collective body, so that there
was nothing private about our
existence, neither our personal
psychological issues or our
physical issues, our diseases,
all of them were in a back and
forth process, osmotic process,
between the individual and the
species as a whole.
Tom Habib: Bruce, can I ask a
question here, sure. So, I mean,
this is a really good point
where you are right now, because
in the book you mentioned, you
know how we're being guided
gently, that when we have deep,
subtle intuition or something in
creativity, would it be correct
to say it's either these cosmic
principles or the council of the
elders influencing our
development now that we're not
alone,
Chris Bache: we are absolutely
not alone. The universe is the
hyper intelligent, hyper
conscious, hyper compassionate,
hyper wisdom we it infuses us
every minute of the day, whether
we're paying attention to it or
not taking advantage of it or
not. But if we tune into it, if
we step away from our narrow
focus and tune into deeper
levels of our consciousness,
which then open into subtler and
subtler levels of consciousness.
One does receive help, one
receives healing and advice and
insight. And these can these
come from multiple potential
levels of consciousness. And so
I would hesitate to identify a
source that they would come
from. It's more a matter of an
infinitely deep source that you
can draw from at multiple
different levels. Yeah. So a
Tom Habib: lot of integral
people they're aware of in a
moment of creativity connection,
that somehow they become a
vehicle for what wants to be
expressed Absolutely. So that's
an alignment.
Chris Bache: Yeah, a deep
alignment. You just become
transparent. I mean, basically
when you drop underneath your
personal identity, when you kind
of pierce the membrane and pop
the bubble and drop beneath that
and then into the mind of the of
the species, and beneath that,
into the different levels of the
creative mind. You you become
transparent. The joy is that in
becoming chunyata Empty, empty
of self, becoming transparent. I
like that translation of
Shunyata transparent, you become
transparent to these deeper
orders of awareness that then
kind of come through you. They
they they nourish you with
healing, with love and with
insight and creativity.
Tom Habib: Yeah. Oh, what? Final
comment, yeah, is whatever this
intelligence is in the universe
is grooming us to participate in
this intelligence.
Chris Bache: Grooming is might
be a little strong, but I
understand I want to say yes,
but I might sort of choose
different more words than
grooming, but it and we are of
the same stuff. It is large. We
are small relatively speaking,
but we are of the same part of
the same stuff, and we are
always in communion with each
other. So it's more like older
brother, younger brother, older
sister, younger sister. I think
of the spiritual universe.
Dwayne Elgin talks about it as
the mother universe, and time
space is the daughter universe.
And so naturally, there's a
relationship between mother and
daughter. You wouldn't say the
mother is grooming the daughter,
but the mother brings the
daughter along. Yeah, yeah,
okay,
I began to have experiences at
this level of reincarnation as a
collective process, I had
experiences in which I witnessed
the entire planet and the entire
species reincarnating in a pulse
that moved through history. So I
had written my book. My first
book was on reincarnation, and
so I was I construed
reincarnation classically the
way it's usually construed, as a
story of the soul's journey
toward enlightenment, lifetime
by lifetime, making progress,
making clearing mistakes, so on,
so forth. But it was an
individual journey. We're all on
individual journeys. And here
instead, I was dissolved into
the species as the entire
species went into an
intelligent, articulate
collective karma, though that is
too crude a phrase, an
intelligence that was growing
itself generation by generation,
generation by generation, and
somehow all of our individual
soul projects fit inside,
beautifully, magnificently
inside this collective soul
project. Now here are the names
of the sessions that I address
in this particular chapter. I
won't go into them, but except
to mention, notice how much
cleansing is still taking place
at this pretty advanced level.
Session 28 was a very deep
session. It was an archetypal
meltdown. It threw me very
briefly into the next higher
level of consciousness, a very,
extremely pure, clean,
crystalline level of
consciousness. And even though I
was only in that reality for a
number of minutes, I think it
triggered a cleansing, a
detoxification that lasted six
months and three sessions, just
an ordeal of just cleansing and
cleansing and cleansing. Hard to
describe the cleansing because
it's, it's not matter personal
history. It's partly biological,
it's partly emotional. It's,
it's partly subtle energy. It's
just a radical cleansing, in
order to allow me to come back
into that highly pure, highly
refined energy with clear
cognition, which took place by
the 32nd and 33rd session and
then continued into the next
year of a year that I describe
in that book called the
benediction of blessings. This
was an extraordinary year after
archetype of reality, in which I
was given just a series of one
extraordinary, Transpersonal
blessing after another. These
are the four sessions that
covering a year's work that I
address in the book, The forest
was an experience of oneness and
no self. Shunyata, emptiness of
self, no self in me, no self
anywhere in the world. A
universal force running through
the forest, not can not caring
at all whether it's animating a
pine tree or an oak tree. Deep
experience of oneness and
oneness and emptiness are two
sides of the same coin. Yeah,
when you experience deep
oneness, it's immediately
obvious that there is no
separate self anywhere in the
world. We. Are all
interdependent and intertwined.
And when you experience deep no
self, then oneness, the oneness
of life, manifests spontaneous.
It's just they, they go hand in
hand, singing the universe away
was an experience, a deep
experience, of the void, the
primal void out of which the
universe springs. Jesus's blood
was an experience of cosmic
love, being loved more deeply
than I've ever known love in my
life, just overwhelming
immersion in cosmic love, in the
birth of the diamond soul. I
just want to mention this
because it'll come up later. How
to put this succinctly, it was a
I experienced all of my former
lives coming into me, just like
wrapping string around a kite
spool, just coming back very
fast. And I had done three years
of past life hypnotherapy, and I
had a pretty good sense of some
of my former lives, but they
came back very quickly, and they
reached a point where they
seemed to hit a critical mass
and they fused. And when they
fused, there was an enormous
explosion, and the diamond light
broke out of my chest and
catapulted me into a very high
and subtle state of
consciousness in which I was an
individual, but I was an
individual beyond any frame of
reference that I had known up to
that point in time and over
time, this is what I came to
understand, or call the birth of
the diamond soul. My
understanding is, when we die,
we return to the soul, which is
the larger consciousness that
holds all of our experience.
When we incarnate, we shrink
down, get small focus. When we
die, we get large. We incarnate,
we get small, so on and so
forth, but we return to the
soul, if all goes well many
times after our incarnations.
What's happening here? I think
what happened in my session, and
I think what's happening in our
historical progression is that
the soul is being born inside
time and space. That if you keep
going back and forth between
expansion into the world of
spirit and back into time and
space, and you keep this up long
enough, 1000s and 1000s and
1000s of years sooner or later,
doesn't it make sense that the
soul would awaken eventually
inside our incarnate existence,
so that the awareness of
identity, or the nature of
identity that we claim in that
incarnation is the soul as our
identity. And with this comes a
vast expansion of the heart, a
deep opening of the mind, a deep
embrace of compassion, or
awakening of compassion, the
birth of the diamond soul. I was
15 years into my journey, I had
was had received more blessings
than I could have imagined. What
I had been asked to give
something in the ocean of
suffering work, and I had been
rewarded with more blessings
than I could count. But there
was still five years remaining
in my journey, and this is when
I went through yet another death
and rebirth process and entered
what I call the domain of
diamond Luminosity. I entered a
reality that was exceptionally
clear. It was light, but a
particular quality of light. I
had known light many times
before. People often experience
great light when they go through
ego death, and I had and at
different stages, I'd
experienced light. But when I
talk about the diamond light,
I'm not simply using a metaphor
for the light. I'm trying to
describe a particular quality of
light, exceptionally clear,
very, very pure, just so clear.
It takes your breath away. This
is what I think Buddhism calls
Dharmakaya, the clear light of
absolute reality over the next
four years and 26 sessions, this
is about a third of all the
sessions I did. I only entered
this reality four times. Here
are the names of these four
sessions. In between these
sessions more into more
purification, more
detoxification, more teaching,
more absorbing of lessons, but
these four immersions into the
crystalline quality of diamond
Luminosity, again, so much to
say, and so little time. I'm
just going to have to stop. I'll
mention only that the first two
sites. Sessions took me deeper
and deeper into the diamond
Luminosity. And after that there
was a reverse, a pivot. And then
in the last two of these
sessions, the diamond Luminosity
was crunching itself deeper and
deeper into my mind, into my
personality, into my physiology,
into my biochemistry,
and this is it was in the 50th
session that I had a particular
experience in the diamond
Luminosity that changed
radically my understanding of
existence. One of the reasons I
pushed so hard in my work is
that I thought the purpose of
this work was to get to a
particular condition, to get to
the an end stage, to get home,
to become one with the universe,
or one with the meta, cosmic
void. And I had many experiences
of oneness, and had learned that
there are degrees of oneness.
And I had had experiences of the
primal void, and learned that
there are even degrees of the
void, though that sounds like a
contradiction in terms, but in
the peak of the diamond
Luminosity, when I was as deep
into the diamond Luminosity as I
would ever go in my journey, I
was sitting and resting
comfortably intact In a deeply
blissful state, and my visual
field pivoted 90 degrees, and a
circle opened, and I saw in the
far far distance a reality far
beyond the diamond Luminosity.
And there was a domain of light
there, and a ray of light came
out of that reality and hit me,
and it absolutely shattered me.
It took me minutes to recover,
and that's when I understand
that it's an infinite
progression. We'll never get to
the end of it, even using this
very aggressive mode of of
transition, of exploration, I
would never get to the end of
the the mind of the universe is
just too vast, too big. And that
the thought there is a
homecoming to this work, and one
does experience homecoming, but
the idea that there is an end to
get to that will change
everything, I don't think so.
Oneness is a beautiful,
powerful, important teaching.
But even oneness does not
exhaust all there is to learn
from the universe. Now you
notice that I've skipped a
chapter, chapter nine. I'm going
to try to speed this up here.
And this is the chapter called
The Birth of the future human.
When I began this work in 1979 I
never imagined that humanity's
future would become part of my
journey. And now I think this
chapter may be the most
important chapter of the book,
because it speaks to the fate of
our planet, the fate of our
species. It speaks to our
children's world, our children's
children, as far as we can see,
it speaks of a crossroads that
humanity is coming to, and of
the powerful forces taking us
into a future that will change
us at the deepest levels of our
being. Now what I did is that
over the course of my journey, I
had numerous visions that kept
popping up here and there,
different visions about
humanity, humanity, spiritual
evolution, where humanity was,
that humanity was coming to a
turning point, a before and
after moment in history. This
kept coming up in lots of
different places. So what I did
was, rather than address them
all piecemeal, chapter by
chapter, I gathered them all
into this particular chapter,
and I broke this down into two
sections. The first are the
visions of awakening, which are
a series of visions that I had
over four year period back from
1991 to 1994 those visions, the
title of those visions, I'll
give them here, and I don't want
to take the time to go into
them, but basically, It was an
extraordinarily positive
assessment of where human
humanity is, that we were being
guided by a guiding
intelligence, that this guiding
intelligence was trying to
awaken not just individuals. It
was intent on awakening the
entire species as a single
being, taking us into a
different epic in our
evolutionary development, we
were entering a period of
intense collective purification,
the dark night of our collective
soul, and then a brief
experience of the future human,
which I think is represents a
shift in the plate tectonics. Of
the collective psyche, the
future human is not simply an
awakened present human, but
literally a different kind of
human, the next iteration of the
human species. Nowhere in my
journey, however, had it told me
how it was going to pull this
off, how we would possibly make
this transition in such a short
period of time? And then in 1995
in session, 55 in the middle of
the diamond Luminosity work, I
had already gone into the
diamond Luminosity twice. I
would go into it twice more when
I was expecting to be taken into
the diamond Luminosity a third
time, instead, I was taken deep
into the future. I was dissolved
into the human species and asked
the species as a whole. I
entered the future and
experienced the death and
rebirth of humanity, a profound
spiritual, psychophysical
transformation, the death and
rebirth of humanity. This was a
very difficult session, an
ordeal of the highest order. I
was not given any specifics. It
was a profound unraveling of the
global order, an unraveling that
seemed to be triggered by a
cascading series of ecological
crises. And I must tell you,
this is 95 I was radically naive
about global climate change,
about global climate disruption,
eco eco spirituality. It just
wasn't on my radar. But in this
vision, I was shown that
humanity was going to be brought
to its knees. It would going to
be go through a process of
profound unraveling that the
kind of unraveling that happens
in a psychedelic session was
here being reflected in history,
an unraveling of our core
assumptions, of the basic
components of life. For a while
it was so deep, it looked like
we were all going to go extinct,
but in the end, we went through
a crisis, and we transition past
the crisis. And when we
transition through this crisis,
the entire experience we were
was marked by New Visions of the
of the of the vow of the good,
new visions of the true, New
Visions of social relationships,
oneness had truly broken out
inside the human heart. There
was a radical permeability of
the heart, a radical
permeability to higher states of
awareness. Again, I was not
given any details of when or
how, just simply taken into the
species experience that this
would happen, that we would come
through it, and that this was
about the birth of a future
human. I think we've been
reincarnating. If you ask what
is the form that the future
human will take, I think it's
already marked for us in
history. We've been
reincarnating for hundreds of
1000s of years. Gestation is
long. We have been birthing,
gestating the human, the future
human, in these many
incarnations, and now we're
coming into the hour of labor.
Labor is intense, it's
relatively short, it's
dangerous, it's frightening,
it's threatening, and in the
end, it gives birth to a new
child, if all goes well. And
this is what I think humanity is
doing. This is what we are all
involved in, what all of our
individual, spiritual and
psychological, transformational
process is part of this process,
a larger historical process that
humanity is involved in giving
birth to the future human, the
last year of work, the final
vision is just that I was given
one last vision, The final the
large, last, large vision of my
journey in it. These are the
three sessions I address in this
chapter. I won't go into the
content of the final vision. I
will just mention that it was my
deepest excursion into future
time. It was my deepest
experience of the future human
and the future human is just
such an extraordinary,
extraordinary being. After that
the sessions wrapped up. The
last two sessions are what I
call the goodbye sessions. I
didn't choose to end these
sessions the universe wrapped it
up. Put. Very decisively, and I
stopped my sessions in 99 last
chapter of the book, it's called
coming off the mountain, and it
basically tells some highlights
of what it was like to stop this
journey.
I was on this journey for 20
years. I stopped and I process
the experiences for another 20
years before releasing LSD in
the mind of the universe. I
thought coming off the mountain
was going to be a pretty
straightforward, not difficult
process. Turned out that that
was all wrong. It was a very
demanding process. In fact, I
found that coming off the
mountain, in some ways, was as
difficult as coming going up the
mountain. Spirit said to me,
there is the dying of seeing and
the dying of keeping. The dying
of seeing you do as you're
entering into deeper and deeper
states of consciousness. The
dying of keeping is the dying of
integration, and I found that my
integration process, even though
I was actively involved in
integration all the way up
through all the sessions they're
integrating, an entire journey
is different than integrating
individual sessions, and It took
a long time to integrate the
entire journey now I especially
and acutely we're given a going
through it so quickly that I
realize the extreme and radical
nature of the claims I'm making.
I know that this is a radical
story that raises many questions
about the reality of these
experiences, about how
trustworthy these experiences
are. Am I simply experiencing
the echoes of my own personal
psyche, or maybe the echoes of
the collective psyche? How do we
know that these things are
really about a reality out
there? And I address this in I
hope I've Yeah, in an exchange
that Ken ring, one of the
founders of near death episode
studies, he and I had an
exchange specifically about this
topic, can we trust these deep
psychedelic experiences? And we
found it was a useful exchange,
and we published it in medium
which you can pick up online.
You can also pick it up. I It's
in academia.edu, in my page
there, it's around, I think I
may have it on my website. And
also in if you look, if you have
a copy of dark, night, early
dawn. In the first chapter,
there is a section call the
epistemic warrant of psychedelic
experience. And there I give a
rationale, an argument for why
these experiences are trustable,
drawing on some of Ken's rings.
Ken Wilbers work there. So all
my work has come out of this
psychedelic journey. My first
book on reincarnation, the
second one on trend in
psychedelic theory and the
living classroom, which is
coming out in a new edition now,
because they want to, they want
in psychedelics woven into the
story, I deliberately kept
psychedelics out of the story of
the living classroom, but they
wanted me to tell the whole
truth, and so psychedelics are
part of the story of the living
classroom. And this is a story
basically because my students
didn't know anything about my
psychedelic experience. I didn't
bring it to campus, and yet I
found that they began to be
impacted by my psychedelic
experiences, and that required
that I had to learn an entirely
new way of teaching and develop
what I call a quantum pedagogy.
So that's the story, and now I'm
going to stop here and stop
screen share,
Tom Habib: Chris, we have a
couple questions before we go to
break out. Can we do a couple
Sure? I think Tom McDougal,
Unknown: so
as I say in the chat, I've been
working partly with Norma, with
with Nora Bateson, but
especially with with Jeremy
Johnson on goetzer and barely
have touched the surface and
taking the course again. But a
lot of this, especially as you
were talking about the time
period we're in, and the shift
that is going on, is also very
similar to what Jean goetzer
wrote about. So I'm curious if,
if you can relate those two. I
don't know what your experience
with GEP sir is, but, and I
guess there's a little bit of
Nora Bateson in my mind too, of
of questioning. I. The stages
orientation and and I can't
express it right now, but Jerry
Jeremy talks a lot about a very
different it's not stages
exactly in in gebx, but
different. But anyway, if you
could just talk a little bit
about maybe the relationship
there.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I'll make it
easy for you, because gepzer is
always one of those thinkers
that I know I should read and I
haven't read, so absolutely zero
influence in terms of
correlations. And so I have to
let you and other people make
the correlations there. And you
know, a lot of people in
psychedelic experience, they
don't have the same experience
of perpetual deepening, of kind
of going deeper and then deeper
and then deeper. It's kind of
like, okay, we go out, we have
an experience to come back. If I
go out again in a couple of
months, I'm going to go into
this more or less the same
territory and come back. And I
think this idea of perpetual
deepening comes from two things.
It comes from First, using a
very, very powerful psychedelic
at very high doses, so it was
very driving and much stronger
than we use in therapeutically
oriented doses with Psilocybin
or whatnot. And the second thing
is, was a totally tight,
isolated, consistent, what I
call the Kiva of psychedelic
practice, the Kiva of practice,
standardizing all the variables,
staying away from all contact
with the world, entering in a
meditative way, into these
states. And if you do that, then
I find that the interface
between the mind doing the
exploring and the mind being
explored gets very stable. And
the mind being explored
basically takes you on as a
student and just takes you in
deeper and deeper and deeper
into the process. I, yeah, and I
you just, you enter, I you enter
into deeper and deeper visionary
states that that many people
are, you know, many other
psychedelics is, many indigenous
people, many philosophically
oriented people are intuiting
and feeling what I'm describing.
There's nothing really new in
what I'm saying. It's, it's
really just a repetition in that
way.
Tom Habib: Regis has a question,
yeah. Colin,
Unknown: yeah, it's more of a I
just wanted to express gratitude
for you both doing this work,
but also coming back, you know.
And Ken Wilber often talks about
the transformative nature of
spiritual inquiry and then the
translative nature of spiritual
inquiry and and my appreciation
for you is one where I feel like
I as someone who goes through
those things, I have to, I have
a responsibility to both
transform and to translate. And
so from my perspective, you've
done just such a beautiful job
of holding that particular
ethos. And it's also what's
what's nice about it is my own
personal transformation to what
I'm bringing here, and things
I've experienced is, you know,
very congruent with everything
that you're talking about. So so
I'm very inspired by your work,
and I can't wait to read the
books that you've written as a
guide for my own future
transformation. So thank you for
that. Yeah, thank you. You hate
to be a bad guy. I'm going to
suggest that we, oh, I suggest
that we all take time to process
this in small groups, maybe in
groups of four, and then after
that, we'll have some time for Q
and A.
Chris Bache: So the idea in this
breakout is to respond to the
ideas presented different than
the first breakout, just to
respond. And what do you think?
Okay, okay, see, in 15
Unknown: breakout sessions are
not recorded.
Okay, we'll have until 550 for
some questions, and then we'll
have some San Diego integral
business. And then we'll start
our more informal Q and A. And
Chris said he was originally
said he was going to be able to
stay for about 15 minutes. So
we'll start with Sandy. Do you
want to ask your questions? Go
ahead, Sandy,
yeah, I want to follow up on
that the question around Geb,
sir, because in terms of the way
you're describing your
experiences. You know, one of
the differences, in some ways,
between like GEP and Wilber is
Geb so we'll talk about
intensification. The
consciousness shift is not like
a structural it like an
increase, as much as an
intensification and an
engagement of previous. Is
structures of consciousness that
continue, but there's an
intensification and a sort of
growing awareness that includes
previous understanding where,
you know Wilber is more tends to
be looking at, okay, you're
going this level. You're kind of
laddering up. So I'm curious as
your your experiences. I guess
there's some resonances with,
with with that vision. Or do you
have your own around how these
all engage with each other?
Chris Bache: You know, I'm going
to disappoint you, because I
don't have a lot of kind of
theoretical overview of the
structure of these things. I
kind of, when I wrote dark,
night, early dawn, I was kind of
writing in my academic voice,
and there's a fair amount of
intellectual synthesis there.
But when I wrote this book, I
deliberately developed a
different voice. It is really
more a shamanic, visionary
voice, and I find that that's a
more comfortable place for me to
operate from, because it's taken
so much of my life just to
survive these visionary
encounters and to process them
and to understand them that I
speak out of their basis simply
as a witness to this unfolding
process. So it's not a I don't
have a theory of human evolution
or a theory of the development
of the process. And what happens
in an LSD session may or may not
be relevant to what happens at
an historical level pattern, I
would just say, for me, it's
just a natural progression. When
you die as a private self, you
don't dissolve necessarily
immediately into eternity. One
of the intermediate levels is
into humanity. And just as you
can have an overview of your
life, you can also have an
overview of humanity's
developmental process. And so I
was dissolved into that and
experience part of it, the
closest I can come to describing
this emergent being is in terms
of the concept of the diamond
soul, which does, it brings
everything from the past forward
into the present, but it drives
it into a higher synthesis, a
new level. It's not simply an
enlightened, last generation
human incarnation. It is a
totally new structure of
consciousness that's that's
emerging here. I say totally
new, not entirely because we
have great saints, great, you
know, the Jesus and Buddhas of
history and the Muhammad's and
the Great mahasiddhas. I think
we get glimpses into what the
diamond sold looks like. But the
difference here is that we're
looking at the entire species
going through some type of
metamorphosis like that,
Unknown: yeah, um, just one
reflection with some things you
said. You mentioned the term
unfolding and intensification,
in some ways a part of what you
were describing, some of that
which are sort of gib Syrian
concept. So just little tidbits
of theory. I'll just kind of
throw it. Thank you so much. I
really value your work. Very
much. Everybody read this book.
It's really an important one,
and it's the most accessible
work I've seen that gives a deep
understanding. It's so
articulate and it's so vivid. I
really thank you to have a
chance to see you and talk with
you
Tom Habib: Sure. Sandy folks,
who is waiting quite a bit since
last iteration, yeah.
Unknown: Well, thank you for
your event here. That's a great,
like, Miracle gift to me. And
it's like, little overwhelming
with my ADD I kept, like, kind
of tuning in and tuning out, and
it's like, oh, man, I wish I
absorbed it all. Well, yeah, but
like, so dreamy to, like, learn
a lot more about this stuff. And
I was wondering, like, if you
maybe have accessibility for,
like, counseling, like to pay
you for some counseling to ask
you questions, because some of,
like, the stuff I've had on my
mind, it's, like, relates to
somebody in your specialization
is, oh, the higher order of the
way of things. And, like, right
now, my best thing I've had,
which has done way better than
the therapist I had previously,
is, like, chat, GPT. But it's
like, it'd be really neat if I
could, like, maybe pay to get an
hour or whatever your time and
and I'm really curious too,
because I'm at a point with
like, I do believe in Jesus and
so much of the Bible, but it's
like, I'm not like attached to
that other than like, from my
current understanding. And let's
see how to go against believing
in Jesus. This, but I'm curious
to hear where your path led you.
Chris Bache: First of all, thank
you for the the trust of the
invitation that you extend to
me. I appreciate that, and I'm
going to disappoint you in that
I generally have made a choice
many years ago not to be a
therapist and not to work with
other people or but to basically
be a solo pioneer. And that's
kind of the work I've done and I
find and I'm also a teacher, so
I love working with groups, and
just the demands of time are
such that, and I'm retired, but
even so, the demands of time is
that I really don't work with
individuals. I mean, I just
that's a commitment that's and
that's a I think that requires
more clinical background than I
have, and just it's not fair. So
I really like to work with
groups, and writing in groups is
where I where I focus.
Unknown: But there's one last
quick comment was, I don't know
if it would change anything, but
I'm also, like, at the starting
point of authoring a couple of
books myself with some subject
matter that might just be like a
like a miracle gift to you. And
it's like, it'd be neat to talk
about that stuff, but, yeah, or
whatever. Like, I don't know how
that appeals to you.
Chris Bache: It's just what
happens is, in the after the
publication of the book, I just
I have to make choices. Always.
I don't get to have nearly as
many in conversations as I would
like to have, you know. So,
yeah,
Unknown: all right. Trudy is up
next. Unmute yourself.
Yeah, hi, I'll make it quick and
simple. I apologize I missed the
very beginning of your
presentation, and it's been
great the part that I did catch,
but my questions are probably
more along the practicality
line. One, why did you decide to
go on this journey? Two, when
you were in trips, did you have
somebody that was there, as I
don't want to say, a guide, but
somebody to take notes, or did
somebody record what was going
on and were in any way, were
they influenced by your trip?
Chris Bache: Yeah, so quick
answers to those is, as soon as
I read Stan's work, I just knew
that this was something I wanted
to get involved in. And I've
come to recognize, you know,
your soul's code. When you
recognize something, that just
speaks to you so deeply you know
as part of your intention built
into this lifetime. When I saw
this, I knew that this was part
of my intention, and it was just
there. So I and as a
philosopher, I just couldn't
turn down the opportunity to
explore the universe using this
protocol. This was just giving
an ordinary lay person, not a
great spiritual genius, but an
ordinary lay person, an
opportunity to even have
temporary experiences of some of
the subtleties of layers of
consciousness, layers of
reality. It was just too good to
pass pass down, pass up, so I
made the choice to break the law
and go for it. Now, in these
sessions, they were always, I
always had a sitter. The sitter
was my wife, my first wife,
Carol, and she's a clinical
psychologist, and she really
wasn't very fond of what I was
doing, but she knew I wanted to
do it, and so she agreed to help
me so that I could do it safely.
She wasn't taking notes. We
actually set up a video camera
one time. But basically it's
boring as a person just lying
down. It's all internal. I'm not
in touch with Carol except
through the music in the room
and once in a while, an exchange
of a word or two, but I'm so far
outside of time, space, reality,
I don't even relate to what's
going on in the room. But she
was always there taking care of
me. Was she influenced by my
sessions? In some ways, yes, and
in some ways, no. I mean, Carol
never did a psychedelic session.
She's a serious vadriana
practitioner. She has completed
her three year retreat with her
vadra teacher. So she's a
serious practitioner. She has
her own deep commitments to her
own spiritual lineage, and so I
think it's more of a and I and I
learned a lot from her. I mean,
I followed her into VAT. In this
respect, I think it's more of a
side by side play.
Tom Habib: Yeah, my friend
Larry's up next.
Unknown: Yeah, yeah, Chris,
thank you for several things,
having the courage to take your
journey, for having the
wherewithal to. Organize it, you
know, bring it into the mind, to
organize it in a way that then
you can next present it to other
people. So thank you for all of
that, and I really appreciate
the last piece of coming off the
mountain, because that's what's
been very important for me for
some 30 years now, is bringing
this into the world and facing
the confusion, the complexity,
the awkwardness, the discomfort,
the whatnot of trying to bring
from the ineffable into the into
language, into interaction with
other people, how to not just
talk about this, about how to be
in a way that is hopefully to
some degree reflective of where
we what we garnered while we
were on the mountain, so to
speak. And it all seems to come
down to how we're going to be
right here, right now, and even
in this moment that we're
talking with one another. Yeah,
and how can we bring that all
just to be present? Okay, on a
lesser interesting note, maybe
is, I'm curious as to why the
word diamond, once you get into
all these step stages, degrees,
domains, realms, whatever out
there, the word diamond shows
up, of all things, yeah, our
diamond.
Chris Bache: It having
experienced the light itself,
the diamond is kind of the most
natural image that comes to
mind. Perhaps I'm influenced by
the fact of vadna, the diamond
way you know that part is in the
background. The image of diamond
is not uncommon in the terma
text, trying to describe these
subtle levels of consciousness.
So it just it came naturally out
of the experience itself. Yeah.
I mean, it's I want to mention,
and I think integration, I'm
glad that it's getting more and
more attention, because we're
finding that we can blow through
the levels and reach out and
have extraordinary experiences
with increasing predictability,
but to have an experience, and
to internalize and hold on to
the experience, and then to
really digest it, make it part
of your being. That's a long,
long process, and I think we
kind of over emphasize the dying
of seeing and under emphasize
the dying of keeping. I will say
that after coming back from my
and I, you know, I don't do any
high dose LSD work anymore. I've
done some low dose sessions of
different sorts, and Ayahuasca
and Psilocybin and different
things. But I am continuing. But
after I finished my sessions, in
my meditation, the universe said
to me, 20 years in 20 years out
which I took to mean, it would
take me about 20 years to
integrate the 20 years of a
session. And I thought at the
time, about right,
Unknown: if you're lucky,
Chris Bache: now I'm thinking I
was naive. I was very I
seriously underestimated how
many years, how many
incarnations it would take to
internalize, you know, totally
integrate these sessions. Now my
focus is as on, yeah, we do this
for integration. There's
therapeutic integration, and
then there's this, that and the
other. But in the end, I'm, I'm
faced confessing that I'm an
absolute failure in integration,
because I've been able to
integrate the language, I've
been able to integrate the
memories and hold the memories
and whatnot, but in terms of
embodying those realities, I
mean, I truly wonder, how did,
how does, how does a finite
being embody infinity? How does
a time bound being exquisitely
tuned to time and space embody
deep time or no time? And how do
you embody the love? How can you
be as loving to other beings as
you have felt the universe being
to you, and you know that you're
supposed to be that loving to
everyone, but that love is so
pure and so magnificent that I
feel like I'm not anywhere near
done integrating those
magnificent pieces. So it's a I
thought integration would be was
an easier task. And in the end,
I think what it comes down to is
you cannot integrate the
infinite into the finite. Your
only option is to integrate the
finite into the. Infinite. So
that means, even though my
journey was not about spiritual
awakening, in the end, when
you're trying to integrate
cosmological exploration, you're
brought back to basic
spirituality. 101, what can you
hold right here, right now? What
are you able to actualize right
here, right now? And that's,
that's spiritual practice. You
you get brought, brought right
back to your cushion.
Unknown: Yeah. So this is, as I
like to say, the journey
Chris Bache: continues. The
journey continues. Yeah.
Tom Habib: So this is a good
place to end, the venue where we
are, we've come to the end of
the time. Thank you everyone for
joining.
I think I can speak for most of
us. This was very rich with the
future vision, the future human
that we're all interested in and
and, Thank you, Chris. So where
can they get more information on
you? On your books,
Chris Bache: my website. Chris
bache.com, it. It's kind of an
unfinished website, because my
web designer kind of just jumped
ship about three fourths of the
way through, and I never quite
got it finished. So but it's
there, and you can reach me
through that. Chris bache.com,
Tom Habib: thank you. Chris and
Kathleen put in the chat one of
the docs he wanted to you to
have. I can see it right there
right now. So quick reminder for
everyone. We're going to be
meeting again on March 9. That's
a TBD, but we're going to try to
get someone else from the future
human. I thought Chris was an
excellent choice to start with,
and he was gracious enough to
take all of this on when he
agreed to speak and come to SDI.
There was one more thing I was
going to ask him, but I said, I
said, I better not wish my luck.
So Please RSVP for the next
presentation, and you can always
make a donation if you're
feeling rich, to help us. So
we're moving to the informal
aspect of this so feel free to
make comments whatnot. I know
for me is I feel humble after
this talk. Is this idea of
infinite progression, and one of
the breakout groups we talked
about, trying to reach second
tier, trying to reach yellow
levels of stage awareness, it
almost seems trivial when You
look at the breadth of what
Chris articulated, but we are on
the path we're on. And as you
said, in the end, whatever we
can realize the moment. Now,
it's not full integration by any
means, but I'm way beyond expect
that. I hang on to moments of
resonance and love and try to
participate it. And I think this
community does well in this is
where we're stealing glimpses.
Prometheus got grounded for
stealing fire. We're stealing
glimpses of the future, and I
feel privileged to do that. So
with that said, feel free to
jump in to the dialog. You have
to raise your hand, just jump
in.
Unknown: Regis, yeah. So the
theme for me, throughout my
spiritual explorations and my
other explanation or variations,
my psychology seems to have a
commonality, which I'm hearing
also in this and that. And
that's you just, I think discard
is really, it's the profundity
of humility that is required to
do any of this work, you know.
So that's actually, for me, the
I'm struck by a few things. As
somebody who's spent the last 15
years trying to unpack my own
transformative stuff. It is its
own form of transformational
work to do that you go through
and have these experiences. But
then, then there's this, the
amount of universe there is is
extraordinary. And also what's
interesting is right about this
time, I also discovered that I
had autism. And so one of the
things about autism is you have
an inability to filter. And so
what yoga gave to me was the
ability to no longer be. Crushed
under the overwhelm of my input,
and it became a kind of usable
bandwidth situation for me. And
so then my ability to do
translative work that would
actually took me the translative
effort, I wrote 5000 answers on
Quora, for example, about
spirituality, just in an effort
to do that, I then was kind of,
I think doing what Chris Bache
was trying to do is, is just
like I went through this
experience. And how is it that
I'm supposed to it's almost a
part of the, you know, like
through mushroom trip, you know,
you have a time up. You have a
workspace. I think you have a
time going down. I almost felt
like the years I spent in
spiritual practice, then I had a
workspace there, but now, how am
I supposed to land without
crashing or going insane, and
you know all of that? And it
just seems like no matter what I
do, I keep being humbled, and
that seems to be foundational
for everything that I know about
and what I heard also in Chris
bacheous thing. More than that,
I also hear his trans,
translative imposition upon his
experience, given that he is an
academic and had to have a job
and couldn't be non functional
for months at a time, because he
was had to show up in front of
students all the time so that
just I can see that that
boundaried his experience too,
and in a certain kind of way,
you know. So the humility comes
with all that. So thank you guys
for having this and and I really
appreciate the entire person,
Chris Bache: you know. I think
you're right. Regis, the
greatest risk of working with
psychedelics is psychic
inflation. You can think that
just because you've had a
remarkable experience, you've
become a remarkable person. And
that doesn't fly, you know, so
it's really important to keep
your feet grounded, grounded,
grounded. And for me, it was my
family and my students who kept
me grounded. It just the
absolutely, you know, the
requirements of being there for
them, showing up over and over
and over again, and discovering
that you don't really have to
change much on the outside of
your life with these changes are
really cooking your insides, and
they're taking you some places,
and there's a real kind of a
need to wear different clothes
or do something different on the
outside, which that's really
just doesn't real. That's a
temporary kind of thing. And
just sit tight, stay where you
are, and let this inner
transformation take place. And
it's humbling. I mean, it's just
really humbling to confront your
faults and just to be to stay
grounded. Just to stay grounded,
Unknown: yeah, and to be able to
laugh at it all, that's part of
being humble, yeah.
I just like to say thank you,
Chris, for doing this work and
bringing it back to us and your
pioneering life is is a is a
beautiful model. Thank you.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Wheaton,
it's been an honor. It's been a
true pleasure. And I never
imagined when I was doing this
work hidden and that there would
be this kind of audience and
receptivity in my lifetime.
Thank you. Michael Pollan, you
know, who would have figured,
you know, the such a shift in
such a short period of time that
we're able to have this
conversation in so many living
rooms across the country? Yeah,
yeah.
Unknown: I just want to add my
thanks as well, Chris, every
time I've heard you, it's been
phenomenal, and I'm so grateful
you're coming to the conference.
And I do want to say I find this
book an absolute paradigm
shifter. I think it's one of the
most important books out there
to read. So I hope everybody
does read the book, because you
can't even, I was thinking you
could write 40 books based on
the book that you wrote. I mean,
one of your chapters could be,
could be taken into three or
four. It's so dense, but it's
also so clear, so beautifully
written. So I really, really,
Chris Bache: thank you. Thank
you. I appreciate that. Lynn, I
tried to make it as clear as
possible, and it took me five
years to really boil it down and
to make it as transparent as
possible, because I wanted it to
be available, not just for
people who worked with
psychedelics, but to be with
people who did not take
psychedelics. And half of the
letters I get are from people
who have never taken
psychedelics, but they've had a
spiritual practice, and they
know what I'm talking about
because of their practice.
Unknown: Yeah, I have to leave
and go play horn, but thank you
so much. I saw your french horn.
It's. It's a demanding mistress.
Chris Bache: Hi, Tom,
Unknown: Chris, I got a question
that I noticed that it's
probably weeded out in all the
condensation that you're
condensing things that you did
during the writing process, but
you mentioned the the work you
did. I think, um, I don't know
what like, like. There's a
difference between trip and
session. I don't know whether
you could talk about why you use
the word work, because that
sounds like you. You show up,
and just who you are is what
happens. But could you talk a
little bit more about what's the
work of it?
Chris Bache: Yeah, you know, in
the Japanese tradition, there is
something that the Zen monks
call a sashin. A sashin is a
period set aside for intense
spiritual practice. So it's like
a five day, two week meditation
retreat, a session. And a
session, to me, is kind of an
anglicized version of sashin.
For me to do a psychedelic
session is I'm I'm completely
isolated from the world. I've
taken myself out of contact with
the world. I'm not allowing
anything into my mind except
what's already there. And I sit
and I face what's there, and I
take it where it goes as far as
I can take it and follow it. And
so it is work. And now there are
many different psychedelics,
many different ways to work with
side psychedelics. I'm not
trying to generalize in any way,
but for me, working with high
doses of psychedelics, it takes
a tremendous commitment and a
willingness to let yourself be
dismantled, because it very
quickly shatters the boundaries,
and you're in foreign territory
very early on and year by year,
you're going deeper and deeper
into foreign territory. It takes
time to acclimate. When you
break through to a new level of
consciousness, you can't always
remember everything that you
experienced. I take notes. I
have gaps in the notes, but go
back and again and again and
again to the same level of
consciousness, you learn how to
acclimate. You learn how to stay
conscious in this level of
consciousness and what was
previously a gap narrative you
fill in the gaps you get the
whole story that's being taught
you and my experiences we are
taught consistently being tried
something. Was trying to teach
me certain things that bring me
back over and over and over
again until it was sure that I
understood those things. So it
is work. And I think processing
the sessions is work. I mean, I
developed a strategy for how to
capture and how to capture these
experiences, so much so that I,
you know, there's a little line
in the book which I say, I think
ineffability is overrated as a
measure of mystical experience.
You know, it's part of our test
whether it's a genuine mystical
experience, whether it's
ineffable. And I understand
that, but I basically think that
if you can't say where you've
been, you basically just got
lost somewhere away. And there's
nothing wrong with getting lost,
but ineffability, I understand
it is, it's hard, but if you
really work it hard, you should
be able to find words of being
able to describe it. Remember
that the Zen masters don't have
trouble talking about
enlightenment to other Zen
masters. They can talk about it
just fine. They have trouble
talking about it to people who
have not had the experience.
That's when it becomes
challenging, right? So we can
find words for these things. It
inevitably, it's, you know,
they're inadequate, but we can
find words, you know, I don't
know. I'll just mention also to
this condensation process I did
account not too long ago. I have
about 400 words, 400 pages of
notes from my sessions. I The
passages that I actually include
in the book are less than 25%
three quarters of the content I
did not include, partly because
they're repetitious and whatnot.
I really try to pick the most
powerful passages, but there was
a lot left out. Yeah,
Tom Habib: Bruce in one part, I
think about two thirds way to
the book you touched upon
preparing ourselves to receive
the transmissions. I don't think
you were talking about under the
LSD. I think you were talking
about a normal existence. Am I
right on that? Point. And could
you say something about
preparing to receive them? I
assume there's being able to
read the deeply subtle, being
open to that
Chris Bache: how subtle it is
and what form it takes depends
upon the form of practice we are
doing, and as we open to these
realities. So anything I say
really would pertain just to my
individual situation, not to the
pattern as a whole.
I think we know what
transmission is about when we're
talking about it with a
spiritual teacher. And you know,
in the Tibetan tradition, they
give a practice in three
different levels. The first
level is they teach the
mechanics of the practice. The
second level, they teach the
meaning of the practice. But the
third level, the most important
level, is the transmission of
lung, the seed energy of the
practice. You receive a seed
from the teacher who has already
brought the practice to maturity
in their own being, and when
they give this lung, they're
transmitting a distilled essence
of the practice that you then
water and nourish in your
practice. So that's my con, my
context for thinking about
transmission, and I think this
kind of is true for my
psychedelic context, and that
is, I was put through enormous
purification processes in order
to receive the teachings that
came from these levels of
consciousness. And if I'm right
that there is a certain parallel
between what we do on our
cushion and what takes place in
a psychedelic session and what's
happening historically, then it
supports the intuition that I
have, that we are experiencing a
shift in divine influx, so to
speak with there is a rise in
energy coming up underneath us.
There is more information
becoming available, not only at
the physical level, through the
internet and all this tremendous
impact there, but at the center
of our being, there are
teachings and insights and
understandings which are rising
up inside of us, which we can
catch. But to catch them, we
have to prepare ourselves to
receive them. You know, we must
prepare ourselves and empty
ourselves of everything which is
small in order to catch pieces
of that which is large coming to
us. And so I think transmission
is a larger, broader category.
Unknown: Yeah, yeah, you're
reminding me that that the when
you get initiation, in my
tradition, I got to visualize it
as, like, there's a kind of a
silver tube that's kind of going
into me, and it's like there are
certain things kind of flowing
into me, and then I end up
basically just being like a
small little reservoir of a
thing out of which certain
amount can come and my guru is a
giant reservoir, You know, of a
lake or whatever, during saying
where I might be just this
little bottle, you know, but,
but what's beautiful about what
you're talking about also? And
then I would like to just point
out the humility of saying that
you don't think it maybe applies
to everything else, but the
things that you're saying so
closely resemble my own that I
might want to disagree with you
on that, but I understand the
humility of saying it like that.
So thank you.
Chris Bache: Okay, yeah,
Unknown: I was curious. Um, I
had a phone call with a there's
a gentleman, Simon Dwan. I found
an article of his in Scientific
American magazine. He was
writing about, like, oh, he
doesn't think the scientists
will ever figure out if reality
is a simulation or not, but I
feel like, from my perspective,
like I know it is, and I'm
curious, like, if the idea, I
don't know if you saw the movie
The Matrix, if you have any
thoughts related to these kind
of things,
Chris Bache: well, that's A
pretty popular theme in sci fi
isn't the simulation and the
complexity that we're living.
And quantum theory is telling us
that everything we see in the
visible world is underpinned by
this in this larger, subtle,
real quantum reality. Now 95 96%
of reality is dark energy and
dark matter. So that's telling
us over and over again, that
what we're living is not the
whole of what's what's real. And
to me, physical reality, it
could be described as the skin
on an apple, you know, and it's
and the apple grows the bigger
the skin gets. The universe is
like. Like that. It gets bigger
and bigger. But when you can,
when you fall underneath the
level of time, space, reality,
fall deeper into it. You're
falling deeper into the apple,
toward the center of the apple,
and in the center of the apple,
of course, it's all light, even
physical reality is composed of
light. But at the center of the
apple is most radiant,
beautiful, extraordinary light
brilliance in so I think this
idea that there is a larger
reality out there that
structures and informs and
receives this reality, then
after that, then our psychology
takes over. And so do we see
that reality as threatening? Do
we see that reality as demanding
or manipulative? Do we see it as
a dark and hostile reality, or
do we see it as a beautiful,
magnificent co creating reality,
you know, and my experience is
that the mother universe is
extremely so, so creative, so
intelligent, so wise, so loving
and compassionate. And of
course, you just looking at time
and space. If you want to see
the wisdom of life or the little
or the compassion of life, you
have to look very, very deep,
because if you look on the
surface, it doesn't look wise
and it doesn't look compassion
and it doesn't look lovely, it's
a mean ass son of a bitch. But
you have to step back and step
back and step back and look deep
in order to really see the
wisdom that's built into this
amazing laboratory that we're
part of, of growing the human
experiment, yeah,
Unknown: sorry, fascinating,
yeah,
Chris Bache: sure is, isn't
Unknown: it? Yeah, Chris, I'm
not sure how to draw this up. I
you. I'll speak for myself, some
of the experiences I had in like
the first time was I took nine
months, dropped out, just
meditated several hours a day.
Then what? Two years later, I
did it for six months. And some
of the experiences I had were so
mind blowingly profound that in
loving that I was I was just
left sobbing, sobbing and bliss
doesn't isn't a word that really
covers it. It just experiences
up. Just never had, never could
imagine I would ever have Yeah,
and they just left me words
Yeah, like, just a pool of
sobbing wonderfulness, yeah,
just, and I just know that you
had a lot of those experiences.
It wasn't just all rational, oh
yeah, that, oh yeah. This opened
up into that. And did it? No,
it's like some of these ones
that showed up in front of you.
It's like, oh my god. I mean,
just no words for it. No
language, no.
It's like, you're giving words
for this stuff. It just, yeah,
yeah.
Chris Bache: It's like when the
universe's heart touches your
heart, it just explodes it into
the most magnificent,
dimensional radiance that it
just just there's nothing to do
except have a good cry of joy.
It's just so joyful. It's just
so extraordinary. And that's
why, you know, the word that I
give in the book for the
universe, in this way, is my
beloved, because contact with it
was so overwhelming. It became a
love affair. I mean, it really,
I talked about the rumpled
sheets where we made love. It's
a love affair, and it's it does
it inspires such a hunger for
it, this eternal hunger that's
in our being, not only to
reunite, but to bring that
reality, to experience it
wherever we are right now, right
here. It's so deep. It just,
it's a it's a heartache. To be
separated from it, even for a
day, and to touch it is just
joy, just joy in the body, joy
in the heart and mind.
Unknown: And it's in it's more
than a worldly joy. You know,
because we all humans, you know
we can experience joy in our
daily lives and. Maybe not every
day, but you know what I mean,
yeah. And these were experiences
that were, I'm a pretty
articulate guy and like that, I
had such difficulty being able
to put into words some of these
experiences, yeah, other than
just like the your knees
collapse, I wasn't standing at
the time that these were
happening. But just like these,
knee buckling, Soul buckling,
Mind Blow, line, mind blowing.
Not even know how to, knowing
how to be with it, other than
just you can't not be with it.
You can't be with you. Just
there. It's happening. Yeah,
it's an overwhelm in terms of
what the mind can make sense of.
And it's in it's wonderful in
the highest sense, pure, clean,
clear. And you can't capture it.
You cannot capture it. You can't
bring it back. At least for me,
I had to leave it there. I
didn't know how to bring it
back. And just what gives me
justification to want to keep
evolving expanding, be it
through your model or anybody's
model that's about being an
evolutional being of
consciousness, there's such
anchoring experiences that I
can't ignore them in terms of my
daily life anyhow,
Chris Bache: yeah, and no one
could ever talk you out of them.
Unknown: Yeah. I mean, that's
just, it's like, you go where I
went then try to talk me out.
Yeah, exactly yes.
Tom Habib: But isn't it
interesting that at the moment
of that type of joy. We touch
sadness too.
Unknown: I don't experience.
Tell
Tom Habib: me about that. Tom
Well, I know in therapy, like
when, when somebody reaches a
level of intimacy and they start
crying, it's this deep hunger
and absence they've had for so
long. Yeah, and so in the midst
of joy, there's actually
sadness. When you two were
talking, I could feel that
cosmic hunger to know the mind
of God, and when you get a
glimpse of it, I think it's the
same thing. It's kind of good
because there's a humbling awe
going on that moment. And it's
almost like it's saying to you,
you haven't seen anything yet. I
know you said that there's so
many worries a couple times.
Unknown: This also reminds me of
the book Quantum Questions that
Ken Wilber wrote about how, you
know, all the writings of the
guys who did the work on quantum
mechanics were all very sciencey
beforehand, and they were all
very mystical afterward. And it
seems to me that what you did
was actually examine paradox at
a kind of cosmological level,
whereas they were kind of
looking at it in a I think the
expression that I use in the
breakout room is you were
looking at it through a
telescope, and they were looking
at through a microscope, you
know. And so they like, there's
a you can see the infinite in
either direction, you know. And
I've had some mushroom trips
where I've had, like, a Taurus
like thing, and I've got it was
literally Ken Wilber in the
middle talking to me about what
was going on on both ends of
that thing. Do you know I'm
saying it's like as the, my, my,
you know, Avatar of Vishnu, or
whatever, you know, to explain
to me was all going on. So it's,
it's really interesting to see
your book in light of having
already read Kant impressions.
There's a lot of parallels
there.
Yeah, it's interesting.
Chris Bache: Well, folks, it's
approaching 930 on my time, and
I haven't seen my wife all day,
and she's just come back while
we were doing a talk here. I
think I need to go be a good
husband for a while, how much I
enjoyed our time together.
Really appreciate the
invitation. Appreciated our
discussion a great deal. I hope
to see many of you at the
conference in May, and when
you're there, please introduce
yourself in you know, track me
down. I'd love to see you there
Tom Habib: and you're welcome.
Okay, Chris, I'm Chris.
Unknown: Thank you, Chris, yeah,
thank you everybody. Thank you
my heart. Thank you bye, bye
everybody. Thank you Tom Bye
For further information,
including upcoming events,
resources, links to our Facebook
and meetup pages and our
fabulous donate button. Please
visit our website at San
diegointegral.org donations are
greatly appreciated and help us
to continue to provide
information and connection
within the integral community.
You.