Steve Thayer: Steve Thayer,
welcome back to psychedelic
therapy frontiers, the podcast
devoted to exploring the
frontiers of psychedelic
medicine and what it takes to
cultivate a healthy mind, body
and spirit, as always,
psychedelic therapy frontiers is
brought to you by Numinous. I'm
Dr Steve Thayer, and today my co
host, Dr Reed Robinson and I are
joined by Dr Christopher Bache,
PhD. Chris is a professor
emeritus in the Department of
Philosophy and Religious Studies
at Youngtown State University,
adjunct faculty at the
California Institute for
integral studies, Emeritus
fellow at the Institute of
Noetic Sciences and on the
Advisory Council of Grof legacy
training. He's the author of
several books, but the one that
prompted us to reach out to him
for this interview is LSD and
the mind of the universe, an
account of what Chris
experienced and learned from 73
high dose LSD journeys that he
embarked on over the course of
20 years. In today's
conversation, we explore Chris's
LSD session protocol, the
difference between using
psychedelics for what he calls
cosmological exploration versus
spiritual enlightenment or even
psychological healing. Talk
about how Chris processed and
integrated his very intense
experiences, what he learned
about reincarnation, evolution
at the collective and individual
levels, what humans need to do
to survive the mounting
existential threats we face.
What he means by Diamond
Luminosity and diamond soul, and
of course, much, much more,
Chris's book had a profound
impact on me. His disciplined,
scholarly approach to
psychedelic exploration,
combined with his ability to
articulate and teach what for
most of us would be an
overwhelming or ineffable
experience has resulted in a
must read, in my opinion, for
anyone who thinks deeply about
questions like, Who are we? What
are we doing here, and where we
might go from here? If you've
ever listened to an episode of
psychedelic therapy frontiers
and thought to yourself, you
know, I wonder where I could
find good training on how to use
psychedelics in a clinical
practice. Well, wonder no
longer. Numinous has several
excellent psychedelic therapy
training programs. Click on the
link in the show notes, or go
directly to numinous.com forward
slash hour, dash training, dash
selection, and use the code PDF
10 for 10% off selected
trainings. You hear Reed and I
talk a lot about the psychedelic
clinical trial work that
Numinous does, if you or someone
you know is interested or might
be interested in being a
participant in a psychedelic
clinical trial, you can click on
the link in the show notes, or
go directly to numinous.com
forward slash research to learn
about the trials we're currently
running. If you'd like to
support the show, you can do so
by leaving us a rating and
review in places like Apple
podcasts or Spotify if you're
watching on YouTube, please
click the like button subscribe
to the channel or share the
episode with somebody you think
might enjoy it. Please enjoy our
conversation with Dr Chris
Bache. Welcome back, folks to
psychedelic therapy frontiers.
Reed and I are very honored
today to be joined by Dr Chris
Bache, Chris, thank you so much
for joining us.
Chris Bache: It's a pleasure to
be here with you today. So why
don't
Steve Thayer: we just start
Chris by introducing yourself to
our audience, and you can, you
know, share as much or as little
as you'd like, just to give us
some context,
Chris Bache: well, I'm a
professor, retired professor of
religious studies. I've made my
living teaching in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies in Youngstown
State University, which is a
state university in Northeast
Ohio. So my what brings me to
this program, I guess, is the
book that I published three
years ago called LSD in the mind
of the universe, which is a
strange book for a professor of
religious studies to have
written. So my story is that
right at the very beginning of
my academic career, 1978 I just
finished my graduate work at
Brown in philosophy of religion,
and I met the work of Stan Grof,
and I immediately recognized
that his research and LSD
psychedelics in general were
extraordinarily important, not
just for clinical psychology and
for therapy, but for philosophy,
which was what interested me the
most. And so I began, even
though it was illegal, I began
of quiet, private psychedelic
practice, which ended up
continuing for 20 years. I
worked for four years, I then
stopped for six years for
reasons I described in the book,
and then I worked for another 10
years, and then I spent another
10 years digest. This is from 79
to 99 when I was 50 to 30 to 50,
and then I spent the next 20
years digesting those
experiences, trying to absorb
them, trying to extrapolate and
clarify the cosmological
implications of those
experiences. And that's. And
then I published LSD in the mind
of the universe. So that's kind
of a brief sketch of what brings
me here.
Steve Thayer: Yeah, it's an it's
and I remember, as I was reading
your book, I was thinking, what
a heroic undertaking. I don't
know if heroic is a word that
lands for you, Chris, but I mean
heroic in the sense of a hero's
journey, the things you describe
in the book, the experiences
that you had, not for the faint
of heart, and I've heard you say
that you don't necessarily
recommend the protocol, the
things that you did to others,
and I was curious as to why.
Chris Bache: Well, first, let me
describe the protocol. First,
everything I did was within a
strict therapeutic protocol. I
followed Stan's protocols from
his book, LSD psychotherapy, so
traditionals, lying down, eye
shades, earphones, listening to
very carefully choreographed
music to guide the session. I
was always, always in private,
always protected, always with a
sitter, who was my wife at the
time, who was a clinical
psychologist, so established in
what I call the psychedelic
Kiva. And, you know, a Kiva of
spiritual practice, for reasons
that we can go into, but we
don't need to. I chose to work
with very high doses of LSD.
After about three sessions, 250
micrograms, I chose to work at
500 to 600 micrograms, which is
the upper limit. It's, it's the
body saturation point. And
naively, I was thinking at the
time that this work was about
personal transformation, even
personal spiritual awakening.
And all the spiritual literature
described one's karma ultimately
as finite, even though it may
involve, you know, causation
patterns from multiple
incarnations, but ultimately
it's finite. So I thought that
this therapeutic work is a
process of clearing the
conditioning of my of my psyche,
and essentially engaging and
clarifying and purifying karma.
And I thought if I worked with
large doses of LSD, I could
basically go through this faster
if I could manage the intensity
of the work, essentially taking
bigger bites of karma in every
session. Well, I found out down
the road that all those
assumptions I was making were
wrong. This work was not about
personal transformation, not
working at this high dose level.
If you're working with a gentler
psychedelic or in lower doses,
then the activation and the
purification and the healing
that would take place might be
constricted or to personal
levels. But if you're working
with a very powerful
psychedelic, like this much LSD,
you basically amplify
consciousness so deeply that
what may have begun as a
personal transformative process
becomes engaged in collective
processes that having to do with
the collective unconscious, the
species mind. And from there
you're off to the races into
deeper and deeper levels of
consciousness, cycles of death
and rebirth, not just ego, death
and ego death is the first of
many deaths that you face on
this journey, but as you go
through one level of
consciousness after another,
systematically, you go Through
many forms of death that are
more foreign, perhaps, than ego
death. So that's that's why I
don't recommend the protocol,
because it's an extremely
demanding protocol. It takes a
lot of it basically becomes the
center focus of much of your
life, just to engage these deep
states, to navigate them, to
absorb them and integrate them
into your life, and integrate
them into your your social life,
and into your body. If and I
also, I thought that there was
an end point to this journey.
You know, one of my false
assumptions. Was the reason for
doing this work was to get
somewhere, to get to
enlightenment, or to become one
with God, or to enter into the
primal void of existence. And I
had all of those experiences,
and I discovered that there were
many levels of divinity that one
can enter into communion with.
And there were even many levels
of the of the pure void, of the
fertile void. And about, oh, 15
years into my experience, I had
a particular experience when I
was as deep into the universe as
I would ever go deep. To what I
call the diamond Luminosity
domain, and I had an experience
that I saw reality far, far into
the distance which and the beam
of light hit me from that
reality, and it shattered me. It
just shattered me. And I was in
a very high and subtle state of
consciousness, and that's when I
realized it's an Infinite
Journey. You'll never get to the
end of the universe. The
universe is just too vast. The
depth of the divinity is just so
great. So now that, if I were to
start this journey over again, I
would be much gentler with
myself. I'd work with gentle I
balance low dose, high dose,
organic psychedelics, synthetic
psychedelics, because now I
understand that the real goal of
this work is to open yourself to
let in as much of the love and
intelligence and wisdom of the
universe as you can into your
system, and then to digest it
and hold on to it and draw it
into your life and let it guide
you. And it's not about getting
to some final destination
Reid Robison: that's beautiful.
Chris, thank you for for
sharing. I'm so many questions
come up, but one thing I wanted
to ask along those lines is,
what do you think the risks are
of going straight to those
higher deep states, like going
to the higher doses and perhaps
bypassing some of the healing
work or the lower dose work? Is
there a little more you can
share on how you might use those
two different dose ranges as
tools? Yeah.
Chris Bache: Well, first of all,
any work with psychedelics,
especially if you're working
with higher doses in a
therapeutic protocol, any work
with psychedelics can be
challenging, and therefore calls
for good psychological screening
to make sure that you have a
psyche that's ready to engage
these deep levels. As you know,
there are some people who should
never go near psychedelic
psychedelics, and there are some
people who should really work
very gently with psychedelics,
if they work with psychedelics
at all. I happen to have a
constitution that can become
large or can flow into expansive
states pretty readily and
congeal pretty readily and
smoothly at the end of the day,
not everybody is wired like
that. And so it's, you know, all
the cautions have to be taken,
all the clinical you know,
criteria have to be met for this
type of work. Now, if you work
with high doses, you can bypass,
I mean, you can get into
situations where you can chase a
particular level of experience
and bypass but that wasn't that
didn't happen to me. It wasn't
part of my work. I spent the
first 10 sessions and two and a
half years in very grueling kind
of work with in what Stan calls
the perinatal level of a level
of consciousness, the interface
between your personal
unconscious and the collective
or Transpersonal, personal
consciousness. So it's you know
you're You're reliving your
birth. You're dealing with all
sorts of existential crises.
You're really grinding things
very deeply at that level. Now I
will say that late in my
sessions, rather late. I mean,
15 years down the road. I mean,
there was lots of personal
healing that took place along
the way. Don't get me wrong.
There were personal healings
that took place in those first
10 sessions, and other down the
road. Often they would take
place at the beginning and
ending of my sessions, if I
would, when I was leaving space
time and when I was coming back
into space time. Because when I
was working in the peak of the
sessions after about, you know,
the first two or three years of
work, I was working in states of
consciousness that were far
beyond my personal consciousness
and far beyond space time even.
But along the way, you know,
packaged around the areas, there
was lots of healing at different
parts. And late in the sessions,
there was some very quick
healings of pieces of my life.
And I think if I had been
working with lower doses, those
healings would have taken place
earlier. But I found that in my
particular instance, I don't
think it was because I was
jumping over. Any problems, or
was not willing to confront any
problems, because the things you
confront at the deep levels of
the psyche are much, much more
severe than anything that you
confront at the personal level
in the psyche. And I want to say
that, you know, I came into this
work, I wasn't carrying any
personal trauma, I had a pretty
easy start in life. I had good
parents, good good home
environment, nothing more than
the ordinary push pull in a
family. And so there wasn't a
deep wound that I took into this
work, other than the deeper
wound is really the wounds that
everybody, every human being,
carries when they enter time and
space. That is the wound of
stabilizing within time and
space and understanding why we
are here. What is the whole
purpose my existence in this
domain? And can I? Can I
discover what my reason for
being here is, and can I enter
into communion with the
intelligence that I believe
saturates all existence? So in
my particular case, I what I
found was that, and I have to
say this carefully for someone
who doesn't know my work. It may
sound grandiose, and I apologize
for that, but I found that my
personal wounds were not kind of
healed until late in my work,
because it was my personal
wounds that anchored me in the
larger fields of consciousness
in such a way that it allowed me
to accomplish, or to be used to
accomplish, some of the healing
of the collective psyche that
took place in my work. And that
is I it's like the way I
describe it in the book, my
personal wound anchored one side
of a bridge and the other side
of the bridge was the collective
psyche. And by having that
bridge, when I went deep into
awareness consciousness, it
allowed my sessions to become a
conduit to pull some of the pain
of the collective psyche out of
the collective psyche and to
transform it. And if my personal
wounds had been healed early on,
that ability to do that would
have been compromised. And what
I learned along the way is that
this function, this specific
function, to engage the
collective psyche in a way, to
bring a certain measure of
healing to it was part of my
soul's work. It was something
that I kind of signed up for in
this incarnation. And I think,
personally, I think there are a
lot of people who are doing this
type of work and have signed up
for this type of work. I don't
think is anything special or
unusual about my choice to do
this work. It is,
Reid Robison: from our
perspective, a very brave hero's
journey, as Steve mentioned
earlier when we were chatting,
but, but I'm also curious about
that disposition you mentioned,
because it comes into play in
people we work with, and a lot
of questions we get. How much of
it do you think is nature versus
nurture? How much can you
cultivate as an ability to
expand and hold those states
without, you know, shattering
into overwhelm or getting
discombobulated, wondering if
you have some thoughts on that,
Chris Bache: I'm I'm sure you, I
mean, I know we can learn how to
enter these states more
skillfully. Some people have a
natural aptitude for moving into
them, but whatever the level of
aptitude is, we practice in
these states, and we enter into
them carefully. And if you enter
carefully and process carefully
and debrief carefully, we can
learn how to enter these states
better in future, in future
sessions, I really think
integration and very careful
debrief, careful recording of
your session after it's over,
processing it really sitting
with the content of it is really
important, because it
establishes the baseline for
your next entry into your non
ordinary state. And so it's like
a cycle, and integrating your
work as you could hold is really
important to the next step in
your work. Now I want to mention
that in my work, particularly
since it was being it was being
driven by such highly amplified
states of consciousness. So in
my work, I kept as many
variables stable as possible. So
for all these sessions, I worked
in the same sentence, setting,
same substance, same dose, same
sitter, same recording process,
even the same part of the
country, because any of these
variables can change some of the
texture, and that's not bad to
change the texture, but by
standardizing the variables, I
think it created a container
which allowed my conversation
with the universe and my
communion with the universe to
progressively deepen deep get
deeper and deeper over time. So
by stabilizing the content, the
contact, the zone of contact I
made with the universe, it
allowed the deepening to take
place. Now, of course, what kind
of communication or contact we
have with the universe partly
depends upon the headroom of the
psychedelic that we're using.
And all psychedelics, you know,
Psilocybin, Ibogaine, MDMA,
five, MEO, DMT, LSD, they all
have certain qualities of how
they engage consciousness, and
they have a certain spectrum, a
range of engaging. And I think
one of the reasons I kept
breaking through over 20 years
one level of consciousness after
another had to do with holding
the posture, holding the
setting, but also with the sheer
power of the psychedelic that I
was using, if I had been working
with say Psilocybin, I'm sure my
experiences would have
overlapped a great deal, but I
don't think it would have had as
much headroom, cosmological
headroom, as working with LSD
did.
Reid Robison: And how did your
your wife then feel about the
trip sitting duty, that's kudos
to her on the dedication for
that role as well. Was it hard
to hard to convince her to do
that? Or was she kind of with
you in this purpose of the the
philosophical adventure?
Chris Bache: Carol did this out
of love for me. She was never
particularly drawn to working
with psychedelics. They were too
much too fast. In her opinion.
She's a deeply spiritual person,
and we eventually, after 24
years of marriage, we separated,
and she has got we're friends,
and we stay in contact with each
other and with our children,
particularly around our
children. She has gone on to
complete her three year, three
month retreat in the vadna
tradition. So she's a serious
practitioner, and she has a deep
spiritual orientation. It's been
it's lifelong, and it was a
tremendous value to me to have
her spiritual wisdom grounding
me while I entered into this
work. But it was never her work,
and she did it because she knew
I wanted to do it, and we always
supported each other in our
spiritual paths.
Reid Robison: That's really
neat. No thanks for sharing all
this.
Steve Thayer: Yeah, Chris, I'm
I'm really captivated by the the
very scientific like approach
that you took, or at least a
very careful and deliberate and
disciplined approach. And the
way I imagine it is by
controlling for those variables,
you were able to return to maybe
the same drill site and just
sort of auger down and get this
very, very deep core sample of
the cosmos. You know, very, very
deep core sample of the
universe. And you know, as it
manifested in you, and you
manifested in it, as opposed to
what some Psychonauts or people
who are approaching psychedelics
for therapeutic or spiritual
exploration purposes do, where
they just sort of pockmark the
surface by not paying close
attention to set and setting, or
they're experimenting with many
different types of of
substances,
Chris Bache: yeah, yeah. I think
that's I think that's true
there, of course, there's no
right or wrong way to use
psychedelics. There are so many
ways of using them, and many
good ways of using them. So I
just happened to represent one
particular strategy. I was
trained as a philosopher of
religion. I have a natural
orientation towards precision
and analysis, and so
particularly since I wasn't
didn't fully know what I was
getting into, I wanted to leave
breadcrumbs in case I needed to
work my way back out again. It
turns out that was a that was
not a needed concern. I'm sorry
I'm losing my train of thought
here a little bit.
Steve Thayer: Well, no, I have,
I guess I have a follow up
question here, Chris. Because.
Yes, as a trained philosopher of
religion, I think I've read, if
not in the book, it might have
been in the post script that you
wrote for paradigm explore that
you know you when you started
approaching this work, you might
have described yourself as an
agnostic, sort of atheist,
leaning agnostic. Yeah, and I'm
curious to hear how your belief
in or relationship to the Divine
changed, if at all, as a result
of your experience with this
substance and this protocol.
Chris Bache: Well, you know,
basically through all the
Graduate Studies and I went
through, I basically studied my
way out of religion entirely,
and out of theism, and out of
any belief in the divinity as I
had learned it by studying world
religions and the history of
theology and philosophy. And so
I began this work as as not just
an agnostic, but an
atheistically inclined agnostic.
It was like, Okay, you're going
to put up or shut up on this
one. Because right now it's, it
doesn't look good. I mean, my
the whole, I think science has
just gone through and wiped out
anything, any thing that smacks
of traditional religion, because
the God of the religions of the
Axial Age, that deity is just
too small for the universe that
science is showing us is, is
here just the massive scale and
scope and intelligence of it.
And, you know, it's just, I
think it just erased the
Blackboard, and we're still
catching up with this erased
Blackboard. So I brought a mind
that was not adverse to
religion, but was adverse to
theology in a way, and but when
you begin to have experiences of
the reality that the religions
have been talking about, well
that changes everything very
quickly, so that when one goes
does this work? And you go
through cycles of death and
rebirth, and you go through this
process of losing your reality
or surrendering your reality as
you have known it, inside time
and space. And you go through a
death of that reality and a
rebirth. You wake up in another
level of reality, another
dimension of existence, and you
do that again and again in a
systematic way. Then the reality
of the reality of a reality
beyond space and time, just
becomes overwhelmingly clear and
true to you, and your ability to
understand it and to absorb it
and to taste it becomes second
nature. Now, in all the years I
did this work, and all the
levels of consciousness I went
through, I never encountered
anything that might be
recognized as a deity or even a
personal spiritual guide, which
is pretty common in many
shamanic traditions. But I
always felt myself to be
engaging an intelligence that
was essentially guiding my
experiences, or kind of feeding
these experiences to me in an
interactive, participatory
manner. And this this
consciousness, boundaries of
this consciousness, kept
deepening the deeper my practice
when in that context, I could
speak about God, but I don't
really like to, because God has
so many connotations in the West
that I'm not comfortable with.
And you I could speak about
divine, divinity, but that's
just kind of smuggling in, you
know, through a side door. So I
tend to speak about the creative
intelligence of the universe,
because, in one way, a way of
understanding the scale and
scope of what I actually
experienced is to understand
that the universe has a mind the
and actually the universe arises
out of a mind. It arises out of
a consciousness, and it's always
sustained and nurtured, nurtured
by a more fundamental reality,
which you can call it spiritual.
You can call it dark energy,
dark matter, you know, but now
we know that 96% of the universe
is invisible, dark energy, dark
matter. So it's not that radical
to sort of suggest that there is
a reality behind physical
reality. I think all our
historical concepts of God have
been profoundly. Incomplete,
inadequate, and we are entering
a period of history where we're
basically going to be rewriting
that story. And I think
psychedelics have an important
role to play, because it lets
ordinary mortals, in a way, just
ordinary lay people, have first
hand contact with this vast
expanse of spiritual reality
that gives you experiences that
you know are the kind of
experiences that previously in
earlier generations, people
would have described as the
experience of God.
Steve Thayer: So Chris, who are
we in this story? You know, are
we, as others have stated, are
we sort of this, this, you know,
unique organization of molecules
that is the universe
experiencing itself. This, each
one of us a fractal, you know
that where the universe gets to
joy and experiencing itself in a
way that wouldn't have
otherwise. Like, what do you
think we are?
Chris Bache: I think you say it
pretty well. I think you know
this. That question has so many
levels to it, and it depends on
how we want to frame it going
in, we are clearly part of the
creative experiment that the
universe is. We are. We are an
aspect of it. We're not
separated from it. We are our
nature, our body, the cells of
our biology, arise out of this
evolutionary masterpiece. And
our mind, just as our body
derives from the universe. Our
mind derives from the universe.
Now, I know in our period of
history, we're taught that the
universe is a machine, and it
moves with the machine's
blindness, and it evolves
through random mutation and
genetic mutation and random
variation and screening by a
necessity, but that's just a
story that we've told, and it's
not been a bad story, but it's a
profoundly incomplete story,
because when you when you sink
down into the depths of your
mind, you drop eventually out of
your mind into deeper layers of
mind, into the species mind,
into the, you know, a solar
system or galactic mind. And as
you drop down into that, you
engage you, you find yourself
confronting or being dissolved
into an intelligence that is
just stunningly vast. I mean,
it's just a massive intelligence
and a depth of love and
compassion that's behind that
intelligence and and it's this
intelligence which is
manifesting the universe that we
experience. It's manifesting
itself. Ask the universe, and we
are fortunate enough to be cells
within this body of divine self
manifestation, fractally
embedded in it, so that our
story is part of its story, its
story is part of our story. Now
that's at one level, and then at
a deeper level, if we add
reincarnation into it. And of
course, that's an assumed in my
worldview, not because of faith,
but because of the empirical
evidence that we have a mass at
this point in time. My first
book was on reincarnation, and I
think that's just part of how
nature functions. We don't
really know how it came to
function this way, but nature
has found a way to fold learning
forward, not only at the species
level, in an eval in a broad
species evolutionary sense, but
it's found a way to fold
individual learning forward in a
way that I think reincarnation
is simply a higher octave of
evolution. And once we add
evolution of reincarnation into
the story, once we understand
that we are participants in this
evolving universe for not just
100 years, but for 100,000
years, then the plot really
thickens. Then we're looking at
the universe is intensely
involved in manifesting
galaxies, solar systems,
planets, life, self aware life,
and then evolving, reincarnating
life, that puts us on some type
of profound co footing with
creation, with existence, so
that we really are, our
evolution and its evolution are
really part of the same fabric,
human evolution, individual
evolution, they're really two
different aspects. Is of the
same process.
Steve Thayer: So if you'll
permit me, Chris, to just keep
pulling on this thread, because
it's one that's fascinated me
and preoccupied me, frankly, for
my entire life. I mean, this
notion of who we are in relation
to the universe. What is the
what is divinity? Because when
you when we're preoccupied with
the month, what feels like the
mundane, you know, mundane of
daily life, paying our taxes,
going to work, that kind of
thing. And we think of ourselves
as this, as I said before, sort
of this fractal piece of what
you describe as this practically
infinite intelligence, the
substrate of which it sounds
like is love. It causes me to
think like, Well, so are we,
have we always existed in some
way, shape or form, as an
individualized intelligence
related to this grant, this
grander one? Because when you
talk about reincarnation, it
makes me wonder, like, was
there, is there some continuity
to Steve Thayer that goes back
hundreds and hundreds of 1000s
of years that I just don't
remember, right? Or is it, each
time we're we're deconstructed
to our constituent parts and
reassembled with new parts and
and it's just sort of pieces
that move forward in time. What
do you think?
Chris Bache: Yeah, but you know,
we don't know the answers to all
the all the answers to those
questions. We don't really know
how reincarnation works. We
don't know what the physics of
reincarnation is. Even if we
have evidence, evidence that
reincarnation is a fact of
nature, we don't know the nature
of it, how it goes, how it
works. But it seems to be that
the universe is a learning
system, and reincarnation is a
part of a learning system. So
because our consciousness did
not begin with our body, but our
consciousness goes back farther,
we can then use a concept like
Soul, some type of concept that
holds and gathers the learning
from all of the incarnations
that we've experienced. How far
back does it go? Two questions,
how far back does it go? Right?
And the answer is, nobody knows
for sure. But all the cultures
that have believed in
reincarnation say it doesn't
start with human beings. It
starts before human beings. How
far before human beings? Well,
we're not really sure. Now my
sense is that it's it starts
when individuality begins to
emerge within the evolutionary
matrix. And I'll use the term
evolution frequently, as you
know, as you've heard, but that
and I believe in the concept of
progressive development, of
progressive unfolding, but that
doesn't mean I agree with the
kind of standard textbook theory
of what's driving reincarnation.
So when I use the term
evolution, I don't mean that
theory of that reductive
determinist theory.
It's about learning. How far
back does it go? Somewhere along
the way between grasses and
chimpanzees, it's hard to think
of individual blades of grass
having individual consciousness.
We usually think in terms of
broad classes, but somewhere in
the evolutionary process, an
individuality emerges, and as
that individuality emerges,
there's a learning that deepens
that individuality over time,
and that's when I think
reincarnation becomes possible.
Classically, they look to
animals that are well lower than
the mammalian change, but
somewhere around in somewhere in
the animal life form, but
wherever it emerges. The next
question is, what are we
underneath these evolved
changes? And I think the answer
to that is you have to get that
takes us down into a deeper
level underneath the soul. And
we ask, well, what is the
essence of the soul? What is the
essence of our individuality?
What's the essence that makes
this evolving individuality
possible? And there, I think we
we find the same answers in
psychedelic work that we find in
the classic mystical traditions,
classic high spiritual
traditions. And that is, the
essence of the individual is the
essence of the Divine. The
essence of the one is the
essence of the totality we are,
in essence derived from the
Divine sparks of the Divine.
We've been sort of teased out of
the unitive matrix of the
Divinity, and been given the
privilege of individuated
existence, which then is
polished and refined and deep
and over. 1000s and 1000s and
1000s of years of going back and
forth between spirit and matter,
spirit and matter, spirit and
matter, taking us onto a
developmental process. But the
essence of what we are is the
divine itself. The manifestation
of what we are depends upon how
long we've been cooking.
Reid Robison: That's
fascinating. And how you
mentioned karma earlier, how you
viewed it going into this work,
and suggested that maybe it
changed, but wondering how you
view karma now, in this, in this
broad perspective that you've
been sharing,
Chris Bache: it's simply as
cause and effect. You know, it's
karma, vipaka, cause and effect.
It's simply making it course the
universe pulses with cause and
effect right at all of its
levels. But here we're simply
talking about a substrate of
cause and effect, the causes
that are set in motion by the
exercise of our capacity to
choose. We make choices, we
inherit the consequences of
those choices. In that new
context, we make new choices,
and then we inherit the
consequences of those choices.
So if we've been smoking two
packs of cigarettes every day
for five years, we're not free
to not want that next cigarette,
but we are free to begin to set
in motion a series of choices
that can free us from that
addiction to those cigarettes.
So we're constantly making
choices. We inherit the
consequences of those choices.
One of the ways in which my
thinking has changed over the
years since writing life cycles,
my first book is that I have a
much deeper appreciation of the
synergistic relationship between
individual development or
individual karma and collective
development or collective karma.
I think that we have a tendency
in the West to over personalize
the concept of Karma, to really
kind of tell the story of the
individual soul in maturing over
many lifetimes and reaching
enlightenment or whatever. And I
think this our species is
evolving, pulsing every 100
years in reincarnation, and
there is a collective learning
process taking place, which our
individual learning process is
part of. And so the boundary
between collective learning and
individual learning is porous,
and I have much more respect or
sensitivity to the collective
karma that I had might have
previously seen as personal
karma.
Reid Robison: Yeah, wow. And
earlier you mentioned the role
psychedelics might be playing in
this kind of evolution of
consciousness these days, and
when we were talking about that
place between blades of grass
and chimpanzees, I'm wondering
what your thoughts are on
Terence McKenna's like stone day
hypothesis, and if that was an
example of The Universe between
spirit and matter, learning as
it evolved. And if you viewed
psychedelics as playing a role
in history as well,
Chris Bache: Terence is
hypothesis. There is
interesting, isn't it? Yeah, and
I don't have, I don't have an
opinion on that. I don't have
any particular, any new insights
to add to that, I hold it as an
interesting hypothesis. I don't
have any individual, any
independent way of assessing
that. Well, I just don't know.
Now. I do think that we are
coming to a turning point in
history. We are coming to a make
or break point in history, and I
think that psychedelics have a
significant role to play, and
they're giving us extra
awareness at a time when we
desperately need extra
awareness. They also are giving
us a form of accelerated and
deepening healing at a time when
we desperately need accelerated
and deepening healing. Because I
think that there is a tremendous
inner fermentation process
taking place, a tremendous
detoxification taking place at
the collective level as well as
an individual level, and it
manifests itself in our
individual lives in terms of
this kind of more up rushing of
content of karmic content of
conditioning, of pain and trauma
that we've been carrying in our
soul history. But I think this
has. Happening, not just to a
few select individuals who are
middle class able to attend to
this, but it's happening
underneath us, in our social
movements and underneath the
world at large. And I think
psychedelics by giving us an
amplified experience of our
consciousness and our
consciousness and the
consciousness that we are part
of it not only helps us heal and
helps us manage this
purification process, but it
also gives us a wider world
view, which it only takes, you
know, a one good, deep
psychedelic experience of
communion with the deep
structure of the universe to
shatter materialism, the
philosophy of that matter, is
the only thing that's real. I
think Huston Smith was right
that a mystical experience does
not a mystic make, but a
mystical experience can an
atheist unmake, you know, and I
think psychedelics have a very
important role to play in that
now. How far can will this go?
How deep will psychedelic
healing reach in our culture?
How fast, with these insights
realized under psychedelic
communion, change or contribute
to the paradigm shift that's
taking place, which is being
driven by multiple disciplines
right now. I don't know, but it
seems that you know the fact
that LSD was invented the same
decade that the nuclear bomb was
invented, and the nuclear bomb
has changed the order of global
order, I think, is maybe a
significant, significant
synchronicity.
Steve Thayer: So speaking of
this time in human development,
and as somebody who has really
dedicated his academic and
personal life to exploring what
it means to be human, I'm
curious to know if you have an
opinion on artificial
intelligence. You know, some
folks who talk about the way
psychedelics are helping us
learn who we are might be
really, really important, given
that we might be creating
something that is different, but
also conscious. I'm curious to
know if you have an opinion.
Chris Bache: You know, I don't
really have an opinion. People,
it has not come up in any of my
sessions. I, you know, I
finished my sessions in 1999
artificial intelligence never
came up in my sessions. I stand
on the sidelines as a lay
person, and kind of an old lay
person. I'm 74 years old, and
this is really a younger
generation's work. And I watch
what's happening in artificial
intelligence work just from the
edges, and I can see that it's
developing much faster than I
could possibly keep track of
personally, I'm concerned about
it, but clearly it's here. It's
happening now. It's going to
have huge impact on us in the
future. I don't know what role
it will play, whether it will be
a friend or an enemy over time.
I'm more concerned about the
ecological cliff that we're
going over, because this is very
we can extrapolate, and we are
getting a clearer and clearer
vision of how the imbalances
that we have generated in the
industrial era are beginning to
manifest with catastrophic
consequences, and the cumulative
effect of these ecological
crises, which are going to keep
hitting again and again until we
get on top of this, and we're
not anywhere near to beginning
to get on top of it. This is
turning the 21st Century, I
think, into a tremendous century
of tremendous global instability
and global unraveling and
crisis. So that, to me, has been
kind of focal point in my
thinking how artificial
intelligence plays into this, I
don't know.
Reid Robison: And on the
ecological front, how much of
that realization of the problems
that we face, how much of that
came from these psychedelic deep
dives and or how much of it is
just from kind of your
experience in life, and did you
get any insights, any any ways
you think psychedelics or the
expansion of awareness or
raising consciousness might help
us In our in a better path
forward?
Chris Bache: Well, let's hold
the second part of that question
of how psychedelics might help
us in a better path forward, and
let me address the first part of
it, because this was one of the
biggest surprises of my of my
work. I mean, first I had to let
go of the framing. Of my work is
personal journey, personal
transformation, personal
healing, personal awakening,
spiritual awakening. Get
involved in a much larger dance
with the species mind, with the
collective unconscious, being
catapulted from there into
levels of archetypal reality and
then being catapulted into
deeper, causal levels of
reality. And so I say this just
to mark that I understand that
what I'm about to say about
human where we are and where
we're going historically, will
sound outrageous and they will
sound highly speculative. But
when you my experience is very
simply, when you work very, very
deeply, way under, far
underneath the personal psyche,
dropping into the collective
psyche and into the creative
intent underlying evolution, the
evolution of our species. These
things come naturally into focus
in a way which make perfect
sense from a quantum paradigm or
a post Newtonian atomistic
materialist paradigm. So there's
a chapter in LSD, in the mind of
the future and the universe,
which is the birth of the future
human. And it's a chapter where
I gather together all the
experiences that took place in
my journey that bear on this
question, where is humanity
right now, and where are we
going? And it was one of the
complete surprise to me that
this came up in my sessions, and
this was a long this is a long
time ago, before I had any
ecological awareness, you know,
before I had absorbed the
information that we're all
absorbing today. These visions
took place between 1991 and 1995
so, you know, a long time ago, I
was completely naive about
hitting our environmental
limits, hitting our ecological
limits, the crisis that was
building in our culture. What
began to happen is tucked in
around the edges here and there.
I began to be given visions of
where humanity was in its
evolutionary saga. I began to be
given visions that we were
coming to a turning point, a
definitive turning point in
human history, an evolutionary
pivot. I began to be given
visions that we are entering a
magnificent period of human
history where there was just
tremendous blessings coming to
us, a period of profound
transformation, that the future
of humanity would be radically
unlike its present and its past,
and there was some fundamental
process that we were undergoing
that was taking us there. But
for the first three or four
years of this, I was given these
consistent visions of a future,
but was given no indication of
how we would actually get there.
How was nature going to pull
off? Because you look around us,
it doesn't look very positive.
Guys. I mean, you know, more
people are at the shopping mall
than they are in transformative
weekend workshops. Violence is
escalating. How? How are we
going to make this transition.
And then in 1995 in December of
95 when I was very far along in
my psychedelic work, I had
entered a stage of work that I
call the diamond Luminosity
material. So I was halfway
through years of work in this
very subtle, exquisitely sublime
diamond Luminosity work. And in
the middle of that in a rhythm,
when I was expecting to be taken
back into the diamond
Luminosity, instead, I was
dissolved into the species mind.
So and in that context, ask the
species, I went through a
process, or I experienced a
death and rebirth of the human
family. I experienced a profound
unraveling of life as we had
known it, a profound challenging
i
It's hard to describe this,
because most of our experiences,
we experience from within a self
referential point and and it
sounds ludicrous to say I
describe the death of humanity
as humanity, but I experience.
Is this tremendous building
crisis in the world and the
unraveling of people's lives and
the shattering of expectations
and the shattering of systems,
until eventually humanity was
reduced to the bare challenge of
survival. Just bare survival. It
was so deep it looked for a
while like it was going to be an
extinction event. It was a
global systems crisis, which
appeared to be driven by a
cascading series of eco crises.
I wasn't given any details
beyond that. I wasn't given any
timetable. I wasn't given any
sense of how this would happen.
I was just taken into this deep
cultural collective crisis, and
then just when it was at its
worst, we seemed to move through
this crisis, and when we began
to pick ourselves up on the
other side of this crisis. We
had been changed by this crisis.
We had been changed radically.
They had taken place an opening
of the human heart, an opening
of compassion, a profound change
in human we would say,
classically, in human nature. I
would describe it as a shift in
the fundamental structure of the
collective unconscious. What
we're looking at is what you
might think of it as, a shift in
the plate tectonics of the
collective psyche. When we move
through this crisis, as we began
to reassemble ourselves, the
entire world was saturated with
new values, new perceptions of
the good, new social
institutions. This was a huge
transformation of the human
heart. And then I was given many
instructions on the mechanisms,
how we would make through this,
make it through this crisis
faster than we would think
possible given given the space
at which history moves, and it
has to do with understanding the
function of the collective
psyche as a field. The the you
know, this is going on maybe a
little long, but the synopsis is
that the collective psyche is a
unified field, and this crisis
will be so severe, it will shove
not only individual psyches into
a non equilibrium, into an
highly altered state, but it
will shove the collective psyche
of humanity into a non
equilibrium, or far from
equilibrium condition. We have a
certain knowledge about how
physical systems, when they are
shoved into a non equilibrium
state, behave. We've learned
this from chaos theory a number
of different areas. There is a
sense in which I was shown that
the human psyche, when shoved
into a similar non equilibrium
state, will exhibit some of the
same characteristics, the
capacity for rapid change, the
emergence of new structures,
emerging from the floor of the
collective psyche, that small
iteration, small changes, can
produce dramatic outcomes the
net. The bottom line of this is
that we were going to be moving
through this crisis much faster
than we would think possible,
because of the severity and the
negative impact this crisis was
going to be having on lives all
Around the world subsequent
sessions in the years following,
I was given the experience
moving into deep time. Again,
it's moving beyond linear time,
experiencing what I call the
future human, experiencing the
archetypal form of humanity. And
I experienced this being. This
being is an extraordinarily
beautiful being, just a
magnificent being. This being
is, in some ways, as far beyond
us as we are, beyond our earlier
Homo erectus cousins, a being
with a massive heart, a healed
heart, an open mind. And not
just a transformation of our
heart and a transformation of
our mind that opens up all sorts
of possibilities, but actually a
transformation of our sensory
experience, we tend to have a
mechanical understanding of our
theory about how senses work,
but I was shown. I was given the
experience that the more
consciousness is consolidated in
our body, the more refined our
experience, our sensory
experiences can become. So I had
an experience at the very end of
my journey, of my vision. 100
times sharper than it is an
ordinary consciousness, and so
the same applies to our hearing
in all our other senses. So this
is a pivot of a radically
transformed human species, of a
radically opened heart,
radically open mind and a
radically augmented physical
capacity. All right, so I think
this is the story of our
century. This is the story of
the century that we're all
dealing with is, how do we make
this transition? How do we make
this pivot from our present
condition into our next
evolutionary form? And this is
what I call the birth of the
diamond soul. But I'll stop here
and give you a chance to ask any
questions.
Reid Robison: Well, one follow
up question on that last note,
but I definitely want to get
into the birth of the diamond
soul. But do any of as a
professor of religious studies
and just wondering if any of the
the ways certain religions or
philosophies view this line up
with what you're describing. I'm
thinking in particular of, say,
the Kali Yuga from Hinduism.
And, you know, 1000s of years
ago, the beginning of this dark
age and materialism and
corruption and the the ancient
sages or Rishis kind of retreat
into the the Himalayas or
wherever, but haven't
disappeared entirely. And then
kind of that, the turn of this
age into the Golden Age, or
Satya Yuga, you have the return
of wisdom, intelligence,
compassion. And I'm wondering if
any of those line up, or if you
apply any frameworks to help
understand this. From from your
other studies,
Chris Bache: in addition to the
ones you mentioned, we have a
number of Hopi prophecies. Of
course, there are a number of
indigenous cultures that have
been seeing this profound
transformation. They've been
talking about it for a long,
long time, and it's interesting,
and it does line up. I think the
general perception is that we
are, we are in a period of
darkness, but I would
conceptualize that darkness as a
period in which the conditioning
of the past, which is, you know,
kind of the karmic patterns
which shape the human psyche at
deep structural levels. We are
entering a period of infusion of
grace and infusion of energy,
which is driving, driving this
past to the surface of our
psyche so we can deal with it,
all the hatreds of history, the
divisions which we've carved in
the human psyche, which we've
carved on the planet, the
divisions of race, the divisions
of gender, divisions of
nationality, the divisions of
haves and have nots this all the
patterns of splitting the world
between in these categories are
being driven to the surface. And
they're all these toxicities are
coming out of us and have to
come out of us in order to make
make us available to the influx
of the divine energy which is
entering you can think of it as
entering us from above or coming
up within us underneath. But I
think there's something deeply
true about these ancient
prophecies, that we are, in a
sense, in the age of the Kali
Yuga, and we are coming into a
profound new age when it will
hit us, when we are how we will
get there, I don't know, but I
think there's a relation between
these prophecies.
Steve Thayer: It is something
that feels as I hear you talk
about it, Chris, it's something
that does feel very true. And I,
as a psychologist, you know,
I've been very curious about the
human psyche, and kind of, like
the questions I asked earlier
about who we are, have always
been on my mind, because when I
look at the human organism, I
see a being that is capable of
so much more than we currently
tend to produce, that is a
capable of great violence, that
is capable of fear and terrible
behaviors that are based on fear
but also capable of great
creativity and adaptation and
love and inclusion and
compassion were such a paradox
and I and as terrifying as it
sounds, the things that you
described, this sort of maturity
process, this next stage of
development, it does sound
necessary that we would need
some kind of crisis to I don't
know if the right word is force
or draw out this next stage of
our development. And I look at
my own psychedelic experiences
and those of my clients and
others that I've read about as
almost an exercise in
existential crisis, right? It's
almost like going through a
refiners. I are to to kind of
burn away the dross, so that the
purity of what you really are
can come forward. But, but back
to our conversation about
integration. I think because of
how intense that can be and how
confusing it can be, it can be
really hard to make use of in
sort of our imminent life,
right, day to day life.
Chris Bache: Yeah, it can. It
really can. What happens, I
think, is that once we get into
this work deeply, we suddenly
realize we're playing on a
different playing field than we
had thought we were playing on
before. And it's a lot, it's a
much bigger game that's afoot.
It's not about our own personal
life and personal
transformation, but we are
involved in historic processes
of enormous import. And so if
you're going to engage the deep
psyche, you're kind of going
into the deep end of the pool.
You're you're going into the
deep water. And the deep water
is moving very fast right now,
and there's a tremendous kind of
a bubbling taking place. And
everybody has a certain
tolerance for being able to
handle the complexity and the
intensity of what's taking place
at that very deep level. So when
we come back, we need to not
only record as carefully as we
can. What is the nature of our
visionary experience? But then
we really have to take care of
ourselves as we try to integrate
those experiences. I'll tell you
that it took me a year to
recover from that experience,
that session I told you about
the birth of the future human
that collapsed the death and
rebirth of humanity. It took me
about a year to really recover
from that and to sort of
stabilize that. And even then, I
mean, for for the years that
I've held that vision, you
really have to practice the arts
of grounding. If you're going to
go deep, you better be well
grounded in all levels,
physically, emotionally,
psychologically and socially
with your peer groups, because
it's a demanding process that
we're involved in now, my sense
is, before my understanding of
how reincarnation works is we
get to choose the life that we
incarnate in. We are given a
certain set of options of and we
sort of see what we're going
into if we choose the lives that
we're going into. And that
means, I think, that every
person here on this planet has
chosen to be here in the form
that they are, and that means
that all of us have chosen to
incarnate at this very demanding
time in history. We want to be a
player in this demanding time in
history from a spiritual
perspective. Well, let me back
up. Be careful on this. I don't
want to go too far, too fast,
but I think we all knew what we
were getting into when we
incarnated, and we chose to be
part of this process for our
benefit, for the benefit of our
children and our grandchildren
all around the world, and for
the development, for the benefit
of the Divine itself. Because
the Divine is working. I mean,
this is not something humanity
is doing. This is something
nature is doing. And whatever
the intelligence is that lies
behind and within nature that
that's doing.
Steve Thayer: You know, this has
always been a question I've had
about this notion of choosing to
incarnate, and if you'd rather
not go down this path, we don't
have to Chris, but you know the
idea that somebody would choose
to incarnate as as a baby born
with fetal alcohol syndrome, or
somebody would choose to
incarnate as a kid who was born
in the last year in some war
torn country or a place where
there was a lot of disease and
conflict? Yeah, again, if you'd
rather not try to tackle that,
it's okay. I know there are some
things we just don't have
answers to. But how does, how
does a reincarnation perspective
grapple with those realities?
Chris Bache: Yeah, in just
terrible, terrible suffering,
babies born without brain,
without neocortex, and in
cephalic children, babies who
born into violent circumstances,
destined to die after a very
short left life with terrible
pain. How can we possibly assert
that there is intelligence, let
alone compassion behind in such
a universe? And I think in order
to see the wisdom and to see the
intelligence, we have to look
very deep. We have to look deep,
and we have to look wide. I.
Because on the surface, life is
a mean son of a bitch, and life
is cruel and vindictive, and
it's as filled as decimated by
by circumstances that just crush
the human heart. From a
reincarnation perspective, the
awareness is that life did not
our life did not begin with
birth, and our life does not end
at death, that our life is part
of a larger story. Why one would
choose? Someone would choose a
life that involves so much
suffering is a, maybe an
impossible question to answer
from within, inside a time,
space perspective and from
within an individual, almost
centric perspective. In order to
perhaps glimpse some of the
larger patterns of life, we
really have to open up into a
very large perspective, an
evolutionary perspective, a
spiritual perspective. The
important that I think the most
important thing to be aware or
to understand is that all of our
suffering is preserved, is
conserved and use, and it's all
of our suffering. All human
suffering is experienced by the
Divine. There is no divine
outside of human suffering
watching us suffering, doing
something that's making it
possible or not possible. But
everything that humanity
suffers, everything that the
animal kingdom suffers, the
spiritual world suffers at a
very deep level.
Steve Thayer: So, yeah, I mean,
if we are the as we talked about
before, the universe
experiencing itself, it's not
just the people with awesome
lives that the universe is
experiencing, right? It's every
instantiation of the universe,
every life, the ones that suffer
and the ones that don't suffer
as much.
Chris Bache: And you know, and I
address this in life cycles,
human suffering brings us to our
knees, and I don't think we have
an adequate understanding or
explanation of it. In my
experience, when I have been
drawn into this larger overview,
and when I have experienced the
intelligence behind this
process, I have found myself
trusting beyond what I can
understand, and I trust because
of the quality of the of The
being that I encounter that's
behind these circumstances. So I
can't understand all the pain
behind all this, and I can, I
have, I can come up with any
number of kind of partial and
incomplete theories for how this
stuff works or how it goes, but
in the end, I think we're
ultimately brought to our knees
in trying to understand it
intellectually. But if you
experience the love and wisdom
of the universe, then it gives
us confidence that there truly
is a logic to it. And I want to
say, I want to the universe is a
hard task master. And you know,
if when you look at pictures of
Kali, the destroyer, you know,
and she is a liberator of of
brings about enlightenment, but
she brings death and destruction
in one hand and enlightenment at
the other, these things go
together. There is nothing
easier gentle about the love of
the universe or the love of the
Divine. It is a fierce, fierce
place that we are part of. It's
a very, very demanding world.
But the question is, does the
universe in a deeper sense, is
it paying attention to our pain?
Is it? Is there a way in which,
by engaging our pain as
conscientiously as we can, does
it lead to our own development
in the long term? And is the
universe listening to us as we
are in pain? And I think it is.
I think it is an intentional
process, even though I can't
answer your question
satisfactorily.
Steve Thayer: Well, it was a
beautiful answer, and I really
appreciate you taking it and
trying to answer that question,
Chris, because I certainly feel
like I'm on my knees, and I
think I read somewhere, maybe
this was yours or someone else,
but that the divine, as you've
described it, as something that
we can experience but not
necessarily comprehend. And that
concept has actually brought me
quite a bit of peace as somebody
who's, you know, a self
described truth seeker, really,
really wanting to understand
things, thinking that that would
give me some kind of assurance
that everything would be okay,
or help me understand what I
should do or shouldn't do, you
know, kind of at. Typical
experience of somebody who's
looking for for the answers, so
permission to not know all the
answers is quite comforting.
Yeah.
Reid Robison: And Chris, do you
have certain people you count as
teachers or like, your
philosophical and spiritual
perspective and leanings. Now
I'm thinking of that question
that, you know, I hope we can
get into next of, how does one
proceed on a path of exploration
like this? Wisely? What are good
preparatory, you know,
philosophies and spiritual
frameworks and systems to to
check out or try on, perhaps,
yeah,
Chris Bache: well, I had the
benefit of being a professor of
religious studies, and so I
spent a lot of My life, my
professional life, teaching
courses in comparative
mysticism, in Buddhism, in, you
know, introductory courses in
Eastern traditions and Western
traditions. And so I got to
study a lot of the masters and
learn their stories. And they
were always my kind of guide.
Post, the great masters, the
great spiritual beings, were
always even though my work was
not focused on spiritual
awakening, we haven't talked too
much about that, but still, the
great masters were my
touchstones, and I tried to hold
myself accountable to them As I
conducted myself in this unusual
spiritual practice. I indigenous
cultures. I have tremendous
respect for I have not
academically studied them. I
have a, you know, kind of a
layman's reading of a number of
books, and a respect for them.
And I really appreciate that
people who are undertaking this
type of work, it's very
beneficial to do it under the
tutelage of an experienced
teacher, of a guide, or someone
who can help them process what
they're experiencing. That
hasn't been my particular
destiny, my particular work.
I've never had a teacher. I've
never been advised by an elder
in a psychedelic community. In
this way, the only teacher that
I've personally had has been the
universe itself and and she has
been a fierce and a loyal, uh,
teacher. She's broken me down,
ground me up, spit me out, and
beat me severely, and she's also
helped me and blessed me and
loved me and taught me more
things than I ever imagined were
possible when we do this type of
work, it's foolish to do it
alone. These were my
circumstances, and I had the
constitution to survive it. And
I had the companionship of my
partner, who was a very wise,
spiritual woman, who helped keep
me grounded. And I had the
advice of the elders that I was
studying in my courses. For most
people, when we do this work,
it's dude. It's good to do this
work in groups. It's good to do
this work under the guidance of
someone who has more experience
in these states than we do,
because this is a new territory,
and when I say a guidance, I
don't mind someone who's guiding
our experiences, but someone who
can help us enter these states
safely, and someone who can help
us understand and process the
our experiences when we come
back out of that. And I think
it's important to have people
that we can talk to. This was
one of the burdens of my
particular journey, and that
because I was working in
isolation, because it was all
illegal, I could not bring it to
the office. I could not bring it
to campus. I could not talk to
my students about it. I'm a
teacher. I love to learn and
share, and I'm a gabber, so I
could not talk about this stuff.
And that's not a healthy way to
be. It's good to have community
that you can share your
experiences with and that you
can listen to other people's
experiences, and as that
experience grows, we know that
we're all in this together. We
really learn from each other as
we're going deeper into this. So
I think it's really important to
do this work in a responsible
way, with the guidance or
tutelage of people who have more
experience than you do, yeah.
Reid Robison: Oh, thank you for
that. And, and I know time is
whizzing by, as it tends to do,
but I'm just on the edge of my
seat dying to know if there's
anything you could share about
the birth of the diamond soul,
or however you put it, or that
second part. Of the the kind of
evolution and ecology of
consciousness or or where we
might focus our intentions on a
path forward.
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, about
halfway through my journey, in
the 38th session, in a year of
great blessings, it's just
enormous blessings I was taken
on experience that was preceded
with some very, very intense
purification processes, very
intense Death-Rebirth process.
And at one phase in this
journey, I had the experience of
all my former lives coming into
me. I mean, I had done past life
therapy before. I was familiar
with about a dozen of my past
lives. I'd already written the
book on reincarnation, so I was
comfortable with the idea of
reincarnation, but I began to
experience my former lives
coming into me. And it was like
winding a string a kite spool.
And what happened is they seemed
to hit a critical mass, and when
they hit a critical mass, they
fused. And there was there was
an explosion of energy, and all
of these separate lives fused
into one life. There was an
explosion of diamond light out
of my chest, and I was
catapulted into a state of
consciousness that was beyond
anything that I had realized up
to that point in time. I was an
individual, but an individual
beyond any frame of reference
that I had known before. And I
came and then I was given a
whole lot of teachings and over
and over again so that I would
understand what was happening,
and this came to be, it changed
my whole understanding of how
reincarnation works and where
it's taking us. The classic
understanding of reincarnation
in Eastern cultures is that you
know you incarnate, you make
some proof. You self challenge,
you make mistakes, you make
progress, but basically you get
better and better, stronger and
stronger, more compassionate
over time, until eventually you
reach some type of spiritual
realization, some awakening
experience, enlightenment
experience. And once you reach
that, then you're free to leave
the system of space time. So
it's an up and out cosmology.
And all the religions of the
Axial Age of last 5000 years,
they're all up and out
cosmologies. So you achieve
salvation, and then or you
achieve enlightenment, and then
the fruition comes in an off
planet, spiritual paradise. My
experience in my sessions, the
teaching I received in my
sessions is that that is not an
adequate description of what's
happening. That's a first stage
approximation that humanity made
when they began to have
sufficient depth of experiences
that they began to have contact
with spiritual reality. They
began to understand
reincarnation, but it's stopping
halfway. I think the what I was
shown in in my experiences, was
that humanity is not simply
evolving one lifetime after a
lifetime after lifetime, making
small, incremental improvements
in our quality of the souls
existence sooner or later. I
mean, we, sooner or later, all
of our lives, come together
inside our physical existence.
Now we die, we expand into the
soul. We incarnate into our
narrow, egoic experience. We
die, incarnate into the soul. We
incarnate in an individual
lifetime. We know the soul in
between our lifetimes. But if we
keep this incarnational rhythm
up long enough, and I have my
students sometimes do this as an
exercise for 15 minutes, we're
doing this each lifetime,
expanding out sooner or later,
the soul wakes up inside our
physical existence, and this is
what I call the birth of the
diamond soul. When the soul
wakes up inside our physical
existence, not only is there a
tremendous expansion of our
heart and mind, but it changes
our entire orientation. It it.
We focus on the long term
vision, the long term good, the
wide good. Because we have, in a
sense, an intuitive awareness of
all the hundreds of people,
1000s of people we've been in
relationship with through
history. We have been every
race. We've been every religion
through time, we've been up and
down the economic ladder. We've
had all the roles in history
possible that when all those
lives come together and wake up
into a singular consciousness,
it radically changes one's
perceptive perception of. What's
taking place, who we are, and
where we're going. I think this
when people ask, what form will
the future human take? And we're
exploring this with all sorts of
science fiction, you know, what
the form of the future human
will be, but I think it's really
much more simple than that. We
have been developing and
gestating the future human for
hundreds of 1000s of years
reincarnation, we've been
gestating the future human
through reincarnation for
hundreds of 1000s of years.
Gestation is long, labor is
short and intense. I think we
are entering a period of history
of labor, and I think we are
desperately trying to grow into
the largest, deepest, richest
version of ourselves, and that
is the diamond soul. I think the
diamond soul is being born in
history. The diamond soul is the
form that the future human would
take and imagine if the entire
species went through this
process, not just a few Christ
and the Buddha and Muhammad and
a few saints privileged here and
there, but if the entire species
went through this transition
that they awakened spiritually
to this deeper identity that's
been gestating inside of them
all these years, what an
extraordinary species that would
be, and what would that species,
what an extraordinary history
that species would create. I
think we've reached a point in
history where we simply cannot
run this planet out of egoic
consciousness. We either grow up
or we go extinct. And extinction
is a tremendous evolutionary
accelerator. So I think we are,
personally, I think this crisis
evolving this century is going
to take us to our edge. But my
experience is that we do make it
through this crisis. I've, I've
experienced the future human as
a task to be actualized and also
an accomplishment that has
already been realized. So from
my personal perspective, I
deeply believe that we will make
it through this crisis. We will
make it through the
developmental challenges, and
when we do and we're looking
back over human history and our
individual soul history, we will
recognize that everything, all
the pain we suffered, all the
hardship that we went through to
get to this place, it's been
worth it. It's been worth it.
We're giving birth to a new
child in history, and it will be
worth it,
Steve Thayer: Chris, I am
finding myself feeling very
grateful to you for your life's
work, for your willingness to
share it. I'm glad that you
decided to come forward and
share with you know, all of us,
not just your students, that you
had to you know, do so almost
covertly, just by living the
difference, but also now through
your written work, through
coming on podcasts like ours, it
means a lot to me personally,
and I'm just so grateful for
your willingness to come on our
show.
Chris Bache: It's an honor to
have this discussion with you,
gentlemen, and it's an honor to
share these ideas and this
teaching with your audience, it
truly is
Reid Robison: Thank you, Chris,
this has been such a delightful
honor and pleasure, so we'll
cherish this conversation. Thank
you for your generosity in
sharing with us.
Chris Bache: Thank you for your
work, gentlemen, thank you for
the healing you bring into the
world and the insight you're
bringing into the world.
Steve Thayer: And Chris is there
anywhere in particular you'd
like to point people a website,
any of your current work? Where
can they find out more about
you?
Chris Bache: They can contact me
through my website. Chris
bache.com it's a website in need
of an overhaul, but it's there,
and I have posted, you know,
things I've written there and
but, you know, I'm all over
YouTube. Various podcasts and
talks I've given are on YouTube.
They can find if there, if the
articles, the things that I've
written are not on my website,
they'll be on academia.edu,
under my name there, all my
articles are published there, so
all the most important things
that I've written are available
and they can reach me on my
website. I'm not doing any
structured teaching at present.
I may be doing some retreats in
the near future, but those are
still in the planning stages
right now. I'm just doing some
talks here and there at
conferences, maybe some retreats
being coordinated by some of the
people I've been working with
individually. But basically I'm
just following the work. Gotten
into the world. I really don't
have, I really don't have an
agenda. Right now, I'm
responding to where the book
takes me. People read the book,
they get interested like you,
and I'm just following it out.
Steve Thayer: Well, Chris Bache
retreat sounds awesome. I'll put
it on my bucket list tonight.
I'll be looking for it and
willing to your website and
places where people can find
your work in our on our episode.
Show notes again. Thank you so
much.
Chris Bache: Chris, you bet
Thank you.
Steve Thayer: Psychedelic
therapy frontiers is brought to
you by Numinous, a mental
wellness company committed to
tackling the global mental
health crisis by delivering best
in class psychedelic assisted
therapies, contributing to the
body of primary and clinical
psychedelic research and
fostering healing through
community connection and social
responsibility. You can learn
more about numinous@numinous.com
that's n u m, I n u s.com. If
you enjoyed the show today and
you want to support us. Here's
how you do it. Rate and review
the show on platforms like Apple
podcast and Spotify. Subscribe
to the Numinous YouTube channel.
Like the videos and share it.
Share the show or clips of the
show with someone that you think
will enjoy it. The content of
this podcast does not constitute
medical advice or mental health
treatment. Consult with a
medical or mental health
professional if you believe you
are in need of mental health
treatment, you.