Unknown: You You You You
announcer. Welcome to om times
TV, a division of OM times media
and broadcasting.
Welcome to the no BS spiritual
book clubs, live streaming
interview series where leading
New Thought teachers, speakers
and authors share the intimate
stories behind the 10 Best
spiritual books that inspired
them the most on their spiritual
journey, from well known
classics to hidden gems you
might never have heard of, the
no BS spiritual book club saves
you time and money by sharing
reliable recommendations from
those who've walked The path
before you the no BS spiritual
book club, the only no BS guide
to the best spiritual books to
inspire your own journey of self
discovery. Here's your host,
founder of the no BS spiritual
book club, Sandy sedgebear,
Sandy Sedgbeer: hello and
welcome joining me today to
share the 10 Best spiritual
books that inspired him the most
on his life journey is award
winning teacher and
international speaker
Christopher M Bache, whose
latest book LSD and the mind of
the universe is, in my opinion,
probably the most important book
of our time. Chris Bache is
professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University, where he
taught for 33 years. He's a
fellow at the Institute of
Noetic Sciences and advisory
board member for Grof
Transpersonal training and the
Grof Foundation. And if you want
to know why I regard LSD and the
mind of the universe as the most
important book of this time,
stay tuned. We'll find out more
about that later in the show.
Meantime, Chris Bache, welcome
to the show.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Sandy.
It's a pleasure to be here with
you.
Sandy Sedgbeer: I'm always
intrigued to know. Books our
guests will choose, but I've
been especially keen to learn
and share with our audience your
timber spiritual books. When I
saw it, I saw the list, I said,
Well, that is one list, the only
one so far where all 10 books
have favorites of mine.
Chris Bache: Well, that's good
to hear straight. Yeah. Yeah.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So how did you
how did you find the process of
having to pick your Stan?
Chris Bache: It's kind of
interesting that there were so
many books to choose from, and
in the process of choosing the
ones that spoke most deeply to
me at any particular time in my
life, I found myself kind of
drawn to kind of more
intellectually oriented books,
because I'm an academic. And at
the end, I was quite struck by
how much I don't know. You know,
the books helped me so much, but
there's, there's so much that
I've left untouched in the
spiritual field. Wow.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Well, I beg to
differ, and their audience will
find out later why I say that. I
mean, when you say there's so
much you need to know, I would
have thought, you know you know
what we all want to know, and
that's enough.
Chris Bache: It's not so much
what I need to know. It's just
stuff that I don't know. I feel
content with what I have learned
through my journey. Yeah,
Sandy Sedgbeer: but the Yeah,
well, the don't know bit, I
mean, you know, we can go on
forever there. So your first
book, understandably, is Stan is
left, Grof, realms of the human
unconscious realms, um,
observations from LSD research
published in 1975 you're a great
supporter of his work,
Chris Bache: aren't you? I am. I
think Stan's work is so
critically important to the
emerging paradigm in
Transpersonal psychology. And I
came upon this book right after
I was out of graduate school,
just beginning my teaching
career, just beginning to look
around for where to take my
research next. And I came upon
this first book by Stan that was
published just two years before.
And as soon as I read it, it
activated something in me, and I
knew I needed to get involved in
this process, even though
psychedelics were illegal at the
time, this was almost 10 years,
eight years after they had been
made illegal. I nevertheless,
decided to begin what became a
20 year journey, working with
LSD in a therapeutic protocol
that Stan lays out, working with
high dose sessions. Not not as a
clinician. I wasn't a
psychologist. I wasn't primarily
oriented towards healing. I'm a
philosopher of religion by
trade. I was interested in the
cosmic logical significance of
these substances, how they would
give us the head the potential
to show us new insights into the
deep structure of the universe,
and it that book just really
sort of lit the fuse for me.
Now, how old were you then? I
was 30 years old.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Yeah, wow. And
that started your 20 year
journey.
Chris Bache: Yeah, between 30
and 50 that. That's really the
book that started it all for me.
And of course, I read all of
Stan's books as they came
through, and I always felt that
my books were largely first and
foremost in dialog with Stan's
work.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So book number
two, Ian Stevenson, 20 cases
suggestive of reincarnation,
published in 1966
Chris Bache: Yeah, I met this
book at the same time, I met
Stan's book, and at the time, I
was a deeply convinced agnostic
with strong atheistic leanings.
And I encountered this book by
Stevenson, which I think
presents overwhelming evidence,
the first of many books of his
that prevent present
overwhelming evidence that
reincarnation is simply a fact
of life. It's a natural fact of
life, which required that I
erase my entire intellectual
Blackboard, because
reincarnation had never been
taken seriously by any of the
courses that I had taken in
college or graduate school. I
had to erase the Blackboard and
start from scratch, which
resulted eventually, about 10
years later, in my publishing my
book on reincarnation life
cycles, which is my response to
Ian Stevenson's pioneering work.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So when you I'm
getting a bit of feedback now,
when you went down that path,
did you risk? You know the ire
of your colleagues. I
Chris Bache: did actually. I
went on sabbatical, my first
sabbatical, my head not planned
to write a book. I had not
planned to write this book, but
I came back with the book, the
Manuscript of the Book, and my
colleagues were not terribly
happy with it. I. But it got
published, and then it got
translated into several foreign
languages, and they began to pay
more attention to the subject
matter, so it didn't affect your
career. It didn't. I was afraid
that it might when I first did
it, but this is a kind of a
personal, karmic thing. I've
paid the penalty for going
against the grain in former
lives. This lifetime, it seems
that it's important for me to
continue to go against the grain
and not and not receive any
negative consequences, and only
receiving positive consequences.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Book number
three, journey of souls, case
studies of life between lives by
Michael Newton in 1994
Chris Bache: Yeah, Michael
Newton's work is so beautiful
and so important. Started as a
past life therapist then
accidentally gave an ambiguous
instruction to a client, through
which he learned that we could
regress people, not only to
their former lives, but we could
regress people to the time in
between their death and their
subsequent rebirth. And he began
to give us a a not an
autobiographical people,
individual experiences of what
happened to them in their time
between their incarnations and
his series of books just were
fantastic about this. They had
not been published when I
published my book at first, but
they certainly do complement it
very beautifully.
Sandy Sedgbeer: I mean, he
really was a pioneer, there
wasn't he. I mean, so many
people I speak to trained with
Michael Newton,
Chris Bache: yeah, really was
and and his description of the
Bardo existence concurs with my
experience in psychedelics
completely with the provision
that I think he's he's seeing
more the lower half of the
Bardo, not the upper edges of
the Bardo. But yeah.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Well, book
number four is lessons from the
light what we can learn from the
Near-Death Experience by Kenneth
ring, and that one was published
in 1998
Chris Bache: Yeah, I again,
which one of these books by each
of these authors we focus on?
Kenneth ring has always been a
colleague and friend. He wrote
the forward to life cycles. His
work on near death episodes was
so critically important. I
taught a course for many years
at the University called
Transpersonal studies in which
we always included near death
episode research. And I always
use Ken ring's books because
they were so accessible to the
students and so well researched.
And this book is kind of Ken's
last book on near death episode
research. It's an overview. It's
a compendium. It contains
beautiful passages all sorts of
empirical analysis. But my
favorite chapter in the book
comes towards the end where he's
describing the deepest near
death episodes that he has
recorded, and they are just
magnificent. Personally, as a
psychedelic oriented person, I
feel deepest compatibility or a
deepest resonance with people
who have had deep near death
episodes. Yeah.
Sandy Sedgbeer: So continuing
the theme Robert Monroe far
journey is his best selling
classic, published in 1985 Yeah.
Chris Bache: Robert Monroe has
been a real companion to me on
the journey through his works.
This book came out when I was on
my first sabbatical, and I was
writing life cycles. And I this
book came out, and I immediately
made a reservation to go and do
a week's training program at the
Monroe Institute, because I was
so impressed by his work. And
then I went back one more time
right after he passed, to go
back to the Monroe Institute for
a week's training to say
goodbye. Monroe, I think, is an
under studied figure in the
consciousness community. Maybe
it's because he's on the East
Coast and doesn't penetrate West
Coast circles so much, but the
model of the universe that he
presents, that emerged over
decades of his going out of his
body every every night, every
time he went to sleep, is just a
stunning model, idiosyncratic,
very candid. He Monroe just says
it. Calls it like he sees it.
But it's a very compatible model
with Eastern, particularly
Buddhist cosmology, the
structure of the Bardo, the long
the large model, I think, is
just a fantastic excursion, and
I've read it multiple times
through
Sandy Sedgbeer: the years. Did
you have many June. Awareness
when you
Chris Bache: were there. You
know, getting out of my body is
never an aptitude that I seem to
have developed. I when I was
there, I had definitely
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, expansive,
diffuse and constant states of
consciousness where I was able
to make contact, for example,
with people who had died and
were in the Bardo, but they
weren't accompanied by the
sensation of being out of my
body. And this is true for all
my psychedelic work. I never had
the sensation of leaving my
body. Rather, my consciousness
expanded exponentially beyond
the limits of my body, but not
as kind of a separate
consciousness, individualized
consciousness, traveling out.
Sandy Sedgbeer: I always wanted
to go there. I never got there,
but I did attend a weekend
session by somebody who had
trained to do it and didn't
really work for me. Didn't I'm
so disappointed. Yeah, yeah.
Book number six by a man whose
work I love, Dwayne Aldous,
choosing Earth humanity's great
transition to a mature planetary
civilization. Published, I think
that was 2020 but there's been a
new edition published.
Chris Bache: Yes, he's updated
it, put it in a new edition.
Dwayne Elgin is a dear friend,
great colleague. Jokes. He's one
of my heroes. He's been trying
to raise the alarm about
humanity's Pearl and what we're
doing to the planet and the
limitations of our understanding
of the universe, the
consequences of buying into a
materialist paradigm instead of
a Living Universe paradigm. One
of his books The Living
Universe, from his first book on
voluntary simplicity, where he
points us where we need to be
going, reducing our impact on
the planet, living a simpler
life with more focus on what we
want to achieve with our life,
not a life of doing less, but a
life of doing more with less.
But this book, choosing Earth is
a distillation of decades and
decades of his thinking on the
earth. He lays out a very
carefully, scientifically
informed proposal for what the
next 50 years are going to look
like, decade by decade, and then
he follows this with a series of
recommendations for how we can
consciously and intelligently
engage this crisis and work to
ensure a better outcome. It's
just, it's a beautiful book, and
his wife, Colleen has produced a
film that is the companion to
the book. So you and they're
giving away the book and giving
away the film for free. It is.
Dwayne says it's too important.
We are right now. Things are too
important to try to make money
Sandy Sedgbeer: out of this
pearl. Do you know where people
can go to find the movie and
what's it called?
Chris Bache: It's called, oh my
goodness, I'm having a senior
moment. Here you can go to
Dwayne Elgin's website. Dwayne
elgin.com and his books are
listed there, and the movie is
there. His wife's name is
Colleen ladru Elgin. Yeah.
Sandy Sedgbeer: I'll check it
out. Yeah. Number seven, another
author whose work I admire
tremendously, Rupert Sheldrake,
a new science of life, the
hypothesis of Morphic resonance,
published in 1981
Chris Bache: against a person
has written such an extra
ordinary series of books when I
was trying to understand, as I
say in my notes here, when I was
trying to understand why my
psychedelic purification healing
experiences had expanded so
exponentially to include
hundreds of 1000s of human
beings, the whole breadth of the
human species, and later, when I
was trying to understand some of
the dynamics that were being
that were showing up in my
classroom, that seemed this
permeability between my mind And
my students mind. Rupert
sheldrake's work was really
helpful to me, and very
important because he helped me
understand that our individual
minds of every being is always
also simultaneously network into
a species mind, so that as the
species learns, the individual
learns, as the individual
learns, the species learns, and
a complex feedback dynamic, and
this was extraordinarily helpful
when I it helped me make the
transition of thinking about
what was happening in my
sessions in terms of a personal
model of transformation into a
collective model of
transformation. And this became
the primary theme of my second
book, Dark Night early dawn,
where I'm really talking about
the collective that the dark
night of our collective soul,
the transformation of our
collective soul. And that has
Rupert's fingerprints all over
it.
Sandy Sedgbeer: He took a lot of
flack, didn't he? He really has,
you know, had to fight the good
fight there. And yet, he's said
to me that some of the people
who publicly deny his work
privately,
Chris Bache: yeah, too often in
academia, we have our public
reputations and our private
convictions that don't match our
public positions.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Sad, isn't it?
Yeah, people don't feel that
they can be authentic and say
what they think.
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah. And
Rupert's been just a real hero
in challenging the status quo,
in scientific thought and just
pushing and pushing and pushing
the issues on the table that he
believes in,
Sandy Sedgbeer: yeah, yeah. So
book number eight Richard
Tarnas, cosmic and psyche,
intimations of a new world view,
published in 1996 Yeah.
Chris Bache: Rick Tarnas is
another colleague and dear
friend, an extra ordinary
astrologer. After establishing
his professional reputation as
an historian of intellectual
thought with his book passion of
the Western mind, he then came
up with this book, Cosmos and
psyche, in which he makes the
case that astrology not only
illumines the lives of
individuals, and he demonstrates
this very powerfully in the book
with known historical figures,
but that Astrology can be used
to illumine historical epics.
And it's so, it's that is the
larger thesis which is so
particularly provocative is his
analysis of history in terms of
the rhythms of the of the
archetypal astrological pulses
of our solar system, and showing
a correlation between the
quality of the archetypal
energies that are being brought
into focus from an archetype
from an astrological lens to
looking at what's actually
happening at an historical level
and showing the correlations.
And I think it's an
extraordinarily important and
very valuable book, also a real
tour de force. You have to strap
in when you read one of Rick's
Sandy Sedgbeer: books. Yeah,
yeah. I'm sure I was looking at
looking it up earlier, and I
think it was contents list one,
one of the things on there that
caught my eye, because it really
relates so much to your work and
what's in your book, the
transformation of the cosmos,
the birth of the modern self,
and the dawn of A new universe,
which is pretty much where we
are now, the birth of the modern
self. I mean, you talk about the
future human in your book. What
is, what is the modern self?
Chris Bache: I think the modern
self is a birth that was given,
is the self sense that was given
birth to in the Age of
Enlightenment, and it's the
rational self, it's that gives
birth to science, the scientific
self. And I think what we're
seeing is now that the modern
self is thoroughly and deeply
established. The modern self is
someone who, like Martin Luther
can pound his 96 thesis on the
door of the cathedral and
basically say to this multi 100
year old religious tradition of
the Roman Catholicism, you're
wrong and you're wrong on this,
this and this, that self
consolidated within ourselves so
that we can become critical,
Turn a critical lens on our
history and our culture and our
context, that self, now
thoroughly established in
history, is yielding to a post
modern self, I think, and that's
the future human that so many of
us are feeling, intuiting and
experiencing in our
contemplative practices. The
post modern self doesn't negate
the modern self, but it
reconnects the modern self to
the underlying, deeper fabric of
consciousness that runs through
all things, not only through all
human beings, but through all of
life. So the modern self is
being recontextualized within
the larger fabric of existence.
And that is, I think, the future
human, the and the way I
understand that the technical
parts of that is in terms of the
birth of the diamond soul.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Well, we will
talk more about that after the
break. So book number nine.
Nine, Sri Aurobindo, or the
adventure of consciousness by
sat Prem, published in 1968
Chris Bache: Sri Aurobindo is
one of my heroes. He's just such
a brilliant man, Oxford,
educated and Hindu saint and
Guru transition from being a
political activist to being a
Spiritual Activist. And he more
or less channeled all his books.
I mean, apparently all of his
books were written within six
years. He just channeled them.
But they're very dense. They're,
you know, you really have to sit
down with a cup of coffee if
you're going to read Aurobindo,
because he's so rich. Sat RAM is
a has written a biography which
basically extracts the core
insights that that Aurobindo
presented in his writing, but he
does it in a way which makes
them more accessible to the
average reader like me and I
just I really appreciate it
saprem Because he gives me a
back door way into aurobindo's
thought, and he it makes it
easier for me when I want to
tangle the tackle. The primary
text
Sandy Sedgbeer: we had a guest
on a few months ago who
recommended, I don't know if it
was this book, but one of his,
and was talking about how he and
the mother, I believe it was
during the war they would
meditate, and they would
basically send thoughts, yeah,
you know, to Hitler, good
thoughts. And they would see and
and they'd send thoughts to
Churchill as well. And they
basically sent one particular
thought to Churchill about how
he would mobilize, you know, the
British spirit, you know, to
back him completely. And in
fact, what he then said in his
next speech was almost word for
word. They had transmitted,
yeah, yeah.
Chris Bache: They just, they
live in the truth of the open
expanse of mind, and that our
individual thoughts and minds,
when focus, can travel into the
ocean of consciousness and reach
your intended destination.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Yes, yeah, it
made me, you know, I've got to
put him on my reading list. The
last book is the flight of the
Garuda teachings of the Dzogchen
tradition of Tibetan Buddhism,
by Keith Dow and published in
Chris Bache: Well, Vadnais
Buddhism has been a large
influence on me, and the
question the challenge I had
was, which of the many books
that have moved me so deeply in
Buddhism, could I put here? One
that I considered almost put so
I just want to mention is the
book graceful exits, which is a
story of how great beings,
enlightened beings, die. It's a
collection by, oh, I'm blanking
on her name of just the death
experiences of enlightened
beings. But I chose, in the end,
one of my favorite tantric
texts, the flight of the Garuda,
which basically was a bit
controversial when it was first
published, because many
traditional Vadnais
practitioners did not believe
that he should have made public
such an esoteric text as this.
Personally, I love it when I
read tantric texts like this.
I'm always bringing to it all of
my background in psychedelic
experience. And when I read this
text, and as his commentary, I
just feel illumined. I feel so
at home with it, and I learned
so much from it that helps me
process my own psychedelic
experiences. Dzogchen is
considered the fastest path, the
direct path in Vadnais,
Buddhism. It's a form of
Buddhist practice which more or
less kind of starts at the end,
instead of kind of developing
stage by stage, stage by stage,
up the mountain. It kind of
draws upon the insight that
where we end up at the end of
our spiritual practice, our end
of our journey in enlightenment
is in a condition which always
existed from the very beginning.
It's not something which is
brought into being, but it is
always there, never changes,
never ceases to exist, never
begins to exist. Once you know
that, then you can build your
spiritual practice around the
fact of this pre existing
condition, the direct path, and
that's what this book is coming
out of.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Of those 10
books, do you have a favorite?
Chris Bache: Oh, I have so many.
I guess I'm I've lived my life
around the first two I.
Stevenson and Stan Grof, just
because I believe that
reincarnation is an absolutely
essential understanding to life,
and psychedelics have been the
way for me to personally explore
the deep structure of the
universe. So I guess I'd have to
say those. But all of them are
favorites of mine. They're all
on my must read list.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Well, some of
these people you know, of those
that you don't know. Who would
you most like to meet
Chris Bache: those I don't know?
Well, I would love to have met
Michael Newton, yeah, he's now
passed on, so I'll be looking
him up when I die, that's for
sure, because he's he
contributed so much to my life.
Yeah, I
Sandy Sedgbeer: bet you're not
the only one who'll be looking
him up.
Chris Bache: Yes, you know,
Marjorie Monroe says we can go
anywhere and find anyone that we
want when we die, all we have to
do is know their know their ID,
you know. And so we can, we can
check up on people
Sandy Sedgbeer: that'll keep us
busy until we come back again, I
guess. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Well,
that's your 10 Best list, but
it's by no means the whole of
this show. We're going to take a
brief break now and when we get
back, put your listening ears
on. You're listening to a No BS
spiritual book club interview
and sharing the 10 Best Books
that had the biggest influence
on his life. Journey today is
award winning teacher,
international speaker and author
of the seminal book the mind,
LSD in the mind of the universe,
diamonds from heaven. We'll be
back with more from Christopher
Bache after the break, stay
tuned home. Times TV. Maya
Angelo once said that there is
no greater agony than bearing an
untold story inside you, I'm
Sandy sedgebear, and when I'm
not hosting on times Media's
flagship radio show, what is
going on and the no BS spiritual
book club, I help people share
their untold stories. Books Are
My life, my joy and my passion,
and there is no greater reward
than helping aspiring writers
get their books out of their
heads and into the hands of
those who are waiting to read
them. If you feel that you have
a book in you but don't know
where to begin, visit
sedgebear.com click on the work
with me, tab and find out how my
experience helping others tell
their stories might be just what
you've been looking for. That's
search beer.com S, E, D, G, B,
E, r.com
Unknown: imagine becoming a
super influencer, reinvent
yourself, invest in your brand,
and then manifest your success
with a robust spheric approach,
own times media and broadcasting
offers a unique and multifaceted
way to become the spiritual and
conscious influencer you deserve
to be by putting your message
across our powerful platform
with its proven record of
integrity and excellence through
our produced shows, om times
offers the opportunity to become
a social media TV personality, a
radio show host, an OM Times
magazine columnist and a
syndicated podcaster all in one
shot by live streaming your show
on om times TV and broadcasting
it across the extensive om times
radio and TV networks, you
become more than a host. You
become an ambassador and a force
for positive change. Om times
open yourself to the
possibilities.
There are 16 million children
struggling with hunger in
America. That's one in five
daughters, sons, neighbors and
classmates who don't know where
their next meal is coming from.
Yet, billions of pounds of good
food go to waste every year.
It's time we do something about
it. Feeding America is a
nationwide network of food banks
that helps provide meals to
millions of kids and families in
need visit feeding america.org
to help them feed even more
together, we can solve hunger
together. We're Feeding America.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Christ, welcome
back. Christopher Bache, in 1979
you embarked on a life changing
journey, you said, to explore
your mind and the mind of the
universe as deeply and as
systematically as possible, with
the help of LSD, and over the
next 20 years, you experienced
73 high dose sessions following
Stan grofs protocols, those
journeys which were intensely
grueling and also equally
blissful, took you Beyond The
Beyond took you to a place I
would love to go. Into a unified
field of consciousness that
underlies all physical
existence. So many questions, so
many questions. We won't have
time for all of them. But why
don't you tell us what is the
most important thing that you
think we need to know that you
learned on those journeys? Well?
Chris Bache: Oh, that's a hard
question. First thing it pops in
my mind is, don't do what I did.
I wouldn't do it the same way if
I did it over again, but getting
I would be much gentler on
myself. And that's partly one of
the things I learned was, I
thought the purpose of this work
was kind of get to an end state,
that there was an end state that
would change my life, transform
my life. And what I learned
along the way, and I was 17
years into this journey at this
point, is that it's an infinite
progression. It's an infinite
universe. You'll never get to
the end of it. And so the whole
project of pushing as hard as I
did with the thought that I
could get to the end of it was
just it was a mistaken concept
that I brought to it. You know,
what happens in a psychedelic
state is an amplification of
what's taking place in life, in
ordinary processes. So in order
to understand what happens in a
psychedelic state, you have to
know what's life. It's what's
happening in ordinary life. And
here, I think we have to come
understand reincarnation. We
have to understand that this is
the rhythm of life, that we are
cosmic being, that we are a
being that lives in time frames
of hundreds of 1000s, millions
of years, that this particular
incarnation is only one of many
incarnations on this planet. In
order to understand what life is
about, we have to look out in
terms of the one short term, 100
year old lifespan. We have to
think in terms of the soul's
lifespan, which is vast. So
that's, that's the first thing
is an underscoring and
reinforcing of reincarnation,
also just the encounter with the
living intelligence, which is, I
call it the mind of the
universe, because our concepts
of the Divine and God have so
many cultural limitations built
into them through history. I
don't want to affirm those,
though I do sometimes speak of
the Divine less often, but I'll
talk about God, but the
consciousness, which one can
encounter, which one can
dissolve into the intelligence,
the genius. I mean, just to
experience briefly, the
intelligence of of the mind
that's generating the universe
and the compassion and love and
wisdom. And you know, when you
just look at life, it looks
hard. I mean, it is hard and it
looks like it could have been
created by a despot, because it
is so seemingly cruel. But in
order to understand the genius
of it and the wisdom of it and
the compassion of it, you have
to be able to step back and look
very deep. It's like stepping
back off of the planet to
understand what's happening on
the planet. And in that context,
we experience, you can
experience the universe as this
magnificent garden that has been
created specifically for our
transformation, our share of it,
our transformation, and we have
unlimited amount of time to
continue to learn and grow in
this garden. And it's a it's not
an easy garden. It's a hard
place to live and grow, but it
offers us infinite potential to
develop the essential being that
we are, and our essential being
is the divine being, our light
of the Divine. We come from the
Divine. We are a spark of the
divine light. And yet we're
small and kind of immature in
the early stages, but we develop
it and develop it and develop it
until eventually we can become a
being that has complete control
over their incarnation, complete
control over the health of their
body, complete control over the
wealth of their mind and
creativity. And we're growing
and growing and growing in this
direction, toward that
direction. And I guess one of
the other major takeaways is an
understanding of where we are in
history, where humanity is and
here so many visionary
experiences that humanity is
coming to a turning point.
Humanity is coming to a
bifurcation point, a radical
deconstruction. And followed by
a reconstruction at a higher
organizational level. I think we
are entering, after hundreds of
1000s years of reincarnation,
where we have been gestating the
future human lifetime by
lifetime by lifetime, gestating
the future humans form we are
now have entered the period of
labor, and the day of labor is a
very intense, very dangerous
time, very painful time. But
when it's over, the mother gives
birth to a new child, and I
think humanity is in the process
of giving birth to a new child
to the latest iteration of its
own fundamental form. I think
we're we're witnessing in this
century and the next, a shift in
the in the collective psyche, a
shift in the fundamental
architecture of the collective
unconscious, so that all future
human beings who are born after
we make this transition will be
living in the context of a
different fundamentally
structured psyche. This is what
I call the birth the diamond
soul. I think that after all
these years of incarnating, we
are reaching a period in history
where these lives are coming
together inside us, and as they
come together, we first have to
purify and heal all their broken
and hurt pieces. But as we do
that, they move into deeper and
deeper, either gradually or
suddenly, there is an ignition
that takes place and the soul is
born. And that is, the soul is
the intelligence that holds all
of our experiences through all
of our incarnations. And that, I
think, is the emerging future
human in history. The soul is
being born inside history. So
how can I pick and choose which
of those concepts are the most
important?
Sandy Sedgbeer: Yeah, I know
well you, you said in the book
that there are many, many layers
to heaven and to the death
experience, and that there is no
hell, but there is confrontation
and accountability. Is that what
many people you know regard as
the life review, yeah, karma,
yeah. More about that.
Chris Bache: You know, our
understandings of the God and
our understandings of life have
been so primitive historically.
I mean, we, we're, we only began
to make contact, experiential
contact, with the core,
essential nature of our being,
the divine nature of our being,
about five or 6000 years ago as
a species, and we're just
getting started, and so many of
our concepts of God and
punishment and reward and Heaven
Hell, I think, are just just
completely inadequate to really
understand the true scale and
scope of the intention of
creation when we die, when we
die, in the life review, we
encounter not only a detailed
remembering of everything we've
ever done in this lifetime, but
we also experience how it
impacted, how it touched the
lives of those around us, both
directly and indirectly, touches
their lives, and to the extent
that we have made bad choices,
then that comes back to us in
the experience of hell, and to
the extent that we've made good
choices, that comes back to us
in the experience of heaven. But
in the end, the goal of this
whole system is not to punish us
or reward us in some cheap way,
but to educate us, to teach us
so that we can learn, so we
learn from our mistakes, and we
learn from other things we've
done well. And we keep on
growing. We keep on moving
through the idea that Infinite
Intelligence and infinite
compassion could produce
something like the eternal
damnation that hell envisions is
just ridiculous. It just it's
done so much damage, I think, to
human beings through history,
and it's just wrong.
Sandy Sedgbeer: You know, it's
the experiences you've had. And
the concept of the Infinite is a
very hard concept. You know, to
think that you could go on
journeying and journeying and
journeying and reincarnation and
reincarnation. You know, the
mind has to get to a point where
it's. Says enough, you know, I
don't want to do this anymore.
It's, it's endless, yeah. How do
you feel about
Chris Bache: that? I think when
we die, we go home. I mean, we
return to spirit, and we return
to our soul, the larger and
consciousness, and we read, we
are brought back into peace.
We're brought back into
wholeness, and we're brought
back home. Now the trick is
there are many, many levels of
home, and so you can experience
homecoming in the spiritual
world at an introductory level,
an intermediate level and a very
advanced level. There are many
levels of joy. So I think there
is a sense in which we get to
stop and pause and rest and
refresh ourselves after every
incarnation. Now there are
sometimes some people die under
such traumatic circumstances
that can get thrown off in
different ways, but for the most
part, most people return home
without any difficulties. When
we are there, we are restored,
we are reconnected with the
divine, and it's in that context
where we make the choice of
first, whether to incarnate
again, and where to reincarnate
again, and ask what to
reincarnate again. So what
sounds and so I think it's
natural as we go through life,
if, if we live our life well,
we're tired at the end, we don't
the idea of living multiple
times it's like that's
exhausting. We're already tired,
but from the soul's perspective,
it's from the period, from the
perspective of having been
refreshed and rejuvenated, that
we voluntarily choose another
course of instruction to deepen
ourselves as a human being and
to help other human beings,
because eventually it becomes
clear we're not in this alone.
We're all in this together, and
it's the most natural thing in
the world to want to help other
human beings in their own
evolutionary journey.
Sandy Sedgbeer: When you say
that there are so many different
levels, that makes a lot of
sense to me. So many people
write about the afterlife have
messages from the afterlife.
Hear about, you know, how the
loved ones are living in the
afterlife or existing, and
they're all so contradictory.
But if there are many levels,
you know, then that really does
explain a lot. But the other
thing I want to talk about is
you talked earlier about
transformation. You know, we are
on a journey of transformation,
and we are the sparks. And it
makes me think then that we must
be very young sparks if we need
to keep on being refined and
transformed. I mean, do older
sparks not come back?
Chris Bache: Good question, good
question. And again, to even
begin to address that question,
we have to push back the walls
of our assumptions. We have to
really begin to think deeper and
longer and larger. The spiritual
traditions that believe in
reincarnation say reincarnation
is obligatory up to a certain
point in our developmental
process. So we may drag our
feet, we may take time, but
sooner or later we have to come
back to the reincarnation
process, but there comes a time
when you no longer have to. Now,
the early Eastern tradition said
that's the that's the critical
moment when you can leave, and
everybody wants to leave, and
that's what the religions are
all about, moksha, escape,
getting to the Pure Land,
getting to heaven. I don't think
that's really what it's all
about, I think, but it is a
significant turning point,
because once we no longer have
to participate in the
reincarnation cycle, once it's
purely an it's purely optional,
then we can choose to
participate freely, and more
strategically, to support, not
necessarily our own individual
development, maybe, but not
necessarily, but to be able to
support the development of other
human beings. You might think of
them as our grandchildren, our
great grandchildren, in the end,
from a deep, spiritual
perspective, they're all our
children. They're all our
grandchildren. All of humanity
is now. There are some beings, I
think, who have reached that
point, and they've gone on to
explore other dimensions of
existence, the physical
universe. Universe is only one
dimension of a multi dimensional
cosmos in spiritual reality. So
as vast as the physical universe
is, it seems to be only one
universe out of a multi universe
system. So in order to sort of
ask, Are there no Are there no
old souls here? Or where do old
sparks of light go? That just
takes us really deep into the
vast expanse of things. You
know, when the Buddha was asked
this question, he didn't, he
refused to answer it. He about,
where does an enlightened being
go, he said that however he
answered it, it would confuse
the listener, and it was better
to just work on your own
transformation, until you can
have the experience of awakening
yourself, and then you'll know
for your own truth where we're
going when We die, and what's
available to us when we die.
Because if you say the awakened
one does not exist as they die,
then that leads to a mistake. If
you say that the awakened one
does exist when they die, that
also leads to a mistake, because
the conditions are so different
than that either or recognizes
Sandy Sedgbeer: you talked about
this incredible intelligent
consciousness, this, I'll call
it a divine being, because I
don't know how else to describe
it. But of course, calling it a
being minimizes it. It's
infinite. Is this something that
we all can experience? Oh
Chris Bache: yes, absolutely,
because its nature is our
nature. And so when we
experience the deepest aspect of
our own being, we experience its
being. We experience its nature.
It's impossible to step out of
this being. This being, the body
of this being, is the body of
the universe. All the vast
expanse of spiritual reality is
the consciousness of the
universe, the non physical
aspect of this, of this being.
And again, like you, I hesitate
to call it a being, because that
gives it kind of a boundary
quality, and there are no
boundaries, yeah, but yeah, this
is not only can we experience
it, but it is our destiny to
experience it. And I think when
we die, we return to the
remembrance of this nature, and
that's why we want to incarnate
again, in order to deepen our
experience of our essential
nature. It's kind of like when
we die, our cup is filled to the
brim. But you can have a half a
cup, three quarters of a cup,
full cup, or two cups, you know,
and we want a bigger and bigger
cup so we can experience more
and more of the divine bliss.
Sandy Sedgbeer: You You said in
the book how painful it was. It
became painful to leave the
presence of that being, and
that's ultimately one of the
reasons why you stopped having
the sessions. Have you found
other ways to experience it that
aren't so painful
Chris Bache: the full intensity
of communion with light of
existence? No, I have not found
other ways of experiencing it in
its full intensity. I have
committed myself to grabbing
physical existence, my physical
existence, and not letting it
go, and learning to love the
manifest body of the divine in
that I see around me, in every
person and in the stars at
night, I am comfortable in this
world. I love this world, and I
do my spiritual practice and you
know, but in terms of getting
access to those same dimensions
of diamond Luminosity, no, I've
had to let go of that for the
time being. That said, I know
there are beings who do you
know? I know there are great
spiritual beings, truly the, you
know, the mahasiddhas, the great
beings, who are able to live in
conscious communion with those
subtle planes of existence. I
don't happen to be one of those
beings yet. So it's still hope.
I think if I practice every day
for the rest of my life. In this
incarnation, I still not would
not be able to realize, in my
particular case, in traditional
contemplative practice, the
levels of reality that I access,
what that I was accessing after
20 years of work in this
particular form of practice.
With psychedelics,
Sandy Sedgbeer: but knowing what
you know, knowing what it feels
like, knowing you know where
you've been and what you've
experienced, it must make life a
little bit hard. You know,
knowing that that is always
there,
Chris Bache: it makes it hard
and it makes it easier. It makes
it easier, because now I know. I
know it in my heart and in my
bones that we are always
surrounded and suffused with
this divine intelligence and
love, and one can draw on it
continuously, so that, in that
sense, it makes it easier,
because the greatest burden I
think of physical existence is
not knowing. And we're we get
driven crazy by not knowing, and
that burden has been lifted from
me, but it does make it hard in
the sense that to once you. And
this is nothing unique to
psychedelic journey. People who
have deep, n des near death
experiences, same thing they
they have to. It's a challenge
to come back into time and space
and be content with living here
and that aspect, it is harder
because you know that it's
there, and you know that it's
only your own silliness which is
keeping you from enjoying it
fully right here, right now.
It's only my own imperfections
which are keeping me out of that
state right here, right now.
Sandy Sedgbeer: This 200 100 200
years of transformation that we
are going to go through. Yeah,
it's, it's a wonderful thing,
and it gives a lot of people a
lot of hope. And goodness knows,
you know, we're all aware of
what's happening in the world
today and how challenging that
is to live with, and many people
are very afraid. But when we're
in a human form, if we haven't
had the experiences that you've
had, it's also very hard to
think I'm not going to see it in
my lifetime. I've got to wait a
couple of 100 years that it just
sounds too much.
Chris Bache: You know, the
timetable was not given to me,
and the details of the
transformation were not given to
me in my visionary experiences,
what I was given was the
experience of the human species
undergoing the pain of a deep
and profound global collapse and
this and the beauty and this
first and the certainty that we
would make it through, and a lot
of people are beginning to think
that we're not going to make it
through. It's an extinction
event. My visionary experience
is that we do make it through,
and we are profoundly changed in
this process. You know, it's
kind of like, you know, when a
woman starts labor in the
morning, when she's starting
labor, she might think, Oh, I
don't want to do this today.
Let's do something else. But
there's no choice. We're in it,
and I think that's what's going
to happen to us. Now, we may not
want to be in it, but we're in
it, and the key to navigating it
well is to do it well. Each of
us has a small share in this
collective transformation, and
the actions of individuals have
disproportionately arch large
outcomes in a time of intense
and accelerated change and non
linear systems, so that each one
of us can have a positive impact
on a good outcome of this crisis
that we're going through. And I
don't know how long it's going
to take us, but this is the work
of the hour. This is what we are
all here working toward.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Yeah, and it's
not as though we're not going to
experience that transformation.
Because if we keep coming back,
we're definitely going to be a
part of it.
Chris Bache: Yeah, and I think
the joy when we begin to
experience in between our
lifetimes and on earth,
eventually, when we experience
this new human being that is
coming forward in history and we
aren't, you know, nature, or the
force behind nature, is giving
birth to this being. When we
experience this being as just
like experience a newborn babe,
it will all be worth it. All the
pain and suffering will be worth
it. This is of an extra ordinary
event in human history.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Chris Bache, I'm
afraid we're out of time. Thank
you for adding your 10 Best list
of spiritual books to the no BS
spiritual book clubs, Library of
recommendations. And thank you
for taking that journey for all
of us.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Sandy.
Thank you for the work you're
doing. Thank you for the
tremendous source of information
that you bring into the world.
You're just doing such good
work. And thank you for the
attention you've you've paid my
work.
Sandy Sedgbeer: Thank you, Chris
So Christopher Bache is 10 Best
lists can be found at the no BS
spiritual book club. And if you
go to Sandy's bookworms, you can
download an excerpt from LSD
and. Mind of the universe,
diamonds from heaven, which is
published by inner traditions,
bear and company. For more
information about Chris's
articles, events and other
books, visit his website at
Chris bache.com this show is
also available as a free
downloadable podcast at home
times.com Spotify, iTunes,
Amazon, Audible, and all of the
major podcast platforms. So if
you'd rather listen than view,
you know where to go for it.
That's it for this week. I'm
Sandy sedgebear. I'll be back at
the same time next week with
another 10 best interview for
the no BS spiritual book club.
Till then, it's goodbye from me,
and thank you deeply. To Chris
Bache, Thank you, Sandy. You
you.