Jeffrey Mishlove: Allowed is
presented by the California
Institute for Human science,
okay? And then I'll shut that
Emmy Vadnais: and then I'm going
to go ahead and share my screen.
Minimizing.
Jeffrey Mishlove: There we go.
And so as of this moment,
announcements are being sent out
to one of our followers, and
they'll be logging in, and so
they'll be able to hear
everything we say, and their
screen will sort of look like
this. They'll see little
thumbnails of our images. So in
just
Emmy Vadnais: a minute, I'll
start the countdown clock timer,
and then for those listening and
joining, welcome and thank you
for being with us. If you want
to chat in where you're joining
from in the world, from your
neck of the word, neck of the
woods. In the world, we'd love
to hear where you're from. And
then in just a minute, I'll
start the timer.
Jeffrey Mishlove: I might
mention for people who are
watching the archival video, and
they're wondering, why do they
have to sit through 10 minutes
of our conversation beforehand,
before we begin the program? And
it's because, once we start the
timer and go live, YouTube
automatically makes it this
archival recording, which
YouTube then takes public. So I
suppose the option would be for
us to capture a recording on on
our hard drive and then edit it
before we let it go public. So
in theory, we could edit out the
first 10 minutes because I I got
a complaint from a viewer who
was unhappy that they had to
least they didn't understand.
They could fast forward, I
suppose, to the beginning of the
video. So for viewers who who
don't want to sit through our
preliminary conversation? Fast
forward at 10 minutes,
Emmy Vadnais: right? That's why
there's a timer. It says nine
minutes until livestream, but
this is yeah, to give a
notification so that our
subscribers will be notified
that we're going live in a few
minutes and if we were to take
it down and re upload it, the
only thing is, is that we've
already shared this particular
URL all over the internet, so
then we would lose this
particular
Jeffrey Mishlove: Yeah, would
have to have a new URL. I kind
of like keeping things the way
they are, because I if I were to
start downloading the and we're
on Zoom. It's a Zoom video,
which is not the highest quality
from the Zoom recorder, to be
honest. And then I would want
to, anytime you mention another
person, I would want to insert a
book cover or something the way
we normally do for our
interviews, which would create
additional delays, but this way,
the archival video goes up as
soon as we finish talking,
Emmy Vadnais: yeah, it's pretty
easy just to fast forward a
YouTube video to when it
actually begins, and
Jeffrey Mishlove: typically by
the time the day is over, there
are three or four times as many
people who watch the archival
video is who were with us live.
Chris Bache: How many years have
you been doing this? Jeffrey,
Jeffrey Mishlove: I started in
1972 doing interviews, but a
YouTube channel. This is our
10th year on YouTube. Okay? I
began KPFA radio, Pacifica
radio, nonprofit station in
Berkeley back in 1972
Chris Bache: that's a lot of
good information streamed out to
a lot of people.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Yeah, really,
and I was guided to do it by a
dream, really, yes, yeah, at a
time in my life when I didn't
own a radio or a television and
I was a long haired Berkeley
hippie. I didn't believe in
radio or television. I thought
they were all phony baloney, but
I had this dream, and I acted on
it and changed my mind, and for
most of the last half century,
I've been doing interviews.
Chris Bache: Wow, that's
fascinating. Another example of
the wisdom of the deep
consciousness of the world,
communicating and giving us
directions in our private lives,
our so called Private Lives.
Yeah,
Jeffrey Mishlove: and I'm very
interested in people who have
had what I would call life
changing dreams. Yes, because
that, that dream that I had, was
a life changer. I mean, here I
am, half a century later, still
acting on that information.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, yeah. And
live streams have been on
YouTube. Have been, what, three,
four years, Jeff, you've been
doing these,
Jeffrey Mishlove: yeah, maybe
even,
Emmy Vadnais: I think maybe five
years.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Yeah. In fact,
yes, five years.
Emmy Vadnais: Emmy, like,
usually every two to three
weeks, we have fabulous guests
on like you, Chris
Chris Bache: and how did you get
into this particular role? Emmy,
what drew you here?
Emmy Vadnais: Well, Jeff was a
guest on my podcast back in 2018
and I originally learned about
him and thinking aloud on public
television back in 1987 when I
was probably 13 years old, and
he was, yeah, interviewing
wonderful people. But even even
then, on public television from
1986 to 2002 although my
understanding was is that it was
sent out to on the satellite in
1987 so I began watching it, and
was just fascinated and very
intrigued with the information.
I didn't understand all of it at
the time because I was 13, but I
understood enough that I wanted
to learn more. And in
retrospect, I think it really
did help set the tone for my
career in understanding more
about holistic health,
intuition, spirituality,
consciousness, and even back
then, Jeff you, were talking
about UFOs and interviewing
people like Jacques valet and
John Mack and and I thought,
well, this man is really
intelligent. There must be
something to all of this. And
then I was researching for a
book I wrote and about
intuition, and Jeff's name kept
coming up. And then I realized,
oh, Jeffrey Mishlove, he was the
host of that program. And then I
realized he had a doctorate in
parapsychology, which was very
downplayed on that original
program and and then I thought,
well, I'd love to talk to him,
and I'll invite him on my
podcast. And he said, Yes. And
then in 2020 Jeff, you put out a
call for volunteers, and then I
started volunteering with you.
And then he won the Bigelow
essay competition for the best
evidence for the continuation of
consciousness in the afterlife
in 2021 so he invited me to be a
guest host, and then shortly
thereafter, I became the co
host. And then now he's invited
other guest hosts, and yeah, I'm
just grateful to be here and
help share this information and
learn from one of the best, best
people in the field, doing this
Chris Bache: in such in such a
way, our lives are all
intertwined around each other,
aren't they?
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, yeah. Very
true. And Chris, I know we're
going to learn more about you in
a few minutes. When did you
start? I know you bet you were a
professor for many, many years.
When did you start public
speaking or getting interested
in these kind of topics?
Chris Bache: Well, you know,
when I started the LSD work in
79 I had to keep it pretty under
tight wraps. I mean, I just
couldn't bring it out publicly
at all. And it wasn't until I
wrote dark night, early dawn,
which was my first book on
psychedelic work, which which
came out in 2000 that I began
going to conferences and began
to teach at CIS in that area.
But I really didn't go public
until I retired from the
University in 2013 and then I,
you know, I was working on LSD
in the mind of the universe for
five years during that period.
And when it finally came out in
2019 I became, I was more
public, just increasingly
public. So I was out of the
psychedelic closet, formally,
kind of when that book came out.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, and it's a
wonderful book, LSD and the mind
of the universe. I really
enjoyed reading it. And I like
how you also put many of your
session notes in there, which
was you bring the reader. I felt
like I was sometimes along on
the trip with you.
Chris Bache: Yeah, that's what I
wanted to do. My sense was that
in order to have the
philosophical conversation about
the potential of psychedelics,
first people have to understand
what happens in deep sessions.
So the first task was
descriptive, and then later the
second or third round would be
more evaluative and analytic. So
I really tried to bring the
reader along with me into those
sessions. So I had to learn a
whole new way of writing. I had
to lose my academic voice and
develop a different voice.
Emmy Vadnais: Well, you did it
beautifully, I would say, you
nailed it.
Unknown: Thank you. Yeah, so
Emmy Vadnais: we just got about
a minute before we officially
begin the program.
Jeffrey Mishlove: In retrospect
that the the impulse that I had
to act on that dream and to be
alert to it and so on, I was
primed for that from having had
LSD a number of times prior.
Chris Bache: Yeah, and with the
depth of our interweaving
continues to go, Yeah,
Jeffrey Mishlove: all right,
welcome everybody. I'm Jeffrey
Mishlove. I'm with my co host
Emmy Vadnais and our honored
guest Chris Bache and Emmy. Will
you introduce Chris?
Emmy Vadnais: Yes, hello and
welcome everybody. We're so
grateful to have Chris Bache
with us today, who is professor
emeritus in the department of
philosophy and religious study
studies at Youngstown State
University in Ohio, where he
taught for 33 years. He is also
adjunct faculty at the
California Institute of integral
studies, Emeritus, excuse me,
Emeritus fellow at the Institute
of Noetic Sciences and on the
Advisory Council of Grof legacy
training. Chris is author of
life cycles, reincarnation in
the web of life, dark night,
early dawn, the living
classroom, teaching and
collective consciousness and LSD
and the mind of the universe,
diamonds from heaven, and his
website is Chris bache.com with
an E at the end. Welcome Chris.
We're so happy to have you here
today to get us started. Do you
want to just go ahead and share
a little bit about your
background, and we also want to
let people know that Chris has
been a guest on new thinking,
allowed with a recorded
interview talking about
psychedelics and the Cosmic
Mind.
Chris Bache: Well, I'm actually
the last person you would have
thought from the beginning of my
life to end up writing a book on
describing what happens on the
long series of high dose LSD
sessions. I was raised in the
Deep South, in Mississippi. I
was a seminarian in the early
days. I was studying to be a
Catholic priest, but eventually
I left that because celibacy and
I didn't get along very well.
Got degrees in theology and New
Testament criticism and
eventually philosophy of
religion from Brown University.
So I had a very classical, very
traditional upbringing. The
psychedelic 60s passed me by
entirely, and it wasn't until I
got to graduate school. I mean,
I got to teaching in 1978 and I
was looking around for where to
take my research that I
encountered the work of
Stanislav Grof and his book,
realms of the human unconscious
was a life changer for me,
because I saw immediately the
philosophical significance of
his work. If what he was saying
was true, it had profound
implications for how we could do
philosophy in the future, not
just healing, but actually
explore the metaphysical
structure underlying structure
of reality. So uncomfortable, I
made the decision to knew I
needed to do this work. I knew I
had to begin my own psychedelic
work, and I was uncomfortable
breaking the law, but I chose to
begin very private,
circumscribed work in this
modality using Stan Grof
protocol. So I divided my life
into two parts. During my day
job, I was a traditional member
of the Department of Philosophy
and Religious Studies at young
sound state and kind of my night
job was doing working with
psychedelics, exploring the I
was healing my own psyche,
working and exploring the deep
structure of the collective
psyche, and then what lies
beyond the collective psyche.
And I worked for four years. I
stopped for six years for
reasons that I give in the book,
and then I resume for another 10
years. So basically. Basically
between the time when I was 30
and 50 years old, I did 73 high
dose LSD sessions using a tight
therapeutic protocol, and then I
took another 20 years to digest
and assimilate those experiences
and to kind of connect the dots
in those experiences before
publishing LSD in the mind of
the universe in 2019 so
actually, it was after I
finished my sessions in one of
my meditations, I heard this
voice say, 20 years in 20 years
out, which I took to mean that
it would take me at least 20
years to integrate and digest
all the experiences I had
collected in those 20 years.
Now, I think that might have
been an overly optimistic
assessment, because I don't
think I have nearly integrated
all the experiences that I had
collected in those first 20
years. Wow.
Emmy Vadnais: So you feel like
you're still integrating the
experiences Very
Chris Bache: much so. In fact,
it raises, it has raised
substantial kind of intellectual
questions, how do you possibly
integrate experiences which so
radically transcend the
conditions of time and space and
our consciousness inside time
and space. If you have temporary
experiences which go radically
beyond spatial consciousness,
radically on temporal
consciousness and linear time,
how do you what does it mean
even to integrate those
experiences? I mean, it really
comes down. The things I'm
thinking about these days is,
what does integration even look
like? What does it mean when
you're dealing with such radical
experiences, if you're dealing
with lower dose work or gentler
psychedelics, where the
experiences come closer to your
world inside time and space,
integration is less demanding,
but if you really open up to the
very deep waters of the deep
psyche, integration becomes a
more substantive issue.
Emmy Vadnais: All right? Well,
we're getting lots of questions
coming in, and I think this
question from Robert Bushman
might be a good place to start,
perhaps, is, what is
consciousness? Is there an
ultimate reality, or is it
infinitely fractal? I guess
there's a few questions in here.
How can an individual's
conscious awareness expand
without psychedelics? How can
one remember past lives, which
actually is a maybe a separate
question, but maybe starting out
with, what is consciousness?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, you
know, I'm happy to let the
psychologists and philosophers
tear their hair out on that one.
I'm willing to sort of go with
whatever definition they come up
with, as long as it's
sufficiently broad to
incorporate the total
phenomenology of consciousness.
I mean, sort of simply,
consciousness comes from calm
shield to know. With
consciousness is that with which
we know? So it is the knowing
function. It is the awareness of
our cognitive capacity through
which we know anything else. And
so again, then we ask the
question, well, how big is
consciousness? We have a
tendency to think that
consciousness kind of fits
inside our skull, but now
increasingly, we realize that's
not an adequate understanding
because of all sorts of
empirical, para psychological,
parapsychological research. So I
think of it more as
consciousness is a field that
our brain allows us to
consolidate and structure inside
our physical existence. But
consciousness in its own right,
is an field. And being a field,
it's open ended, and it's then,
if you ask, how big is that
field? Then we get into the real
cosmological adventure, because
we find, at least, I found that
in if you really go deep into
your psyche, you drop first into
the personal unconscious, into
your personal psyche. If you
keep pushing deeper, you drop
into the collective psyche, the
territory Jung described. But
you can go deeper than that and
drop below the entire psyche of
the human species. You can
transcend the species psyche,
and then you're in a you're in
dimensions of consciousness that
truly, I think of it as the
either the mind of God or I
prefer to think of it as the
mind of the universe, that as
vast as the universe is, you
know, and we know who have a
rough approximation of how many
billions of galaxies are in the
universe, and how huge it is,
how old it is, that
consciousness, that this
universe has a mind, and the
mind is as deep and broad and
old as the universe's body is
so. So that my individual
experience of consciousness is a
simple drop, a fractal aspect of
the totality of consciousness
that flows. And that's why I
gave the book the title LSD in
the mind of the universe.
Because when you go very deep
using a very powerful and
circumscribed protocol, you drop
into deeper and deeper layers,
and you're given the opportunity
to explore the very nature of of
physical reality
Emmy Vadnais: itself. I think we
just lost your video. Chris, I
Chris Bache: lost the video
here. Let's see what's the
audio. Okay, let me see if I can
Jeffrey Mishlove: guess if the
camera is pointing somewhere
else.
Chris Bache: Yeah, let me see if
I don't know why it dropped, but
I can shift to a different
Emmy Vadnais: There we go. Okay,
there's we've got you. We've got
a view of you now here. So,
Okay, wonderful. Okay, good.
Jeffrey Mishlove: You are back.
Well, I think it's important to
emphasize early on in our
discussion, or to repeat what
you said in your earlier
interview with Emmy, that you
are not recommending that other
people do what you did, take
many high doses of LSD that way,
and I know one of our Viewers
has raised the question about
what kind of people, or what
populations of people should not
use psychedelics
Chris Bache: first, I absolutely
agree. I mean, I really do not
recommend that people adopt the
protocol that I adopted, knowing
what I know at the end of this
journey. I if I were starting it
from scratch, I would be much
gentler on myself. I would work
with much lower doses. I would
balance the organic psychedelics
with the synthetic psychedelics.
I just would take a much gentler
approach in but I was young when
I did this work. I had a number
of assumptions that I was making
that turned out not to be
accurate, and I would just be
much gentler and much more
circumscribed in the project.
And there are many, many people,
types of people, who shouldn't
be working with psychedelics
there for either physiological
reasons or psychological reasons
to work with the amplifying
quality means psychedelics are
amplifiers of consciousness.
They take what is far away and
make it available to you, and
they take what is low volume and
make it higher volume. So it's a
tremendous kind of inversion, an
explosion of awareness. And if
you are prepared for it, if you
have the discipline for it, and
if you have the training to
navigate those transitions, and
if you're working with
professionals who can help you
navigate okay, but there are a
lot of people, I think, our best
base, and probably the majority
of people, are Best kind of
working in gentler techniques,
yoga and meditation or trans
dancing, a number of things
which have the same amplifying
effect in a more gentle fashion,
which do in which we can do a
great deal of very good work
without taking psychedelics at
all. In fact, in the mail that
I've gotten from my writing on
psychedelics. Many of the people
who have written me have never
taken psychedelics, or they've
taken psychedelics once or twice
early in their life, but they've
been a meditator for 50 or 50
years, and they are engaging the
cosmology that emerges in my
story and comparing it to the
cosmology that has emerged for
them in their meditative
experience and finding strong
parallels. And so the deepest
level, the issue is not
psychedelics. The issue is
consciousness, the boundaries
and the functions of
consciousness itself. So but
some people should kind of stay
away from these powerful
amplifiers.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, and how many
micrograms? What was the dose
that you were usually working
at? Because I know after we did
that interview, people were some
people were chatting in and
asking what those levels were.
And I think you, like you said,
you would go lower if you were
to do it over again.
Chris Bache: After the first
three sessions, which are medium
dose sessions, I worked at 500
to 600 micrograms, which is
right at the body's maximum
capacity to absorb. Meaning, if
you took more, you don't
necessarily go deeper more or
less. So I was working at very
high levels that basically have
the potential to just shatter,
you know, the structures of
consciousness and take you
temporarily beyond your
traditional ways of knowing
yourself and knowing the world
and again, I would be much
gentler in the early days.
Stanislav. Differentiates
between those psychedelic B
really launched later, over up
to maybe reasons. But at Spring
Grove, they experimented with
working with the population of
clients who were dying of
cancer. They were they were
terminal patients, and they were
trying to address death anxiety,
and they worked with high dose
LSD sessions, essentially trying
to trigger a Near-Death
Experience, so these people
could have an insight into where
they were going, and therefore
relieve the anxiety of death.
And it was quite successful. But
the protocol limited high dose
work to three sessions. And I
came along after years later,
and I thought, well, if you
could work successfully three
times, you could do it more than
three times. And so I adopted
that protocol. I eventually, in
time, I learned I had a capacity
in an aptitude for working at
those levels. I could, I could
let go and expand into the deep
psyche comfortably enough. And I
also did not have problems
consolidating. I tended to
consolidate comfortably and
strongly. And it's just, it's,
it is an unusual, an unusually
intense protocol. I wouldn't do
it again. I'd do it differently.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, in fact, you
have shared, I believe in your
book, and when we had our
previous conversation that near
death experiencers are the group
of people you often relate to
with your own experiences with
Chris Bache: LSD, is that right?
Yeah, I feel the closest, in
some ways, to people who have
near death experiences of any
population, because by when
their body almost dies, they are
catapulted into very deep states
of consciousness. They get
glimpses of the world. They
engage the world. And I think
there's a strong overlap between
what happens in a deep
Near-Death Experience and what
happens in a deep psychedelic,
therapeutically structured
experience. The difference is
that primarily near death,
people get only one take on that
reality. And if you work with
psychedelics like I have, you
get multiple immersions,
multiple initiations into that
reality so that what becomes a
flashing one time exposure
becomes a journey and becomes a
communion that is repeated and
deepened over time.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Yeah. Okay. We
have a question from a viewer
whose YouTube name is greasy,
slick, who would like to know if
you've ever experimented with
DMT, which is considered, I
believe, the most powerful
psychedelic
Chris Bache: I have experience
with other psychedelics other
than LSD, though I consider my
LSD work to be my primary body
of work, I have had some
experiences with DMT, Wilson, of
course, and MDMA and salvia,
Durham and San Pedro. I've had
experiences with five Meo, DMT,
which is an extremely powerful
short acting psychedelic. I
don't have a lot of experiences
with five Meo DMT, I feel like
I'm just beginning to nibble on
that after a long period of not
working with psychedelics,
because I stopped my work
primarily in 1999 and much of my
work with these other
psychedelics came after 1999
when I wasn't so much concerned
with pushing new boundaries, I
was concerned with helping me
integrate the work that I had
already done. But yeah, five Meo
DMT is an extraordinarily
powerful and provocative
psychedelic, and I've had
limited experience with
ketamine, the high dose ketamine
sessions.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Are you able
to draw any meaningful
comparisons between those
entheogens and LSD?
Chris Bache: Well, that's a
conversation we'd have to go
into very carefully, and I don't
think I have enough experience
to really and I don't have
enough knowledge of other
people's experiences to be able
to make a fair comparison at
this time. I do think that there
is a certain advantage to
psychedelics that open a long
window, a window that stays open
for a long period of time, like
LSD, or maybe a little less
Psilocybin, where, if you're
dealing with something like five
Meo DMT, it's a very, very
intense immersion, but it's a
very short acting, a very short
window, and you don't have as
much time for. The infinite
consciousness that you're
accessing or entering into
communion with to impact you and
to clean you and to transform
your life. And I think this is
what Rick Strassman found in his
book on DMT, the spirit
molecule, where he took people
with DMT into very intense
experiences, and some of them
had very deep experiences, but
in the end, he found that they
did not change their lives very
much. These experiences were not
deeply transformative. And I
personally think that part of
the reason is because it is so
short acting versus a long
acting large window. But then
again, even a psychedelic like
LSD, relatively speaking, is
relatively short acting in terms
of compared to other
meditational practices, for
example, where the window is
open for a much longer period of
time. So if we combine
meditation and contemplative and
yogic disciplines, with the
psychedelic practices which give
you a window to experience, then
you have, I think maybe the
optimal conditions for balancing
the virtues of one and the
virtues of the other and
amplifying the transformative
effect.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Wonder off
hand. How many people who do
take LSD, and it's been widely
used in our culture, how many of
those people really have had
their lives transformed the way
you have, and I think I have to
say the way I have, but I'm
under the impression that many,
many people of our generation
took LSD and they weren't even
trying to transform their lives.
It was more a question of
partying.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think
that's the case. And nothing
wrong with that. You know, I
have no criticism of that, but
it is, to me, a kind of a wasted
opportunity. It so much. Ha,
hinges the to me, the
productivity of these really,
for philosophical exploration or
therapeutic applications,
depends on how you handle these
stories of band aware, if you
kind of stay in touch with the
world, and you're having a time,
you're at a concert, or you're
in nature, or you're with some
friends, then that lends itself
to a certain kind of milieu, a
certain level of encounter. But
if you isolate yourself, if you
adopt kind of a zazen
atmosphere, if you create a Kiva
of practice where you're
isolated from the world. You're
wearing eyeshades. So you know
that whatever you're
experiencing is coming only from
within yourself, and if you
engage that with you know
conscious intention, singular
intent, and allow it to take you
where it wants to take you,
which is often not where you
would like to go. It takes you
into the places that you hurt
the most, and then it takes you
into places that you don't even
understand why it hurts so much
when you're going into it,
because you're going beyond the
edge of the maps of the personal
psyche. But if you focus it with
that intent, then something very
exciting opens up as a
possibility, because you not
only have the opportunity to
heal all these knots that are
kind of locked in your heart
from however many incarnations
you've had, but you also, as
these kind of are healed and are
unlocked your receptivity To the
larger fields of consciousness,
which are always there, always
bringing their energy to us,
increases and that really, that
I think is worth a hell of a lot
of concerts.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, Chris, can
you expand a little bit more
about what your session
structures were like, because
somebody commented in the
conversation that we had, they
asked, Why didn't he just go out
and hang out in the mountains
and nature and and how you had
somebody there with you as well.
And I think you look to
Stanislav Grof for how to go
about that, is that, right?
Chris Bache: Yeah, I, you know,
I was Stan's work is so
formidable, and his intellectual
synthesis of so many traditions
is so important that he became
my kind of foundation for doing
this work. And again, remember,
I was, I was doing this work in
Ohio. I was a long way from San
Francisco. I was not part of a
psychedelic community. I was not
part of an Ayahuasca group that
going down to Peru regularly to
work with indigenous shamans
there. I was really working
alone, and I adopted the
protocol that Stan had outlined
in his book LSD psychotherapy,
published. 1980 right in the
very early years of my work. And
so my protocol, and first, I
think it's it's wonderful to go
sit in nature and do a lower,
moderate dose of psychedelics
and enter into that kind of
communion that can open. It's
just not what I did. So my days
would always start early in the
morning. I would have everything
set up. I would be either at a
third floor of our home or later
when we started having children.
I worked in my wife's office.
Carol was a clinical
psychologist, and she was my
sitter for all of my sessions.
So we would start in the early
morning, I would do meditation,
yoga, body stretching and
whatnot, and then we would begin
the session. They were all
guided with very carefully
selected music. So that Carol
had a library of music available
to her, because you want to pace
the rhythm of the shopping the
full peak and the decline of the
section. Different types of
music are appropriate for
different stages of that
process. And you can get lots of
examples of this music from
Holotropic Breathwork sites,
which often catalog extensive
libraries for this type of work.
So basically, I would spend all
day lying down with eyeshades,
and the only way my sitter
primarily related to me was
through the music. One time I
took, we took a movie camera and
set it up to see if it would be
interesting. But actually, it
was frightfully boring, because
it's all the action is taking
place inside. It doesn't show
much on the outside, except
periodically throwing up, which
is, you know, not that great to
watch, but sorry, all day, and
then usually by mid late
afternoon sessions wrapping up.
But even after the session, the
formal session wraps up, the
tail is still very long, and I
learned that you have to give a
lot of space, a lot of time,
because that you're it's the
long tail is a good opportunity
to reflect upon and to integrate
the insights that's emerged.
Because these insights can come
and they can be very powerful,
but like a dream, you can lose
them, and it's important to hold
on to them as well as you can.
And so my custom was the day
after session, the next morning,
I would spend that morning as
long as it took to write out an
complete as thorough and account
of each session. And I found
that I had to develop a strategy
for sort of maximizing recall. I
began I would take the playlist
that was used in the session in
exactly the order in which the
music was played, because my
sitter had kept a record, and
then I would play the music
while I was writing, and I would
play each piece of music over
and over till I felt I had
captured as best I could what
happened during that part of the
Muse session. And then I went on
to the next base of music and
the next piece of music, so that
by the time I was finished, I
had as reliable an account as I
could create of the session. And
once it's in, like that, once
it's locked in, I don't change
it, it's it's locked. And I
found that if I attempted to
make improvements on the text
later, my improvements often
diluted aspects or they took the
sharp edge off of the focus. So
I basically respected the text,
the sessions, as my primary
text, and that's why, in my
book, all the sessions are
produced in a italic text to
separate them from the
commentation. Commentator that
commentator that I put after the
session.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, well, that's
fascinating. I believe in
psychological terms. It's called
state dependent memory, where
you so you were using your music
that you were listening to
during the session to help reach
Chris Bache: because day after
and you're still sort of one
foot in, one foot out, you know,
you're and it's what I call kind
of standing at the edge of the
well, you're you're one foot in
and one foot out. And by playing
the music while you have your
cognitive capacities back, you
can let your mind go back into
that territory and capture it.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Question here
a couple of people have raised
it in different ways, and it has
to do with the way we titled
this program using your phrase
diamond Luminosity. So one of
our viewers, Celia funk, who is
also one of our volunteers and
just had a baby recently,
congratulations. She says, this
may be a silly question, but
does the title diamond
Luminosity. Luminosity refer to
actual diamonds. And then a
different viewer asked, Well, is
it related to the Diamond Sutra?
Chris Bache: Yeah, that's not a
silly question at all. Maybe a
little bit of background, the
phrase diamond Luminosity points
to states of consciousness that
I entered in the last five years
of my work. So I had already
gone through kind of what Stan
Grof calls the perinatal
process, and gone through a
really solid ego death. I'd gone
into what I came to call, later
the ocean of suffering, working
at the collective psyche level.
Had gone into archetypal
reality. I'd gone into causal
level reality, many adventures
in that process, and I was
feeling absolutely
philosophically satiated and
complete by that time, because I
had been I was having
experiences of profound oneness
with existence and even touching
the meta, cosmic void and having
standing under the waterfall of
cosmic love. So I was
existentially very satisfied.
But in the last five years and
26 sessions, I was catapulted
after one more series of death
and rebirth experiences into a
state of consciousness that was
light, but exceptionally pure,
exceptionally clear, light,
clear beyond imagination. Now I
had access light many times
before when you have a an ego
death experience, or you have
other deep experiences. Many
people encounter the light this,
and it's the light is kind of
the signature of these radically
expanded divine states of
consciousness. But when I talk
about diamond Luminosity, I'm
trying to describe a particular
state of consciousness, a hyper,
hyper, clear, clear state of
consciousness. And because I
know the Buddhist literature
better than other spiritual
traditions, at least the
mystical side of it, I correlate
it with what the Buddhists call
Dharmakaya, the clear light of
absolute reality. It is the
foundational metaphysical
structure. It is the light out
of which the Big Bang emerges
and gives birth to the entire
physical universe. So it was
hyper clear, and so it doesn't
have anything to do with
physical diamonds, but it does
have something to do with what
the Diamond Sutra is talking
about, and Vajrayana Buddhism is
vadra diamond. So it's a
diamond, it's a diamond V and
there is a cool at least, other
structures also talk about this
diamond esque Luminosity. But I
know it best from reading the
Buddhist sources about this
reality. And it seems to me that
it correlates with what are
described in the Tantras in the
Vadnais Sutras of the
Dharmakaya. Beautiful.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, there's a
question here from Megan Salar,
who you've mentioned this a few
times about meditation, and she
says he talks about the
importance of meditation and
work outside of this psychedelic
work, what does his daily
practice look like? Or what
would he recommend?
Chris Bache: Well, the longer
that I worked with psychedelics,
the more I appreciated how
important it is to have a daily
spiritual practice. Because when
you go into psychedelics
conscientiously, you open your
system up to a vast field of
consciousness progressively
deeper and deeper, larger and
larger and and you open yourself
up to enormous flows of energy,
because I found that each step
into a deeper state of
consciousness was a step into a
higher level of energy. And to
stabilize consciousness at that
higher level, you have to
acclimate to the high level of
energy that's involved, which
requires intense, hard to
describe, but very intense
purification processes, which
often have the form of fire and
solar flares and volcanic just
tremendous fire energy to
transform your being, so that
you can become a being who can
live for hours at a time, at
that very, very deep level of
consciousness where the world
works at this level and causal
level reality, where it's a it's
a different physics. It's a
different landscape of
consciousness than lower levels
of consciousness, where you
have, you still have individual.
Beings doing individual things
and having individual
experiences. So when you open up
to these deep levels, and then
after it's over, you come back
into your ordinary
consciousness, I find that it's
really important to have a daily
spiritual practice to anchor
you, to help keep your feet
solid on the ground, and also
because the skills that are
acquired in a meditative
practice, in Vipassana practice
or zazen practice, are precisely
the kind of skills of
observations and non attachment,
which you also use in a
psychedelic session, so they
reinforce each other
structurally. But meditation
gives you an environment to
assess some of the content, the
cognitive content of your
temporary sessions, but also it
gives you an environment to
process the energy which is
ignited and set loose in your
psychedelic sessions. So that in
the chapter on Diamond
Luminosity, I talk about my work
on integrating Vajrayana
practice with my psychedelic
practice. And I actually didn't
begin the Vajrayana practice
until about the same time I was
entering the diamond Luminosity,
and it was Carol who brought me
into the vadrayana tradition,
because she did a vadna practice
Chud for me on before one of my
psychedelic sessions. And the
window that opened in that
session, this is the 45th
session. So I was had a lot of
history by that time, but the
window that opened was wider,
deeper, and it stayed open
longer that then had been the
case in earlier sessions. So I
immediately learned that
practice and began to do that
practice before any psychedelic
session. I would never go into
psychedelic space without doing
Chud, which is a cleansing it
means cutting. It's a cleansing
practice. And I found that when
I was working at these very,
very high energetic levels, it
sometimes set in motion
processes which are very
difficult to integrate processes
in my subtle energy system. If
you know Alex Gray's work, and
you you see how beautiful he
depicts the powerful energies
that are triggered in deep
psychedelic work. After the
session is over, they can leave
your system feeling quite achy
and sort of stretched. And I
found that doing Vajrayana
practice, doing the Guru Yoga
practices, or deity yoga
practices, gave that energy a
place to run when I was back in
my ordinary consciousness, back
in my ordinary body. So for lots
of reasons, both for
clarification of cognitive
content, for practicing the
teachings that are given to you
in your psychedelic sessions,
for managing the energetic
consequences of entering into
those states. I think a daily
spiritual practice is really
important. And I would mention
that before I go, would go into
a psychedelic space, I would
always you. I would change my
psychic my spiritual practice
for days and weeks before going
into the session, and then I
would do different practices
coming out of the session. I
would be doing kind of soul
integration practices after a
session, and more cutting
clearing practices before the
session. So there's a lot of
subtlety in in practices. And I
would do yoga, I would
basically, because I would want
my body to be as clear and as
possible for would come to these
states. And I would also, for
example, make sure I get a cut
right if I needed to. Because if
you're if your body is
misaligned structurally or
muscularly or emotionally,
that's and you amp your energy
up, then those blocks are going
to be amplified and become
problematic. So good personal
hygiene, good care of your body,
care of your of yoga, care of
your mind, meditation, before
and after. I think these are all
just good hygiene practices, and
so my what I do for my daily
practice has changed over time.
I've been a meditator for a long
time, worked in the Vajrayana
tradition for a long time.
Though, I do find that one of
the places, because I'm a
talker, because I'm an academic,
and because I like to explain
things I find teaching is
actually has become a spiritual
art form for me, because to
enter, to try to bring these
ideas, spiritual ideas. Make
them available to enter into
dialog with students day after
day, week after week. That
requires, or it invites, a kind
of a existential posture, a
spiritual posture. It's very
demanding kind of work if you're
really going to engage students
at this very deep, existential
level. So for me, teaching is is
its own form, a very demanding
form of spiritual practice.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, thank you
for teaching and sharing with
all of us here. I may have asked
you in the interview we did,
Chris, I don't see any questions
at the moment coming through
quite the same way. And I know
this could be a long answer, but
if what, what is it that you
felt you learned from these
sessions? What is it that yeah,
that is so important that you
think our viewers and listeners
might benefit from Yeah?
Chris Bache: You know that that
is a large topic. And the
challenge of trying to answer
that question is doing justice
to how many layers of
consciousness I went through
over this 20 year journey. Many
of our important books on
psychedelics are based on a much
smaller number of sessions, and
that tends to create
expectations, which shrinks the
metaphysical window. So that
Aldous Huxley's book, The Doors
of Perception, he wrote after
only one session, one Mescaline
session, and Huston Smith's
book, cleansing the doors of
perception, where he gathered a
lifetime of writing on
psychedelics, he had only done
LSD six times. And after that,
he said the bombers increased,
and he decided to take Alan
Watts's advice, once you get the
message, hang up the phone. But
that suggests that the only kind
of one or small number of
messages that might show up,
which may be the case in a
couple of sessions. The
challenging trying to describe
what I learned from it is first
trying to describe the many
stages of initiation that took
place, going from personal to
collective, to increase to
subtler and causal levels of
reality and Non-duality. So a
reporter asked me that question
one time, and I I made a list of
the things which were the
highlighted, and I included it
in the in the last chapter of
the book. And I can't remember
all the things now, so I'll just
try to approximate my memory. I
discovered that underlying all
existence is a singular
intelligence of unbelievable
magnitude, of genius
unbelievable intelligence, and
that the physical universe is
the manifest body of this
genius, of this creative
intelligence, so that the world
that we're living in is the
physical body of the Divine. And
nothing I'm going to say here is
new. It's the cosmology that
emerges in psychedelics is
essentially the same cosmology
that emerges in the great
mystical traditions of classical
contemplative cultures. So
there's nothing new. It's just a
different technique, a different
trigger protocol for accessing
some of these dimensions of
consciousness, so that all
existence is unified in a
fundamental one. Oneness is kind
of the one of the core teachings
that emerges over and over
again. You can enter into
oneness so deeply that you enter
into a condition that the
Buddhas call Shunyata emptiness
of self, or anata Nirvana, the
self is blown out. And when you
are empty of self deeply, you
experience the entire world is
also empty of cells. And if you
experience the world as
completely empty of separate
individual existences, then
within a differentiation of a
physical universe, the entire
universe lives and breathes us,
one, as Plotinus said, so just
and you can enter the
opportunity to enter into
intimacy with this
consciousness, to meet it on
these special days, and to be
engaged by this consciousness
and go deeper and deeper and
deeper into this consciousness.
And so I'll mention, in this
context, I knit, I didn't have
much contact with individual
spirit guides or individual
deities or individual forms. My
it's. Not that I don't think
these things exist. It's just
hasn't been my experience, and I
think it's partly because of the
protocol I used, and because of
the qualities of LSD as the
psychedelic that it was grinding
me up so fine and spreading my
dust so deeply into these layers
of reality that transcend
individual life beings, so that
I had many experiences of being
at different levels, but not
many experiences of individual
beings. So part of it is just
the loving, the communion that
this intelligence is just
extraordinary and also this
oneness, this being is loving
beyond measure. When I have been
tapped into the love that this
being that brought this being to
create and share its existence
in this form, the love is
overwhelming, and that really
surprised me, because I was
okay. I was expecting, you know,
the creative intelligence to be
intelligent, but I was surprised
by how much love was present.
And so when people talk about
love is the primary virtue, I
mean, I understand that. I mean
that really does. I all learned
that our participation in
creation is taking place over
hundreds of 1000s of years,
hundreds of 1000s of years. We
that reincarnation is a simple
fact of life, and that because
reincarnation is a fact of life,
we are not time limited in our
development, we have to have an
understanding. Our spiritual
understanding should recognize
that it's not what happens in
any one particular life which is
paramount, and it's not over at
the end of any one life, but
it's an ongoing progression that
takes us back and forth between
spirit and matter over and over
again, over and over again, in
an evolutionary exercise that
isn't, I don't think it doesn't
culminate in enlightenment. Even
the classic vision is you get
better and better and clearer
and clearer until eventually you
achieve realization, you achieve
enlightenment. And once you
achieve enlightenment, you can
leave, you transcend Samsara,
the cycles of existence, you can
permanently go to some off
planet, spiritual paradise. But
I don't think that's my least
what I've been shown and told is
that's not really the project at
that's an understandable
interpretation from our early
experience, when we first made
contact, several 1000 years ago,
with this profound mother
universe, with the spiritual
mother universe. It's an
understandable Kant In
conclusion, because this
universe is so beautiful and so
ecstatic and and it feels so
much like home. Naturally. We
think that we want to be there.
We belong there. We came from
there, and it leads to the
religions of return, so that
it's all about transcending the
limits of human condition and
returning to where we came from,
where we belong, which generates
up and out cosmology. And I
think that's a reflection not of
the way the world is, but of our
early understanding of the
world, which is now deepening.
Now that we have a better
understanding of how huge the
universe is and how long it's
been in existence, then we if
you really want to understand
life, you have to begin to think
like God. You have to think like
a galaxy and understand that the
creative intelligence thinks in
terms of billions and billions
of years. It doesn't think in
terms of individuals so much as
it thinks of whole species,
whole planetary systems,
galactic systems. And we have to
allow ourselves to expand to
understand what is our role in
such a universe, and
reincarnation allows us to do
that. Reincarnation helps us
understand not only the tensions
that are woven into the body
that we have and the mind that
we have, but it also weaves us.
It gives us an invitation to
participate more fully into the
divine project, so that the goal
becomes to achieve realization,
to achieve some deep
experiential grounding of our of
understanding, our experience of
our true essential nature, which
is underneath our personality
nature. But then once we have
that, once we understand that,
once we understand that every
living thing is grounded in that
same reality, that the essence
of my individuality is the same
as the essence of everybody
else's individuality, we're all
in this together. Then the goal
becomes, I think. To
progressively integrate more and
more and more spiritual reality
into our physical incarnation,
so that we can truly bring
heaven to earth, that we can
truly transform our physical
world into a paradise, and not
in a metaphorical sense, but I
mean in a literal sense, that we
eventually will become a species
of awakened beings, a species of
enlightened beings, a species of
saved beings, and a species of
enlightened beings creates a
different earth than a species
of unenlightened beings. So the
size of the project, the
communion, the opportunity to
enter into communion with the
project. Reincarnation is true.
Reincarnation leads to a
different story, a different
anthropology, if you will, of
the whole creative endeavor.
Those are, I guess, some of the
highlights of the large ideas
that stand out. And as I said,
they're not new. These are all
well established in our classic
mystical
Emmy Vadnais: traditions, and
yet we seem to need to continue
to hear them over and over and
over again. We do. Some of us,
apparently need to.
Jeffrey Mishlove: I think it may
feel like I need to
Chris Bache: me too, you know?
And I think one of the
differences, it's sometimes said
that the age of individual
enlightenment is over now, it's
collective enlightenment that is
a challenge we face because and
I think that's really true. And
the 2000 or so years of
individual enlightenment or
individual salvation, perfectly
well understandable. But now, if
we don't, if the whole species
doesn't awaken, we likely won't
be able to survive on this
planet. We have to grow up. We
have to stop being egoic
children, and we have to grow up
into our soul consciousness in
our deeper spiritual nature,
otherwise we're going to lose
the planet.
Jeffrey Mishlove: I have a
question from Pablo geralda,
who's one of our volunteers.
Pablo is in Argentina, and he
asks you, Chris, if you have
advice for somebody who wants to
try psychedelics for the first
time, and what are are there
legal ways to do it? He's
asking. And another viewer,
Gracie slick, raises the
question, how do you acquire
LSD? To my knowledge, it's
illegal everywhere in the United
States. And so then there's a
question of, obviously, there is
a market for it, but the
question is, how do you know
what you're getting
Chris Bache: absolutely first,
and I do not want to encourage
people to break the law. I mean,
it's just a speaks, be careful
here. This is, that I would not
want anyone to break the law and
get in trouble doing something
like this. There are people who
want to work with Ayahuasca, and
they will go to Peru or to
Brazil to work with in Ayahuasca
communities and sante Daime or
union de vegetal, there are
Ayahuasca communities in the
United States now which have won
the right to use Ayahuasca in
spiritual context. They've won
the right from the Supreme Court
to do this. They are not
plentiful, but they are here
among the psychedelics. Ketamine
is the only one that's legal
right now. The MDMA, which is an
empathogen, more than a strict
psychedelic, but it's important
therapeutic instrument, got
turned down just last year, but
it'll be here. It'll be coming
back. It will be made legal,
probably within three years,
Psilocybin won't be far behind.
So what's legal now and what's
legal in 10 years will be very
different even five years. So
the number of psychedelics that
one might be able to use is
increasing in the years to come.
How do you know whether what
you've gotten is pure, and
that's really an important
issue, because you do not want
street drugs are filled with all
sorts of contaminants that you
do not want to put into your
system. And you can send these
to labs sponsored by the federal
government. You can send them
anonymously to be tested, and
you'll be told what's in them.
And so you can check and verify
at the state level or the
federal level what it is that
you've got here, what you're
taking and how strong it is. So
yeah, and
Emmy Vadnais: as far as
procuring it, no comment or
that's up to each person to you.
Find a path themselves.
Chris Bache: Maybe, yeah, no
comment, because there you can
grow mushrooms. You can learn
how to grow mushrooms. I mean,
you can create your own
Psilocybin mushrooms. And there
is, of course, a clear
underground throughout the
country, which some of them is
some of many, much of it is very
irresponsible in terms of
impurities, and some of the
people are very conscientious
about this. But still, you have
to proceed with caution and
always test what you have. Yeah,
great.
Emmy Vadnais: Here's a question
from first Deacon Gemini. They
ask, what is the difference
between ego death and
disassociation or de realization
both entail detachment and
depending on the person, it can
feel good, bad or neutral?
Chris Bache: Yeah. Well, I'm not
a psychologist, so take what I
say, de realization with a grain
of salt here. I understand that
to be a psychological experience
or condition in which you feel
yourself to be dissolving or not
grounded in your real or
conventional identity, and it is
some it's often associated with
various forms of
psychopathology, because if it
becomes endemic, it undermines
your capacity to function as a
strong individual within the
World. Ego Death is sort of
similar to that, but different.
It's sometimes said you have to
have a strong ego for to go
through ego death to have a good
ego death. Ego Death is
basically, let me back up, if
you are grounded in the way most
people are, in our bodily
consciousness, and a
consciousness which basically
reflects the history of this
body in this time reality, if
you begin to open up into deeper
spiritual realities, then sooner
or later, you have to let go of
your egoic identity, your body
mind identity, to begin to have
access to these deeper, broader
states where the ego doesn't
have a function. In mystical
traditions, in classic
contemplative traditions, the
death of self is well known and
recognized. It's usually
achieved through a lifestyle of
compassion, lifestyle of
service, a lifestyle of
generosity, prayer, practicing,
spiritual practice,
contemplative practice. It's a
slow, gradual softening of the
heart and then opening up to
kind of an infusion of divine
flux, which is always there.
It's always pressing it upon us.
We just the ego keeps it out. So
if you kind of sacrifice the ego
and take it apart through
generosity, selflessness, acts
of prayer, you're making a
transition from a consciousness
which is time, space, grounded,
bodily, grounded into a
consciousness which is more
mystical, more open. What
happens in a psychedelic session
is the same process, but it's
accelerated and intensified. If
I'm thinking now, I'm a
professor of religious studies,
so I've always held the
spiritual traditions in the back
of my mind while I'm doing
psychedelic work. And to me,
I've always approached
psychedelic work as a spiritual
practice, even though the goal
of my work was kind of
different. It wasn't awakening
so much as it was cosmological
exploration, but basically
taking the lessons that we've
learned about how to become a
more spiritually attuned person
from the spiritual traditions,
and taking that into the
psychedelic context. And in the
psychedelic context where you
are very powerfully activating
deeper levels of awareness,
which open up the floodgates, in
a way, to this deeper spiritual
reality. You reach a point where
the ego is put under pressure
and it just it just ruptures.
You can't contain consciousness
within the structure of your
ego. And when you get a lot of
people, a lot of psychologists,
a lot of exercise, a lot of ink
and sweat over the complexity
and strength and durability of
the ego, but from a spiritual
perspective, when you get right
down to it, it's not that hard
to take it apart. You really
can. Just break it apart, and
when I went through my major ego
death experience, the universe
just snapped me like a twig. It
didn't involve de realization,
but it involved a frightening
confrontation, because I was
turned into something which was
the exact opposite of everything
I had always known myself to be.
I had always known myself to be
a man, to be an intellectual, to
be white, to be passionately
concerned with the meaning of
existence. In this critical
session, I was turned into the
opposite of this. I was turned
into women. I was turned into
women of color, women who had no
philosophical expectations or
interests at all, and it was the
perfect health for male academic
philosopher. It scared the
bajibas out of me. And then when
I let go and I allowed myself to
become these women, then first,
I was immediately relaxed, and I
was taken under the arm of the
Great Mother and taken into an
extraordinary journey into the
lives of women, into hundreds
and hundreds of women. And then
after the session was over, as I
was coming back, my male
identity reasserted itself, and
because I like being a man, but
I knew that my masculinity and
my whiteness and my intellectual
would never confine me the way
it had confined me before. The
problem wasn't of women, of
course, or the anti the non
intellectual issues. The problem
was the tight fit that my social
identity had on my
consciousness, and that had to
be broken. It was as if the
universe was saying to me,
listen, where you're going.
Gender does not exist. Let go.
And that's when I let go, and I
went into states of
consciousness that don't
differentiate between male and
female, and then eventually
going into states of
consciousness which don't
differentiate between human and
non human, right? And then going
into states of consciousness
which go beyond space and time
entirely. So ego death is just
that, that kind of rupture which
can be slow or fast, depending
on what method you're using to
let go of your preoccupation
with self, you know. The
Tibetans call it self clinging,
you know. And we can see self
clinging when you look at a
picture, the group picture, like
a class picture, and where does
your eye go? Your eye kind of
goes quick to where you are in
the picture. That's a symptom of
self clinging. It's that
constant self referencing into
your own life experience, which
is understandable from one
perspective, but so sad from
another perspective, right? So
it's like if, if you take it, if
you think of the ego like an ice
cube, and you put an ice cube
next to a candle, it melts very
slowly, it drips and melts down.
And I think this is like what
happens in contemplative
practice, where you melt this
ego slowly. But if you take the
same ice cube and you throw it
on a hot iron, cast iron
skillet, it jumps around and it
melts faster, but it explodes
and bounces all over the place,
and I think that's kind of like
how Ego Death manifests itself
in psychedelic sessions. So
there's not a right way or a
wrong way, but the pattern is
that we'd have to let go of the
confines of these bars that keep
us imprisoned in our self
referential existence.
Emmy Vadnais: And do you feel
that the ego serves any purpose,
since we all seem to have it, or
is it just something to be
dissolved or eliminated or
accepted and then transformed,
or however, Yeah, that happens.
Chris Bache: No, I think ego
gets a bad rap in many spiritual
traditions. And I think the ego,
and by that, I mean our
individual identity, our
individual body, mind identity.
It's a beautiful thing. It's
really It's magnificent. And I
think it's a cosmologically
important thing. I think it's
one of the major gifts that we
are given by entering into time
space. Now, a number of
spiritual traditions, again, in
the kind of the classic schools,
they say, well, the goal is to
destroy ego, lose ego, and to
return to God. So it's like a
drop of water that returns to
the ocean. When the drop goes
back to the ocean, it doesn't
exist anymore. And that's the
Vedanta picture, is you
basically eliminate ego so that
you can live the life divine,
but you just live the life
divine, no longer as an
individual. You just. Surrender
completely and become the
divine. And I don't think that's
an adequate cosmology. I think
that, I think that the creative
intelligence has created a
system which, first of all, we
have a life as individual, as an
individual, and we we explore
and deepen and expand this
individual experience lifetime
after lifetime after lifetime.
And the goal is not to
completely abandon our
individuality, but the goal is
to is to engage what is left out
of the individual ego's
experience to engage the
tremendous power of
consciousness, the love that
runs through existence, the
intelligence that runs through
existence, so that you are both
an individual, but you are all
now transparent to The Divine
condition. I don't think
individuality is destroyed when
you go deeper and deeper. I
think it's actually transformed.
And I think individuality is
truly one of the great gifts of
the mother. It's one of the
great gifts of time, space,
existence. And I think if you
study the biographies of the
autobiographies are biographies
of great spiritual adepts, of
great masters. You find that
they are individual. You know
they're they're quite
distinctive individual. So
enlightenment is about anata, no
self, but it doesn't mean that
your individuality is shattered
irrevocably and doesn't come
back. If that's happening, then
that's a kind of a form of
psychopathology, even spiritual
pathology. I think healthy
spiritual maturity is you have
individual experience. You have
your individual reference point,
but you're not imprisoned within
that reference point. You build
bridges, you you connect and
receive this. You you you care
about more than just yourself,
you care about more than just
your species. You care about
more than just your generation,
and you live large. You're an
individual, but you're living a
much larger life.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, you know,
you recognize the
interconnectedness, and perhaps
can merge with that, and that
really seems to be a definition
of yoga is union with the
divine, perhaps,
Chris Bache: yes, yeah, union
with the Divine and not
dissolving irrevocably so that
you don't have an individual
awareness or individuality.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah. Thank you
for all of these answers. Chris
and we just want to let our
viewers and listeners know that
we are over 60 minutes in. We've
got about 25 minutes left of the
live stream.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Here's a
question from a viewer whose
YouTube name is Fabius, who
says, How can we reconcile the
ideal of transforming Earth into
a paradise with the spiritual
necessity of contrast and
suffering as essential
conditions for learning and
growth in the human experience.
Chris Bache: Great question,
good question. Now that the
question of suffering is a
profound question, and that we
could take the whole program
just to explore that particular
topic. I mean, if there is, if
the creative intelligence is an
intelligence and it's loving,
how could we, how could it
possibly have tolerated, let
alone manifested, a world which
is so painful, which which is,
which terrible things happen at
a very organic level, let alone
a social level. And I think in
order, in order to really
understand and to even have an
attempt to comprehend suffering,
we have to develop a very long
time horizon. We have to look
deep into the workings of the
universe, and we have to sort of
adopt a galactic perspective.
And I think this is important to
understand that the human
species is a radically
unfinished species. It's a very
incomplete species. And so if
you think of all, how young are
we? I mean, are we kind of like
one to 100 are we 95% finished?
Are we 5% finished? You know?
And I think we're maybe more
like five or 10% finished. We
just woke up. I mean, 5000 4000
years ago, we just woke up to
this underlying level of
consciousness that we've begun
to recognize in the true
religious traditions. This
universe has been building this
world for 3.7 billion years, and
we're just waking up in this
universe and just coming to
understand and to engage in it
consciously, rather than un.
Unconsciously, and the
capacities that we see in the
highest, most spiritually
realized individuals, the
capacity of not only compassion,
but the capacity to have control
over their own physical process,
and even the capacity to have to
change matter around them to
manipulate matter, as some of
the great mahasiddhas have the
capacity to do. We see in those
beings, the symptoms or the
qualities that are emerging are
emergent qualities in spirit in
beings who are integrating more
and more spiritual capacity
inside this physical body. So if
we look to the future and we
ask, what is what are we
becoming? What is the project?
The project is not human beings
as they exist in the 21st
Century. The project is how
human beings will exist in the
23rd 25th 3/30, century, 40th
century. And in that context,
suffering? Yeah, I don't want
to. I don't want to. A lot of
people who are listening, who
are watching, have suffered
greatly in their life. We've all
suffered, and some of us have
suffered deeply and profoundly
in our life, and I do not mean
to make light of that in any
way, in anything that I would
say, but suffering is part of
the crucible within which we are
learning and on this planet. And
suffering has individual roots,
sometimes in our individual
karma. Of the past, bad choices
we've made. But suffering also
has collective roots. Sometimes
the suffering that we engage in
this life is not because of
anything that we've done
personally, but it's because of
where the collective is, where
the herd is. It's a suffering
which is generated by a common
denominator of the of the
learning of the human species.
We are just in the early stages
of really understanding the full
power of our nature, of our true
and essential nature. And the
goal of this access to this deep
nature is not simply to be happy
and to be relaxed and to be
comfortable, but it's literally
to transform our experience of
being an incarnation of
spiritual being, so that the
goal is to increasingly change
the conditions of our life, so
that we are literally living not
only a spiritually relaxed and
comfortable and good existence,
but that we are able we are
gradually changing the
conditions of our physical
existence. I think they'll in
the future, we will see we will
have more control over our
body's diseases and more ability
to intervene in the diseases of
the body and to produce a
healthier and healthier body. I
think we'll be seeing all sorts
of traits that we consider
miraculous becoming increasingly
natural and manifest. And I
think when we come to this
pivot, when we go through the
pivot that I think we're coming
into. You know, I have a chapter
in the book on the birth of the
future human I think we have
entered a really critical pivot
point in the human story. We are
being taken into the next level
of our human evolution. I think
we will see a significant
amelioration of our collective
suffering. As we make this
transition, I think we are going
towards a period where
individually and collectively, a
world of less suffering, a world
of greater joy, a world of
greater spiritual empowerment
and physical ease as we go
forward and as we go through
this transition, this is just
the next iteration of an
evolutionary story which has
been going on for hundreds,
millions of years, millions of
years, and will continue to go
on for millions, billions of
years, four. So in order to
understand why we suffer, we
have to, if we really want to
understand, we have to go very,
very deep. We have to go deep
into the divine intention. We
have to go deep and open up a
very, very large vision of
history, even if we're going to
begin to have a chance of
understanding why existence is
so hard.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Well, if I
could follow up with a related
question, the previous question
was sort of the paradox of the
necessity of suffering and as
compared to the goal of a.
Establishing more of a paradise
on earth. Another paradox, to me
seems to be the idea that you've
expressed, that consciousness is
fundamental, it's primary, it's
it's the foundation of all
existence, yeah, and yet it's
through a chemical substance
that you got there, which would
lead a lot of materialists to
say, see, it's consciousness is
nothing more than a product of
chemistry. Yeah.
Chris Bache: And the same thing
happens if you just sit on a
meditation cushion for long
periods of time and become an
increasingly proficient, and in
that form, we can now monitor
the brain wave patterns, and we
can even explore the
biochemistry of meditative
states of consciousness. And we
can say the same thing. See,
it's biochemistry and
electrical, you know, wave forms
in the brain which are actually
inducing this. But that really
kind of doesn't really solve the
problem, does it? Because it
that that is the application of
a particular metaphysical
worldview of materialism. And
there, if we want to probe that
worldview, we can find lots of
counter evidence that will
demonstrate that that's an
inadequate worldview. It was an
adequate worldview in the 18th,
19th century, when we got into
it. But it's not an adequate
worldview to handle the wide
range of experiences that occur
in lots of different contexts.
Parapsychological research,
psychedelic research, different
you know, near death, Episode
research, reincarnation
research, all of that undermine
if you're really paying
attention the the plausibility
of the Metaphysic of the
metaphysics of materialism. So
but it is an ironic thing that
we have this chemical substance
which interacts with our body in
a way that seems to open us to
it opens the floodgates of our
Well, see, I tend to think of
the mind as kind of more like a
transceiver. It is a gate
controller, and so it changes
the gate structure. It kind of
puts our default mode network
and allow into quiescence, and
it allows us to temporarily have
states of awareness that go
beyond the default mode network.
But it we that kind of mechanism
is subject to different
interpretations, if we apply a
materialist interpretation, or
if we bring to it a non
materialist, spiritual
perspective in which we can
understand human existence. The
way I understand the human being
is that we are living at a
synthesis. We are a synthesis of
two different systems to be very
simply, between a spiritual
reality and a physical reality.
They are always intertwined. We
are. We are living them
continuously. If we survive the
destruction of our body, it's
not because of something that
happens to us when we die. It's
because of something that we
already are. We already are
living with one foot in two
worlds, and we know that if we
shift the balance, we can open
ourselves to that spiritual
dimension without leaving our
physical body. And we can do it
through any number of different
contemplative practices and
yogic practices. We can also do
it using Soma, using some of the
ancient sacred medicines in the
tradition that doesn't prove
materialism, it just proves,
again, if we start with a model
that we are a synthesis of two
metaphysical systems, then we
can explain all the phenomena
and more of the phenomena than
materialism can explain.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, here's a
question from my husband,
Xander, and as humans, we have a
sensory system and a motor
system through which you
mentioned it with the brain,
that's the central nervous
system, and some refer to that
as being a filter of
consciousness. And he asks, If
you had synesthetic experiences,
what sense our senses were most
active, so synesthesia, where
maybe you like hear smells, or,
yeah, based vision, or
Chris Bache: no, I'm not in a
good position to answer that
question. I'm afraid Xander, I
just because those kind of
experiences are not, are not, do
not figure largely in my
experience. So I haven't thought
about them a lot. I haven't
studied them very much. I don't
when I've taken psychedelics, I
don't hallucinate on them. I
mean, I'm always wrapped up with
eye shades and whatnot. But even
when I've taken the eye shades
off, I don't. Have visual
distortions in my world around
me. If I had stayed in touch
with physical reality, I'm sure
I would have, and then I might
have had some of the experiences
you're referring to. But if you
internalize your experience
completely, you engage conscious
reality, and then you're on a
conscious experience. And I see
many things, and I experience
many things, but I don't
experience them as kind of a
permutation or distortion of my
physical sensation. It's kind of
like I just let go of physical
sensation and I just plunge into
the conscious, the tunnel of
consciousness, and go there. Now
I'm sure there's a good answer
to your question, and I'm sure
people, maybe even people on
this podcast right now, who
would be able to give you a good
answer to that question. I'm
just afraid I'm not one of them.
Emmy Vadnais: Well, I think he's
had those experiences, and
that's why he was curious if
that's something you you had
also experienced.
Chris Bache: Yeah, yeah. The
permeability between our senses
shows up in several different
contexts. I know it shows up in
shamanic drumming, for example.
The different fluidity there we
are such a complex being this
blending of spirit and matter,
it shows up at very broad
levels, and it shows up at very
micro levels in our sensation.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Here's a
question from a viewer named
Corey Burdick, who asks, what
are some of the most powerful or
inspiring examples of the
emergence of the new human.
Chris Bache: Well, I think when
we see somebody who's willing to
lay down his life for others,
that's an extraordinary example
when we see people who spend
their entire life working to
help other people, and they they
they bypass putting their energy
towards enhancing their life,
and they invest all their energy
in helping other people live a
full, enriched life. Those are
symptoms of the of the future
human, the way I understand the
future human, I'll step aside
for just a second and come back
to the focus. We've been
incarnating for 1000s and 1000s,
hundreds of 1000s of years.
We've been incarnating and the
pattern in our religious
structures have sort of seen a
linear development in our
reincarnation. We go backwards,
you go forward. But basically
making a linear development, it
in so that we become eventually
more compassionate, more
intelligent, more creative, so
on so forth. But I think at
least as it's as it's been shown
to me, and as I've been taken
into it, I think we are coming
to a time of history in general,
and people individually where,
well, let me just say how it
happened to me. I reached a
point in one of my sessions when
all of my former lives started
coming into me, and I had done
years of past life, therapy
work, so I was familiar with
some of my former lives, but
they began to come into me. I
could feel them entering me. And
it was like wrapping a filament
of white light around a kite
spool. And after a certain
period, they seemed to fuse. And
when they fuse, there was a
tremendous explosion of energy,
and I was catapulted into a
state of consciousness in which
I was an individual, but I was
an individual beyond any frame
of reference that I had known
before. And this is what I came
to call the birth of the diamond
soul, or the birth of the soul.
And then I was given a series of
teachings that was explaining
what happened, what was
happening. And I think I was
being shown that this is what
happens to a species that
reincarnates. As we reincarnate,
we come to a point where there's
a long period of individual
development, of linear
development, but there comes a
point where it's just natural
that all of our former lives
achieve a synthesis of the soul.
Now this synthesis exists in
spiritual reality. When we die,
we return to soul consciousness.
We return to the consciousness
that holds all of our former
lives. And then we incarnate, we
get narrow, we die, we get
large, we incarnate, we get
lateral. And if we keep this up
for a few 1000s of years, sooner
or later, doesn't it make sense
that the soul, the whole soul,
the 100,000 year old being,
incarnates in a physical
incarnation, so that the kind.
Consciousness that lives in that
body is not a consciousness that
ever is tempted to think of him
or herself as 100 year old
being, but it's it's natural
consciousness as aware that is
an ancient being, and it has
ancient relationships with all
these beings. It has been male,
female, rich, poor, black,
white, every possible
permutation, all of those live
within us, but when they achieve
a synthesis, when they become
one, then there is this
explosion of identity. And I
think that this is what is
happening to the planet right
now. We are undergoing a
spiritual process, where we are
transitioning from egoic
identity to soul identity. We
are growing up out of our
childish, egoic past into a
mature self where we are we are
learning to we are basically
becoming incarnate diamond
souls. And I think we can see
this in some of the great
spiritual masters of history,
that they are different from
ordinary people and but the
difference is that they are
bigger, older, deeper. They are
distillations of the soul. So
what are the, what are the
symptoms of, I think, the soul
emerging in history. It doesn't
happen like all at once, or
something dramatic. It happens
gradually and slowly in
different all sorts of different
ways. And so the symptoms are
when you see people who take the
long view, who really see the
seven generations. Consider the
seven generations of impact of
one's actions when you have the
wide view, when they are
naturally their compassion
expands, extends to whole
classes of people. When we see
the Gandhi's of the world, or
the Martin Luther Kings of the
world, people who live their
lives in service of other
people, trying to lift other
people, help other people along.
You see it in the in the music
teacher who's teaching fifth
graders, year after year after
year, sharing his or her musical
knowledge to give that musical
knowledge to others so that they
can reach their life and go
forward. So I think we see the
symptoms of an older soul or the
new human, when we see symptoms
of great compassion, great
vision, great service,
selflessness and we can see, we
can recognize those around us
without necessarily
understanding what we are, what
We were seeing, what we're
seeing is the soul emerging in
that in that life form, in that
life being, and I think that we
are coming to a time in history
where we have to grow up into
the soul's consciousness, and
just there's a synergistic
relationship as the world is
trying to become one To solve
the problems which has generated
the soul is trying to become
one, and because we have the
history of the world inside our
soul as the World Challenge
basically deals with all the
ways it's divided life into bits
and pieces and preferring some
people and discouraging other
people, we have all these
tensions inside of us, and so
that there's a synergistic
relationship between us trying
to become one and whole within
ourselves and the world trying
to become one and whole. And I
think we are being guided into
the transformation, which will
not be easy. I think it's going
to be very painful where we're
going, but we are coming into
labor. We've been gestating the
future human for hundreds of
1000s of years. Gestation is
long, labor is short. And I
think we're coming into labor.
We have to deliver the soul into
history. We have to grow up. And
I think we will. I mean, I think
we will make this transition. A
lot of serious people think that
we won't, that it's we're in a
we are an extinct species. We're
just living on borrowed time.
But my experience is that we do
make this transition, we will
make it. It will be very
painful, but we will give birth
to the soul in history. I Well,
Jeffrey Mishlove: that's
beautifully put, and it's
probably a good note to close
our live stream on Chris, it's
been a real joy to be with you.
Emmy. Do you have any concluding
thoughts?
Emmy Vadnais: I just want to say
thank you for the hope and
inspiration, and it sounds like
you possibly were given
precognitive information in your
LSD sessions, and that you have
some type of wisdom or
knowledge, not only for
yourself, but also for the
collective and because you're
right, there are a lot of
people. Who feel like we might
be devolving and things are
going really south. I'm not
thrilled to hear about the pain
coming up, but hopefully we can
take some of these spiritual
practices and maybe ameliorate
some of that.
Chris Bache: I think we can. I
think we can either go through
this kicking and screaming and
hurting a lot, or we can go
through it being more proactive,
with more foresight, and in a
cooperative relationship with
what's coming. And what I've
been describing is nothing
unique to me. It's these ideas
about the transition comes up in
indigenous peoples tradition. It
comes up in the lives of mystics
and meditators. So, you know, it
comes up in those who work in
deep Jungian, you know, type of
psychotherapy, there's nothing
unique to my perception. There's
nothing really unique to
psychedelics about it. It's just
that I think there are
precognitive aspects to this
type of work, which is when you
let go of your personal
identity, you open to the life
of your species. And just as you
can have insights into your
personal trajectory, you can
also have true insights into
this trajectory of your species.
It's just a very natural thing.
And many people have had these
insights. Many people see we're
coming into and I think we will
make it. I think my concern is
how many of our children will
die before we make it well.
Emmy Vadnais: And it's nice to
hear more people such as
yourself bring these insights.
So the more spiritually evolved
people we have it sounds like
the better, which is perhaps one
of the main reasons we continue
to do these programs on new
thinking allowed.
Chris Bache: I think there are
many Bodhisattvas in the world,
including the people behind this
program, working on behalf of
the good of the whole that's the
essence of the Bodhisattva. And
there are many with us now
today.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Well, once
again, Chris, thank you so much
for being with Emmy and I and
with the new thinking allowed
audience today and Emmy, thank
you once again for the wonderful
job you do as co host on new
thinking allowed. I'd like to
remind our viewers that you can
subscribe for free to our weekly
newsletter you can download for
free the first eight issues of
the new thinking allowed
magazine, and we hope that you
continue to enjoy the videos
that We post daily on the new
thinking allowed channel,
Emmy Vadnais: thank you so much
for being with us. Chris,
Chris Bache: no, thank both of
you for this wonderful
conversation. I enjoyed it very
much. Thank you for your work,
Emmy Vadnais: our pleasure, and
for those of you watching or
listening, thank you for being
with us because you are the
reason that we are here. You.