Chris Bache: The idea that we
all have to get past the same
finish line at the same time in
order for things to work out
right, we all have to be saved
before we die, or something like
this. That doesn't make nearly
as much sense as we are we are
developing flower garden. We are
different types of flowers,
which are developing and
emerging over large periods of
time.
Unknown: Keep watching to learn
more. Book four in the new
thinking allowed dialog series
is Charles T tart. 70 years of
exploring consciousness and
parapsychology, now available on
Amazon.
New thinking allowed is
presented by the California
Institute for Human science, a
fully accredited university
offering distant learning
graduate degrees that focus on
mind, body and spirit. The
topics that we cover here, we
are particularly excited to
announce new degrees emphasizing
Parapsychology and the
paranormal. Visit their
website@cihs.edu
thinking aloud, conversations on
the leading edge of knowledge
and discovery with psychologist
Jeffrey Mishlove.
Emmy Vadnais: You Hello and
welcome. I'm Emmy Vadnais, co
host with Jeffrey Mishlove. Our
topic today is collective karma
and reincarnation, with my
guest, Chris Bache, who is
professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University in Ohio, where
he taught for 33 years. He is
also adjunct faculty at the
California Institute of integral
studies, Emeritus fellow at the
Institute of Noetic Sciences and
on the Advisory Council of Grof
legacy training. Chris is author
of four books, life cycles,
reincarnation and the web of
life, dark night, early dawn,
the living classroom, teaching
and collective consciousness and
LSD in the mind of the universe.
Diamonds from heaven. If you
enjoy this program, please like,
subscribe, press the bell icon
and share. Chris is joining us
from just north of Asheville in
Weaverville, North Carolina. Now
I'll switch over to the internet
video. Welcome Chris. It is a
great joy to be with you on new
thinking aloud today.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Emmy,
it's wonderful to be in
conversation with you.
Emmy Vadnais: This is our second
interview together, although we
also had a live stream. And in
that first conversation, we
talked about your great book,
LSD, in the mind of the
universe, diamonds from heaven.
And I'll link to that interview
in the upper right corner of the
screen in your book, and in that
conversation, you shared about
how through your 73 LSD
sessions, you experienced many
deaths and rebirths. And today
we're going to explore the
notion that it sounds like you
came to an understanding of that
we all have our own individual
or personal karma, and that we
do reincarnate for the
collective good or benefit of
all toward what you describe as
the future human. Yeah, to get
us started, how did you become
interested in this topic of
personal but also collective
karma and reincarnation. Well,
the first
Chris Bache: book I wrote as an
academic was life cycles,
reincarnation and the web of
life. So I was interested in
reincarnation. Early in my
career, I encountered Ian
Stevenson's Research at the
University of Virginia. At about
the same time, I encountered
Stan Grof research in his book,
realms of the human unconscious.
So I really, I took in
Stevenson's research, you know,
deeply, and I began to see the
world in a way that I had never
seen it before. I began to see
the world in terms of
reincarnation, through a lens of
reincarnation, understanding
that every life is continuation
of lives lived in the past and
is leading towards lives in the
future. So I began to study the
evidence for reincarnation, and
I studied a lot of past life
therapy cases, and I began to
sort of understand the deeper
mechanisms of how lives start
many things they don't get
finished, and they sometimes
experience injury and wounds
that don't get healed, or they
have hopes and expectations that
are not fulfilled, and those
transfer into subsequent former
lives, not in a simple or
simplistic way, but in a very
common. Complex and subtle way
that we are living, in a sense,
the continuation of projects
that began before our life and
our life will lead to a
continuation of projects after
we die, after our body dies. So
that was all kind of working
itself out my mind, and then
when I entered into my
psychedelic work that was all
affirmed, and that was
elaborated. I had numerous
experiences of former lives and
the reality of reincarnation is
just a fact of life, was
presented as kind of a natural
exposition of spiritual reality,
and how the physical world and
the spiritual world are deeply
intertwined in this evolutionary
process. But all of that thought
of so far is all on the level of
personal karma, you know,
personal cause and effect,
personal choice conditionings
transferred from lifetime to
lifetime, but in the process of
doing the psychedelic
exploration, I also dropped in,
began to drop into levels of
consciousness that were not
personal, but were collective.
Jung's concept of the Collective
Unconscious is an early
exploration of this idea, but I
dropped into levels of reality,
of conscious reality, where the
working unit was not an
individual human being, but the
working unit was an entire
species. And I began to have
experiences that were working
themselves out in my individual
psychedelic sessions that were
not personal. They were really
focused on collective dynamics,
so that I describe in a chapter
called the ocean of suffering,
entering into what I later came
to understand were memory
matrices held in the collective
psyche of all the suffering that
members of its species had
experienced, if it was
unresolved by the time they
died, memories of war, of
killing, of rape, of pain,
drought, incest, just lots and
lots of painful memories. And I
began to understand that just as
the individual can be burdened
by their past trauma, the psyche
of this of the collective
consciousness of our species is
likewise burdened by its
collective trauma. And then so
that led to a deepening of an
understanding about the
relationship of individual and
collective karma, individual
karma and collective karma, that
really is the fundamental theme
of my second book, dark night,
early dawn, that has to do with
examining that when you get
very, very deep, that boundary
between the individual and the
collective dissolves, and it
leads to a much, much more
dynamic relationship between
what's happening in our
individual lives and what's
happening in this life of the
species of which we are part.
And that, of course, is
contextualized within the life
of the planet, the life of the
galaxy, so on and so forth. And
so I just had many experiences
of being initiated into the life
of our species at a collective
level. So I would I dissolved,
not like into the mystical state
of oneness with God, but before
getting to that, I dissolved
into the consciousness of our
species, and I began to have
experiences of how the species
is evolving through collective
karma and collective
reincarnation, and individuals
within that matrix are evolving
through individual karma and
individual reincarnation.
Emmy Vadnais: Before we go any
further. I know we mentioned
this in our previous interview.
You we are not suggesting that
people engage in LSD per se in
order to have these same
experiences. Yeah, it's not
necessary, right, for a person
to get in touch with these parts
of themselves, to use those
substance necessarily,
absolutely.
Chris Bache: I mean, what I did
was illegal. I did it because I
felt that it was wrong for these
important mind opening drugs to
be made illegal. But I would
never recommend that anyone else
break the law. And there are
other techniques that we can use
in order to get access to these
deep levels of consciousness.
This is simply just one of the
ways that I entered into this
domain. I also did three years
of hypnotherapy exploring my own
former lives. In that process
that nothing to do with any
psychedelics at all.
Emmy Vadnais: You have a whole
career as a professor of
philosophy of religion. What can
you share with us about the
spiritual evidence, if you will?
And then we can go to the
scientific evidence as well for
reincarnation.
Chris Bache: Well, I start on
the empirical side, I found Ian
Stevenson's work intellectually
and philosophically compelling.
He and his teams have done
research and contacted 1000s of
children around the world who
have spontaneous memories of
their most immediate previous
life, and he was able to
document those memories at
sufficient detail to be, I
think, intellectually credible
and overwhelmingly providing
overwhelming evidence that
reincarnation is just a fact of
life. Then later, when I began
to study in past life, therapy
literature, and I began to watch
and work with people who had
experience helping people
remember their deep past in
order to heal, but also in order
to bring forward, consciously
the many gifts that are stored
in their past. Because not all
you know, we have a tendency to
think that we inherit mostly
problems from our past. But
that's not true. We inherit all
the all the pluses, all the
benefits, all the the hard work
they've done in certain areas.
In my meditation, I began to
experience the boundaryless
nature of consciousness itself,
that so I knew that there were
dimensions of my mind, my
consciousness, that were
Transpersonal, that went beyond
my personal identity. And then
when I went into deeper
psychedelic work, I had many
experiences which showed me that
reincarnation is simply true.
It's just a fact of life. And
Stevenson's evidence is really,
really important, but it's the
tip of the iceberg, because it
by itself, his evidence does not
give us a comprehensive picture
of how reincarnation works, how
the universe is working in
reincarnation. And there's so
much we don't know. I mean, I
want to say up front, we don't
have any idea of what the
physics of the soul is. We don't
know how consciousness leaves at
death and brings all the
memories forward. We don't
really understand the physics of
how that consciousness
reintegrates with another
incarnation, how its store of
knowledge interacts with or
interfaces with genetic
conditions, genetic and social
conditions. We there's so much
that we don't know. There's a
lot to be learned with research
ahead. But experientially, when
you remember your previous
lives, and when you you run deep
into the fabric of life, so that
you begin to understand that our
entire species is reincarnation
generation by generation. It's
not just individuals who are
living and growing. The entire
species is living and growing
collectively in that process,
it's just there's theory and
then there's direct experience.
And in this case, theory and
direct experience reinforce each
other,
Emmy Vadnais: yes, in your
experiences, using LSD and other
forms of substances to take you
deeper, beyond your personal
self, you described how you
really felt a sense of oneness.
And can you kind of recap that a
little bit for us or for those
who might be new to your story?
Yeah,
Chris Bache: this is a deeper
theme than simply the theme of
reincarnation, so let's go
there, and then we can bring it
back into reincarnation, however
you would like. The truth of
reincarnation is a truth that we
are an evolving consciousness
over a large, large swath of
time. But there, there are many
other truths. And one of the
other truths is if we ask, where
did we come from, and what are
we? And in essence, underneath
all this social conditioning and
psychological conditioning, what
are we? And there, the spiritual
traditions are very clear, and
they speak with one voice that
the essence of the individual is
the essence of the totality that
we can we are, at core, the
essence our essence is the
essence of the Divine, or the
essence of God, if you use that
language. And so that's another
truth. And then you go deeper
into that, you you realize that
what your essence is is the same
as the essence of every living
thing in this world. World,
every inanim, so called
inanimate thing, so that when
that happens, when that opens,
there's a profound feeling of
oneness that you know, in a
sense self dissolves, in the
sense of there being a boundary,
a firm boundary between self and
other that disappears and one
experience is the marvelous
miracle of life, living and
breathing as one. You are just
part of life. It's surrounding
you. There's a profound feeling
of intimacy, kinship, those
graces of being touched by
oneness, they can change your
life forever, because it shows
you a truth that even if you
can't sustain that experience,
you've seen the truth. You know
the truth of it. You can use
that truth to guide your life.
It leads you to become more
compassionate with people. It
leads you to become more
compassionate with yourself. You
always are kind of spontaneously
looking out for the good of the
whole that's the natural and
natural outcome of experiencing
oneness is compassion. That's
why, in the mystical traditions,
wisdom, insight and compassion
move hand in hand. The deeper
you experience oneness, the more
compassionate you become.
Emmy Vadnais: Can you describe a
little bit about your own
personal experience of that
oneness and what that was like
for you?
Chris Bache: That's a
challenging question, because to
answer your question, I have to
remember, and to remember, I
have to sink into the memory.
Otherwise it's just a reading of
headlines of it and that that
takes a little time, but working
within the restrictions we have,
one of the things I learned is
there oneness is not like a
switch that goes on and off. But
there are many degrees of
oneness. There are many stages
of initiation into oneness. One
can have a perception of
oneness. One can touch the edges
of oneness and feel the truth of
oneness in the world. But then
you can go deeper into actually,
kind of dissolving into the
quantum structure, if you will.
I'm using that metaphorically of
oneness. It's it's a deeper
immersion in the living totality
of life. It it's challenging,
because at least what I've
learned is that deeper states of
consciousness exist at higher
levels of energy. So the deeper
you're going into a reality in
the consciousness, you're going
into a higher and higher and
higher level of energy. So
oneness with the totality, or
oneness with the Divine, is an
extremely intense state of
consciousness and state of
energy to move into. And in my
case, I approached it through
going through years and years of
very intense purifications in my
psychedelic sessions, when that
oneness, when you're graced with
the an opening into oneness,
it's like the entire world comes
alive in a new way. And it's
like there's a song in the world
that you maybe hadn't heard
before, but it's always been
there. There is a joy and a
falling away of all forms of
loneliness and a and a birthing
into an exquisite spiritual
intimacy, I should say, as an
intimacy which is both spiritual
and physical, because it it it
overflows in compassion towards
the world, and It also overflows
in homecoming, a feeling of
Homecoming to one's essential
nature, one's essential being.
And it's like, finally I found
you, or finally I've been found
by you. And and then it's just,
how deep do you want to go? You
know, how deep into the oneness
of existence. Do you dare to go?
And I think if one goes too
fast, it becomes very
challenging and difficult. It
takes time to assimilate
oneness, and then it takes time
after you've had the experience
to know what to do with it, to
try to we talk about integrating
our psychedelic experiences, and
I'm thinking in many ways that
we don't really understand yet,
how these profound experiences
are impacting our psychological
development, our psycho
spiritual development, because
indigenous people. People have
been having these experiences
for millennia. Of course, we in
the West are relatively new to
cultivating these experiences,
and so we're taking all of our
learning and all of our
scientific knowledge and all of
our, you know, high academic
knowledge, into these states.
And in some ways, we're like the
first generation to combine
everything that we have learned
about the world, from science
and ridiculed critical analysis
and now entering into these
deep, deep states of
consciousness, and we're holding
memories that very few people in
history have tried to hold.
We're holding memories of a
profound Transcendence, profound
intimacy with the divine,
profound Transcendence of time,
moving into deep time,
permutations of time moving into
cosmic void, experiences and
those are living memories. I
mean, I can tell you what I was
doing on a particular day in a
particular year, 30 years ago.
They're very specific, and I
remember them the way that most
people remember their 50th
birthday party. You can just
remember it, but how those
experiences, which are so
transcendent, how they are
impacting us and infusing
themselves deeper into our
being. I think we're just
beginning to map some of those
processes
Emmy Vadnais: from those
experiences. It sounds like you
had a more personal insight into
how everything that each of us
perceivedly, individually, do,
think, feel, impacts the
oneness. Yes, think of it this
Chris Bache: way. Let's say any
of the list of negative
qualities that we have
personally, that we're bothered
by and we would like to get rid
of and we'd like to transform,
etc, etc, those. None of those
are private. All of these are
part of a social configuration.
Any problem we have personally
is part of a social problem.
It's part of a cultural problem.
So where is the line between
solving my personal issue and
the society solving its
collective issue. Now we in
classically in Western thought,
we have thought we're all
individual monads. We can't
communicate with each other.
We're all separate self
contained, egoic structures. So
we're kind of we may be one in
aggregate, but we're really just
a whole bunch of people shoved
up against each other, and we
used to have our own individual
experience. But I don't think
that's the way it works, at
least that's not what I was
shown. What I have experienced
is that each human being is a
cell in the tissue of humanity.
Every mind is a light, a cell of
light in the fabric of human
consciousness and even our
bodies, our cells within the
body of humanity as a whole, and
that just as we don't none of
our problems or issues or
virtues, we arrive at them
individually. We kind of arrive
at them together collectively.
They're part of an historical
landscape, part of a cultural
landscape. Also when we solve
our problems, when we have
spiritual breakthroughs, when we
have psychological
breakthroughs, those
breakthroughs radiate out into
the world, and they touch lives.
Now that's all spiritual
traditions have recognized this,
Christian, Jewish, Muslim,
Buddhist, Hindu traditions have
recognized this collective
nature. But one of the ways I
experienced it as kind of
empirically demonstrated, was in
my classroom. Because all the
years when I was working very
intensely with psychedelics, I
was working very privately, and
because they were illegal, I
couldn't talk about it, and I
never talked to my students
about my own personal
psychedelic practice. But what I
found over time was that my
psychedelic practice was
impacting my students and I
began to have experiences or
have access to their minds in a
way that was showing me that my
individual process of
transformation was radiating out
and influencing other people's
processes of self
transformation, and this, I was
completely I didn't expect this
at all, and it took me a while.
Took me years, really, to
understand what was happening,
until eventually I wrote my
book, The living classroom,
which is now just come out in a
new edition, where I. I can't
explicitly say that the
practices that I was doing,
which was driving this kind of
collective awakening in my
classroom, was a psychedelic
practice, primarily, but it was
showing me that truly, we are in
a boundaryless condition, not
just in high, subtle, mystical
states of awareness, but we are
in a boundaryless condition all
the time that we are always
there's always a porosity, an
interconnectedness between
what's going on in our life,
what's going on in the world
around us. So that I think we
have more and more reason to
believe that when we live our
life well, and when we rise to
the challenges that are
presented to us in life,
whatever they are, whether
they're, you know, surgical,
political, social activists,
meditative, psychological,
whatever those artistic whatever
those breakthroughs are, that
those breakthroughs have a
nourishing effect on everyone
around us.
Emmy Vadnais: Among the world's
spiritual traditions and
religions, some of them are
advocates or proponents of
reincarnation. They just take it
as a given, it's natural. And
then there are other religions
and practices where some have
suggested that has been removed
from those religious practices.
And I'm just wondering if you
can comment about that, because
there are people who might
adhere to a particular religion
where they have been taught sure
reincarnation just does not
exist. And in fact, you have one
shot to get it right, and that's
it. You're either going to go to
heaven or hell or maybe
purgatory. If you don't, if
you're really screw it up, you
could also go there. Yeah.
Chris Bache: Isn't that
interesting? It's interesting.
You know, religions have many
levels to them. There's kind of
the exterior lay level of
religion. And then there's the
esoteric, mystical, high, deep,
spiritual practitioner level of
religion. And what we find is
that some religions, like the
religions of the East, Buddhism,
Hinduism, even Taoism, they they
naturally affirm reincarnation.
But even in the West, where
reincarnation is not absorbed
into the primary religions,
there is, it's often present in
the mystical branch of that
religion. So that in Judaism,
Judaism doesn't affirm
reincarnation. Rabbinic Judaism
doesn't at a collective level,
but Hasidism the mystical
tradition in Judaism, it does,
and likewise in Islam,
traditional mainstream Islam,
does not place any emphasis on
reincarnation, but mystical
Islam, the Sufi tradition, does
affirm reincarnation. With
Christianity, it's a little more
complicated, because
Christianity tended to execute
any of its mystics who were
affirming reincarnation. There
were, have been crusades, of
course, against the Cathars and
others. When we look back at the
history of Christianity, it
appears that reincarnation was
taught by certain early sex
within Christianity, it was
taught in what later came to be
called Gnostic sex, which were
then delivered decided to be
heretical and not accepted. But
it was, you know, was taught as
a standard kind of operating
interpretation of Christianity
for hundreds of years. But then
as as the ecclesiastical church
began to consolidate itself
under the remember the
background this around third,
fourth century, ad under the
falling of the collapse of the
Roman Empire and a really
disintegration of order at the
social level. The church really
believed that it's its survival
depended upon a strong
ecclesiastical center, and
reincarnation gave too much
autonomy to individuals to work
out their own reincarnation. And
so a particular council was
held, and there was a decision
that reincarnation was not going
to be included as an acceptable
form of Christianity,
particularly for this particular
reason, I think, is it's it's
not that it's incompatible with
the teaching of Jesus. They
never said that it was
incompatible. It's that it gives
too much autonomy, it undermines
the the primacy of
ecclesiastical authority in the
church. Now, that may have been
helpful for Christianity at that
time, it may have helped
Christianity survive the Dark
Ages it followed. But now that
we have reincarnation evidence
coming forward from scholarly
sources, there is nothing in
Christianity that prohibits
Christians from reassessing that
old teaching. 18 and looking at
it anew, we know that from
several national surveys that
approximately 25% of American
Catholics believe in
reincarnation, and it's about
the same number for Protestants,
26% for Protestants, and so
clearly, 25% of Catholics aren't
waiting for a papal encyclical
saying that reincarnation is
okay to accept. In fact, the
largest chapter I have in my
book in life cycles is a chapter
on reincarnation and
Christianity, where I as most of
my students who I was teaching
at the State University, they
came out of Christian
backgrounds. They were also
trained to follow the evidence,
to believe, let your beliefs be
guided by the evidence. So they
were having evidence of
reincarnation presented to them,
and yet their religious
tradition said that evidence
can't be true, but they saw the
quality of the evidence, and in
this chapter, I'm basically
sharing my experiences with
students, helping them
understand how they can
reevaluate reincarnation and
what a reincarnation is
Christianity might look like.
And I outline a minimal option
and a maximal option, but trying
to show the way in which you can
affirm deep Christian values and
even dogma and incorporate a
reincarnation element. And it
makes me make more sense. You
know, because the real devilment
of Western theology, which
believes our Christian theology,
which believes in a one time
through metaphysics, is that it
it makes life radically
inexplicable. Why do some people
have so much and some people
have so little? Why are some
people so burdened with pain and
suffering, and some people just
have so much ease in their
lifetime? And ultimately, this
gets thrown into an inscrutable
God, a God that makes no sense
whatsoever. We just can't
understand it. We just have to
live it and abide by its
jurisdiction, and hopefully
things will work out well. But
when you open up to a
reincarnational perspective,
suddenly certain possibilities
emerge and things begin to make
more sense, and suddenly the
inscrutability is not God's
inscrutability. It's an
inscrutability that is
introduced by believing
something which isn't true, and
that is that we live on in life,
on life only once. Now let's be
careful. We have to say these
things carefully. Chris Bache
only lives once, the soul which
Chris Bache is part of, that
soul lives more than once. So
you know, you just have to, you
know, say things carefully to
make your points clear. Yeah,
the
Emmy Vadnais: personality or the
or the identity of Chris Bache
or Emmy Vadnais lives once.
However, the soul that is our
consciousness, our energy or
animates us, or however you
term, that lives lives on,
perhaps forever
Chris Bache: lives on. That's
right, it's like each
personality, each incarnation,
is a facet of the diamond. The
diamond lives forever. The facet
doesn't necessarily live
forever. Well, it lives forever
in the diamond, but the diamond
lives
Emmy Vadnais: forever. Yeah, the
story of Jesus's death, where he
rises on the third day, some
have suggested that is really a
metaphor for reincarnation? It's
Chris Bache: an interesting
question, and I have an appendix
in in life cycles, where I
address interpretations, which
of certain interpretations of
certain biblical passages which
have been offered to suggest
that Jesus himself believed in
reincarnation. You know, we get
into a real Biblical studies,
you know, rabbit hole on that
one, yeah, yeah. And my sense is
that I don't think there's
compelling evidence that he did
teach reincarnation, but there
certainly is very strong
evidence that his teaching is
compatible with reincarnation.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, I mention it
because it is a very significant
holiday, Easter for many
Christians and Catholics.
Chris Bache: My first love, my
first academic pursuit, was in
New Testament studies, and I
learned Greek and Hebrew, and I
really was going to become a New
Testament scholar, but I changed
and shifted later on, but up
through my master's I was doing
Biblical Studies work. We
learned that the oldest gospel,
Mark's gospel, does not have a
resurrection, does not have an
empty tomb seen in it. In fact,
it it ends with death and the
the power, the influence, of the
story of the resurrection was so
strong from the. Later gospels,
Matthew, Luke and John, that
there was an actual a new ending
added in the last chapter of
Mark's gospel to include that
kind of experience. I think that
when we ask historically, what
is the deepest level of
experience that may lie behind
the belief in the resurrection,
I think it is the the experience
that Jesus followers experienced
him as being alive, even though
he was dead, he was alive, and
therefore death is conquered.
Christian theology tended to
interpret that in unique terms
that made Jesus's survival of
death somehow unique, and he was
uniquely the Son of God and
uniquely sharing this gift with
humanity, who accepts it on
faith that would be that's one
way of interpreting, and another
way of interpreting is that what
he's showing us is a universal
truth, that when we die, we are
still alive. You know that
there's a larger dynamic
unfolding here.
Emmy Vadnais: Going back to the
oneness that physics shows seems
to be a reality with quantum
entanglement, some people really
embrace that. Find it beautiful,
such as yourself. I think it's
quite beautiful, although there
are probably people listening to
this thinking, Well, I don't
want to be a part of that other
individual or and I know it's
not just humans. There's also
creatures and animals and
bacteria that we're all a part
of as well. I'm wondering if you
want to comment on on on those
thoughts,
Chris Bache: I think when we
first begin to entertain
possibilities that we are larger
than we conventionally have
thought that we are, and that we
have these interconnections
which are larger than we thought
that we are, I understand the
kind of fear and reflex To draw
back and say, not me. You know
that that doesn't work, and
that's an understandable it's a
natural reflex. But if we let
that pass, and we sort of relax
and begin to look at the data,
if we begin to look at near
death episode research, people
who have get glimpses what's
going on behind the scenes, and
we look at not just a few of
them, but look at hundreds of
them, and begin to sort out the
kind universal threads that run
through their accounts. When we
look at past life, therapy
research, and look at, you know,
the demonstrated continuity
between lives and the richness
which emerges in a person's life
when they untangle some of those
knots from their past, and when
we just begin to look deeply
into where did this come from,
where did this body mind come
from? And we trace its long
evolutionary pedigree back
through its physical pedigree on
the emergence of our beautiful
body. It turns out that the mind
has a similar elegant,
magnificent pedigree, reaching
back through time, and the more
we absorb the fact that this
body is not ours privately, and
our mind is not ours privately.
It's always been a collective
summation, in a way, always from
the start, then I think that
feeling of anxiety or push back
softens and we begin to open to
a different world. And it's not
a world that dissolves the
individual or washes out the
individual. It's a world which
actually affirms the individual
very deeply, but it
contextualizes the individual
within a web work of
interconnections which is larger
than the individual, which we
draw from and we give back to
just as a leaf draws energy from
the tree and gives back energy
to the tree. And that just it
becomes a natural way of seeing
things. It's just a it's an easy
secondary way of seeing things.
And I'm glad the physicists have
jumped on with quantum physics
and unified systems theory and
all those good things, but
fundamentally this can be an
experiential thing, that when we
when we quiet our mind, when we
calm our heart, and we enter
into deeper states of self aware
stillness, Then there are
perceptions. There are
instincts, which are usually so
subtle that we don't notice
them, but in the space of a
quiet, meditative mind, these
things make themselves felt. And
when you when these arise, you
begin to realize that they're
it's like they're threads that
connect us to other people's
lives. Then you. There's no
breaking these threads. They're
part of the fabric of life, just
like there's no breaking the
threads between any one leaf on
a tree and other leaves on the
tree. They are connected into
the same organism,
Emmy Vadnais: yeah, and the
roots of the trees, the roots, I
like how you're describing it as
a collective mind, or collective
consciousness, that we are all a
part of, and and I agree with
you. I had the pleasure of
speaking with Jill Bolte Taylor,
who has written the book my
Stroke of Insight, and followed
up with a where she had a stroke
and the left side of her brain
went offline and she only had
the right side of her brain. And
she talked about how she felt
this merging of oneness, and
could even sense the energy that
people were bringing into her
space, even if they were just
visiting for less than, no less
than five minutes. And she wrote
a follow up book about whole
brain living, because she wanted
to share with people how they
can also have these experiences
as well. Yeah. What is the
significance of reincarnation?
How does karma play a role with
that, and how does it give
meaning to our lives, or even
change our lives if we engage
with that potential?
Chris Bache: Well, that's a
large question, so let me just
start with how it impacted me,
and share with you maybe some of
how it impacts the students that
I've shared these ideas with.
You know, decades first, I think
it changes everything. It makes
life more intelligible. It makes
the experience that all of us
have make more sense. All of us
have things that we know how to
do that no one ever taught us,
or we have aptitudes towards
certain types of activities that
are different from everyone else
in our family. Some people are
oriented towards private
intellectual chess, like games,
and other people like full
contact rugby, rugby, social,
things. There's all these
differences. Some people have
tremendous capacity to create an
art and music, and other people
are writers. Where do those come
from? Where do those qualities
and traits come from? And
classically, we think they come
through genetic mutation. It's
random, it's it's just
accidental. There's no logic to
it. You got a good luck, good
you good genes, good. They're
great. But when you actually
sink into them, it begins to
make more sense that everything
which is large in a life comes
from a line of choices, where at
some time in our past, they were
small. So an interest in music
begins small, but it's practice,
and it's develops until
eventually you have someone like
Mozart, who's writing concertos
when he's six years old. So
everything which is large, even
in one case, I'm remembering
from past life cases, an ability
with guns, an ability to be very
facile and very quick. Draw came
from a history of a former life
of a marshal on the frontier,
you know? And that makes sense,
and it also is grounds for hope,
because it means not that we are
prisoner of our past, but we
operate within a context which
has been shaped by our past.
Within that context, we make
choices which then begin they
feed into the to our future and
our future lives future. So it's
a very empowering position,
because even though you may be
temporarily burdened if you are
by something that's got a deeper
history, you have the power to
change your history. You have a
power to exert your will and
exert your choices, make better
choices or stronger different
choices and lead into a better,
better future. It begins when
you when you look at the world
through reincarnation of size,
you realize that everybody's
playing a different game.
They're not playing your game.
And if it's like, I think of it
like school. There are some
people who are in kindergarten
and first grade, some people who
are in high school, some people
are doing postgraduate work. And
that gives you tremendous
permission to let people be
themselves, just to let them be
because they're working on their
court, their rules that they're
working on. Somebody else is
working on a different court,
different rules. And the idea
that we all have to get past the
same finish line at the same
time in order for things to work
out right. We all have to be
saved before we die or something
like this. That doesn't make
nearly as much sense as we are
we are developing flower garden.
We are different types of
flowers which are developing and
emerging over large periods of
time. We have an open ended
amount of time with which to
develop ourselves. I tell my
students sometimes the only
important question you should be
asking yourself is, what do you
want to be doing in 10,000
years?
Emmy Vadnais: That's a simple
question,
Chris Bache: question, but
provoking,
Emmy Vadnais: isn't it? Oh,
well, I'm joking. It's it's
profound. It's like,
Chris Bache: take the large
perspective people, the creative
intelligence of the universe
thinks large. It doesn't think
small, right? And if we we have
this, the greatest thing about
reincarnation is, and it's the
Hindus thought this was a
burden. I mean that when they
discovered reincarnation, they
thought, Oh, my God, we go round
and round and round. We have to
go through puberty all these
times we have to go hardship of
life, over and over and over
again. They did not think it was
a joy. They thought it was a
burden. But I think we can
appreciate that the greatest
burden of in the psyche of the
modern man, modern humanity is
this idea that's terrible idea
that we are nothing more than
our biology, everything mental
condenses to physics, and that
when the body dies, our mind
disappears and dissolves. We're
nothing. There's no survival of
the of the body. Reincarnation
opens this puts the myth to
that. It shows us that we are
developing over vast tracks of
time, and that allows us to
elevate our assessment of what
the purpose of life might be. If
I give an in class test, a quiz,
I have a right to expect a
certain set of results. If I
give them an hour long test, I
expect more because I've given
in the more time. And if I give
them a research paper, I expect
more because they have more time
to develop it. If the universe
has a purpose, if it has a
purpose, it should be
proportionate to the amount of
time we have to realize that
purpose. If we only have one
lifetime. Remember, for some
people, that's just five minutes
before they're dead out of the
delivery room. Sometimes it's
five days. If life has a
purpose, it can't be greater
than the amount of time we have
to realize that purpose. Okay,
with reincarnation, we learn
that we have open ended infinite
amount of time. That doesn't
cause us to be lazy. Anybody who
wants to say, oh, I'll just deal
with it later. They're stupid,
you know, they haven't really
taken into how hard it is to be
working here. But when we have
open ended amount of time, it
lifts the ceiling and it allows
us to look at the beautiful
pictures that come from the
Hubble telescope, for example,
pictures of our galaxies and
nebulas and the infinite depth
of the universe, and to
recognize that we aren't just a
little bit short 100 year part
player in this drama. We are an
ancient player in this drama,
and it allows us to look at the
magnificent grandeur of a
galaxy, and recognize that we
have a meaningful part in this
magnificent galaxies unfolding
of intelligence on its planets,
around its suns. That's that
changes everything, doesn't it?
What do you
Emmy Vadnais: feel the purpose
of our individual karma is that
contributes to the collective
what are we reincarnating
toward?
Chris Bache: Well, let me kind
of start with a general
observation, then go to the more
specific observations. What are
we reincarnating toward? To me,
the boundary between individual
and collective has been made
poor so many times that I see it
as one living organism with
different kind of folks. Eye of
light the individual is an
individual, but it's
contextualized within an
individuality of a species. And
our species, as a single
consciousness, is an individual.
I mean, it's humanity on planet
Earth is different than some
other species on some other
planet, on some other galaxy,
the mind of our species, the
collective psyche, the memory of
our species, is unique in its
history and in its components.
In our mind, we are part of
that. So my understanding is we
live in a constant dialog, a
constant transmission back and
forth between the collective and
the individual to the
collective. So then we ask the
question, okay, what are we
evolving toward? Where is it
taking us? And that gets us into
very interesting territory,
probably the large majority of
the answers that we would give
that we. Are evolving to love or
to compassion or to knowledge or
something like this, inevitably
that probably is going to end up
being too small, because we're
going to formulate those goals
out of our particular moment in
history and take something good
and project it forward, but ask
the same question in 5000 years,
and would probably give a
different, richer answer. So I
think the safest answers are in
terms of process answers, not in
terms of goal answers. I tend to
think the essence of the whole
process is growth and
empowerment of the nature that
we have, the empowerment of the
form that we are, growth, growth
toward what that comes the
tricky part. I mean, I would
like to say growth towards
oneness, growth towards love,
growth towards wisdom, growth
towards I mean literally
intelligence, more intelligence,
more esthetic capacity, more
creative capacity, more
communion between human
intelligence and spiritual
intelligence. But those are just
limited intermediate baby steps,
I think, but that there is a
progression towards growth, I
think we can extract from the
evolutionary record, and also a
growth towards individuality. I
think of reincarnation as a
higher octave of evolution.
Evolution evolves whole groups
forward. It folds learning
forward of whole groups.
Reincarnation. Folds the
learning forward of individuals
within certain species. Nature
has somehow found a way of, kind
of letting individuals run
forward in time. Where is it
going to go? Well, we've been
doing it for hundreds of 1000s
of years, and a universe has
been evolving for 13 point 7
billion years, and it's going to
continue for hundreds of
billions of years. Yet, where
are we going? I mean, what? What
could we become if we had 10,000
years to work with? Yeah, we'll
become more, I think, better,
more in tune with reality, and I
deeply mean spiritual reality
will become stronger because
we'll be working together to
solve our problems. Instead of
fighting over a small plate of
food, we'll be lower.
Emmy Vadnais: How can people
engage in the karmic and
reincarnation process more
consciously? Because I imagine
there are those listening
thinking, Well, I have a
horrible lot in this lifetime. I
don't want to be here anymore.
I'm never coming back here. In
fact, some people truly believe
that this is a prison planet and
it's run by dark forces that are
trying to control us or that do
control us.
Chris Bache: Yeah, my heart goes
out to people who are suffering
that much pain. I mean, I know
people who are suffering that
much pain, and I think
inevitably, when we try to
understand what's going on,
inevitably, we kind of project
out of our own living
circumstance. So if we see
ourselves living on a planet
that's it's a prison planet
controlled by Dark Forces. I
mean, I can't help but think
that there is a projection of
one's own psychological
experience into metaphysical
parameters. But, and I can only
suggest that as you get clear,
as you go through deepening your
experience of your own life
through various spiritual
practices, and by living as good
a life as you can live as fair
and compassion, as just and
compassion and generous life as
we can live, your mind gets
clearer. The forces that
constrict your life loosen and
you begin to realize that all
along you in very subtle and
often mysterious ways, you are
controlling the flow of energy
that is your life. And if you've
made choices that have
constricted that flow in the
past, you can reverse those
choices in the present. If
you've had bad karma,
constrictive, tight karma in the
past, you can choose, begin to
choose different, generous
karma, clear karma. And all the
spiritual traditions have
procedures to help you move into
deeper clarity. The Buddhists
start with the five, the Four
Noble Truths. They start with
the fundamental truths of do no
harm, do no injury, right?
Speech, right conduct, so on, so
forth. Every religion has these
commandments, if you will, these
guidelines, how to clear your
mind, how to clear your heart.
As you clear your mind and clear
your heart, a different picture
of the universe emerges, one
which is not governed by Dark
Forces. Though, clearly, if you
look at if you look at certain
political movements and certain
social movements and movements
of war and whatnot, there's a
lot of darkness and there's a
lot of oppressive forces, and
there's a lot of greed and
negativity in there. But your
experience of the universe
itself changes. It opens into a
divine banquet, a wonderful
mystery, but a divine banquet.
And how do I connect with that?
I mean, how do I begin to change
my life so that I can begin to
have that kind of experience, or
I can feel that affinity with
the fellow human beings who are
traveling with me. This is, this
is kind of like basic
spirituality, 101, so anything
which you do which favors
yourself over someone else, stop
doing that. Everything you do
which hurts other people around
you, stop doing that. Every time
you injure someone with your
speech, stop doing that, and
just the whole system slowly
begins to calm down. And then
there are other techniques which
teach you how to bring your mind
underneath all the turbulence
that's on the surface. And we
can just start to live a
lifestyle which is calmer,
quieter, more peaceful. Doesn't
mean we're not in the world.
We're in the world. We're making
a living, we're doing our jobs.
We have to deal with everything
everybody else does, but you can
engage it in a different way,
and as you individually come
into greater clarity. I think
crystallizing around you will be
opportunities of greater growth
around you. We are not trapped
by our karma. Karma is simply a
platform we can reach beyond our
past and to create a future
which may still have its own
challenges, but it'll be clear,
it'll be gentler, more exciting.
Can
Emmy Vadnais: you share a little
bit more about your
understanding of karma? Because
some people listening might be
thinking, well, it's simply
cause and effect, or maybe even
a form of punishment,
Chris Bache: not punishment, but
certainly cause and effect. The
in Hindi terms, is karma,
vipaka, cause and effect. And so
the basic idea is this, we live
in an entire universe of cause
and effect. Everything has
cause. Everything has effects.
Everything. There's not a single
part of this universe which
doesn't have cause and effect.
Except the fundamental ground
state, it's all cause and
effect. So we don't have any
problem with that. In the
scientific world, we recognize
molecules, atoms, you know, move
into things. They have cause and
effect, no problem. Yeah. Now we
get to the nub of it. The Hindus
would say, in ancient
traditions, would say, choice
has cause and effect the choices
we make, which is to say we are
learning systems. We are
constantly learning. And when we
make a choice, we are basically
setting in motion a trajectory
of learning when we make a
choice to push away something or
to include something to hurt or
to support. We are always making
choices. Those choices basically
echo back around and become part
of our subsequent experiences.
One of the easiest ways to
describe some of the logic of
this when the people talk about
good karma and bad karma
inheriting the consequences of
the VIPA. Technically, it's the
good vipaka That comes from good
action, the bad vipaka That
comes from bad action, bad
karma. When we are experiencing
these cycles, what's at the
center of it is giving the human
being incredible power to
control their destiny. They may
not be able to control it in the
short term because there's so
much momentum in the system, but
if you begin to systematically
engage the momentum of the
causal forces powering pushing
your life, you can begin making
clear and clear and clear
choices. And as you begin making
clear choices, your inner
environment becomes clear and
your outer environment begins to
become clear. For Hinduism, this
would be simple Dharma 101, this
is just kind of how life works.
We are here to grow. We are here
to learn and. An academic
transcript is a history of
grades in various courses. You
could say it's karma. You make
choices. You make choices for
what to pay attention, not to
pay attention, to apply
yourself, not to apply yourself.
You make choices. The cumulative
effect of all those choices is
your transcript at the end of
college. Okay? It's like that in
life. We're making choices
constantly. There's nothing
magic, magical or infamous about
karma. It's just reminding us
that not only does the physical
world move according to cause
and effect, but our
psychological world also moves
according to cause and effect,
and our spiritual world does
too, except that there is a
there is a depth in the
spiritual level. There may be
also in the quantum level as
well, but there is a depth in
the physical level, which you
discover deep inside your center
that is not part of cause and
effect. It's outside of cause
and effect. And so that's the
spiritual traditions make a
great deal of emphasis of
reducing the turbulence of karma
cause and effect until one can
actually experience the aspect
of your own being which is free
of cause and effect. It's part
of it. There's that when they
describe the one's essential
nature, of one's de mind, divine
nature, it never begins, it
never ends. It doesn't have a
beginning and end. It's always
present. It's always stable.
Karma has beginning and end. It
runs around, does all sort like
a playground. But underneath
there is this reality which has
neither beginning nor end. And
so spiritual practice is about
living more in your more of your
life from that reality, rather
than living your life from that
turbulence, cause and effect.
What
Emmy Vadnais: role do historical
traumas and collective traumas
play and what we're experiencing
here on earth, of course, I know
you mentioned earlier, there's a
lot of pleasant attributes we
bring with us as well. All the
Chris Bache: virtues of history
are poured into us that surround
us, as well as all the burdens
of bad choices of history, all
the sins of history. We seem to
be in a very intense time now.
We're coming into a critical
time in human history. We've
never been here before. We've
had pieces of continents in
danger, but now we have an
entire planet that's in danger
of becoming unable to sustain
our population, and we're doing
it. It's man, it's human made.
We're making the choices. We're
causing the problem. Nature is
not causing the problem. We are
causing the problem. And so we
seem to be in a time of
increasing turbulence,
disruption, chaos. We're dealing
with a lot of social uncertainty
and social divisiveness because
many people are not clear how to
face the challenges that we're
coming into as a species. We
know that global climate change
is going to have enormous
impact. We're going to be losing
many, many, many lives in the
near future, in the future, and
this leads to uncertainty and a
lot of turbulence. And if we
look at this same situation from
within a deep spiritual
perspective, and we ask, what is
causing this inner turbulence?
Well, we might look at, in some
ways, I look towards the lives
of individual mystics. When we
look at the life of an
individual mystic, this is well,
kind of documented and testified
that before the breakthrough of
enlightenment, before the
breakthrough of the universal
one heart, we go through the
dark night of the soul. We go
through a period of deep, deep,
intense, personal cleansing. And
another way of thinking about
this, from a reincarnational
perspective, is that we're
cleaning the basement all the
things inside of us which are
incompatible with enlightenment,
all the history which has led us
to have convictions and urges
and whatnot which are
incompatible with universal love
are being forced out of the
system. And when and in your
meditation, they the spiritual
practitioners can experience
that. They experience upheavals
coming up from within them.
Sometimes they're they're crying
on the meditation cushion.
Sometimes they're feeling
unspeakable rage. But the advice
is always the same, keep
centered. Let it flow through
you. It will pass. It will move
through you. If we kind of think
of the entire species. As a
single meditating being, I think
something like this is
happening. I personally think we
are entering into a profoundly
important, very positive turning
point in human evolution, which
will take us into a higher level
of psycho spiritual functioning
at a across the board platform
for us to actualize this, for us
to realize this, we have to get
we have to clear ourselves of
everything which is keeping us
from experiencing this state
right here, right now, today,
and the things which are
experience keeping us from
experiencing this is all our
collective karma from collective
history and all our cultural
institutions and the history
that we, each of us, carry
individually, and we all carry
collectively together. So I
think that we are actually
experiencing a time of
tremendous purification,
tremendous kind of, you know,
it's kind of like you have to
expose the shadow before you can
heal the shadow. And we are
certainly exposing the shadow of
humanity right now in many of
the very destructive and self
absorbed and injurious policies
or practices that are arising in
our midst. I think of this as
kind of a collective
purification, which is part and
parcel of leading into a
spiritual awakening, a deep and
profound spiritual awakening.
Emmy Vadnais: Yes, Carl Jung and
the shadow, yeah, focusing on
our own individual shadow cells
are letting ourselves maybe heal
from what ails us. Yeah, what
would you suggest people
consider doing as far as, do
they primarily focus on their
own selves and or assisting the
collective. I mean, I understand
what you're saying, that as we
focus on ourselves, we're part
of the collective.
Chris Bache: Yeah, it's a both
end situation, isn't it? Yeah?
Because while an enlightened
individual in a monastery in a
mountain with no contact in the
world may have an uplifting
effect on the whole, and that
has that person, has that
reality. Most of us live
embodied in the world. And we
would like to do more than
heaven, a meditative effect,
uplifting the collective from
the ground. We would like to do
something practical. I mean,
we'd like to help the world be a
better place, leave it a better
place before we die. We'd like
to sort of help people in need,
or help to solve the problems
that are endemic to our culture.
If we do that, or try to do that
without deep inner clarity, we
may get some success, but will
also leave more damage behind
too. So I think it's a both and
becoming socially active to work
for social clarity, social
peace, and to be personally,
inwardly clear and at peace
oneself. I did this years and
years of psychedelic practice
and other spiritual practices
that time. But I was always
working as an academic. I was
working hard at an open
enrollment University and trying
to raise the corner. That corner
that was my garden, that was
where I worked, and where I was
trying to make things better.
And all of my colleagues, they
had their gardens. They were
working to make things better in
the world. And so I don't think
it's an either or. I think some
people are drawn more to the
this incarnation, to an
individual interior project.
Other people are drawn more to
an exterior, social project.
There's not a right or wrong
here. I think it's both.
Emmy Vadnais: And what would you
like to say to someone who may
be listening thinking, Well, I'm
doing my part, but that person
or that group or that
institution or that country is
really messing things up, and
they're the problem,
Chris Bache: yeah, and they may
be, and there are certainly
people, other players in the
world besides ourselves, and
they're, they're doing bad
things in the world. Any right
thinking person would want to
try to mitigate those bad
things. If we see someone
beating a child, naturally, we
try to intervene, to stop
without thinking. We just we do
it to protect the child. But at
a deeper level, a sort of a more
philosophical level, one of the
things that that comes with the
reincarnational worldview and
understanding the deep, deep
forces that guide people's lives
and set up circumstances is.
It's an absolute waste of time
to be envious of someone else's
good fortune. You should never
judge someone else's bad
fortune. We don't know what got
them there. We don't know
whether this is a saint or a
sinner. It could be a sinner
inheriting bad karma, or it
could be a saint who's taken on
hard somebody else's bad karma
we don't know. Best to take care
of your own shop. Best to do the
very, very best you can with the
circumstances in which you find
yourselves in, because there's
meaning and intention in those
circumstances, engage that part
of the outside world which is
yours to engage. A lot of it is
recognizing that people are at
different stages of their life,
their souls life, and we have to
take the we have to stand the
ground, that we need to stand
but most of our judgments aren't
about standing ground. It's just
being judgmental in the way that
creates more barriers that only
have to be taken down later.
Judgments are barriers. You
know, there's a way in which we
can draw conclusions, but
without living within the harsh
boundaries of judgments. You
know,
Emmy Vadnais: do you feel we're
going through a collective
Near-Death Experience, even
though we don't really die,
since our consciousness seems to
continue.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I think we
are going through something like
that. You know what happens when
people have a near fatal
accident, and we, we know that
when they they're in, their mind
speeds up. They become able to
do physical things that they
would never have dreamed, that
they could do if they're falling
off a mountain, they can take,
you know, action along the way.
And the mind speeds up. And
often the heart opens, the mind
opens, one begins, enters into
Transcendence spaces under the
pressure of almost dying. Now,
it's not being alarmist to say
that we are going into a near
extinction event on this planet.
The crises, which have only now
just just beginning to start,
are going to be getting worse,
and everything we're doing in
this country, I'm afraid,
politically, is going to make
that crisis, that confrontation
with the planet's limits, even
harder and more severe. So
clearly, we're going into very,
very difficult and challenging
times, and there are some very
smart people, good, clear
thinking people, who basically
have concluded that's it.
Humanity is toast. We're living
on extended time. There's no
reversing this process. We're
going to go extinct. We're going
to die. We just don't know it
yet, but it's the if you look at
the statistics, you look at the
information, you look at the
patterns, we're going extinct. I
personally don't think we are
going extinct, but I don't
believe that, like on rational
calculus grounds, I believe it
because of my spiritual
experiences that we do make it
through this crisis, but it
clearly is going to be a planet
changing crisis. It's going to
be a civilization changing
crisis. It's going to be a
Near-Death Experience of our
culture, of our life on this
planet. And we might learn
something about what might
happen during it, if we study
people, individuals who have had
near death experiences. So I
think we are I think things are
speeding up. I think things are
becoming dire. I think there are
fewer and fewer innocent
decisions. Every decision has
infinite ramifications. I think
we're coming into a make or
break point. This is we're
coming into a point of grow up
or die. And the threat of
extinction is a tremendous
evolutionary accelerator, and I
think we're coming into a time
where we're beginning to realize
that if we don't change our
practices, we're going to lose
our life on this planet. And
that core deep down inside this
transformation that's required
is not simply a transformation
of politics or economics or
industrial production or
agricultural it's not that
primarily. It is fundamentally a
crisis of consciousness. It is
the structure of human
consciousness that has gotten us
into this mess. It's the
limitations of ego, the
loneliness, the self
centeredness of our so called
cut off ego that has led us into
these dead end scenarios of just
consuming more and more and more
but not experience any
satisfaction that really. It
gives us any steep, true psycho
spiritual nourishment, we either
make it through this crisis or
we go extinct. I personally,
because that's the visions I've
been given. I think we make it
through. My concern is how many
of our children and
grandchildren and great
grandchildren are going to die
before we make it through.
That's my major concern.
Emmy Vadnais: There may be those
listening thinking, Well, if
there is this oceanic wave of
love and oneness, why does it
have to get so bad or hard? Why
do we have to get to this point,
why do we have to suffer so
much? Why does there have to be
pain and suffering and people
being treated poorly and dying a
bodily death when maybe they
didn't otherwise have to?
Chris Bache: Yeah, boy, that's a
hard question. You're asking
hard questions today. You're
basically asking the question,
why is there suffering, if there
is intelligence and wisdom and
love as a starting point of
creation, why is it so damn
hard? Why do we suffer so much?
Why didn't somebody give us an
instruction manual, you know,
help us do better? Why is it so
hard? And we get angry at the
divine intelligence, and we say,
we think we could do it better.
If I were doing this universe, I
could design a better universe.
There wouldn't be as much
suffering. You know, we do it
differently, but all of that
assumes that we know what is
being built. We judge from the
context of our own historical
position, and we make judgments
about what a good humanity would
look like, or what a spiritually
realized humanity would look
like, or just what a peaceful
humanity would look like, and
this is how we could build
toward that. But maybe we're not
building toward that. Maybe
we're building through that.
Clearly, the creative
intelligence thinks on a huge
landscape. When you really just
meditate on what astrophysics
has taught us and astronomy has
taught us, the landscape of
creation is vast and
magnificent. So we have to
genuinely ask ourselves, okay,
what is this intelligence
creating in this species? What
is the project? Where are we
going? What might we become? And
if we expand in even lightly,
100,000 years, which is a second
in cosmic time, even if we
imagine what would be the best
that we could become in 100,000
years, could we might begin to
understand where suffering fits
into this larger agenda, which
is larger than most of our
agenda. Most of us would think
if we could just get comfortable
and be a happy human being as we
are, and live, eat and die, we'd
be okay. But maybe that's not
the agenda of existence at all,
of the creative intelligence,
and I don't mean to treat people
suffering cavalierly. I truly do
not mean so I mean it's all
great respect to those who
suffer honestly, but suffering
in some ways in our time is like
when we're building a house, and
we have the walls up, the stud
walls up, and we have the
trusses up, but we haven't put
on the roof. And if it rains,
rain comes in, it's because the
house is unfinished. It's not
because there's any structural
design flaw in the house. The
house is just not finished.
Humanity is an unfinished
species. Sri Aurobindo made a
large point of this. He talked
about how humanity is a
transitional species. We are
transitioning from what we were
100,000 years ago into what we
are in the process of becoming
deep. We are not the end of the
project. We are just in the
middle of the project. In that
context, if we take disease, for
example, we are we are only at
the early stages of developing
our consciousness so clearly and
strongly that we can heal
diseases in our body with our
minds. We know
psychoneuroimmunology has shown
us this, but I'm talking about
the serious diseases that seem
so resistance to this subtle
manipulation. We are just
getting started in basically
exploring the potential of our
consciousness to keep this
system healthy and strong and
some of the suffering of
disease, it's just an unfinished
business. We haven't gotten to
the point where we can control
ourselves. It much Our knowledge
has not expanded yet to be able
to supplement what we can do
with our mind. There's just so
much which is unfinished. So
before we kind of take over
control and blame God for doing
such a mess up, we might examine
our own assumptions of what the
what the purpose of the project
is what the goal of the project
is.
Emmy Vadnais: Because you're a
man of deep philosophy and
religious and spiritual studies.
I know you mentioned this in
your book in our previous
conversation, and since you
brought up God, can you briefly
mention your relationship to
that term?
Chris Bache: I was raised in a
Catholic tradition. I was
studying to be a priest in the
early years. For four years, I
have learned a lot in watching
religions coming to existence.
And in some ways, dogma is kind
of like sausage. You never want
to see one being made, you know,
because it's it may look good on
the outside, but boy, a whole
lot of personality gets involved
in the forging of dogma in
history, you know. So it's a
sobering experience to truly
watch how religions come into
existence. And so I've learned
just from the study of history
that one of the most dangerous
things that a human being is can
say is, I know what God wants
you to do. You should do this,
you know. And there's so many
limitations, cultural
limitations, historical
limitations, that are built into
God vocabulary, to the god
language, that I prefer not to
use that term, but, and I would
talk about the divine, but even
the Divine is super loaded with
historical associations. And so
the in the title of my book on
psychedelic work is LSD in the
mind of the universe. And I
chose not to kind of concretize
that with an image of divinity,
because I see those images of
divinity as so historically
conditioned that they weren't
large enough to envision what I
was trying to describe. Now we
have a sense of how vast the
universe is, so we count its
distance in light years. And
each light year is 6 million
million miles, and we count it
in terms of multiple 1000s of
light years. And then to imagine
that there is a mind which is as
large as this universe is large.
And then to try to fathom what
that mind might be like, and
then to take a journey in which
you, you self, initiate into the
edges of that vast, expensive
mind, several things kind of
happen, or at least happen to
me. One is that I fell in love.
I fell in love with this
reality. Once you experience it
in its clarity, it's so powerful
and so magnificent and so
beautiful that it I call it my
beloved. It's just it is a love
relationship with life, with
this deeper intelligence
embedded in life. Now I
sometimes talk about the divine,
as I have here, and sometimes
I'll even talk about God if I
feel that the context is clear
that I'm not using those terms
in their conventional
references, but I'm using to
point to what those terms point
to, ideally, this infinitely
large horizon, this expanse,
this beauty, this knowledge,
this genius. We're talking about
cosmic genius in this universe.
The hardest thing that I found
in negotiating all of my
psychedelic work was not what
happened in that journey during
the sessions, the hardest part
came when I ended that journey,
and everything was fine,
everything was good. There was
no trauma. I was I had, had, had
been given many, many gifts of
intimacy with the divine. But
then when I withdrew, and I
stepped out of it, and I was no
longer making contact,
experiential contact, with that
deeper reality, for reasons that
I explained in the book, it was
the loss of contact with my
beloved. Even though I knew the
beloved was always here, I knew
that it was only my own blinders
which were keeping me from
experiencing it. I knew it was
always the warp and woof of
reality that I was embedded in,
but the intensity of being
dissolved into the body of light
that is the underlying light of
universe. It it caused such a
deep sadness. Us a deep
withdrawal. It was very
difficult, and it really took me
about 10 years after I stopped
my sessions, to really get fully
grounded and committed to living
in this earth on its terms.
Again, I give you that anecdote
just to say that my journey into
the divine had many stages and
many layers over many years. I
would not trade any of those
days for any treasures on earth.
And learning how to live without
the constant immersion or the
repetitive immersion into those
treasures has been a real
learning exercise for me that it
continues.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, Chris, how
do you suggest? Or what do you
recommend? Are ways that people
can explore themselves, get in
touch with the deeper creative
intelligence inside of them to
be able to move that karmic part
of them forward. Are there any
particular practices that are
maybe outside or part of
psychedelics that can assist
people listening?
Chris Bache: There's so many
practices, because what we're
talking about is spirituality.
And the Christians have an
approach to spirituality, the
Jews, Muslims, Buddhists, they
have an approach to spirituality
with a lot of common ground. But
it's no secret. And now we live
in a time in history where these
previously secret teachings are
now available on every street
corner. You know, after China
invaded Tibet, lineage, holders
of this tremendous, ancient
spiritual lineage have now
flooded into the Western
countries, and we have centers
throughout the United States and
Europe. We're talking about
basic spiritual practices. We're
also talking about maybe psycho
therapeutic practices, we're
basically using a
psychotherapeutic approach to
heal some of the surface wounds
of this of the heart. My first
sitter was my wife, Carl, and
she's clinical psychologist, and
she never did a psychedelic
session. It wasn't her cup of
tea. She really found everything
she needed on her meditation
cushion. And
Emmy Vadnais: just to clarify
you by sitter, you mean the
person who was with you during
your LSD sessions.
Chris Bache: Yeah, she was, she
was my sitter and holding the
fort while I was in my LSD
sessions, and she was managing
them with music and whatnot. She
never wanted to sit her setting
that wanted to do a session
herself. She has subsequently
gone on to complete her three
year, three month, three day
solo retreat in the Vajrayana
tradition, she's been made and
recognized as a lama within her
community, and she has a very,
very rich interior life. We're
friends, and it didn't involve
psychedelics at all. So there's
so many there's so many lineages
of spiritual teachings. There's
Celtic lineages, so many Native
American lineages, there's South
American lineages. There are the
Ayahuasca traditions, there are
some psychedelic shamanic
traditions that are entering our
country strongly now. There are
everyday wisdom traditions that
are available in abundance at
any bookstore at any airport.
Sounds true, and this program is
an example of inner teachings
being made publicly available.
Even if I started a list, it
would be just a fraction of
what's really available. We can
find the practices that can help
us live a calmer, quieter, more
centered, richer life. You know,
those are available and the
practices which are taught are
pretty much the same. First,
kindness, non injury,
simplicity, voluntary
simplicity, centering,
stillness, social, kindness,
social being good to people. And
it's a long road, and it's not a
road which is going to be
traveled in any one lifetime. So
this is a road that's going to
be traveled over many lifetimes,
but every lifetime can get
better than the life before it.
Emmy Vadnais: We've also touched
on the shadow part, and in
addition and kind of building on
what you just shared, how much
of a role does having a good
time, joy, love, following your
own bliss or creativity play a
role in a person's karma and
reincarnation?
Chris Bache: Yeah, it certainly
does. I mean, it's just part of
the fabric. I. Think, because we
learn about reincarnation from
reading the books from
therapists, we have a tendency
to cast the thinking about
reincarnation in a negative
light, because people go to
therapists who are in pain and
but if you are exceptionally
brilliant, creative composer.
You know you can explore that
dimension of your life and find
and trace the roots of your love
of music, and you'll find that
it goes deeper than this present
lifetime. All of our past gives
us, all of our virtues and all
of our vices, and we honor
existence by accepting the
virtues, building on them and
then working to reduce the
vices, to unlock their unlock
them and let them go.
Emmy Vadnais: What role does
self love play in this process?
Chris Bache: How can you be in
love? How can you love the world
if you don't love yourself? It's
one of the things that came real
clear in some of my teachings,
that if you're going to become
one with the God, if you're
going to become one with all of
life, you must become one with
yourself. And therefore, when
you try to become one with God,
one with the universe.
Everything which is incompatible
with becoming one with yourself
is forced to the surface. So all
of your injuries, all of your
trauma, all of your self
defeating habits and behaviors,
these are all shoved to the
surface right inside you, right
in front of you. So self love,
self acceptance is absolutely
critical, but not superficial.
Self Love, real deep self love,
love that's willing to take on
the shadow, love which is
willing to love that shadow
until that shadow becomes a baby
in your arms, and you take care
of it and nurture it. You know
the deep love, really deep, the
type of love a mother has for
her child. That love was the
type of love we have to have for
ourselves and so we can handle
we can clean anything that needs
to be cleaned in it,
Emmy Vadnais: unconditional love
and unconditional acceptance and
love covers a multitude of sins.
Chris Bache: Well, let's say it
compensates, doesn't it?
Emmy Vadnais: Chris, you've
shared so much today about
collective karma and
reincarnation, and I know we're
going to have another
conversation about the birth of
a future human that you
discovered in your LSD sessions.
And I'm wondering if you want to
just touch on that a little bit
to prime us for our next
conversation and what that's
about,
Chris Bache: I'd love to one of
the surprises for me in my
psychedelic work, because I
began this work adopting a model
of transformation, a model of
personal transformation, which
is pretty widespread in the
Transpersonal community, that
when you do these practices,
it's about personal
transformation, Personal
awakening, personal healing,
personal enlightenment, and one
of the surprises for me has been
how much of my work didn't seem
to be about me personally at
all. It was about collective and
it was collective dynamics, and
my love for myself expanded to
embrace the love of my people,
and the love of my planet, and
the love of all the beings on
the planet. So it just wasn't
about me personally. As that
deepened over the years, I began
to be initiated into a series of
visions where it was not about
my spiritual evolution, it was
about the spiritual evolution of
humanity, where humanity was
going. And this is, this is, I
just want to emphasize. This is
an utterly natural phenomenon
our individual mind. When we
relax the boundaries of our
individual mind, our
consciousness opens and deep
into our personal unconscious.
But as you keep clearing and you
keep relaxing, it opens up into
this underlying field that Jung
called the collective psyche.
And it's just natural that when
you go deeper into that
collective psyche, and even
pushing through it to the matrix
underneath that, that you
inherit insights into what's
going on in the life of this
being. We count our lives in
years. It counts its life in
millennia, right? So it's just
it opens up naturally, and I
began to have insights of
humanity poised on the edge of
a. Global death and rebirth
process, that what I had
experienced is death and
rebirth, and what every
meditator experiences in terms
of death and rebirth on the
meditation cushion, that there
was actually now fermenting
within history, a death and
rebirth dynamic that was so
large, so powerful, it was
carrying all of humanity in its
grip. This was a surprise, an
absolute surprise to me, but it
leave led me to have a certain
understanding that the project
of history at this point, I
think, a way of summing up the a
project is to give birth to a
new kind of human being, the
giving birth into what I call
the future human. Some people
call it Homo spiritualis, Homo
noeticus, the different words
for it, but a new form of human
being who isn't simply the old
human being, polished up and
cleaned up and, you know, doing
better, but truly a revolution
that causes the plate tectonics
of the collective psyche to
shift so that all children born
after this shift takes place.
And I'm not talking about a
shift that takes place in 24
hours, but takes place over
decades of work. All children
born after this pivot are
literally functioning within a
different collective psyche.
This is something that's taking
place at a very, very deep
collective level. And I was
given teachings to explain how
this is working out through
reincarnation, what the project
of reincarnation is, how does it
play into this? I introduce
concepts that will talk about
the birth of the diamond soul,
this integration of all of our
former lives, coming into a
unity synthesis and leading to
an exponential explosion of
insight and compassion inside
the human heart and human mind.
That's what we're going to be
talking about. We're going to be
talking about where humanity is
taking where reincarnation is
taking humanity, what some of
the mechanisms are trying to
understand underneath the
turmoil of our times, which are
getting more and more tumultuous
almost year by year, and where,
where we might be going, what
the larger project is. And I
must confess, I found what I was
given deeply reassuring, because
I feel the growing waves of
darkness. I feel the chaos, and
I see the social struggle that
we don't know how to navigate
the falling apart process, but I
take great strength in being
given an understanding of what's
going on here at a deeper level,
and that's what I'd like to
share with you in our next
conversation.
Emmy Vadnais: Well, I'm very
much looking forward to the
conversation about the birth of
the future human and Chris, is
there anything else you want to
share about collective karma and
reincarnation today?
Chris Bache: Well, I'll just
share one visionary experience,
which I share in LSD, in the
mind of the universe. It was
late in my journey. It was, I
don't know, 15 years or so into
my journey, and I had already
gone through multiple layers of
death into deeper and deeper
levels, and I opened up into a
very, very deep level in which I
experienced all of humanity as a
single organism, reincarnation,
generation by generation, the
entire the entire family of
humanity was going through this
developmental process that all
of us individually are going
through and experiencing all of
humanity in this flow of
learning and in this flow of
perpetual development, perpetual
integration of more and more
spiritual reality into their
lives, was, on the one hand, an
extremely uplifting experience,
and It was also a devastating
experience, because I saw from
the one perspective, you might
say, that whole generations will
be sacrifice in this historical
transformation we're going
through. And it had the
ruthlessness of Kali, the
destroyer of, you know, of you
know, the gods which bring death
and destruction in order to
liberate and at the same time,
this was not something which is
being done to us. This is some a
role that we voluntarily took on
as our offering to the creative
intelligence in the evolution of
this species at this point in
time. So it. Was hard teaching,
and it was a magnificent,
ecstatic teaching, all at the
same time. And the key is just
to realize that what is taking
place in the lives of
individuals is also taking place
in the lives of the species. We
are all in this together. We're
moving ultimately, we are all
have to move together. Some
people may get a little ahead,
some people may drag a little
behind, but ultimately, we are
moving together as we move
through this, this transition
and the magnitude of the beauty
of what we are becoming, I don't
know how I'm going to talk about
that without crying when we talk
next it's just so magnificent.
Emmy Vadnais: Oh, I know I
teared up a few times in this
conversation today, and also
when I read your fabulous book,
LSD and the mind of the
universe, it is very deeply
moving, and I look forward to
exploring more with you in the
next conversation. Chris Bache,
thank you so much once again for
this incredible conversation
that I hope many find insightful
and hopefully uplifting in this
journey of life that we're all a
part of together. Thank you for
being with me today.
Chris Bache: Thank you, Emmy.
It's been a real pleasure and an
honor. Thank you.
Emmy Vadnais: My pleasure as
well, and for those of you
watching or listening, thank you
for being with us, because you
are the reason that we are here.
Unknown: You four in the new
thinking aloud dialog series is
Charles T tart. 70 years of
exploring consciousness and
parapsychology now available on
Amazon. You can
now download all eight copies of
the new thinking allowed
magazine for free or order
beautiful printed copies. Go to
new thinking aloud.org.