Chris Bache: Hi everybody. It's
nice to see your faces. Nice to
see the Meet the Klan who is
interested in the things that
the presenters are interested
in. Short Introduction, I've
made my living as a university
professor in Ohio. I taught in
the Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at young sound
state. I taught in religious
studies, Eastern religion,
psychology of mysticism,
comparative spirituality,
Eastern thought. But what brings
me here today is not that work,
but it's my work with
psychedelics, which basically I
did for 20 years while I was an
academic, but I wasn't really
allowed to speak about those
things in the academic
environment, and it was only
after I retired that I was able
to write a book that I'd like to
speak from today. Now let me see
if I can get this working
correctly. This is a book that I
published at the end of last
year. It's a book I'd like to
speak from today. It tells the
story of where I went. Over 20
years of working with LSD, I
followed a protocol established
by Stan Grof, working in
psychedelic therapy, which is
totally isolated, isolated. The
conventional sort of therapeutic
environment, totally isolated.
Working with headphones and
eyeshades and music and all
those traditional trappings,
except that I worked with very
high doses. I did 73 sessions
over 20 years, working with
between 506 100 micrograms. I
don't recommend this protocol. I
wouldn't do it the same way if I
were starting over again, but
that's what I did, and this is
the story. When someone asks me,
what's it like taking that doses
of LSD that's high, I say it's
it's like being the middle of a
nuclear explosion. It just
completely shatters all the
dimensions of your mind and the
boundaries of consciousness. And
if you keep this up for long
periods of time, it reveals
levels of reality that lie
beyond time, space reality, it
is like this nuclear explosion,
which, as it pushes higher into
the atmosphere, it takes levels
of the atmosphere that are
invisible and makes them visible
when you work systematically
with psychedelics, whether it's
an indigenous context, or in
contemporary context, you
basically go through a process
that reveals levels of existence
that lie beyond your ordinary
sensory experience. Very
briefly, in the book, I tell the
story of the levels of
consciousness that I went
through in this process, going
through a series of death and
rebirth experiences, a series
that took place at first the
personal level of mind, where
one is dealing with personal
issues, eventually going through
ego death, and then at the
collective level of mind, where
you're engaging deep structures
within the collective psyche.
Third, the archetypal dimension
of mind, going beyond time
space, reality, entering into
being, dissolved into some of
the archetypal structures that
underlie physical existence.
Fourth, going into causal level
reality, causal oneness. And
finally, entering, for me,
entering into what I call the
diamond Luminosity, what
Buddhism calls Dharmakaya, or
the absolute, the clear light of
absolute reality. Making a
transition from one level to
another involves going through a
series of deaths and rebirth.
It's not simply ego death. It's
going through a death that takes
place at the collective level,
deaths that take place at the
archetypal level, and so on and
so forth, entering into deeper
intimacy with the universe. Now
that's all the slides I wanted
to share, let me see if I can
get out of that. Such a long
journey, so many years, so many
levels of consciousness, it's
impossible for me to summarize
them very succinctly. But for
today's presentation, I simply
wanted to focus on two aspects
of this story which I think are
relevant to this discussion of
the relationship between
consciousness and the
exploration of consciousness and
building the regenerative
society. The first issue has to
do with something that happened
in the collective level of mind,
and the second has to do with
what I call the birth of the
future human. After I had gone
through ego death. After I had
worked for a couple of years and
had gone through a number of
different ego death experiences,
I entered a domain that involved
large quantities of vast
territories of collective
suffering, a domain that I call
the. Ocean of suffering. It
eventually expanded over two
years to encompass hundreds of
1000s of beings, of persons and
1000s of years of time. And this
was confusing to me at first,
because I did this work, like
many people working with
psychedelics, thinking that I
was doing this work for my
personal benefit that I was
doing it to heal myself, to
enlighten myself, to accelerate
my own spiritual development,
but it was always kind of self
or self referencing. What I
found was that this ocean of
suffering went on for so long
and it was so challenging and
involved so many 1000s of people
that eventually it shattered the
very model that I had brought to
working with psychedelics, and I
abandoned what I would call the
individual model of
transformation, and I adopted a
collective model of
transformation. That is, I
believe that what I was doing
when I entered into the ocean of
suffering was actually being
used or facilitating a healing
that was not focused in my
personal life or my personal
soul even, but it was focused on
the collective psyche of
Humanity, that something was
using my sessions to drain
toxins that live in human psyche
that are the residue of
unresolved trauma from 1000s and
1000s of years of war and the
terrible things that we've done
to each Other through history.
Eventually, this work culminated
in an orgy of cleansing and
purification and healing, and I
was jettisoned from there on
into archetype of reality, and I
never returned into the ocean of
suffering. My point from this,
to keep it very short, my point
is everything we do when we are
working in deep states of
consciousness not only affects
our personal being, but it
affects the beings of those
around us. It affects those who
are immediately around us in our
system of social relationships.
Some of my work affected my
students, for example, without
them knowing what I was doing.
But it also reaches deeper than
that. It reaches deep into the
fiber of the collective psyche
of humanity. And I think when we
work in deep, Non-ordinary
states, we are if we choose to
do it, if we choose to allow
this to happen, or if it is our
karma for this to happen, we go
through processes. We do things
which allow us to facilitate a
direct healing, a direct
transformation of our species as
a whole, of our deep family,
there is no private self in the
world. We are part of a species.
Our species is part of the
ecosystem of Earth, and earth is
part of the galaxy and so on and
so forth. And when we do this
work conscientiously, we are
given opportunities to bring
about a transformation which I
think extends far beyond our
personal life and far beyond our
moment in time. Now, perhaps
because of this very strong
collective orientation my work,
something else began to happen.
Over the course of the 20 years
that I was doing this work, I
began to experience a series of
visions about the human
trajectory of evolution, about
where evolution was taking
humanity, where we were, what
was happening in the larger
scheme of things, I entered
repeatedly, a state of
consciousness that I would
describe as deep time. Deep time
is not eternity. It isn't
timelessness. It's a it's a
condition of time in which you
can experience hundreds of
years, or even 1000s and 10s of
1000s of years in a very
compressed time frame, sometimes
as a simultaneous now, I entered
into deep time, slowly,
personally, with my own personal
deep time, and then I entered
from there into collective deep
time in which I was given
teachings about where humanity
was in its evolution and what
was happening and where we were
going. There is a chapter in the
book called The Birth of the
future human, and the focus of
these visions was that humanity
was coming into a culmination
point.
They were coming we were coming
into a before and after point, a
turning point, a critical
transformation that involved the
entire human family. What? Is
emphasized was that the creative
intelligence of the universe was
not simply trying to awaken
individuals. It's almost as if
the age of individual
enlightenment was over, but the
creative intelligence was
actually trying to awaken the
entire human species, and that
we were poised on the cusp of a
profound transformation of the
human condition, a
transformation that would change
not only our economy and our
ecological values and our social
orientation. It would reach so
deep that it would actually
change the bedrock of the human
psyche. It would change the
fundamental archetypal blueprint
of the human psyche that that,
in my understanding, is that is
our hour of history. That is
what's happening. That is what
we are entering. The visions
that I had for this I did this
work between 1979 and 1999 so
when I when this was taking
place. This is 30 to 25 years
ago in which I was experiencing
these things. And in one
critical series of sessions, I
was taken deep into humanity's
future, and I experienced the
death and rebirth of humanity.
All mystics tell us, we learn
from the mystical traditions
that before Great Awakening,
there takes place a great death,
before the awakening of mystical
oneness, we experience the dark
night of the soul. Humanity as a
whole was entering the dark
night of the soul, of its soul,
which is a time of intense
purification, a content
confrontation with our
historical karma, with the
limitations that we have created
and lived with in history. And
in this series of sessions, I
went deep into the future, and I
experienced the complete
collapse of civilization as we
know. It, just a profound
implosion that seemed to be
driven by an ecological crisis,
but an ecological crisis that
was so deep that it triggered a
global systems disintegration at
our collective level and just at
the depth of this death process
when it looked like it was going
to be an extinction event, I
experienced that the worst of
the problem that was like a
storm passing over, a hurricane
passing over a Pacific Island.
The storm passed and the
survivors began to get up and
pick themselves up and began to
begin anew, and when they began
anew, they were different human
beings that a transformation
took place in the depth of this
death and rebirth process in
which we let go fundamental
beliefs and values and patterns
of our past and we engage the
future as different human beings
with an expanded heart, a
profound, innate sense of the
oneness of existence and our
oneness with other human beings,
a profound a deeper transparency
to the mind of the universe as A
whole. This truly was a before
and after point in time. It took
me literally years to recover
from the tremendous time
expansion and this encounter
with this, at the one hand,
awesome, and at the other hand,
very challenging and very
difficult confrontation with the
human story, or extension of the
human story, but this has been
the reality that I've lived with
ever since. It's been the
reality that I understand what
is taking place in history
today. It's been the reality
that basically is my background
to confronting the covid 19
crisis, the pandemic, which I
see, is simply just an overture
to a much series of punctuated
historical crises that lie ahead
for us in the 21st Century. And
I think there is a correlation
between what's happening in the
outer world and what's happening
in the inner world that as the
at the outer world, as we are
trying to become one planet, an
integrated planet with an
integrated citizen, Sri and a
healthy planet. That external
drive to oneness is being
mirrored in an internal drive to
oneness, which involves, I
think, an integration of the
soul into time, space, reality.
And by the soul, I mean the
consciousness that holds all the
experiences of all of our former
lives. I think basically our
consciousness of all of our
former lives is coming together
and fusing, and when they fuse,
it creates a higher form of
consciousness. Which really, I
think, is the new platform of
humanity in future time. Now I
think I probably close to the
end of my time. I know I've
thrown a lot of large ideas out
there, so I'll just stop there
and see where we take this.
Daniel Pinchbeck: Christopher,
that was wonderful. Thank you so
much for sharing. I really love
your work, and I love your
vision, and it's kind of, yeah,
I mean, extraordinary to talk
with somebody who has explored
the sort of depth dimensions of
the LSD space, perhaps as much
as anybody alive right now. I'm
kind of curious. What's your
perspective on LSD. I mean, did
you have any perspective on what
it is in this, in this
exploration? Is it itself a you
know, is there an entities
attached to it? Is it a being?
Is it just a chemical catalyst?
Is it here accidentally? Is
there some kind of
intentionality to it?
Chris Bache: Well, given the
synchronicity of the birth of
the atomic bomb and the birth of
LSD in the same decade, I don't
think it's an accident that it's
here. I understand it to be an
amplifier and a catalyst of
consciousness, similar to S is
Psilocybin and Ayahuasca and DMT
and five Meo DMT, each of these
are fundamental catalysts of
consciousness. Each of them have
their own distinctive
characteristics. One of the
things I think, which is
different about LSD is it's
relatively new, and therefore
humanity doesn't have a lot of
history with it. I my sense is
that when we do Ayahuasca and
when we do Psilocybin, we don't
only experience the
physiological absorption of this
chemical into our biophysiology,
but we also engage the fields
which have been fields of
consciousness, which have been
created by all the beings who
have worked with this substance
through through time. So because
we've been using Psilocybin for
1000s of years, we've been using
Ayahuasca for 1000s of years.
They are very strong fields
associated with these substances
that we encounter when we use
these substances. LSD is a
relatively young substance, and
therefore I experience it being
unusually clean. In this
respect, I did not experience
much of a cultural overlay, much
of an historical overlay. It
seems to be particularly clean.
And I experience it as and
remember, I was working at high
levels, higher levels than I
recommend, 500 to 600
micrograms. It has a tendency to
drive to the high ceiling of the
high cosmological ceiling.
Psilocybin is much more body
grounded at the states of
consciousness that awakens are
much more, kind of closer to
where we live in our body. LSD
isn't necessarily so at lower
doses, yes, but in higher doses,
it tends to dry, drive high into
the cosmology.
Daniel Pinchbeck: I'm also kind
of curious. I bet you seem like
you have a bit of a Buddhist
orientation also. Am I correct
in
Chris Bache: that that's true?
Yeah,
Daniel Pinchbeck: you mentioned
reincarnation in past lives. I'm
kind of curious, if you have a
insight into what that means. I
mean, I got very excited by
amitha Swamis book. I think it
was called the self aware
universe. Amigos, a quantum
physicist who was, I believe,
working at Institute of Noetic
Sciences, and he began to look
at how quantum physics, action
at a distance, could kind of
provide a, you know, at least a
you know, starting point for
scientific hypothesis around how
there might be kind of an
aggregate, kind of a quantum
aggregate of, you know, feeling
willing, thinking, that somehow
continues, connected, you know,
after, after the physical death,
and kind of seeks to re
aggregate, to continue some
process towards maybe the
ultimate goal of, you know,
unification or realization or
enlightenment. I don't know if
you had any any thoughts in
those regards.
Chris Bache: Regards I do.
Reincarnation is a fundamental
part of my worldview. The first
book I wrote is a book on
reincarnation, life cycles, and
it discusses the empirical
evidence. As a philosopher, I
believe that the physical, the
evidence, the scientific
evidence for reincarnation now
is overwhelming. We have
extraordinary number of cases.
Ian Stevenson's work with young
children at the University of
Virginia basically established
the empirical database for
justifying a belief in
reincarnation. Now that doesn't
mean we understand the physics
of it. There's so much we still
don't understand about it, but a
fundamental principle that I
take away from Stevenson's work
and all the work done by past
life therapist in the cycle
psychotherapeutic community is
that nature retains its
learning. Nature holds on to its
learning. My understanding is
that reincarnation is the higher
octave of evolution. So an
evolution. Then we find that
nature folds forward the
learning of groups in
reincarnation, nature has found
a way of folding forward in
time, the learning of
individuals. Now, I think
eventually, lifetime after
lifetime after lifetime, we're
learning more, we're becoming
more. We're acquiring more
skills. We're activating more
potentials that are late within
our structure, sooner or later,
sooner or later, I believe all
of our reincarnational history
becomes integrated into a higher
order of intelligence. I've
experienced this in my sessions
where all of my former lives
came together and they came
together, and they fused. And
when they fuse, there was an
enormous explosion of energy of
diamond light broke out of my
chest, and it shot me into a
state of consciousness in which
I was an individual, but I was
an individual beyond any frame
of reference I had previously
known.
Daniel Pinchbeck: We had a
question from Deanna. She's
curious to know your thoughts
and experience and people
getting to these places of
insight, integration and deep
time without the use of mind
altering drugs or plant
medicines.
Chris Bache: Absolutely, I've
had many people write me since
this book has been published,
and they say I understand what
you're talking about. I've had
experiences similar to what
you're describing, but I've
never done psychedelics. I'm a
lifelong meditator. I've had
these experiences under Med,
with meditation, and I think
that's absolutely true. If LSD
is an amplifier of
consciousness, it is
consciousness that does the
work, and there are many ways of
intensifying and amplifying
consciousness. We know many of
the forms, LSD or psychedelics,
is simply another form, another
key to working with
consciousness, but it's
consciousness that does the
work.
Daniel Pinchbeck: Yeah, and what
kind of since you have these
insights into kind of the
future, although didn't exactly
seem like you had an exact time
frame, but I remember in dark
night, early dawn, you kind of
said it was going to be a very
compressed period when
civilization began to crack
apart, and these kind of
emergent new properties of the
new human, you know, kind of
began to integrate together. You
know what you know? Maybe that's
not, that's what I remember, but
you tell me if I'm wrong. But
then also I'm curious, like, you
know, how would you ground that
into, like, practical advice for
people in this time? Is there,
you know? Should you know? Is
doing these psychedelic,
entheogenic explorations a form
of a way to prepare oneself for
what's coming? You know? Is
there a way we can minimize the
destructive impacts of what's
coming, because it definitely
feels like there's a bit of a
destructive express train
heading our way right now.
Chris Bache: There is, it's kind
of a Kali destroyer. In order to
make room for the new I think
there are many things we can do.
I think basically collectively,
we're facing our collective
shadow, and that collective
shadow is a shadow that all of
us have personally had a hand in
creating, in the sense that we
have lived through history, and
therefore we have been part of
our history. And this kind of
confrontation with the
collective shadow is part of our
common work. Now, I think one of
the ways in which we can
consciously participate in this
process is first by
understanding what's taking
place. And you're right, I
wasn't given any specific
details of date. I wasn't given
any details of exactly how, when
and where this was going to take
place. I was given experiences
of this, of this meltdown, not
as an individual would
experience, but But literally
ask the human species as a whole
would experience it. And I think
the one of the key things we can
do is basically take responsible
for responsibility for our own
shadow, to do whatever
psychotherapeutic work,
psychedelic work, meditational
work, spiritual work, to
basically help us confront the
the shadow dimensions of our own
being, in order to dissolve
those and let light in where
previously darkness had reigned.
But then at another level, we
can collectively participate and
help others in confronting the
shadow of our culture, the
shadow of history. That's the
kind of political action side,
the social action side.
Daniel Pinchbeck: Beautiful
Christopher, I love it. I think
that'll be great to have David,
Luke, come on and speak for a
bit, and then maybe have a
little bit of a dialog after So,
David, if you are there, do you
want to jump in?
David Luke: Yeah, sure. Hi. Can
you hear me? Okay, yep. Oh,
great, yeah. Good to be here.
Thanks for inviting me along.
Good see everybody. Thanks for
that. Chris, fantastic. Is that?
To hear you talk. So I'll just
give you a little bit of
background about me, and I'm
going to give you kind of pricey
of I've been doing for the last
few decades, or what the
insights I've kind of come to so
I'm a psychologist by training,
primarily parapsychologist,
Transpersonal psychologist, and
my kind of big umbrella area of
interest is kind of altered
states of consciousness and
anomalous or Transpersonal
experiences. So I've done a lot
of research on all kinds of old
states. I do a lot of research,
specifically with psychedelics.
I do a lot of research when I'm
not on psychedelics as well, but
it's not as much fun. And so I'm
going to give you a kind of a
bit of an overview of some of
the insights I've had that come
from the research, but also my
own particular journey as well.
So insights that are coming from
the research and what the
journey involves and what it
leads to, you could pretty much
sum up the kind of the where we
are currently with our kind of
intellectual quest, by
suggesting that psychedelics and
altered states in general,
because I think all old states
have a have a kind of continuity
with psychedelic experiences.
Just perhaps the volumes turned
up more with psychedelic
experiences is they increase
connectivity, and they increase
connectivity across the whole
kind of spectrum of experience,
from the biological through the
psychological, the sociological,
the ecological, and even into
the cosmological or spiritual
realms, perhaps so on a
biological level, we know from
research at Imperial College,
for instance, they increase
connectivity within different
brain regions, so areas of your
brain, which don't normally
communicate with each other,
suddenly become very
communicative. They have hyper
connectivity. And on a kind of
cognitive level, this explains
things like synaesthesia,
divergent thinking and increased
creativity, cognitive
flexibility and so on. On a
psychological level, they
connect us with ourselves, so
they give us access to our
unconscious material. Tap
straight into that your shadow,
as Chris said, your personal
history, your past traumas and
so on, and hopefully through a
kind of assistance, or through
being guided through that
journey, you can come to some
kind of resolution of your prior
traumas. I just found a
brilliant quote by GABA Matt a
about half an hour ago. He says,
Every human being has a true,
genuine, authentic self, and the
trauma is the disconnection from
it, and the healing is the
reconnection with it, and we
know that this results in a kind
of enhanced mood, well being and
enhanced mindfulness. From a
site, psychological, scientific
perspective on a sociological
level, psychedelics in old
states can help us connect,
increase our connection to each
other. They can increase our
openness to experience, our
willingness to engage with, you
know, culture and art and
different perspectives. They
increase our empathy. They
increase compassion. And this
can lead to increase in pro
social behavior and enhanced
value orientations. This is
where my own particular area of
research has been, kind of deep
diving more recently, is into
the ecological perspective on
that level, and that we find
that these states of
consciousness can increase our
connection to nature, which I
think is kind of pretty vital
right now. So we have an
increase in Eco consciousness or
biophilia, interspecies
communications or interspecies
connections also increase, and
this has a concomitant knock on
effect of increases in
ecologically orientated
behavior. So from a big survey I
conducted, we found that of the
people had taken psychedelics.
They said their psychedelic
experiences and the majority had
made them change their diet,
become more raw, more vegan,
more local, more vegetarian. It
also increased in the majority
of the sample, the amount of
gardening they do, which is a
massive take home news.
Headline, psychedelics increase
gardening. This is big news
everybody. And they can also
increase people's ecological
activism. And even people change
their career as a result of
their psychedelic experiences.
And then so we go beyond the
environment, the ecosystem and
the biosphere into the
cosmological levels as well. We
find that people have a greater
sense of connection to the
universe God, the other,
whatever it might be, and went
to the realms of Transpersonal
and mystical experiences, which
have the knock on effect of
helping people reduce their fear
of death, enhancing
spirituality, enhancing their
sense of purpose and meaning,
increasing self, Transcendence.
And we find in the clinical
research with psychedelics that
those people who have had a
mystical experience by the kind
of standard psychological
measures are the ones that have
the best clinical outcomes in
terms of dealing with
addictions, fighting depression,
anxiety or even end of life
fears. So. So all of that is
encapsulated within this kind of
notion of of course, we need the
appropriate set, setting and
substance and the preparation
and integration to book end it.
So there's some kind of insights
about where we are with the
research currently, insights
directly from the journey. I
think I'm going to give over a
few points here, one of which
is, I think the psychonaut and
scientist John Lily best
encapsulated this for me, and
that is that he had this famous
dictum, which is in the province
of the mind, what one believes
to be true is either true or
becomes true within certain
limits. These limits are to be
found experimentally, I through
science and experientially so
through personal endeavor, and
when these are found, they just
turn out to be more beliefs to
be transcended. In the problems
of the mind, there are no
limits. He did add a little
addendum to that, however, after
a few near death experiences,
pushing his physical body to the
limits, and he said, however, in
the promise of the body, there
are certain limits not to be
transcended, but in the problems
to the mind is limitless. So
this kind of gives off two other
kind of interesting points and
avenues. Is that what the first
one is that beliefs are our
reality. Our reality is only
constrained by our beliefs. But
there's a danger in that as
well, because they can our
beliefs can also be prisons. Our
convictions can make us
convicts, and we know that
because what kind of
psychological rabbit holes we
can fall down, such as
confirmation bias, whereby our
beliefs prescribe the kind of
things and information that
we're willing to accept or even
look for in the first place, and
we just end up bootstrapping our
own dogmas and belief systems.
And we see this kind of kind of
transposed into into science and
the endeavor of the research of
consciousness, where, you know,
the kind of the academy and the
scientific endeavor is pretty
much constrained by its a priori
dogmatic kind of reliance on
materialist reductionism, This
kind of neuro reductionist
perspective on physicalism, and
this view that the human
organism and consciousness
itself is merely just a
mechanistic process, and that
consciousness and life is kind
of devoid of any kind of real
sentience or or life, for that
matter. So and how that
translates is this, these kind
of limiting beliefs therefore
constrain the kind of questions
that scientists even ask in the
first place, so they only ask
questions which tend to support
these kind of prior dogmatic
belief systems about the
material nature of the universe.
And therefore, you know, fields
of research like Transpersonal
psychology and parapsychology
don't receive any funding, and
so we don't just kind of get a
big enough voice in the kind of
dominant paradigm and worldview.
So basically, make an argument
for agnosticism and plurality,
plurality that we should have,
you know, be, should be open to
many, many world views and
perspectives and and try not to
believe anything particularly,
you know, just to just beware,
be wary of beliefs in general,
and that's kind of quite useful
in this era of apparent fake
news, you know, post truth era.
And I think we've always been in
a post truth era since, you
know, the dawn of communication,
because we see in nature that
nature is constantly using
deception for its own particular
survival. So, you know, there's
never been such a thing as real
news, right, or true news. But I
think it's good to kind of take
an agnostic position and a
plurality and not get too hooked
on any particular belief system.
The other dictum, I think, that
comes out of John Lilly's famous
sentence, is that the mind is
infinite. Okay? So, I mean, we
can see that as apparent from,
you know, evidence from genius,
inspiration, creativity, along
with the findings of things like
parapsychology, which show that,
you know it by the empirical
evidence standards of today,
there is, I think there's very
we can talk to Dean Radin about
this. There's very little room
to consider that the evidence is
not substantial enough to pause
the idea that we can transcend
time and space and access any
point of time and space with our
mind. And I think Chris would
probably back that up with his
various LSD sessions. And I
think the research and theory
and physics is beginning to look
more like Parapsychology all the
time. There's an increasing
conceptual confluence of both
the fundamental quantities and
forces of physics with
consciousness. You know, time is
now considered to be somewhat
time. Subjective. Human
Experience of time is considered
to be illusory, and things like
pre cognition become more and
more possible all the time. And
then finally, my final point is,
then everything is connected.
That's one thing of
parapsychology and psychedelics
and Transpersonal psychology has
shown us that everything is
connected. We can transcend time
and space. We know that from the
evidence, from precognition to
empathy and. Clairvoyance,
synchronicities and so on,
although that is circumscribed
by point two, you know, that's
circumscribed by our beliefs and
the limitations of our beliefs.
And as a result of that, we
should act with openness
transparency in everything that
we do, with compassion and with
the spirit of reciprocity. And
so that we kind of start to move
away from all kinds of isms,
including the ones that aren't
given much air time these days,
you know, things like
ethnocentrism, but also species
centrism, stepping outside the
box of thinking we're at the top
of the of the food chain, and
even cognoscentricism. So that
is the view that, you know, only
one state of consciousness is
valued in our current society,
everything to be more
pluralistic and value everything
from dreams to meditation to
psychedelics and so on. And that
takes us back to the beginning,
is that these old states of
consciousness can help us move
towards increased connectivity.
So that's it,
Daniel Pinchbeck: David, that
was awesome. Thank you so much.
And, yeah, the work you're doing
is tremendous. Yeah, I guess I'm
curious a little bit about, you
know, what you wrote about in
the book about extraordinary
experiences, kind of like, you
know, the psychic and the
paranormal experiences that are
so common in psychedelic states,
and what that kind of reveals
about consciousness in your
perspective?
David Luke: Yeah, I think, I
think it poses an enormous
question mark against the idea
that you know brain, or that
consciousness is confined to the
brain, right? I mean, we already
have kind of 135 years of
evidence from Parapsychology
that you know, psychic abilities
and the Transcendence of time
and space. Have some really good
evidence to back it up. It's not
an everyday experience, but it
happens to enough people enough
times and under control
laboratory situations that we
can say, Okay, this is ability
to transcend time and space and
psychedelics pretty much just
turn up the volume on that. You
know, people have way more of
these psychic experiences,
paranormal like experiences,
Transpersonal experiences with
psychedelics. And I believe, you
know, a good proportion of those
are probably very genuine. Some
of them may be a bit delusional,
but some of them may be very
genuine. And I think the
evidence is moving towards that.
There hasn't been enough
research done on that, but we
have, you know, 1000s of years
of shamanic practice using
psychedelics and other states of
consciousness, which is for that
very purpose. And I think we
need to spend more time
listening and communicating with
indigenous peoples who have this
animistic, shamanistic world
view and what can be learned
from that. So I think we come to
this point where, you know, the
cork is out of the genus bottle.
Now the academy is once more
exploring psychedelics in a kind
of serious way. We can't deny
that the people are having a
large amount of these
Transpersonal and even
parapsychological, paranormal
like experiences, and we should
openly investigate them with an
open mind at face value, rather
than just trying to explain
Daniel Pinchbeck: them away. I
guess my understanding is that
psychic and paranormal effects
are extremely difficult to study
under normal, traditional
research methods. I've heard,
for instance, that even when an
effect seems to be demonstrated
at first with repeat
experiments, it seems that the
correlation goes down. It's
almost like the secret, you
know, there's a secret that
tries to protect itself or that
doesn't want to make itself
known to humanity at this point.
David Luke: Well, you can ask
Dean more about that. I think
there is a sense in which a lot
of the Parapsychology
experiments aren't immediately
repeatable, but when you stack
them together with meta
analyzes, you do find this kind
of highly significant data set.
When you take all the research
that's been done, you add it all
together, and these results are
kind of highly compelling. There
is a sense in which some of the
effects do reduce over time, but
they hit a plateau, you know. So
like the gansfield studies, have
remained a kind of 35% kind of
32% above chance, you know,
figure beyond this kind of
initial decline. So overall,
when you stack the data, the
effects are actually there, but
in a way, it's very hard to
learn much about them, largely
due to the complexity, I think,
of the factors involved. You
know, we're dealing with with
kind of turning a mirror on
consciousness itself, and it
becomes a very slippery
endeavor. It's like we the some
of the major problems are we
don't know where the psychic
abilities are coming from,
theoretically, because it could
always just be the experimenter
themselves are exerting their
psychic abilities, their
precognition, whatever it is, to
try and get the results they
need. And so all, I think we
need to take that very
seriously, because it applies to
the whole and scientific
endeavor. Like, for instance,
you know the Higgs boson, the
discovery. The CERN particle
accelerator, the way that
experiments set up, it's kind of
completely indistinguishable,
really in effect and size, from
the global consciousness
project, right? You have lots
and lots of people seemingly
coming together in a kind of
concerted, focused consciousness
trying to affect this kind of
random number generator. And in
global consciousness project,
and you get these hugely super
significant figures, right?
Whereas in the Higgs boson
experiments, you've got all
these physics coming together,
spending millions of pounds or
dollars, even, you know,
building this kind of massive
particle accelerator to try and
find something which they think
it exists, and all you get is a
probabilistic outcome, right,
that it exists and it's no more
significant than the global
consciousness project.
So I'm not sure where I was
gonna leave that point there.
Daniel Pinchbeck: What about you
know, you were talking about,
kind of the positive ecological
and psychological and
psychological effects of
psychedelics, then we have, you
know, I mean, it's almost
becomes, you know, certain ways
of discussing psychedelics have
now kind of, you know, forged
these kind of, like tracks in
the collective psyche, like, you
know, DMT, you know, like, if
you smoke at N DMT or have a
direct experience of it, the
experience is so incredibly
alien that, yeah, how do you how
do you know, what do you think
about that? Do you think there's
any evidence that suggests many
people talk about having a sense
of there being entities or, you
know, other dimensional
realities? I mean, is it just
the wiring of the brain being,
you know, totally reconnected,
or a switchboard shifted, or,
you know, is there any evidence
that there might be some, some
other, you know, sort of hyper
dimensional reality that we,
that we connect to in these
states?
David Luke: Well, I think the
question of DMT is, is super
interesting, and that one in
particular, because it's the one
most reliable at giving people
encounter experiences with with
some kind of sentient entity,
which they believe most of the
time to be some kind of real
encounter. There isn't been
enough research done on it, like
I say, for all the reasons
pointed out before that. You
know, the scientific endeavor
only looks to kind of bootstrap
its own belief systems by
researching things it can
explain with neuroscience,
right? So, you know, there
hasn't been much, oh, virtually
any research looking into the
nature of these DMT entities.
Most of the data is coming from
Psychonauts and and we see there
are certain commonalities, you
know, certain people tend to
encounter, you know, like the
elves for one, are quite common.
Or these kind of totally
dispassionate beings, which are
kind of doing some kind of neuro
anatomy experiments on people
and extracting their emotions.
That seems to be a pretty common
meme as well, but we can't ever
really separate out the cultural
influences, you know, in in kind
of examining this, this huge
data of phenomenology. But I
think there are commonalities,
and I think they need to be
explored, really, in a more kind
of concerted way. And what I
will say is, you know, some data
came out of Johns Hopkins this
year. Last year showed that of
people having entity encounter,
experiences with with DMT, of
those who were atheists prior to
their experience, less than half
of them were still atheist after
their experience. So they, you
know, that they're deeply,
profoundly world changing
experiences. We tend to lead
people to believe that there is
some kind of genuine other
there, and it's, you know, it's
going to be a tricky kind of
sticky wrestling match with
science to try and kind of bring
out any kind of empirical
validity on the ontology of
these beings, I think, but it's
worth the rest of
Daniel Pinchbeck: David, I know,
in the book on extraordinary
experience, you were also
talking about how you could
envision there being in the
future, some type of research
institute into into
consciousness itself. I mean,
that's something that really
fascinates me. And I think maybe
with everything that's
happening, and the sense of also
the ecological kind of doom
cloud up ahead, you know, maybe
it's time to accelerate that,
you know, and actually bring
that into manifestation. How
would you, how would you
construct such a thing? Do you
think it's possible that we
could, you know, have our kind
of Hogwarts, or, you know,
consciousness, you know, deep
diving, you know, what would
that consist of? What type of
research would you want to see
done?
David Luke: Yeah, I think I
totally can. Thanks for that
question, Daniel. And I think,
you know, we have to bring
together all the kind of
perspectives on it, you know, so
it can't just be a purely kind
science medical model led
endeavor, I think we need
psychiatrists and
psychotherapists and
psychopharmacologists for what
we can learn about, you know,
the brain and all that kind of
part of the jigsaw puzzle. But
we also need to bring people
from kind of wisdom traditions
in as well. So, you know, kind
of people from cultures like the
we Charlie, you know about 1000s
of years of shamanic practice
with we. Substances like Peyote
and and kind of really bring
these together in one kind of
melting pot, and also kind of
wisdom twisted relations, you
know, from from the East as
well. So I think that's what
they'd have to look like. And I
think moving forward, like, you
know, if Psilocybin and other
substances are going to get
licensed pretty much soon, for
for treatment, for depression
and so on and so forth. We're
going to need people who are
more savvy with the kind of
Transpersonal kind of
experiences that end of the
spectrum. Don't just mean
mystical experiences, but I mean
experiences of telepathy,
entity, encounters out of body,
experiences, all these kind of
things. People are going to have
to have some kind of better
understanding of these
experiences. And I don't think
we can leave that to
psychiatrists and
neuroscientists really, to kind
of just deal with, you know. And
I think people like shamans or
Tibetan Buddhist monks and
people like that need we all
need to sit around the table
together. So we need to kind of
a completely multi national,
multi disciplinary kind of
center where we can all share
ideas and exchange.
Daniel Pinchbeck: I was hoping,
I hoping he'll still pop up. But
one of the people I'd invited to
speak today, and who was on a
roster, Sergio Magana, who is a
nawadal Shaman, I don't know if
you know his work at all. He
works in the dream, you know,
kind of the dream, kind of
practices of the Aztecs. And he
wrote a book called The age of
the six son, where he kind of,
you know, cuz I written the book
on 2012 and then, you know,
people were like, Oh, the world
didn't end in 2012 and I was
like, Well, I never said it was
gonna end in 2012 you know. But
we're clearly in some type of
shift, you know, Sergio Magana
perspective, and obviously this
is not a scientifically
verifiable idea, is that we are
in a transition from the fifth
sun to the sixth Sun, which, in
the, you know, Mesoamerican
cosmology, is a shift from a son
of light to son of darkness. The
son of light, for them, is a
period of fascination with
material, technology,
rationality, science, logic. As
you move into the sun of
darkness, it becomes more of.
The psyche becomes more
predominant. The dream world
becomes more predominant.
Reality becomes more like a
waking dream. And I feel that I
find this a very fascinating
notion. I'm kind of curious how
it resonates with you. I also
kind of, in a way, correlate it
with the accelerating or, you
know, kind of popularity of
psychedelics, and a sense that
many more people are kind of
opening these doorways in
different ways right now, and
maybe that's somehow having a
kind of effect, you know, on the
collective psyche that's
happening in a way that you know
is unpredictable. I don't know
what your thoughts on that? I
just thought, and maybe
Christopher has some ideas on
that too.
David Luke: Yeah, I'll just jump
in. I would say, yeah. I mean,
for sure, this kind of revival
of psychedelic interest is going
to have an effect on the
collective consciousness,
certainly in the West, where it
seems to be happening first and
foremost. But, and I think, I
think it can only be a good
thing if we reconnect with this
kind of more dreamy, associative
kind of region of our brain, get
into the mythological and the
unconscious kind of side of
things, you know, as Ian
McGilchrist is has kind of very
neatly, kind of described in his
book
Daniel Pinchbeck: The Master
only in McGilchrist idea, for
those who don't know it.
David Luke: So you know the idea
of when it kind of takes a kind
of more poetic than literal
stance. But also, back to some
science on the nature of the
left brain and the right brain.
The left brain being the kind of
the literal, logical, linear,
linguistic kind of approach to
reality and experience, and the
right brain being more this kind
of dreamlike, associative,
mythological, you know,
endeavor, right? So, and that,
that we've confused the master
with the emissary, right? The
emissary is the left brain, the
bit that is all the
communicating, the mouth, you
know, the language, and we've
got to the point where the
emissary the left brain thinks
it's the master, you know, we
are kind of so heavily skewed
towards this kind of logical,
linear, linguistic mode of of
being in the developed world
that we've completely ignored
the dream Time, the imagination,
the associative thinking, the
mythological to our to our
peril, right? You know, it's
like, kind of our intelligence
has outstripped our wisdom in
many ways, and this is kind of
bringing us to this kind of
cataclysmic point, right, this
kind of moment of crisis. And so
we can it really help us, I
think, to flip that back over
and get these two things in
balance. And I think, yeah, I
think psychedelics have a big
role to play in that. And I
think also the internet and
things like that. The danger is
with the internet, though it's,
you can think of it as kind of
like the news sphere, and it's
kind of like a kind of
technological bootstrapping for
our own kind of clairvoyant
telepathic abilities, right? You
know, we can fake it till we
make it. With with kind of
telecommunications and the
internet, and then we've
probably come to realize that we
can do all that anyway,
hopefully. But meanwhile, we're
going to sifting through an
ocean of detritus, of
misinformation. I'll let Chris
jump in. Yeah.
Chris Bache: I think the analogy
that I use for this in Dark
Knight early dawn is the analogy
of the daytime sky and the
nighttime sky. We are like a
culture that basically head of
the rule that we have to be
behind closed doors by the time
the sun goes down, and we're not
allowed to get out until the sun
is up. So our entire known world
is from the nearby, close at
hand, brilliantly illuminated,
Sun soaked world, but think if
we were a culture like this,
we've missed the night sky. We
just don't see the far away, the
greater context, and so we don't
have we can't answer questions
of cosmology. We can't answer
questions of origin, because
this is the types of questions
that require the depth, which
are available only in the
deepest levels of consciousness,
where we can actually experience
the consciousness of the
universe, which we have come to,
which we are appreciating in the
physical world. But everything
which is physical has a
conscious dimension to it, and
so I think that this balancing
out seeing the nighttime sky of
consciousness really will have a
huge impact on a rebalancing of
our of our worldview.
Daniel Pinchbeck: David, I'm
curious also, what kind of, from
your research, you know, what
would you offer people in terms
of, you know, kind of practical
advice? I mean, do you think
it's kind of the right time for
people to explore these
alternative dimensions of
consciousness through
entheogens? Do you think there
are dangers in them? I guess
another, another question for
you, which could be part of the
same question, is there a Do you
Do you also recognize a dark
side for both of you actually in
psychedelic exploration, you
know? Yeah, so, so curious to
hear what you
David Luke: say, I'd say, you
know, I think it's down to the
individual to determine whether
it's right for them. I don't
necessarily think psychedelics
offer a map for everybody. I
think they can help a lot of
people in lots of different ways
and but they're not necessarily
suited to everybody. And, you
know, I could talk more about
that, but I think there are many
ways to get there. They can be a
kind of good door opener, you
know, they kind of just smash
the door right off its hinges
and show you the other side. Or
you could just kind of open it a
bit more gingerly, perhaps by
getting into your dreams, or
lucid dreaming, meditation,
yoga, practice, whatever it
might be. So there are the other
techniques to get you there as
well, which may be a bit more
controlled. But you know, in
this fast paced 21st Century
existence, a lot of people have
got themselves into a very
sticky rut for all kinds of
reasons, urbanization, 21st
Century, living, etc. I think
they can be a good Fast Track
door opener for many people. But
is there a dark side? I think
potentially, that there can be,
not just in how these things are
distributed or experienced, but
in terms of the experience. I
think that's where you're going
to, Daniel, in terms of the
experiences that people have, or
more about the kind of community
around the use of psychedelics,
are the
Daniel Pinchbeck: experiences
that people have, and even if
you know, they can have
negative, negative, positive
effects on people's character,
but are there cases where they
start to have a very negative
effect also, yeah.
David Luke: I mean, I certainly
can do and it's not all light.
And I think, you know, I think
you maybe have to look at it as
more of a process. I mean,
certainly from the clinical work
that's been done. You know, very
few people, a lot of people, may
have challenging experiences,
which, you know, they're very
difficult for them, but they
usually pass through them, and
those are the ones that
typically give, like, a lot of
insight, and that people feel
they grow more from, even though
it wasn't particularly pleasant.
And a very few people have, you
know, kind of somewhat in the
Division of traumatic
experiences and and regret doing
doing in the first place. So
maybe either there shouldn't be
taking psychedelics, or
psychedelics are not necessary
for them, or they started a
process which, which kind of a
process which, which threw up
too much stuff for them to be
able to immediately deal with. I
haven't really got a clear
answer for that, but you know
that there can be heavy, dark
experiences besides when you go
into the shadow, when you turn
up the volume on the mirror,
you're not necessarily always
going to like what you see in
there. So yeah, and also the
problems of spiritual bypass and
potential narcissism and things
like that which, which kind of
may arise as part of the
journey, but this is a part of
any kind of like journey of
personal or spiritual
development, and not just with
psychedelics, I would say, I'll
hand over to Chris.
Chris Bache: I completely agree
with you. That's David. That's
there are dark experiences that
serve. In these states, and
therefore you have to be well
prepared. You have to fasten
your seat belt, you have to
choose a very careful location
work with all all the safety
precautions. My experience has
been that all these dark
experiences are some form of
purification and clarification.
And in my experiences, I found
that the deepest breakthroughs
into ecstatic knowledge,
ecstatic knowing and visionary
knowing, came after the deepest
purification, dark experiences,
so that in my work, I actually
created the conditions that
would facilitate the deepest and
darkest encounters, not because
I was fond of suffering, but
because I was fond of what took
place on the other side, would
lay on the other side of that
suffering. But to do that, it's
really important to take
psychedelics in a very, very
carefully structured setting,
not in a recreational setting,
not casually, with a lot of
forethought and lot of
discipline preparation, not only
going into the session, but
coming out of the session, for
the integration process, for the
retention process, for the
encoding and eventually the
debrief after your session is
over, and a good, thorough
debrief is actually a very good
way to prevent problems that
emerge in your subsequent
sessions. So it's very
important,
Daniel Pinchbeck: I guess,
Christopher, or actually, for
both of you. Question for you
is, you know, what are, what are
things people can do to prepare
what's the best way to prepare
yourself for psychedelic
experience? I mean, how do you
approach these, these sessions?
For yourself.
Chris Bache: Well, in the
southwestern in the Hopi
Indians, they have a Kiva,
right? It's a hole in the ground
with a circle in the top, and
you climb down with a ladder,
and then they pull up the
ladder, and you're completely
isolated environment for the
duration of the entire
experience. And I always think
of my work with psychedelics.
I'm in a Kiva. I'm in a place
that's completely isolated,
protected. I'm with someone
who's going to take care of my
body. I'm not in a talking
relationship. I'm in an highly
internal, engaged relationship.
I want to have clean contact, so
I want to eliminate all outside
influences. Now it's wonderful
sometimes to take psychedelics
and go into nature, and that's a
wonderful experience. But when
you're going deep into this, in
facing the personal and
collective and historical shadow
that work is best done, I think
in isolation, I do a lot of
spiritual practice before and
after a session, I take care of
my body. I make sure my body is
well tuned and relaxed and
aligned before going into a
session. Because when you're
running in psychedelics, a very
high dose psychedelics, your
body is processing enormous
quantities of energy. It's very,
very demanding on your subtle
energy system. And if you
haven't been taking care of your
subtle energy system well before
your session, you're going to
have more complications arising.
So a lot of care for my body, a
lot of care for my subtle energy
system, a lot of spiritual
practice beforehand, and then a
very careful and sustained
debrief after, afterwards.
That's my approach. And David,
yeah.
David Luke: I mean, I guess it
depends on the your level of
experience, the context, what
you hope to get from the
experience. So, but always, you
know, if you're inexperienced,
do your homework. Make sure you
know what it is you're taking
all the kind of basics, you
know, dosage, substance, purity,
Where'd it come from? Do you
trust the source? Set and
setting. You know where you are,
psychologically, physically with
it, preparation and then
integration afterwards, as Chris
pointed out, but it needn't
necessarily always be a 600 my
deep dive increases process,
which is brilliant, but you
know, it could be, for instance,
we've experimented with 100 mile
low doses with top level
scientists for creative insight,
creative problem solving, on
technical problems, and that,
you know, they seem to be, which
is a completely different agenda
to a kind of completely deep
philosophical, spiritual
journey. And that kind of
produced really good results. So
it all really depends on the
context of use, but, but you
make sure you pay attention to
the context your intentions,
set, setting and substance
preparation and integration.
Daniel Pinchbeck: David, I know
that England, and particularly
the Imperial College, is now
kind of the center, in a sense,
of the sort of cutting edge of
psychedelic kind of research. I
wonder if you could tell people
kind of what's going on there
now, what's what's active, and
what types of discoveries are
being made.
David Luke: So I'm kind of
loosely affiliated to Imperial
College, the psychic research
center there. There haven't been
too much going on recently
because of lockdown. I think
they're beginning to is. Zoom,
kind of recruitment of
participants for various
studies, but some of it is
clinical. So they've been
looking at kind of Psilocybin
for depression as part of a kind
of a kind of global endeavor to
help get Psilocybin kind of
licensed as medicament for
treating depression. But also,
most of their focus is on the
kind of neuro scientific, the
neuro psychopharmacological
research. So how do these
substances work in the brain?
And more importantly, what does
it tell us about the nature of
consciousness, from what we can
discover about how these
substances work in the brain? So
some of the projects have been,
you know, the loss of neuro
imaging of MDMA, Psilocybin, LSD
and Dimethyltryptamine. I'm
working collaborating on the DMT
study. We're looking to do kind
of slow infusion, so taking
people into kind of high dose
breakthrough experiences over
extended periods of time, and
both exploring the neuroscience
connected to that, but also the
kind of the experience as well.
So what comes out of those
experiences? And one of the
things as a parapsychologist,
I'm looking to do with them
there is explore kind of shared
visionary experiences. For
instance, can we get two people
on DMT at the same time in a
kind of prolonged state, in kind
of side by side, by side, but
separated in different kind of
rooms, you know, so doing it at
the same time, and kind of look
at their brain activity, see if
there's any kind of correlation
which we wouldn't expect from if
they did it at different times,
but also in the kind of
experiences that people have, is
there some corollary of the
experience of two people may
have at the same time When, with
the intention of having a shared
journey. I mean, that takes us
into kind of some pretty far out
Transpersonal realms. But, uh,
yeah, that's just to kind of tip
the iceberg of the stuff that's
going on there. They're doing a
lot of really great research and
survey work too, and working
with retreat centers and all
sorts,
Daniel Pinchbeck: um, I'm
tempted to ask both of you just
It may sound like a funny
question, but it's always on
one's mind from your different
personal psychedelic
explorations, how do you what?
What's your philosophy on what
like the purpose of life is, and
the purpose of argument
experience?
David Luke: Nice, small
question, Chris, you want to go
first?
Chris Bache: Goodness? That's
that is a large one. Hey,
listen, the universe has been
unfolding for 13.7 or so billion
years. We don't see any evidence
that it's going to be stopping
for another 13 point 7 billion
years. So I think all of our
attempts to say what the purpose
of life is will always be
inadequate, given the enormity
of the actual project of life.
What we can see, what we can
project, what we can extrapolate
about the purpose may carry us a
certain distance, but it won't
take us through the entire
process. So to me, Central is
learning, loving, deeply
experiencing, opening, learning
and exploring and developing,
expanding our capacities.
Exploring, to me, exploring is
really important, the purpose,
one time within a deep encounter
with this creative intelligence,
this nameless, faceless
intelligence that I was engaging
and the topic of what the
purpose of existence is, what is
it all? And I was popping in and
out between non being or the
pure void and suddenly being.
And by popping back and forth
between being the universe and
non being the primal void out of
which the universe sprang. It
really generated a question,
what is the purpose of being?
What is the purpose of
existence? And this
consciousness said to me, have
we not learned anything? And it
just shattered me. I just broke
down and wept because and it
just seemed like it was all
about learning. I don't think
there's an idea often that this
consciousness is trying to learn
something about itself. I don't
think so so much that that
doesn't persuade me, but that
learning is central to the
entire project seems to be
really important.
Daniel Pinchbeck: Okay, David,
what you got for us?
David Luke: Not that much. I
mean, I guess the thing is, we
are, we are on a quest for
meaning, right? You know, what
is the meaning of the nature of
the universe is like? Well,
that's a human endeavor to
establish meaning. You know, I'm
not sure all species necessarily
try and try and find the
meaning, right? But we are kind
of lost in a way as well. You
know, where we are like? I think
our loss of meaning in a kind of
materialist, reductionist
universes has kind of led us
into all kinds of difficult
places. So I think the quest for
meaning in itself is worthwhile
endeavor, but ultimately it may
be not say meaning. This, but
pointless, because it might be
just about the being, as Chris
said, that is kind of really the
important thing.
But I'm a bit confused. What do
you think Angel?
Daniel Pinchbeck: That's good
question. I mean, I think, yeah,
learning, creativity,
expression, play. I don't think
there's a necessity to it. And I
do think, you know, meaning
itself is a human, created term,
you know, dreaming,
experiencing, creating,
discovering, loving, you know,
maybe multiple purposes. We had
a few questions about the value
of micro dosing, and I was
curious if you had a perspective
on do you see that as a really
helpful tool for people at this
point in time?
David Luke: I guess that might
be for me, because Chris seems
to be bit more in the macro
dosing can either end of the
spectrum. I think micro dosing
may have potential. I don't
think we have enough data yet. I
mean, certainly there's a lot of
kind of uncontrolled data, you
know, like kind of from non
placebo, randomized, controlled
studies from the scientific
perspective, saying that people
feel like it's really beneficial
for all kinds of things, for
depression, inside creativity,
all of that kind of stuff.
There's very little research to
say those experiences or that
kind of outcome may be genuine.
We don't know, right? It could
be one massive placebo effect.
But hey, if people think it's
beneficial, then then that's
might be good enough. I mean,
again, most of my research, I
focus more on low to high macro
dosing, right? So I think
there's potentially a room for
micro dosing. There's some
potentially dangers in it, and I
think, and that is, it's just
the kind of CO opting of
psychedelics as just kind of
mere psycho vitamins when they
can do so much more, right?
Fortunately, what I can gather
from the research is a lot most
people who microdose invariably
end up accidentally macro dosing
at some point, and you should
get a surprise, and that might
be beneficial.
Chris Bache: Yeah, I'll leave
that one in your hands, David,
because I personally don't have
a lot of experience with micro
dosing, because when I have
tried micro dosing with LSD, it
was after years and years of
working at these very high dose
levels. But basically I found
now that I really don't like LSD
in my body. It's like I drove it
so hard with these massive doses
for so many years that my body
developed kind of an allergy to
it, and so it's just not good
for me to use now, and I haven't
used it for years, so I don't
have much experience on micro
dosing. I read the literature,
and like you, there's a lot of
anecdotal, positive literature,
but there isn't as much
scientific, good, solid
literature on micro dosing. I'm
sure it's coming along. And like
you, I also think of that.
That's a good phrase. What was
it? Psychedelic, sort of psycho
micro pill, a vitamin pill. It
can do so much more.
Daniel Pinchbeck: Yeah, later on
in this session, we're going to
have a presentation for my
friend Andrew Camargo, who's
been working very heavily with
Santo Daime and the Ayahuasca
tradition for many, many years.
But I thought first, actually,
if he, if he's up for it, has he
disappeared on me. I was going
to see if Jeremy Johnson wanted
to give us a little bit of
insight into the integral model.
But he may have flown the coop
for a second. Daniel, there you
are. Jeremy. Okay, great. You
want to jump in and give us a 10
Minute kind of overview of
Gensler integral consciousness
model,
Unknown: sure, sure. Yes, yeah.
Thank you, Daniel. And just been
really enjoying today's
presentations already. So some
of you may already be familiar
with integral theory. I know
Rory has mentioned spiral
dynamics a number of times in
the context of like extinction,
rebellion and so on. But I think
when we're talking about the
history of consciousness, I
think a lot of this stuff can be
very abstract and very detached,
and we look at our own history,
our own living history, from the
distance of books, right? So
when it comes to Gene gebsters
work, he's sort of these
foundational thinkers of
integral theory and Ken Wilber,
but GEP sir is very, very
different from Wilber in the
sense that he's not a
developmentalist per se. And if
anyone has engaged with his his
writing. Writing on the topic,
his writing is deeply
phenomenological in that it's
always encouraging us to explore
and inquire our own experience
of consciousness. We've been
talking about the left and the
right brain with McGilchrist and
in many ways, GEP SIRs work is a
kind of if you want to jump in
and begin to explore the left
and the right brain in your own
phenomenology, then he's sort of
a good guidebook towards that.
Now, little bit of background
with me. I'm an integral scholar
and researcher. I've been
working with the gene gebster
Society for the past 10 years or
so, planning to get my PhD work.
Hopefully things go well at CIS
as well. So it's good to see
Christopher here and the PCC
program. So yeah, gepzer
presents us with a phenomenology
of consciousness, very carefully
looking at basically a kind of
an archeology of meaning making,
looking at particular works of
art, forms of literature, the
evolution of language and
etymology, the meaning of
certain words, and how, even in
our language, right, even in our
language has a kind of, how to
put it, a processual movement
from what we're talking about,
sort of night time or side real
dimensions of consciousness into
the waking and he very carefully
constructs a kind of descriptive
process in which human
consciousness has moved from
these side, real nighttime Magic
and mythical forms or structures
into waking apolonic, discerning
ratio oriented, as he says, um,
sort of the secular age, so to
speak. But there are gains and
losses in this, right. And I
think having a more nuanced and
non linear approach to this that
is also encouraging it,
encouraging us to explore these
modes of consciousness in
ourselves can really help us
make these things concrete
rather than abstract, and really
kind of come and become to live
the magic and the mythic again,
rather than to merely
acknowledge them right to live
in some capacity or have some
contact with these earlier modes
of consciousness. So for gepse,
the challenge in our time is not
so much to move to a next level
as to presentiate and to open up
the wealth and the history of
our consciousness, different
modes of time, cyclical forms of
time and participatory
cosmologies, bringing into
contact that with the more
rational and scientific and
secular modes of thinking. And
for gepse, the requirement for
that isn't just to bring those
modes of consciousness back, but
to sort of facilitate and enable
an equanimous and open enough
what he calls it is the
principle of diaphin 80, a clear
enough consciousness to allow
those different modes and
structures to presentiate
themselves in us and as a kind
of a too long didn't read micro
dose of geppser, the idea for
integral consciousness is an
intensification of clarity and
the capacity to bring forth
different modes of being in the
world and being in time,
including linear time,
timelessness, rhythmic time,
right? Cyclical cosmology, etc,
bringing all of those things
forward in the human being, to
bring them forward at will, as
if we were a kind of mercurial
being that was both a living
past and also, interestingly
enough, his theory of time.
We've been talking a little bit
about temporics and transcending
time and space. His theory of
integral consciousness, to me,
is very futuristic in a certain
way, because it's talking about
a way of being in the present,
in which the poetics of the
present is able to be both in
the deep past and in the future.
The future is latent in the
present as a tangible
experience, and there's a
poetics of presence that we can
engage in that allows that to
kind of come forward. Yeah,
somebody's mentioning Ancient
Future. This is what I'm writing
about in my next book called
fragments of an integral
futurism. Very much this idea
that a lot of the future looks a
lot like the past. And in some
ways a poetic statement of this,
because this is too short of a
presentation to really get into
the theoretical details. But a
poetic statement of this would
be when we do and ancestor work
right when we are able to listen
to the dead within us. This is
not an abstract thing. When we
are at our altars and we are
working with our ancestors, they
are present. GEP sir, was very
sensitive to that, and I think
his phenomenology of this
integral future is. The capacity
to listen to the unborn as well,
somehow that the the long dead
and the not yet born are present
in us, and not as just a
conceptual statement, but as a
living communion. Right? How can
we live like this in the present
and also, how can we embrace a
sense of the present, in which
past, present and future
intermingle with one another.
And by doing so, obviously, you
know, I think that would be a
wonderful tool to to, or mode of
being, an ontology to have right
now, right where the past,
present and future are
collapsing into one another,
right, just in terms of climate
change and the modes of thinking
that ecological thought require
of us. It's an intensification
of temporics. And I could get
into all this other stuff, but I
think that's Daniel. I think I
summed it up,
Daniel Pinchbeck: and we have
Jyoti is coming on in a minute.
She's only has a bit of time
today. But I did want to quickly
talk about the structures of
consciousness that Jepson
mentions, which I also talked
about in my book 2012 the return
of Quetzalcoatl. He has this
idea that there are these, I
guess. He identifies four
structures of consciousness, and
he talks about how each one
reaches a crisis in which the
only way forward is to go
through a kind of mutation or
transmutation, break into a new
structure of consciousness about
the the Aboriginal, the archaic,
the tribal, or in the mental
rational. And he kind of would
say that we are at the at the
end of this mental rational
structure with a particular way
of conceiving time and space,
and that we've reached a point
where the only way forward
requires a kind of mutational
break into a new form of
consciousness. Maybe you want
to, you know, kind of just, just
delve into that for a few
minutes, if you can sure, sure.
Unknown: So yes, the context in
which I read GEP sir about a
decade ago was he sets up his
book. And again, I was
interested in integral theory,
etc, and interested in cultural
evolution. But his whole, the
whole premise and thesis of that
book and his work, is that the
20th century, in the 21st
Century, he was a mid century
thinker. He was born in 1905 he
died in 1973 is that we are at a
civilizational juncture point.
There is tremendous
destabilization and
restructuration he lived
through, obviously, the first
half of the 20th century, seeing
that firsthand, he was a
European refugee, fleeing from
one country to another during
that time. But he posits this as
the end of what he calls the
mental, rational perspective
age, and the opening up of the
this integral structure of
consciousness. And he basically
said, Well, hey, look, I'm in
the middle of a transformation.
There's new arts, there's new
sciences, there's breakdowns of
different modes of being in the
world, right? There's a
civilizational collapse
happening at the same time
there's a civilizational
opening. So gepzer is a very key
thinker in this regard, in that
he both lived through and was
deeply sensitive and articulate
of exactly, in my opinion, some
of the deep themes that we're
learning to let go of in terms
of the mental world, right, the
perspective of world, the modes
of time, the relationship
between subject and object, and
Cartesianism is very much
related to the mental rational.
So again, like, if you want to
really cohere the the culture
that in some sense we are being,
we are helping to die, right? We
are help, we're assisting in its
death process. I think epster is
very helpful here, and that he
was a poet, and so he really
makes this something that we can
phenomenologically explore in
ourselves, in terms of our own
embodiment in relation to time
and space. But yes, there's,
there's a general overall
structure, just really quick,
archaic magic, mythic, mental,
integral. And each of these go
through these leaps, and I can
go into this.
Daniel Pinchbeck: Let's maybe
come back to that later and go
into that, because it's a really
great framing, also for thinking
about some of the subjects that
Christopher and David were
speaking about. Yeah.