Ehren Cruz: Before I welcome on
our first wonderful, esteemed
keynote presenter, I want to
leave a little quote from Albert
Hoffman after he had his great
first psychedelic experience,
the psychedelics gave me an
inner joy, an open mindedness, a
gratefulness, open eyes and an
internal sensitivity for the
miracles of creation. I think
that in human evolution has
never been as necessary to have
the substance of LSD, it is just
a tool to turn us into what
we're always supposed to be. Now
with that, I want to welcome
onto the stage here in just a
moment.
Dr Christopher Bache, who is
a professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at Youngstown
State University where he taught
for 33 years. He's also an
adjunct professor at the
California Institute of integral
studies, an emeritus fellow at
the Institute of Noetic
Sciences, is on the advisory
board of the Grof legacy
training. Chris's work explores
the philosophical implications
of Non-ordinary states of
consciousness, especially
psychedelic states. He's an
award winning teacher and
international speaker. Chris has
written four books, life cycles,
a study of reincarnation and
light of contemporary
consciousness, research dark
night, early dawn, a pioneering
work in psychedelic philosophy
and collective consciousness,
the living classroom, an
exploration of collective fields
of consciousness and teaching.
And of course, what many of you
might be familiar with today,
LSD, in the mind of the
universe, the story of his 20
year journey with LSD, everyone,
please welcome Dr Christopher
Bache, you
Chris Bache: what an honor to be
here with you today, to
celebrate bicycle with you
Today, an opportunity for the
psychedelic community to come
together, to see each other, to
reunite, make plans for the
future. Now, I know what you're
probably thinking. You look at
me and you think he doesn't look
like he's done a whole lot of
LSD, I think the divine designed
me as an undercover agent for
the psychedelic revolution. It's
amazing what you can get away
with at a university classroom.
If you look like an accountant,
I tell my students sometimes, if
I look like on the outside, like
I think on the inside, I would
probably look like Jerry Garcia.
So 82 years since bicycle day,
82 years, we've come a long way.
We've come up this Think of how
many people are doing
psychedelics regularly, 82 years
after Albert Hoffman's first
famous bicycle ride, and the
reasons we use psychedelics,
what draws us into psychedelics
and how we use them vary
enormously. I mean, if we were
to do an inventory of everyone
in this room, we would find so
many different approaches to
psychedelics, so many different
methodologies in using
psychedelics, and so many
different results coming out of
that, and the psychedelic
testimony of the community
together is always more
important than the psychedelic
testimony of any one individual,
because it's just so many
medicines, so many ways in which
it impacts human consciousness,
so many ways in which we can use
them to draw out the deeper
reserves of human consciousness
that always the collective is
more important than the work of
an individual. But what I like
to do, to sort of help seed our
awareness is sort of talk about
my work some and talk about some
of the potentials that lie, I
think, untapped so far in the
current psychedelic Renaissance.
The current psychedelic
Renaissance is focused
primarily, first on healing.
That's how we're getting
psychedelics back into the
academic discussion, back into
the intellectual discussion,
back into the mainstream is
demonstrating psychedelics
capacity to heal the wounds of
broken heart, to heal the wounds
of life, even to heal the wounds
of the soul, if it goes deeper.
And this is critically
important, and I understand all
the scientific brethren who are
working hard to document and
legitimate and to verify the
psychedelic the healing that
psychedelics can facilitate and
to refine our ability to
integrate them into our
psychedelic into our clinical
practice. Really, really, very
important. But for me, this is
kind of just like the first
stage, the first step into the
deep waters that psychedelics
make available. So. If you think
of the ocean of consciousness,
of consciousness as an ocean to
me healing or maybe using
psychedelics to augment
creativity, another separate
function, or to sort of generate
insights to go to psychedelic
states in order to gather
insights that one might use to
apply to one's life for changing
circumstances. When you have a
choice, I mean every time I have
an important choice, I mean a
big, important choice. I'm not
going to address that only in my
ordinary state of consciousness.
I will go into psychedelic space
to get to that little larger
expansion, a little more
dilation, a little more
communion, little more intake,
and bring my questions there and
then seek the guidance that I'm
asking for. And I follow the
advice I get there. I follow
that advice in terms of what
books I write next, where the
people are, where to go with the
research, healing, creativity,
enhancing creativity. I think of
my friend Alex gray and all the
psychedelic artists in the
movement insight, but these, to
me, collectively, are still only
in the shallow waters of the
ocean, near the shore, near
where we live in the personal
world. But then there is, what
if we go deeper? What if we use
our psychedelic protocols to go
deeper into the ocean of
consciousness, and we begin to
get into the area of spiritual
awakening? And I'm thinking, for
example, of the dialog between
the Zen Buddhist, between the
Buddhist community and the
psychedelic community that was
published years ago zig zag Zen,
which is the question of, are
psychedelics useful in the
facilitation of genuine
enlightenment, or are they a
hindrance, as classical
Buddhists would hold, Spiritual
Awakening, is different than
healing. It's different than
creativity, because here we're
using psychedelics to break into
the deeper universal themes of
human existence. Enlightenment
is not about personal healing.
You may go through personal
healing, of course, to move
there, but enlightenment is
talking is really grappling with
the fundamental human condition
at its core. What is the core
struggle that we are working
with here? What are the core
issues we're dealing with? What
is the nature of my identity
underneath, all the social
conditioning, all the all the
psychological conditioning
underneath, we feel that there's
something more authentic
underneath. What is that deeper
identity? Until eventually we
come to some type of realization
that the Hindus described as
Atman, the essence of the
individual, is Brahman, the
essence of the totality, the
essence of God Atman is Brahman,
awakening to just immersing
ourselves into seeing first and
then entering into communion
with the creative intelligence
of the universe that permeates
all things different than
healing, right, broad, deep,
Something which we share with
all of the human beings. Our
personal problems we may not
share with all human beings, but
the deep spiritual questions,
the deep seeking at that
underneath level we share with
all human beings. To me, though
healing, creativity, insight,
spiritual awakening, however you
conceptualize that, wherever you
imagine that is still only into
the sort of mid waters of the
ocean of consciousness. And what
I'd like to talk to you about
today is what I call
cosmological exploration, using
psychedelics in a manner, to
probe the deep structure of
reality at the deepest levels
possible, to see experience,
understand what is the
underlying structure of human
existence? What are the layers
of human existence? What is the
source of creativity, the
creativity that gave birth to
our universe, 13 point 7,
billion years ago, my
psychedelic journey began 45
years ago, when I was a brand
new academic, freshly minted out
of graduate school, beginning my
academic work, and I was a
pretty much an atheistically
inclined agnostic at the time.
That's what seven years of
graduate school in religious
studies made me and then I met
Stan Grof work. I met two
people's work my first year, Ian
Stevenson, whose work in
reincarnation, convinced me, in
one reading, that reincarnation
was a fact of life, just a
simple empirical fact of life.
Deal with it, you know. And
that's an academic that. Wasn't
part of my worldview at all in
all of my training. But then
secondly, more importantly, with
Stan Grof, I read his book
realms of the human unconscious,
which turned my life. It was a
major pivot point. And so I
began the psych of psychedelic,
therapeutically oriented work
that I knew would be required
for me to have access to the
kind of experiences that would
allow me to hopefully make some
kind of contribution to my
discipline, which is philosophy
of religion. So I started a
psychedelic practice, which,
after three medium dose sessions
ended up I ended up developing a
facility for working with high
doses of LSD and developing a
protocol following Stan Grof
protocol. And you know that you
know the drill, right? Total
isolation is not group therapy,
group work. Total isolation,
private, protected with a
sitter, carefully curated
playlist all day, engagement,
start to finish, long day, and I
chose to work with 500 to 600
micrograms of LSD. And I don't
recommend that protocol, truly
knowing what I know now, at the
end of that journey, I would do
it differently if I were
starting over again. I would
work with lower doses. I would
balance periodically, maybe
working with high doses of LSD,
with maybe intermediate sessions
of Psilocybin or Ayahuasca. And
I have experience with all those
psychedelics that I mentioned,
but my primary work has been
with LSD, so it may be it's
appropriate to speak to that on
bicycle Day, which we honor
here,
I chose to work in a Stan Grof
kind of paradigm protocol,
always in isolation, and take
these massive doses of
psychedelics I was taking about
doing it about on average five
times a year when I stepped back
and looked at it all. And it
ended up lasting 20 years. I
worked for four years, I stopped
for six years, and then I
resumed again for very intense
10 years. And over that 20 year
period was between when I was 30
and when I was 50 years old. So
I was kind of in the just
started my Saturn Return at 2930
my whole Saturn, second Saturn
cycle was all under my
psychedelic work. And then I
stopped when I was 50 years old,
and I didn't publish LSD in the
mind of the universe for another
20 years for a couple of
reasons. One is, if I published
that book as an academic, I
probably would have been fired,
because the good people of Ohio
where I was teaching don't like
their university professors
doing massive doses of LSD on
the weekend. So I had to kind of
all my work was secret. None of
my students ever knew what I was
doing. My faculty, my close
friends on the campus, knew what
I was doing, but they didn't
really know. They didn't
understand it. We didn't go into
those conversations. It would
usually start, yeah, I remember
I did some psychedelics back in
the day. Yeah, good. Good for
you. But when you're doing 506
100 micrograms, amplified by the
intensification of the most
powerful music that I could pull
down from the world stage of
music, and just drive it
completely hard, you just
Shatter your mind. You shatter
consciousness. You just blow it
all apart, which is a dangerous
undertaking unless you're really
prepared and you really have
your seat belt fastened tight,
and you have a strong support
system and good clinical
grounding, and you have a pretty
solid sense of self, it's not
wise to blow yourself apart that
often. But I found I had a
capacity. And astrologically,
it's in my chart. I have a
capacity to get open, spacious,
Neptune, opening up into deep
states. And then I have a I
congeal, easily. I congeal,
well, so the opening and the
expanding, I could manage. And
then I found, over the first few
years that I had the capacity to
navigate this domain, and I
developed an interest in working
this hard, because what
interested me was not the
clinical applications. It wasn't
the creative applications. What
interested me was the capacity
of LSD to take me into states
where I could truly enter into
the communion with the
intelligence of the universe,
and then that intelligence would
teach me, just like we all have
that experience, right? You open
up, you go deep, you open into
this larger field. So you clean
up your house working, and you
gotta clean up this and clean up
that. But when you're clean,
when you get out and you take in
this larger it speaks to you. It
teaches you. I've often wished
that I had advanced degrees in
quantum physics and astronomy,
quantum astronomy, because if I
had, I would have been able to
understand so much more of what
it was teaching to me. But I had
my background was in Philosophy
and Religious Studies, so it
took me into those areas that I
was most interested in, which is
to understand the paradoxes of
the human condition. Why is it
so hard here? Why is human
existence so hard? Why is there
so much suffering? Why are we so
estranged from our deepest
connection to the universe?
What? Where is reincarnation?
Since I took that into my
psychedelic Where is
reincarnation taking humanity?
Where are we going? Because
reincarnation lifts time off of
our restricted does time ceases
to be a restriction once you
understand that we're
reincarnating. When
reincarnating, we're
reincarnating. There's no place
to go after you leave here, you
come back, you leave here, you
come back and you begin to open
up a time horizon which is
beginning to understand, perhaps
the time horizon that the divine
thinks in. Because the divine
does not think in small term
projects, and the divine does
not think in personal projects
itself. It thinks in large
projects and species projects
and planetary projects. It
thinks in galactic size
projects. So the challenge
becomes, how do we let ourselves
begin to think experience in
galactic size projects? And if
you and the first is to unlock
the barrier of linear time, to
let yourself go beyond the
confines of this process, this
particular moment, as
magnificent as it is, as
beautiful as it is. And this, of
course, is where the divine
lives is in the present moment.
So a lot of spiritual practices
focus on deepening, deepening
experience of the present. But
in psychedelic work, there is a
potential to transcend the
limits of the present, and when
you step outside of linear time
and enter into what I call deep
time, that there are many
dimensions of time in the
universe. There are many levels
of time. There are many
different modalities in which
the universe experiences itself
through the medium of time, and
it will take you into these
deep, vast expanses where you
can experience 100,000 years. In
the course of an hour, you can
experience an acceleration of
time that takes you beyond your
personal story into humanity's
story, beyond your personal
growth into humanity's growth,
into the larger evolution that
the divine intent is working to
seed and nourish and bring
forward in the human community.
Where are we going as a
collective? Sri Aurobindo, the
great Hindu sage, Oxford
educated Hindu sage, I always
think that's interesting. That's
a story. He had said, humanity
is a transitional species. We're
not stable. We're transitioning
from what we were before Homo
sapiens to what's coming. Yet
everything's in motion. Galaxies
are in motion. Earth systems are
in motion. Humanity is in
motion. Where are we going?
What's it going to look like?
The I have to watch my time
here.
I want to inject a cautionary
note. I'm so happy that we're
really spending a lot of time.
We're doing a lot of writing,
and books are being authored on
integration, the importance of
integration, because breaking
out now we have these powerful
chemicals. We can break out of
time, our time space suit,
increasingly easily. But to do
it in a way which is valuable,
to do it the way which we can
bring back something that we can
keep that's actually a harder
part of the work, isn't it, to
bring it in first, to remember
it, because we can go so deep we
can't remember what we
experienced. You have to train
yourself to remember the. Deep
experience is if you go into the
deep waters, into the deep
waters of the ocean, if you go
far beyond personal identity,
even far beyond human identity,
into archetypal reality, into
causal levels of reality, and
into what I call the diamond
Luminosity reality, or what
Buddhism calls Dharmakaya, the
clear light of absolute reality.
You go deep into that, you come
back, it's hard to remember what
your experience was. You have to
train yourself to remember those
experiences. The first step of
integration is to remember. But
my experience was that if you go
back systematically in a cleanly
defined, clearly defined
therapeutic context, the first
time you touch a new level of
reality, I would not always be
able to bring it all back, but
if I went back again and again
and again to that level of
reality, I would begin to be
able to see it more, understand
more. There were fewer gaps in
my session notes, it became
clear. I learned how to bring it
back, and I found that this
pattern repeated itself every
time, when I would break into a
yet another deeper level of
reality. First, there would be
the kind of chaos and the
uncertainty and but then with
repetition, I could hold on to
more of it. I would bring it
back. I would bring it in. The
second reason I took so long to
write diamonds from Heaven is
not just because I was afraid of
losing my job. And I like
teaching. I like my job. I like
being with students. The second
reason is it took a long time.
It takes a long time to digest
and understand what our
experiences are, because a long
history of psychedelic
experiences, a long journey of
psychedelic work, is very
different than just having one
or two or three interesting
sessions on a Saturday
afternoon. And I think some of
our expectations of psychedelics
have been shaped by a literary
tradition around it, which is
based upon very few psychedelic
experiences. Aldous Huxley wrote
his wonderful book, The Doors of
Perception, after only one
experience and you wrote a
beautiful book on one
experience. When Huston Smith,
the great don of Religious
Studies, wrote his book,
cleansing the doors of
perception, where he collected
all of his essays on
psychedelics he had taken LSD
only six times. He stopped, then
he said, because the bummer
seemed to increase and it wasn't
as useful to him and to me,
that's when it starts to get
interesting. When the bummers
increase, that means there's
some deep purification taking
place. Something's coming
forward that's going to be hard
for you to deal with. That's
when it gets interesting. Or
Michael Pollan, when he wrote
his very important book on very
important contribution to
psychedelic community, he had
only taken psychedelics a
handful of times. And this tends
to create a set of expectations,
and I think a very short sighted
set of expectations about what
can happen in a psychedelic
journey and a psychedelic
regimen. But if you go through a
long journey, at least in my
experience, it's not just you're
always starting from the same
spot and getting to the same
level and having experiences at
that level. To me, one goes
through a series of death and
rebirth processes, and the death
of rebirth is a cycle as you go
deeper and deeper and deeper
into the universe, as deep as
one your medicine has the
capacity to carry you. Not all
medicines have the same capacity
to carry you as deeply. Okay,
that's fine. Your capacity to
withstand the chaos that's
inherent in deep psychedelic
exploration and the tightness of
your protocol, whether your
protocol is really designed to
holding you in a very carefully
contained container, a Kiva to
support you while you go deep in
and then come back out,
integrate and then internalize.
When I was at the end of my
journey and working up my notes
in order to write the book, I
identified five basic levels at
which I had worked over the
course of time. The first is
personal mind, the level of
personal mind, psychodynamic
territory. The second is the
level of collective mind, the
collective psyche, Carl Jung's
territory, but more than Carl
Jung's territory. Third Level
archetypal mind, which is, in my
context, a. That platonic sense
of archetypes, not the Jungian
sense of archetypes, but the
Platonic sense of archetypes, is
a domain of reality that lies
beyond human species, beyond the
species mind, in a way, just as
in the personal level, your
egoic mind has to fall away for
you to open up into the deeper,
richer experience in the
collective mind, to get into
archetypal reality, the entire
collective mind of humanity has
to fall away from you. You
literally lose all of your human
roots. You lose all of the
background, subtle textures of
human consciousness, all the
assumptions of human history, of
the assumptions of human
cognition, drop away and you
enter into a reality of
archetypes, into the reality of
the living beings who are
responsible for creating space
and time, who are responsible
creating some of the four
fundamental core themes of space
and time. But beyond archetypal
reality, more cycles of death
and rebirth, entering into
causal reality, where the
signature feature of causal
reality is permeating oneness,
total total oneness. Oneness has
so many permutations, so many
iterations, but in deep causal
reality, the experiencing of
life, free of all dualities,
radical transparency, radical
selflessness, no self here, no
self. There, no self anywhere in
nature, the entire world, as
Plotinus says, lives and
breathes as one, us, ants,
archetypes, all of us living and
breathing as one, to sink into
that oneness, to the
intelligence which is the
intelligence underneath it all,
the intelligence that is shaping
us, driving us, teaching us,
expanding us, holding us
accountable in our rigorous
learning that time and space
does, and taking us somewhere,
somewhere deeper, somewhere
richer, somewhere more
satisfying and then beyond,
calls a love reality. For me,
the last five years of my work
were spent exploring what I came
to call the diamond Luminosity,
more death and rebirth, entering
into states of luminous clarity,
hyper, hyper, hyper, hyper,
Clear, clear, clear, clear,
beyond imagination, I began to
understand better what the
Buddhist meant when they say
touching it once undos 1000s of
years of karma, because the
hyper clarity is just once I
touched that I wasn't interested
in Anything else that I had been
exploring I'd been 15 years
exploring all these other levels
I talked about, but that reality
is so profound and so rich, it's
the only thing I was interested
in was getting back to that
reality. And I got to that
reality in the last five years
of my work and 26 sessions,
which is an entire third of my
journey. I got to that reality
only four four times, four times
out of 26 sessions. A lot of
work being done in those 26
sessions and other things, but
only touching that reality four
times. And they are, for me, the
true diamonds from heaven.
Subtitle of the book,
caution, you can go deeper in
the universe, and is wise for
you to go. You can go. You can
have too much God. That seems
like an oxymoron, right? Because
you all it's better to have more
of God, but at least in this
temporary this method which
gives us temporary access and
then brings us back temporary
access and bring us back, I
think at least it's been my
experience, and even though I
paid a lot of attention to
integration, all the way through
physical integration, subtle
energy integration, emotional
integration, social integration.
Even though I had taken all
those precautions, I found in
the end that I had gone so deep
into Transcendence, I had gone
so deep into the subtle,
luminous body of the Divine that
I lost my interest in living
inside time and space. Time and
space just began to feel kind of
like paper mache when you know
that this reality is not as real
as that reality that is more
real. Than this reality I lost.
I didn't lose my bearings. I was
doing my job, taking care of my
family, and doing all the stuff
that I ordinarily do, but I
found that I was just in my
heart. I was waiting to die so I
could go back, because I reached
a point in my work where I knew
I had to stop for reasons I
talked about in the book, 73
sessions. If you're not cooked
by 73 sessions, forget it. 74 is
not going to give it to you. I
was cooked. I was overcooked. I
was waiting to die. I knew that
I would not do any more deep,
deep work. And to go deep, it
takes years and years. It's like
training an Olympic athlete. You
don't run out and break the
takes years to develop the
momentum, the psychic momentum,
to be able to get back into this
territory. I could not get back
into the territory today, now
that I've stopped this work 20
plus years, I could not get back
into the territory I was
exploring at the end, no matter
how heavy a dose of LSD I took
today, it takes time to be able
to develop the momentum to move
there. So I reached a point
where I knew I had to stop. It
was time to stop, and I knew I
would not get back into this
reality until I died. This is
one of the differences, maybe,
between using psychedelics for
spiritual awakening, where the
goal is to be a goal is to
consume all one's karmic
fixations and all one's blocks
until one can enter into the
transparent condition and enter
into the deep communion with the
eternal dimension of existence
as it courses through this
present moment right here, a
noble goal and the spiritual
masters have always been my
guides on my journey. This is
seven different to enter into so
deep into deep time where you're
dealing with the evolutionary
story of humanity, so deep into
the light which is the source
from which the Big Bang
exploded. When I stopped my
sessions after I stopped my
sessions to took me about 10
years to sort of reground myself
in being committed to living out
the rest of my life inside time
and space. And when I say that,
I don't mean that I was, I was
totally functional in the world.
I was doing all the things I
would have to do, but in terms
of recommitting myself to living
in the imminent divine, instead
of immersing myself in the
transcendent divine, it took me
10 years to kind of recommit
myself until I could be
comfortable living in the
imminent divine, and That's why
a word of caution, you can't go
too deep. You can't go deeper
than is good for you. You can go
deeper than is good for your
family, the people who depend on
you. Where is reincarnation
taking us? I've talked about the
sort of large trajectory. Where
is reincarnation taking us.
There was a point in my sessions
where, and again, I haven't had,
you know, I've always envious of
people who have teachers, lots
of teachers. I mean, I think
that's great. That's really
important. I don't have lots of
teachers. I've only had one
teacher, and that's the
universe. That's the
consciousness of the universe
itself, that's been my only
teacher, and it's been rigorous
teacher. I mean, beat me up,
break me down, crush me, love
me, bring me back to life
multiple times, only one
teacher. And so there was this
one particular day where the
teacher seemed to be interested
in showing me where
reincarnation was taking us. And
I experienced all of my former
lives beginning to come back
into me, fast and furious. I
mean, I had done past life
therapy, had a sense of my
history, but this was larger.
They were all coming back very
quickly. And there was like
wrapping kite string around a
kite spool. His lives were
coming back. And eventually
there reached a time where they
fused. They seemed to fuse into
one. And with that fusion, there
was an explosion of energy that
just exploded inside my chest,
and it was my first deep contact
with diamond light, and I call
this, I was catapulted into a
state of consciousness where I
was an individual. It wasn't
like losing all boundaries and
entering into oneness. I was an
individual. But I was an
individual beyond any frame of
reference I'd ever known before,
and I came to understand that
this is where reincarnation is
taking all of us, every one of
us, we reincarnate, we die, we
come back. We die, we get big
into the soul, we come back into
our incarnate life. We die. We
get big into the soul. We come
back. And if we keep this up, if
we keep this rhythm up of
expansion, contraction,
expansion and contraction, and
keep it up hundreds of 1000s of
years, we keep it up, expanding,
contracting, dying, being born,
dying and being born sooner or
later. Doesn't it make sense,
sooner or later, that the entire
totality of our lives, which we
meet, when we die, when we
return to our total soul, that
that totality of integrated
historical experience would
incarnate eventually inside time
and space. And that's what's
happening, I think, with the
birth of the diamond soul, we
are giving birth to the next
form of human consciousness. And
the next form of human
consciousness is a human being
whose mind is the repository and
the integrated into a
singularity of all the
experiences he or she they have
ever had in all of their lives.
And now they look at the world
and they know they're not this.
They know they're not 100 year
old being they know that their
relationships are steeped in age
and steeped in time. They know
that their life projects are
steeped in 1000s of years of
practice, not 100 years. I don't
think we can continue to run
this planet on the basis of
egoic consciousness, the egoic
consciousness, and I think ego
is a beautiful thing. I'm not
going to bad mouth ego,
individual consciousness is a
magnificent, beautiful,
potentiating, empowering thing.
But left to its own devices,
it's also tends to be cut off
from each other, cut off from
the earth. We've created a
civilization based upon the
psychological limitations and
assets of egoic consciousness,
and right now this civilization
is generating problems of a
magnitude which I don't think
can be solved operating out of
egoic consciousness. We
literally can no longer afford
the luxury of being children on
this planet. We have to grow up.
And growing up, I think, means
owning ourselves, owning our
histories, owning our former
lives, owning the Destiny that's
carrying us through time,
arching through time, taking us
into not our plan for the human
future,
but some I call it the divine.
I'm not always comfortable with
that word, because, you know,
it's been sullied by our world's
religions. But the creative
intelligence the universe, the
creative intelligence that's
taking us into billions and
billions and billions of years
more still to come, which we
have not seen. Personally, I
think we are entering a time of
history of profound challenges.
The challenges we're facing are
not simply political and social
challenges. So they're there.
They're not simply ecological
challenges. So that's going to
be coming more and more and more
and more powerful as we move
forward deeper into the 21st
century. At core, all of these
simple all of these challenges,
I think, are symptoms of a
challenge of consciousness, we
literally do not know who we
are. We don't know what we are.
All we have to do is look at the
White House to see that we do
not know who we are. We do not
know what we are, and we cannot
afford to run on this incomplete
knowledge any longer. The
universe is taking us into a
profound death and rebirth
process, which in many ways will
be very similar to the death and
rebirth process that we have
seen mystics go through when
they enter the dark night of the
soul, a time of intense
purification, purification,
purification until their
natural, spontaneous, spiritual
nature shines free, just as
happens in psychedelic sessions
when we go through those very
dark sessions, which are just
turgid and they're painful and
they're difficult, but you
embrace it and you just take it
down to the bottom. Into you go
through the death process, and
then you're spun into clarity,
kindness, compassion,
understanding, wisdom. I think
the entire planet is going into
a Death-Rebirth process, and
that's why, ever since my book
dark night, early dawn, I talk
about the dark night of our
collective soul, the
purification of our collective
psyche, purification of our
collective institutions. We are
going into a period which, just
as in a psychedelic session, we
lose control. We're losing
control of all the things we
could have thought we could
assume about culture and
civilization. We're losing
control of the ordinary
assumptions of life. We're going
to be facing challenges
unprecedented. The oceans are
rising. You know that? You know
the scenarios you don't I don't
have to repeat them, just coming
at us very fast. Cities going
underwater, mass migrations. Eco
ego, migrant migrants, not that
eco migrants.
We're entering into the time of
the great undoing, just as in a
psychedelic session or on a
meditation cushion, you have to
face the deepest fears, the
deepest anger, the deepest
terrors, in order to melt into
the truer condition, into the
lasting condition, into the true
peace that satisfies the inner
longing. Our culture is going to
do that. I have no idea how it's
going to do it, but in my
sessions, I have seen it. I've
experienced it in deep time, a
period of profound trauma, of
profound uncertainty and a deep
unraveling of the human
community. And yet my
experience, at least, is that we
make it through this. We come
through it. We don't survive it.
We die and we come through a
change transformed that in this
international crisis, we go
through a process and experience
that just breaks open the human
heart and oneness is born in the
human family, concentrated in
some individuals subtly
pervasive for the collective as
a whole, the theme of oneness,
the theme of compassion, the
theme that makes all our
intelligence and all our
discoveries safe. We will stop
using them for war. We will stop
using them for destruction. We
will start using all of our
talents to serve the common
good. I think the global crisis
that we're going into is
synergistically coupled to the
psycho spiritual process that we
are going through in the birth
of the diamond soul and as we
experience our perpetual
transformation taking place in
our psychedelic sessions. That
is, the world is trying to
become one. We cannot solve our
problems within the world of
nation states. Just as the world
is trying to become one, the
soul is trying to become one.
There's an inner wholeness here.
We are trying to become our
deepest self, our deep soul
self, just as the world is
trying to become one, and
there's a synergistic coupling
that I think that as the world
transitions into and through
this crisis, the world is
composed of souls. And souls are
not 100 year old things. Souls
are 100,000 year old things. And
the means that the humanity
that's going into this crisis is
a humanity of 100,000 year old
beings. And personally, I'd
rather go into a global crisis
with 100,000 year old beings
than I would with 100 year old
beings, because we have the
knowledge, we have all the
knowledge, we have the capacity,
it's within us. This is one of
the most exciting centuries you
could possibly be alive in. I
think the changes by the end of
the 21st century and beyond, we
will be living in a very
different world than the world
we're living in now, I don't
know how long it will take us to
make this, navigate this, I
think at least three
generations, maybe more. This is
not something which is going to
be accomplished quickly and
easily. And I'd like to end the.
By reminding ourselves of the
power of psychedelics to
profoundly impact one of the
scariest things that human
beings go through in this life
is dying. My wife of 25 years,
Christina, died a month ago, six
weeks ago. She had cancer. She,
like me, was a Psychonaut. She
had extensive experience of
spiritual reality, and this
completely changed her death and
my experience of her death, she
was not afraid of dying. She
knew where she was going. She
had had first hand experience
where she was going. And that
changes death from a sort of
crushing experience of defeat or
fear and uncertainty into a
celebration of a life well
lived, a life that was brought
to rich fruition conclusion, and
therefore, knowing that she was
returning home into the arms of
the Beloved, she was returning
home to The Great Mother which
had given birth to her. There's
no fear here. There's joy and
celebration. And this is the way
it's supposed to be. This is
what the Center for conscious,
living and dying is helping
bring about in the community
here. This is what death really
is. Death is the celebration.
Death, you should mourn children
who are being born, they're
beginning the hard work. Death,
you're graduating, you're going
back home, right? Psychedelics.
Christina had a lot of
psychedelic experience, it did
not psychedelics were not part
of her active dying process. It
was already done beforehand. She
took what she had learned into
her dying and therefore engaged
death differently than other
people might engage death. If
there were one thing I wish I
could take out of all the
psychedelic work I'd done for
all those years, if there were
one thing I wish I could just
reach into my heart and give it
to people, it would be, please
lose your fear of death. If
you're afraid of dying, you have
your cosmology all upside down.
Death is returning to the world
of plenty, the world of
fullness, the world of light,
the world of super intelligence,
the world of understanding, the
world of infinite compassion.
Being born in Asheville, maybe
not so much. We have to work
hard here. We have to work hard
there. We receive the rewards of
the work that we've done, what a
revolution, 82 years since that
bicycle ride, and we're just
getting started. Aaron said,
we're just getting started. We
are just in baby steps. If we
look forward to 15 years, if we
look forward to 50 years, if we
look forward to 100 years, just
imagine, if we handle this
transition well, if we harness
the energy of psychedelics,
conscientiously, responsibly,
wisely, then we can affect, we
can accelerate this generational
change that we're trying, that I
think nature And the divine
intelligence is trying to bring
about in the human family, and
we are all part of this
revolutionary transition. Simply
by being here, we are
acknowledging that we are part
of this revolutionary
transition. Thank you very much.
You
Ehren Cruz: thank you so much,
everybody, please. Dr
Christopher Bache, applause.
Just taking a moment to just
honor this man's profound
courage. You know, as I shared
before, the mental health the
healing dynamic is the on road
to our reintegration of
psychedelics into our culture,
into our community, and very
much an important on road for
many reasons, but as he has
shared the exploration to
consciousness, into our
connection, to our spirituality
and to our cosmology, there is a
frontier. There a profound
frontier that maybe many of the
ancients might have been aware
of as well, that we are re
stepping into. So let's carry
that in our hearts as we are now
expressions. Of this possibility
we are active members in this
great learning that has been
tasked to us. How do we take
these medicines and grow and
learn beyond the self into a
collective, into a holistic
being?
Unknown: Thank you for watching
and please remember to like this
video and to subscribe to our
channel
Ehren Cruz: for more information
or to make a donation towards
our cause, please visit our
website at.