Unknown: Automatically out
there.
Ehren Cruz: All right,
everybody, we're gonna get go
ahead and get started here.
First and foremost is everybody
here. Everybody hear me, okay,
across the back here doing well,
okay, beautiful. Well, thank you
all so much for coming to
tonight's fireside chat on Sky
Mountain. We have our wonderful
guests here today that will be
speaking, Dr Raymond Turpin, Dr
Christopher Bache. We'll give a
little bit more into them, but
first and foremost, want to give
a big thank you to Melissa and
Joe summerage for letting us
stay at this lovely facility
here to have our talk tonight.
It's such an incredible venue in
and of itself. Thank you so much
for this opportunity here a
couple of housekeeping items,
tart too. There are bathrooms
straight back by the stairs.
There anybody who needs to use
the restroom. Also water
stations over there with hot and
cold water. If anybody needs to
stand up, stretch around. You
know, please feel free to do so.
We'll ask that. You know,
welcome to take pictures and
such. But we are taking a formal
video, which we will release
through the psychedelic Society
website, so if you guys can
refrain from some video, we'll
make sure that we make that
available to everyone. And I'd
like to introduce myself and a
couple of the co founders of
psychedelic society and a little
bit about what we're about here.
My name is Aaron Cruz. I'm a
psychedelic ceremonial
facilitator. I've been working
with Sacramento anthonyogenics
for 15 years, professional
certified coach, third wave
psychedelic certified coach,
anthropologist by trade and and
also, I have a couple of other
wonderful co facilitators, and
also founders of psychedelic
society, of Sarah saleecks Over
here, Levine, Dan Cao over here.
In the back, Daniel Polk, the
original founder who instigated
this whole amazing group here
together, and several community
members who have been a part of
this experience. I see some new
faces here, but many have been a
part of this for now, going on
over a little bit, over a year,
and kind of to just kind of
break things up and thank you,
Chris for this great idea. How
many of you are new to
psychedelics in general? Nude of
psychedelics. Okay, awesome. How
many of you have been kind of on
your own journey with
psychedelics, kind of growing
and emerging that maybe the last
few years, starting to get some
steam and momentum? There any
tenured Psychonauts and deep
divers out here. Okay, plenty of
hands. Excellent. Now, how many
of you guys work within the
mental health field? Just
curious there. Okay, awesome.
And let's see. Let's talk about
some specifics here. Favorable
to Psilocybin. How many people
are Psilocybin. Is your medicine
there? Excellent. LSD, okay, see
several hands going up several
times. Respect MDMA and how
about DMT or Ayahuasca?
Beautiful. Okay. Well, welcome
everybody. This is our tribe.
Before we kind of go into things
here, I'd like to kind of set
the stage with a little bit of
our mission. Of our mission, our
vision, and the ethics that we
represent. Then we'll kind of
dive into the deeper
conversation here. So a mission
of psychedelic Society of
Asheville is to educate,
advocate and create community
around the healing and
transformational power of
psychedelics. Now our vision we
provide support, resources and a
safe container for those seeking
guidance and healing, spiritual
growth and personal development,
through psychedelics, we serve
to foster the development of an
informed culture that respects
indigenous lineage, scientific
research, harm reduction,
principles, ethics and personal
responsibility in the
intentional use and facilitation
of psychedelic medicine for
ethics, These containers that we
strive for provide physical
safety. Just you guys know it's
very important that consent is
the highest priority, both in
what you choose to share, how
you choose to share that, and
how you choose to express and
experience touch and connection.
Psychological safety, of course,
is actually critical importance
as well. What we share here is
to be honored within the
confines of this space, unless
someone gives you a direct word
to take their their truth and
sail it outward. Otherwise,
please honor the respect of
someone's own discretion when
they're sharing with you in this
space transparency. Speak from
the authentic eye. Speak from
your own place of value and
honor those of others as well
diversity, equity and inclusion.
You know, we really strive to
make sure that there is a
balanced representation of
gender, balanced representation
of culture and also for people
how they self identify. And we
are on a quest to continue to
make this a more welcoming and
inviting place for all aspects
and walks of life. So if you see
people that are. Are represented
and curious about this
particular type of work. Please
welcome them in and love to make
them feel that this is a home
for however you identify, this
is a place for you, and we we
love and we're richer for it.
And self care is also incredibly
important to us. So do what you
need to do to feel healthy and
hail that means, you know,
stretching, taking a moment, you
know, all those things are very,
very important, and want to make
sure that you have the space to
shake the body well. So with
that there, we're going to kind
of dive into a few more things.
But first, you know what? Let's
go ahead and do a land
acknowledgement. We are on
Cherokee chilagi First Nation
land out here. And in the deep
time of our work in psychedelics
and deep time of our work in
stewardship of this planet, we
really lean into and learn from
the wisdom of our ancestors. So
I want to take a moment just to
acknowledge that this is sacred
land and that we are gifted with
the opportunity to be stewards
and caretakers of this space,
and may we uphold the virtues
and values they have brought
before us and carry that
forward. So let's give a couple
moments to honor the chilagi
Cherokee, First Nation.
All right, now on to the talk
here. So we are really grateful
to have two amazing gentlemen
here. I know Dr Turpin doesn't
maybe describe himself as an
elder yet, but you are an elder.
De merge, sir, you've made it.
Congratulations. So we you know
these two individuals have done
so much for the community, for
psychedelics at large, not just,
you know, in this particular
region, but in the larger
movement. So I'm going to go and
introduce the them both. You two
here for some basic bios, and
then we'll get into some
questions here for them. So Dr
Bache and November 24 1979
Christopher and Bache took the
first step of what would become
a life changing journey. Drawing
from his training as a
philosopher of religion, Bache
set out to explore his mind and
the mind of the universe as
deeply and systematically as
possible, with the help of
psychedelic drug, LSD, following
protocols established by the
great Stanislav Grof Beijing. 73
high dose LSD sessions over the
course of 20 years drew him into
a deep in communion with cosmic
consciousness. Christopher Bache
is a professor emeritus in the
Department of Philosophy and
Religious Studies at young town
State University, adjunct
faculty at the California
Institute of integral studies,
Emeritus fellow at the Institute
of Noetic Sciences and on the
Advisory Council of the Grof
legacy training. Please welcome
Dr Christopher Bache. The Dr
Turpin has been studying the
therapeutic use of psychedelics
in the relevant literature since
the mid 80s, hoping to
eventually legally use these
medicines in psychology practice
specializing in the treatment of
trauma. Dr perpen Turpin has
extensive experience with
children, adolescents and
families in a multitude of
settings, but has focused his
practice on older adolescents
and adults in recent years, Dr
Turpin earned a bachelors degree
in psychology at the University
of Georgia in 88 his master's
degree in psychology from the
humanistic psychology program at
West Georgia College in 1990 and
his doctoral degree in clinical
psychology from the California
Institute of integral studies in
San Francisco, CIS 1999 in 2017
he earned a certificate in
psychedelic therapy and research
from CIS, in addition to his
private psychotherapy practice
in Waynesville, North Carolina.
Dr Turpin was a mentor for the
2022 23 CIS certificate program
and be lead mentor as well, and
a training mentor in 2324 and
he's one of the co founders of
the pearl psychedelic Institute
here in Waynesville. Everyone,
please welcome Dr children.
All right, so let's dive into
where this all began. So prior
to your first formal experience,
what first turned you guys on to
psychedelics? What was it about
these compounds that initially
piqued your interest and then
sparked engagement?
Raymond Turpin: I would have to
go back to probably 1980 early
84 probably when I was finishing
up my freshman year at the
University of Georgia, and just
kind of actually into the
summer, and I discovered
flashbacks, which was Timothy
Leary's autobiography. He was
still alive at the time, and I
read that, and, you know, I
already knew kind of who he was,
and I was just stunned by the
guy's brilliance in his writing
and his insight. And he wrote a
good bit about Psilocybin and
LSD in that book, and then, much
to my parents chagrin, all the
way to Mississippi at
Thanksgiving, I was in the
backseat chattering about
Timothy Leary, and my dad was
not real excited about that. He
was a little conservative. And
so it wasn't until October of 84
where I. I managed to score some
mushrooms with two of my good
friends that I'd grown up with,
and we migrated out to the
cemetery outside in Athens,
Georgia, which that sounds
creepy, but this was a place we
would kind of go and walk around
and just fascinated reading the
gravestones and putting stories
together. It was kind of a
sacred place to us. And so went
out there, found a little field
laid down by the creek, and I
was laying there, and I had this
intense vision of just seeing
myself. At the time, I was an
advertising major. I'd grown up
in Atlanta, had gone to this
prep school with a lot of old
Atlanta money, and my family was
definitely kind of middle class,
and so I felt like I was a dirt
farmer. And so when I got out of
high school, I thought it was
all about making money, so I
figured, kind of creative, I'll
do the advertising thing. And
during this Psilocybin
experience, which was quite
profound, it just kind of I saw
myself succeeding in this field
and feeling extremely empty
about it. And there was almost a
voice in my head saying, What
are you doing? You're going to
convince people to buy a bunch
of crap they don't need. What
are you doing? And I said, What
am I doing? And then I started
figuring out where this is
coming from. This This wasn't in
the mushrooms. This was
unlocking a part of myself that
had kind of been socialized out
over the last few years, and it
seemed to be more of my true
self. So I got fascinated with
that. And then started going to
the UGA library and pulling off
old bound journals and finding
all the old LSD research,
particularly from the 50s and
the 60s, and realizing what all
was being done with these
compounds back then, and they
were doing some pretty amazing
studies, and some people that
had some pretty refractory
problems were getting well, and
then the fact that it had all
been buried astounded me. And so
I just kind of decided to devote
my life back then to continuing
to study these things,
continuing to research them,
personally and academically, and
hopefully be in a position one
day to be able to use these
things legally. So that's kind
of how it all got started. And
then the Grateful Dead was a big
piece of it. Once I went to my
first dead show Halloween, 1985
that locked me into a whole
nother level of psychedelics and
using it somewhat
ritualistically in large crowds.
So that was another big shaper
of my experiences growing up.
Unknown: Awesome. Yeah, get more
there. Too.
Raymond Turpin: Grateful, dead.
I'm afraid did not ever have a
significant impact on my life in
that respect, but I know I
respect, I was just out of
graduate school, had gone, had
been given the opportunity for a
high quality classical Ivy
League education. I was a pre
confirmed atheistically inclined
agnostic when I finished my
degree in religious studies and
philosophy of religion, and I
met the work of Stan Grof. Let
me back up Saturn Return, just
come out of my Saturn Return,
just begun my teaching career.
The first year of my teaching
career, looking around what to
do, I found Stan's book, realms
of the human unconscious, and he
lit the fire. And I knew that
this was really important to my
discipline, philosophy of
religion. And I knew the only
way to really work, this was not
intellectually and conceptually,
but you had to do the work. You
had to get into it and do the
work. This is 1978 and the work
was illegal at that point, so I
decided to be illegal, and I'm
not an illegal person by nature,
but I decided to sort of do my
academic work, and to do this
work with the idea that sooner
or later, somewhere down the
road I would be able to harvest
it as a philosopher of religion,
to bring it forward for its
cosmic, logical and
philosophical import. I wasn't
primarily interested in
therapeutic healing, though. A
lot of healing came. I wasn't I
started with an interest in
spiritual awakening, kind of
accelerating my spiritual
awakening, but that kind of got
knocked out within the first
couple of years, when the
journey took me in a different
way. After about three sessions,
I always worked in a Grof Ian
protocol, right shades, lying
down, headphones, eye shades.
I've never tripped in a
classical way. I've always done
therapeutically focused, intense
work. And as you know, if you've
done this work, it amplifies the
intensity of the experience many
times. And I think now that we
have the world's collection of
music available to us, and we
can contour our sessions with
that music, it just deepens it
even further. I made a choice
very early on, not to work
therapeutically or not to work
with other people, not to
introduce people into this a
very different responsibility, a
different set of
responsibilities. I always
worked solo, and I was concerned
just to push the boundaries as
far as I could go. This seemed
like a wonderful opportunity for
a philosopher to actually get
first hand experience of some of
the things that some of the
great sages and mystics and had
been talking about. And so
that's. What I did, I jumped in.
I followed a protocol of working
after the first few sessions at
high doses of LSD, 500 to 600
micrograms. I aimed always at
600 but I lower it to 500 just
in case. Some of the stuff I was
using wasn't completely pure,
though it was all pharmaceutical
grade. I do not recommend this
protocol, this is, this is not a
layman's protocol. When you work
at those doses, if that
consistently over 20 years, it
takes you places that are
extremely demanding. They
require a great deal of
discipline. They require a great
deal of spiritual practice to
stabilize and hold on to those
experiences and to work with
them. Yeah, that's, that's how I
got into it.
Ehren Cruz: Wow, yep, 500 Okay,
well, so you guys started
getting the momentum, you had
the impetus early on to kind of
follow that trail, you know, for
you, Dr Turpin, you know the
kind of medicine redirected you,
or kind of brought you into a
different landscape in your
life, and and you had really
kind of set off on this trail
through inspiration for Dr sand
Grof, so can you speak to me
about a particular time period,
maybe a parent dime shifting
moment for you, when you're
working With the medicine that
really just opened up you into a
new spate of awareness. And I
know you had many of those
expressed in your particular
book. There about maybe where
you had felt that this
particular trail, or this path,
it just led you into a different
level of how your devotion to
this work kind of expanded at
that particular time, from from
that experience,
Raymond Turpin: going go ahead.
I can't say any one particular
period or one particular time,
because it true one of the let
me ask for how many people have
read my book? LSD, in the mind
of the universe, that's why.
Okay, good. So I can start some
thoughts from scratch. For the
majority, working in this very
intense fashion. Over 20 years,
there were so many levels of
consciousness that I broke
through, or that the universe
took me through that I can't
point to any one time period as
a kind of culmination of that
period. I just kept at it, and
it kept taking me through level
after level after level of that
process. And I learned, I
learned that you have to learn
how to work with these states. I
mean, they're really complicated
to work with states if you're
dealing with states at the
personal level, that's kind of
one level of complexity. If
you're dealing with states at
the collective psyche level,
that's another level of
complexity. If you're pushing
beyond that into archetypal,
into causal, and transcending
time and space and going into
the deep territory of history,
that I learned requires a
tremendous amount of discipline
to stabilize and to stay
conscious at levels of
consciousness that usually when
you first go into them, it just
it takes your mind right out.
It's hard to hold on to them. It
was the length of the journey
and going through so many
stages, I guess if I were to
point to any one point, no, I'm
not going to point to any one
point. There's too many stages
going through it. There was one
period of the work when we were
experiencing, I think it was the
Neptune Uranus conjunction. And
it was squaring my lunar nodes,
if you're into astrology, it was
a square all year long. And that
particular year, which I think
was around 1993 94 just was
ripped open the level. And it it
opened up a new level. But that
wasn't the last level. That was
just a new level at that time,
but it was a, it was
extraordinarily productive
level. But the deeper level, the
last five years of my working
was what I call the diamond
Luminosity, and I'll just
mention that when I hit the
diamond Luminosity material,
once I touched that realm, I
wasn't interested in any of the
other realms that I had access
getting up to that level,
because the Power and intensity
of that domain was so extra
ordinary and it was so
attractive and so overwhelming
that for the last five years of
my work, that was the only thing
I was interested in getting back
to. But in those five years and
26 sessions, in those five
years, I only got to that
dimension four times, okay, and
that wasn't because, that was
because the cycle involves so
much intense purification in
order to get back into that
territory, than to absorb that
territory. And going through
anyway, I'm getting off on it,
but off track. But yeah, I guess
the diamond Luminosity would
constitute, in some ways, a
major. Turning point for me in
that material.
I'm afraid my story is a little
more terrestrial than yours.
Yeah, first of all, I am. I'm
honored to be on the stage with
this guy here. His book was
incredible, and it meant a lot
to me. When I did read it, I
felt like I was reading almost
like holy texts or something
kind of coming from, like the
king acid head or something, and
the fact that he's still intact
psychologically and emotionally
and everything was really
comforting to me when I finally
got to meet him. But yeah, I'm
kind of like Chris. I can't
really point to an experience
that really was a profound that
stands out more than some of the
others. I just know that, you
know, when I made this decision
back in the mid 80s that I
wanted to change my major to
psychology and work with people
doing this work, and devote my
life, really, to studying
psychedelics, there was no
support. I remember, I went to
the head of the UGA psychology
department, and he was like,
don't waste your time doing
this. This has all been tried.
It's not coming back. And almost
everybody I went to was not very
encouraging about it at Georgia,
which was kind of a conservative
I love the school, but it was
kind of a conservative
psychology department, so I
didn't get much encouragement
there, but I did find out about
West Georgia College, which was
at the time, was a humanistic
psychology program that had been
founded in 1968 and Carlton,
which there's not much going on
in Carlton, Georgia, but I got
out there and there was a guy,
Mike Aarons, who had actually
done some work with creativity,
and LSD back in the 60s. And
that's where we got to meet Stan
crippner. Stan Grof came and did
a talk there. So it was kind of
this deepening and and then
that's what led me to California
Institute of integral studies,
which, at the time was pretty
fringe. It wasn't even APA
accredited. My parents were
completely freaked out. I wanted
to go there and get my
doctorate. They're like, how are
you ever going to get a job? And
I said, I really don't care at
this point. I want to learn what
they're teaching and then I'll
figure it out afterwards. So I'm
not going there to worrying too
much about that. But then I
guess just kind of to kind of
answer your question. I think
there was just so many times of
doubt along the way where I was
worried that I was doing
something that was not going to
maybe, you know, work out for
me, you know, just times where
everybody gets doubts, and then
there was just always something
that would show up that would
reassure me and just kind of say
you're on this path, and it's
important that you stay on this
path. And I think another lesson
I learned very early on with
psychedelics, and I think this
also works as a psychotherapist
too, is maintaining how
important it is to maintain
humility when you're working
with these compounds. I can
remember when I was a therapist,
you know, somebody come in and
we'd have a great session, and
I'd be like, Man, I got this
shit. I'm gonna be like, I'm
Freud. Man, I'm going to be the
next Freud. I got this stuff.
And then about the next day,
somebody would come in
collapsing and talk about how,
you know how terrible they were
doing. Then I'd feel like the
worst therapist ever, and I
didn't know what I was doing.
And so I learned the hard way to
kind of find the middle ground
there. And I think psychedelics
did the same thing. It does not.
It wouldn't allow you to get too
down, and it wouldn't allow you
to get too high on yourself. I
always found that it would just
if I was getting a little high
about something, it would knock
me down. And if I was getting a
little low about something, it
would kind of bring me back to
that middle place. So I think it
was important to just trust that
what felt like the direction I
needed to go in is what I needed
to honor. And I think that's
kind of what was happening along
the way, is just having various
meeting people at particular
times, having particular
experiences that would just kind
of deepen that whole path and
just allow me to just kind of
continue to go on and feel good
about it. I think that's kind of
how it how it happened.
Ehren Cruz: Yeah, I love that.
For both of you too, the
catalyst of the psychedelic you
know, in and of itself, you know
those moments, although they can
be profound, it seems like the
context of your life, how you
synthesize that, how that
encouraged you forward. What you
learned over the larger spectrum
is the real lesson. Is the real
teaching that came through and
and so you guys, for large part
of your careers, you're working
in what was be considered the
dark ages of psychedelics
between, you know, the mid 1970s
through 2016 there's a complete
moratorium on research. You
know, it was pretty much
ostracized to the far reaches of
academia and culturally outside
of the Grateful Dead and a few
courageous other, you know,
keepers of the of the culture.
There was very, very little kind
of happening at that particular
time. So I guess what encouraged
you, you spoke a little bit
toward this, what encouraged you
to kind of continue on that path
where 360 around you, you know
people weren't lifting that up
or supporting you in that and
and the fulfillment of that
particular profession. And also,
were there any kind of prominent
mentors over this period of
time, either that you met, or
perhaps that you were learning
from their work extensively, and
how did that influence your
trajectory as you continue to
move on throughout your life?
Raymond Turpin: Yeah, take it
away. Try to remember all that.
Yeah, I would say, you know, the
thing that probably kept. Me
going more than anything, was
the fact that, you know, I was
learning about conventional
psychology and psychotherapy
techniques at Georgia, and then
later on, and there was just
when, when I was reading the Old
research, there was just
something so unique about the
way that they were working with
mental illness back then, and
that they were using LSD, and it
was a rough treatment. I mean,
people were reliving their fit
their traumas, and so there was
a real need to have safety and
trust with your therapist.
Unlike MDMA is nice because it
shuts down that amygdala, and so
you don't have that fight or
flight response. But when you're
taking LSD to do trauma work or
Psilocybin, it's not working on
the amygdala like that. So
there's a lot of anxiety and
trepidation and fear that can
come up when you're doing that
work and and just noticing the
development of psychiatric
medications, and the fact that
our whole drive was about
symptomology and trying to
mitigate symptoms so that people
could get out and function, that
was really what the with, what
the what the point was, and just
realizing that we weren't
getting At the core stuff. And
that reading that old LSD
research, you know, showed that
we were getting at that core
stuff, and there were these
profound changes taking place.
There was also a lot of
criticism about the research
back in the 50s and 60s, because
it didn't really cotton very
well with the old double blind
science routine study design.
Because, you know, when you got
a placebo and a psychedelic? You
know, within an hour who got the
psychedelic and who got the
placebo? So there was a lot of
criticism about it not being
able to be studied
scientifically. And then there
were some study designs back
then that I think were flawed,
of course, because people didn't
know what they were dealing
with. They were trying this
stuff for the first time. But I
would say probably the people
that really influenced me was
Stan Grof to just still a
brilliant guy. When I read
realms of the human unconscious,
it was, it was a shattering book
for me, just realizing that this
guy was going deeper than
anybody at the time. And and
then when I got the CIS one of
the reasons I went out there was
that Stan was teaching Ralph
Metzner was out there and, you
know, and then just San
Francisco, I got to see the dead
like 12 times a year without
leaving the Bay Area. So that
was always, that was kind of
another attraction out there.
But, you know, I think Jerry
Garcia was another influence of
mine. He wasn't a scientist or a
therapist or anything, but he
took a lot of psychedelics, and
he communicated what he learned
from psychedelics through his
music and and his art, his
guitar playing was everything
that's all he was about, was
expressing through that. And
then he ended up falling in with
these other guys that had the
same commitment and the same
pathway to exploring music and
the deep psyche. And so going to
their shows was something that
always, I would go to their
shows, and they would always
teach me something, or I would
just get reaffirmed that this,
this was this mattered, this
stuff mattered, and it was going
to matter and it was worth
sticking with. So and again, I
think when I read Chris's book,
I thought that was really
fabulous, because I just
thought, I'd always thought,
wow, what would happen if you
just took all the acid you could
and just went as deep as deep as
possible, what would you find?
It seems like there's this
endless well of something down
in there as you go, or out there
and and so when I found his
book, like I said, I was
astounded that somebody had
actually done that and been able
to bring back all that knowledge
about what you experienced was
profound. So, yeah, I've had a
number of teachers, I think
again, Mike Aarons. He was out
at West Georgia. A couple of
West Georgia alumni here, Steve
and David, those guys remember
Mike Aarons. And I think he was
probably pretty important to you
guys too. He was kind of the
soul of that whole program. And
he really kept it humanistic and
very different he didn't worry
about APA accreditation or
anything. Was about people going
in there and learning what he
felt like. It was important not
only to be a good therapist, but
to grow as a human being too.
And so that was really, that was
really important. So yeah,
you know, Stan was huge
influence, because he's such a
powerful intellect, and he had
done 20 years of research before
he wrote realms of the human
unconscious, and I could
recognize the caliber of his
scholarship. And he taught me,
just by reading him. He taught
me some essential things, but I
think the most important thing
he taught me was to absolutely
trust the consciousness of the
universe, to trust the process,
to allow yourself to go into
unknown territory, to allow
yourself to be sliced and diced
and broken down, no matter how
bad, no matter how inscrutable
it is if you're working in a
safe and contained environment,
surrender completely to that
environment, and it'll always
catch you in the end. You'll die
100 times, but it'll catch you
in the end, and it'll embrace
you. And that was a that was the
most and I don't think I would
have had the courage to go some
of the places I ended up going
if I hadn't known that Stan had
been there. First, and he had
survived the to tell about it,
outside of that and Stan, of
course, and I became friends and
colleagues, and he wrote the
forward to dark and early dawn
for me and and brought me to
some of the ITA meetings, where
we had wonderful encounters with
the different people, but I
never had outside of this
intellectual starting point. I
never I always am envious of
people who do Ayahuasca work and
they say, Well, I had this
shaman mentor for 10 years that
I worked with, and this other
person I worked with for another
10 years, and that's just not my
story at all. I've never had a
mentor like that. All of my
mentoring came directly from the
universe itself, which has some
advantages and has some
disadvantages, you know, but I
did not learn anything from
anybody. I mean, intellectually.
But this, we're not talking
intellect. We're talking about,
you know, dissolving into the
Soul of the Universe, dissolving
into the consciousness that that
created the universe. About that
process, I never had anyone to
help me, and it was just a
continuous conversation, but
then a communion, and then
dissolving deeper and deeper
into that, that consciousness,
that power, which is the
illuminating consciousness and
the origin, originating
consciousness of all existence,
coming back, scribbling it down,
trying to make sense of it, and
then digesting the larger
overall journey. And when I was
doing it, like you said, it was,
there was no one doing it. I
mean, I couldn't really talk. I
mean, my friends in the
department knew what I was
doing, but they didn't really
know what I was doing, and I
could never I didn't bring it to
campus. I didn't bring it to my
students. I couldn't teach out
of it, which became a real
problem down the road. Because
I'm a talker, I love to learn
and share, but I could not share
this. I couldn't talk about it.
Wasn't allowed to be part of the
curriculum, even though I did
teach courses in psychedelic
therapy, and I did teach courses
and seminars on Stan's work and
whatnot, I always had to hold my
own personal work back, and it
wasn't until I really set after
I retired and I saved writing
LSD in the Mind of the universe,
or my title for that book is
diamonds from heaven. LSD, in
the mind of the universe is the
publisher's title. My title is
diamonds from heaven. I did not
even try to attempt that until
after I was retired, until I was
after the statute of
limitations, and I knew that
neither the state of Ohio
couldn't fire me and the federal
government couldn't come after
me. But that is not the way it's
supposed to be. Is it?
Indigenous cultures? You come
out of a deep experience, first
thing you do is you share it
with the elders. Because first
of all, it's not your private
vision, necessarily. It's not
necessarily about your private
life. It's about the life of
your tribe. It's about the
larger life, and so the elders
are your first people to share
it with. But in my world, there
were no elders and there was no
sharing. And so it involved a
very long process of holding and
just holding and digesting this
material, personally,
individually, sharing it with my
wife and very small circle, but
it really had to be contained in
that way, and that's not
something I would wish on
anybody. And I'm very glad that
we're coming to a point in
history where no one else has to
go through that, that we can we
have enclaves of people you can
share and process this work,
because I think it's really
important to share and process
this work together and to draw
from other people's experience,
and to have to be able to say
out loud what are probably, for
many of us the deepest
experiences of our life. Yeah, I
think talking about the
indigenous cultures, I mean, one
of the reasons that they used
them so successfully for 1000s
of years, in some cases, is
because they had a framework for
respecting and valuing these
types of experiences, and they
also had a cultural blueprint
for when people came back about
how to integrate and understand
what they had experienced and
learned, and they were able to
do these things safely and
productively for 1000s of years.
And I think one of the issues
with our culture is that we were
up against, even in the 60s,
that there was no framework for
understanding or acceptable way
to use these things. We were all
criminals by taking them in and
of themselves. And so I do think
that's a role everybody has
right now. We're still very
early in this renaissance
period, and I think everybody
has a responsibility to learn
about these substances and how
to use them responsibly and
safely, and also be freely
teaching other people that are
curious about how to use it. So
I think that's a responsibility
all of us have here.
Ehren Cruz: I. Yeah, thank you
guys so much for sharing that.
You know, as part of my own
personal work, I got people
through high dose Psilocybin
experiences as a harm
reductionist, and it's deep and
it's profound, and in many ways,
you know, I feel as much as a
facilitator to doula at times,
and how the nature of our
reorientation and your own
perspective can be that paradigm
shifting that you have to re
acclimate yourself to how you
engage with family and friends
and and what that means to you
now you can't unknow what you
know you know. So with that new
imprint and within you, you have
to kind of set sail into a new
trajectory. So that support
structure is so, so critical and
and in that and then that
consideration there, I think two
things I wanted to ask you,
specifically, Chris, is, you
know, how first were you able
to, you know, how did that
impact your family, your you
know, your father, you have, you
know, a wife, and your wife at
the time that was supporting you
there. And, you know, have a new
partnership now, and all those
things that have transpired,
know, how were you able to kind
of endure in that, in that time
period there and and, yeah,
we'll stop for that one right
now and then have a kind of
follow up to that. But you know
what was? What was your
practice? Essentially, to be
able to do
Raymond Turpin: that, first, I
had a couple of strategic
advantages. I had a PhD in
philosophy in religious studies
and philosophy of religion, and
so I had the opportunity to
study theology and the history
of mysticism and mystical
traditions. I studied Eastern
and Western traditions. I taught
in both traditions. I taught in
Eastern traditions. I taught
courses in comparative
mysticism. So I really, I really
spend a lot of time with the
great masters and psychedelic
experience and great master
contemplative experience. These
are two different genres of
experience. Okay, psychedelic
experience is temporary. You
have to deal with the
temporaryness of it from the
very beginning. You have to use
those hours as productively as
you can. But you also have to
deal with the fact that you are
going into this elevated state,
and then you're coming back out
of it. Then you sit and absorb
and then you're going into it
again, and you're coming back
out of it. Contemplative
practice is different. There is
a fluctuation in and out, but
it's a much more of a you get to
hold on to more of what you
break into, and the psychedelic
state is not like that. And so
the process of stabilizing,
keeping yourself grounded in the
world, and absorbing this and
holding the position is really
important, especially if you're
working with a psychedelic. A
powerful psychedelic, says
pushing boundaries and breaking
structures and taking you in
places that, relatively
speaking, very few people have
gone, and certainly very few in
the academic community, if any,
have gone. So you don't have any
of that type of intellectual
support for it. You know When
Jung went on his deep episode
and of when he broke with Freud,
and he went into this tremendous
self explore, exploration, and
he faces tremendous being
overwhelmed by the content
flooding up from his psyche. He
said what grounded him was his
family and his work. And he
would say to himself every day,
sometimes, this is this is who I
am, this is where I live. These
are the people I live with.
These are my family. These are
my children. And I think that's
really true for me. It was
family. We had children, raising
children, and it was my
students. It was that wherever I
was on Saturday, on Tuesday,
Monday or Tuesday, I was back in
the classroom. I was teaching my
classes. The other thing that
was really important for me, for
stabilizing is to have I had a
sustained spiritual practice,
that a meditative practice. My
partner at the time, Carl, was a
serious meditator, contemplative
practitioner, and that was very
grounding. It was to know the
lives of the great masters, and
they were my role models for
what could be achieved, and to
use them as my role model and to
commit myself to a daily
practice that allowed me to
absorb not only intellectually
or consciously, but to absorb in
my body, to absorb the subtle
energy. The shifts in subtle
energy that psychedelics
activate, because you know, when
you states of consciousness are
states of body. So when you
enter extremely deep states of
consciousness your body, you're
asking your body to go into
extremely state, deep states of
consciousness, of states of
body. And when you enter very,
very pure states of awareness,
your body goes through intense
detoxification processes, which
continue long after the session
is over. So I had the
opportunity to understand. That
within the mystical tradition,
so that it gave me an
opportunity, it gave me a
knowledge that I use to ground
myself in the world. But I think
to me, it was the commitment of
of career, the commitment of
teaching in my students and the
equipment, and the commitment of
working with my children and my
family. I Right? Yeah.
Ehren Cruz: Thank you so much
for sharing that. And you know
that's that's so important to
recognize, is the immersive
quality of the psychedelic you
get that deep, profound
experience, but as it then
starts to subside, then that's
where the practice really, truly
begins. You know, how do we
synthesize that into life.
Choose actions, choose holistic
praise, to allow that to become
part of our walk of you know, to
sustain and support those
revelations through through life
changes and healthy, healthy
living wellness.
Raymond Turpin: After I stopped
my sessions in the very end
stages, one of the things
consciousness told me, and it
was important to me at the time
was there is the dying of
discovery, and we know what
that's about. But then there's
the dying of keeping. The dying
of keeping is different than the
dying of discovery. It's what
it's what you do when you come
back, so that you can hold on to
these experiences in some
meaningful way and integrate
them into your life in some
meaningful way.
Ehren Cruz: Thank you. Chris, so
Dr Turpin, I have a little bit
of a different angle here for
you. So, so it's no no secret
that your accomplished
psychedelic professional, you
know what you've been able to
attain with the pearl
psychedelic Institute, which is
only one of two facilities right
now that are approved for
expanded access trials and MDMA
and treatment for PTSD. And you
recently had someone move
through one of those trials. And
I just want to go ahead and give
a round of applause for the
incredible amount of work just
to do that get it to this level.
Lot of lot of hearts, lot of
hands that have had that happen
there. But one of the things
that I think you've been able to
accomplish is you hold both of
these different traditions. One
is the extremely diligent,
therapeutic professional lane
that has to be every i dotted,
every T crossed, to really
solidify that particular track
and simultaneously, on the other
hand, as you had alluded to
several times, is your deep love
for Grateful Dead and the
ecstatic tradition that other,
that other frontier that is, you
know, perhaps all encompasses a
little bit more wild west, but
does have a lot of power of
community, in some ways, I
think, has had more influence on
culture than any ceremony or
therapeutic the frontier of this
particular tradition. So I want
to get a sense of what your
thoughts are on the importance
of both of these particular
pathways, and take your time
with this. I know there's a lot
going on there importance of
both these particular pathways,
and then how you feel that they
can both be held, not as you
know, this grateful that is the
ugly step child of psychedelic
you know, use. But how can we
embrace both these pathways and
the importance of them,
furthering this renaissance,
furthering this culture?
Raymond Turpin: Good question. I
think it's doable. I think it's
necessary. Yeah, I think, you
know, the medical model that
we're kind of all kind of well,
that we're kind of pursuing
right now, it gets a bad rap
from a lot of folks. And when
you look back historically, 50s
and 60s, early 70s, when
psychedelic research was
happening, you know, it was old
white guys, they were all doing
it. There wasn't people of color
involved, and it was this very
kind of stodgy sciency thing,
guys in white lab coats, even
for a while there and and so I
think that there's some
criticism, some of it is
appropriate, that you know, that
you know, if we just keep this
to be the province of doctors,
that we're going to miss out on
a big piece of what we're trying
to accomplish here. And I think
Albert Hoffman even said,
Whatever you do, don't leave
this only in the hand of the
doctors. This is right before he
passed away, and but I think
that there's a couple of things
to think about. I think that the
way our culture is set up, I
honestly feel like the way that
we are going to finally get to
maybe get one of these schedule
one psychedelics across the
finish line, towards approval,
is going to have to be through
this medical model. It's going
to have to show that it may be
successfully treats mental
illness and other issues that
maybe we're not so successfully
treating right now. And so I do
feel like that that is going to
be important to be able to do
that. I think one of the reasons
maps and Rick Doblin chose to
push MDMA is that first one is
that unlike LSD and Psilocybin,
which can create, you know,
pretty profound perceptual
distortions and sometimes some
disorientation, MDMA even when
you're in the throes of a
person. Heavy dose is that there
is a mental acuity that stays
present, and people tend to have
good recall later about what
their experience was, and you
don't have that disorientation,
and typically not the perceptual
disturbances. And so I think he
thought very wisely that that
would probably be an easier one
to get the authorities, the FDA,
to consider passing and
accepting and making it approved
for medicine. So I think that
that is, it's a legitimate track
of research, and I think it's a
legitimate way to try to get it
in, across the line in our
culture, to get it initially
accepted. You know, now, in the
60s, it started off that way. It
was in the lab even Timothy
Leary, once he started doing his
Psilocybin research in Harvard.
You know, he had people like
Aldous Huxley and Gerald heard
and these philosophers and
writers coming in to Harvard and
having Psilocybin sessions done
with him. And Aldous Huxley was
very adamant about, do not let
this get out. You need to be
careful about who you turn on.
You need to turn on the writers
and the musicians and the
philosophers and the leaders,
and you need to introduce it to
the culture in this way. And
then Leary being at the
forefront of this thing, who
didn't you know. He didn't know
what he was doing. And this guy
was a deep was a deeply flawed
human being. I am a big Tim
Leary fan, but he was a deeply
flawed human being. And one of
the things he said was that he
made the decision that this
should be an egalitarian
experience, that he felt like it
was the fifth freedom, that
everybody should be able to
manage their own nervous
systems. And so he said, thereby
hangs the tail when he made that
decision, that it needed to be
available. And so the problem
was he went out there telling
everybody, everybody's got a
right to take LSD, everybody has
a right to find their inner God,
or whatever it was that people
could find. But the trouble was,
people would take it, go to a
party. Their childhood sexual
abuse would come up, they would
have no support, they would not
be an appropriate setting, and
they'd end up in the ER and on
the front page of the newspaper.
And so enough of those happened,
and it gave the government
everything they needed to do to
try to shut all this down. So I
think that we have to be very
careful about how it's put out
there in some ways. And I do
think right now, one of the
advantages we have that we
didn't have in the 70s is the
internet. You're not going to
put this genie back in the
bottle at this point. There's
too much information out there.
Too many people know about these
substances, and in a lot of
cases, how to use them safely,
because there is some good
information out there on the
internet. So I do feel like that
this medical model is for good
or ill than the necessary model
that we need to use to try to
start to establish these things
as medicines, and if our culture
can maintain some wisdom and
some objectivity in order to
continue to rate to measure
these compounds objectively as
medicines, then we're going to
have a much better chance of
getting these things approved.
So, so that's kind of that
statement over here. I had a lot
of fun, I had a lot of growth, I
had a lot of spiritual
experiences that were just
unbelievable, and these were not
under clinical supervision, you
know. And when you look back on
the use of psychedelics, plant
medicines, ritual and
celebration was a huge
fundamental human thing that
people did, and oftentimes
psychedelics were a part of
that. And so I think that
ability to celebrate being
alive, being here on this
planet, being with your friends,
listening to great music, or
whatever it is that you're
doing, camping or whatever
you're doing. I think that's
also a very important piece of
this. I do think that there is
more risk taking that model. I
definitely went to some shows
and saw some people really
struggling that probably should
not have been there, doing what
they were doing for whatever
reason, but the dead was it
eventually evolved into what I
call just it was psychotherapy
on a mass scale. It felt like
you'd have about 25,000 people
in there, most of them tripping
on something. And this music was
very it was born of LSD. I mean,
Owsley, who was their patron
saint, was probably the largest
LSD chemist in the history of
humanity. And he was basically
buying their equipment and
feeding them LSD, and so they
were high all the time figuring
out how to play their music
together. And so this music that
came out was an amalgamation of
all these different styles of
music, jazz, rock and roll,
blues, Dixieland, experimental.
And so you had this very bizarre
yet somehow familiar type of
music that came out and and I
think it spoke to a lot of
people, particularly when they
were in these states. Robert
hunter and a lot of the
lyricists for the dead, they
wrote very mystical, archetypal
types of songs. The lyrics were
very a song would mean something
to me for five years, and then
I'd be at a show going through a
particular experience in my
life, and that song would speak
to me in a completely different
way that I had been turned off,
had not been aware of before,
which is what great art does.
There's just levels of it in
there. And so it was this just
continuing flower for, I guess,
85 to 95 for 10 years, it was my
psychotherapy, but I felt like
that they had it set up in a way
that there was. Somewhat of a
container. There were rituals
around it, from getting the
tickets to get in there early to
getting in line to get in your
seats, taking care of each other
when you're in there, there was,
there was an idea that everybody
was there to take care of each
other that you don't really see
too much at shows anymore these
days, unfortunately, but back in
the day, there was really that
ethos at the Grateful Dead show.
So it did feel like a fairly
safe place that you could go and
let it all hang out and with a
lot of other people. And I can
remember times opening my eyes
with 20,000 people synced up,
and everybody grooving. And, I
mean, I just felt like my head
was going to explode. It was so
good. And you realize that there
was just a lot more to life than
the one dimensional life that we
kind of get up and go to work
and do a lot of days, and that
sort of inspired me, and
inspired a lot of other people
and a lot of other bands. I
mean, a lot of that. There's a
lot of other bands that came out
of that scene. So I think, to
answer your question, I think
that that whole realm of
psychedelic exploration is
absolutely important. It's
absolutely necessary, I think.
But I think that people have to
recognize that there's a little
more risk that comes with doing
them in that kind of
environment, and so you need to
take it upon yourself to educate
yourself about whatever it is
you're taking, who you're with.
Know something about set and
setting, so that you can go and
have a safe and productive good
time.
Ehren Cruz: Thank you, Ram. Yep,
there's, you know, the movements
that have spawn from that, many
of our favorite bands, from fish
to my personal STS, nine, I have
to give them a little credit out
there. But um, freeze and Mo and
and also other cultures, Rainbow
gatherings, Burning Man, this is
all from the stimulation of
their radical creativity.
Communitas, you know, the
environmental connection that
comes through that. And I think
it's important people forget,
you know, the ellucidian
mysteries, who were the Greek
sacred ceremonial mysteries,
with the ceremonial theater of
initiation, with the Qi, Qi, on
which is the elixir and beverage
that was found to have ergot,
which is the base component of
LSD. 25 two to 3000 people would
go through those mysteries at
the same time. So the idea of
large alchemical ecstatic ritual
is as old as humanity, and an
important part of this, of our
lineage, in a process. So, So,
Chris, I want to ask you about,
now, this high end dosage in
because now, as we've we've
talked about, you know, most of
the time when you're looking at
the research studies you're
working with, you know,
psychedelic doses, maybe a
moderate dose. You know,
everywhere from, I know, with
them, with Psilocybin, be like,
about a gram to about 3.5 grams
or so. And there's a lot of deep
value there that can come
through that particular
experience and is profound as
well. But most of the time that
works with your biographical
healing. You know, your own
personal wounds and traumas and
kind of working back to that
state of acceptance, release,
self forgiveness,
reconciliation. But why the high
dose, you know, like and you
know, there is, you talked about
there, you know, there's a
concept of spiritual, maybe self
actualization, those things.
But, you know, is there a realm
currently, right now, for people
to push further? And if there
is, you know, what is it that I
think, as a collective, we might
be seeking in that particular
space? I
Raymond Turpin: I, first of all,
I really agree with you,
Raymond, that it's the medical
work and the therapeutic work
with psychedelics, which is
bringing psychedelics back into
our society. And that's that's
so important, and it's so
important that we do it well,
and it's so important that we
document the therapeutic
capacity. And as we do and once
we do that, once we get it back
in, then the question naturally
arises, okay, if it's an
amplifier, and if it amplifies
our consciousness, and if it
pulls up all these dark things,
and we can address them and heal
them and and re establish some
type of spiritual communion with
the universe around us, then how
far can we take it? What's going
to happen next and and I think
that it's going to take some
time, and some people are
already, of course, pushing what
we're Where can it go next? But
in terms of institutional
exploration, we're not there
yet, but we will be. It's just a
matter of time, because in these
states, it's it's not the
psychedelic that does the work.
It's consciousness that does the
work. Psychedelic is an
amplifier. And so when you get
right down to it is the
psychedelic that does the work
that and so if you handle the
consciousness carefully. You can
use it in the same way that
happens on a meditation cushion
at a Zen session. And that's, I
call it my work sessions. I'm
very specific about that, and
it's really a play on the
Japanese word session. A session
is a period of concentrated
spiritual practice, all right?
And so that's where I think of
my psychedelic work, is there
were X number of sessions, and I
can tell you exactly what I was
doing on one particular day and
one particular year, on one
particular session in that
process, I really do. I
honestly, sincerely do. Not
recommend that people do what I
did, honestly. I mean, there's
so many ways for this to go
wrong, and I was fortunate, and
I had a constitution that I
found I had a capacity to open
up into great breath and to get
very fluid and to dissolve and
lose my boundaries at level
after level, and then I could
congeal naturally at the end of
the day. Not everybody is built
like that. Not everybody has
that capacity. People need more
support going into this type of
work. And I wouldn't do it the
same way over again. I just
would not. I would be much
gentler with myself. I would
work with the balance of high
doses, occasionally lower doses,
Psilocybin balancing with LSD,
maybe in Ayahuasca, but I really
would take a much more nuanced
balancing approach, integrative
approach. I mean, there's kind
of a breakthrough session, and
then lower dose work, maybe with
Psilocybin to absorb and
integrate that material. But one
of the reasons I would do it
differently than I did it when I
did it is because I had this
mindset in that when I did this
work, first of all, that I was
it was personal, and that I
learned it's not personal.
Personal is the first layer. But
if you push him deeper, then the
dynamics of your work. Stop
being personal. They become
collective. You're working with
the collective psyche. You're
working with, and then you're
working with an evolutionary
process. You're working with an
historical process. And the
visions are not personal
visions, they're historical
visions. They're human human
visions. And it's a different
scale. But I thought when I did
this work, I thought that the
goal was to get somewhere. The
goal was to become enlightened,
or to become one with God, or to
dissolve into the meta cosmic
void, as Dan used to say. And
what I learned is about 17 years
into my work, 16 years into my
work, when I was as deep as I
would ever go. In my psychedelic
exploration, I was in the
diamond Luminosity, and I was in
a sweet spot, way beyond time
and space, resting in the
luminous body of the divine in
Dharmakaya. In that context, I
had a visionary experience. The
World opened and showed me a
world far in the distance, a
light filled world, and a ray of
light hit me from that world,
and it absolutely shattered me.
It took me 20 minutes to kind of
pull myself back together into
the Lama Luminosity condition.
And that's when I learned it's
an infinite progression. There's
no such thing as getting to the
end of it. You're not going to
get to the end of it, no matter.
I couldn't get to the end of it.
And that's when I began to
appreciate that it's really
about opening up, letting as
much of the wisdom and of the
healing energy and the insight
energy that universe, letting as
much of it in this you can
manage as you can handle,
absorbing it, digesting it. It's
not about getting to a condition
of awakening or getting into a
condition of God realization. I
mean, those are all fine. Those
are all wonderful as they come.
But as a psychedelic path, it's
not about getting to a
condition. It's about really how
you live your life. So I'm much
more attentive now, or a
conscious now, of the dying, of
keeping the process of the
dying, of keeping how you live
with those experiences. Because
truly, I'm going to be doing
some teaching soon in the
Kettleman assistant training
program. What's in in San
Francisco? Pardon. Polaris,
yeah, and it, my job is
integration, talking about
integration and talking, you
know, our discussion of
integration works well when
you're working at the
psychodynamic level of the
personal unconscious level, even
when you are having spiritual
experiences, you're tapping into
the, you know, the intelligence
that runs through all things.
And you're tapping into, you
know, your divine nature, which
is part of the nature that runs
through all things. We have
spiritual models for how to
integrate those experiences. But
when you push deep, into the
deep waters, when you're really
tapping into deep levels of the
infinite and when you're
transcending time, how the fuck
do you integrate those
experiences? What does
integration even mean? How does
a finite being integrate the
infinite? How does it being
which is a time space being is
finely tuned to the dynamics of
linear time and three
dimensional space. How does that
being integrate trans temporal
experiences, trans spatial
experiences? What does it mean
to integrate them and and so I
think we have to sort of stop
erase everything that. We've
learned about integration, or
much of what we've learned when
we're talking about working at
the personal, unconscious level,
and it becomes something
different. And I think we can
learn a lot from the indigenous
cultures. But I also think that
if we look at the psychedelics
that indigenous cultures we're
using, and we're looking at the
psychedelics that are available
to us today and the therapeutic
protocols that are available to
us today. It's not an
unreasonable hypothesis that we
are pushing deeper than many of
the indigenous cultures pushed,
and that raises challenges that
go beyond even what we can learn
from the indigenous cultures on
how to navigate those those
encounters. I think we're going
we're going to get there. We're
going to get to these issues
eventually. I don't think we're
going to get to these issues,
probably while I'm alive. I
think this is going to take
time. It's going to take time
for Raymond and all the Raymonds
in this movement to really
achieve a true grounding in our
culture of these psychedelics,
and then we can start to open up
the deeper door, and then we'll
and then we start to open up a
deeper door still, in a deeper
door still, it's going to take,
I think it's going to be
generations moving into this
material. This is not short term
work as a culture. This is long
term work, because what we're
talking about is not just
learning that there is a wisdom
in the universe, that there is
an intelligence guiding the
universe or birthing the
universe in the Big Bang process
and the unfolding process, but
we're talking about changing, or
expanding, radically expanding
our fundamental communion with
that universe, then that that's
a deep, deep journey for all of
us to be making culturally
together.
Ehren Cruz: Yeah. Thank you so
much. Chris. You know, because
the next, the next actual
question I had was showing how
rapidly we're moving, and I
think that's really important
that you immediately caution
that with slowing down and being
patient with the synthesis of
what this means on such a
transcendental level of you know
what it can mean for culture,
for civilization as a whole.
Because, you know, looking at
the current renaissance, you
know, right now, we have over
350 universities opening formal
psychedelic research
departments. We have 25,000 op
eds and over 2000 peer reviewed
journal articles published on
psychedelics in just the past
two years. FDA is impending
clearance of MDMA in 2024 for
therapeutic use and decrim and
legalization movements across
the country, city and state. So
we are hitting a momentum
unprecedented to this level at
this time and and, of course,
you know, from Oprah to Aaron
Rodgers, you know to, you turn
on the TV, and every other day
there's another celebrities
having an experience. So it's,
you know, the genie is very,
very much out the bottle. But
this idea of that, this is going
to leapfrog us directly into a
space where everybody has
touched upon the illumination of
the psychedelic we're all ready
to fully synthesize that into
daily life. I think that's
something that's going to take a
lot of time to do it right, to
have the ethics and honoring and
respect of the deep time of the
lineages and the indigenous that
come before us. So this is kind
of, this question is open ended.
But, you know, where do you see
this headed in the next few
years? You know, I think from
your behalf, Dr Turpin, you're
working right on the front lines
of legality. So you're preparing
for the, at least the the gate
of MDMA to open up. And, you
know, there's this a lot of work
there, I know, just from the,
from the side, part of that all
and and what do you have for
advice for us, as we continue to
step into this ourselves, as as
people that are wanting to be
caretakers of this medicine,
culture and movement now, what
do you think from your
experiences going from the deep,
depths of the underground and
the shadow days to now, where We
are, where it's you know, it's
now becoming contemporary,
acceptable to be open about it.
So those two questions there,
what do you see this immediately
happening, and how's that going
forward?
Raymond Turpin: Good question.
Hmm. Well, you know, if taking a
psychedelic made you better
human being, then we would all
be, probably three fourths of
our country would be Buddhas by
now. So taking a psychedelic
doesn't necessarily make you a
better human being. I think
there's so much about intention
and so much about the
integration. As far as what are
you going to do with the
experience that matters? And so
I think that we've got to
continue to educate people about
the importance of that, it's not
just taking the compound, it's
really doing the ritual work
afterwards and and, you know,
when people come into our
ketamine program, I tell them
right off the bat, don't expect
the ketamine to do the work. You
know, it might make you feel
great. It might absolutely you
know, you might lose a lot of
your depression symptoms you've
had for 20 years. But if you
don't take the insights, the.
You gained in that experience,
and bring them into your
everyday life. Maybe do a little
less of this or more of this,
then chances are you're going to
regress back to baseline in four
to eight weeks. And so there's
it's so important that people
understand that these things are
windows into the unconscious and
windows into the deep self. I
like to use the Jung Ian giant s
self that you know the self is
this almost limitless thing
underneath our I know it's part
and parcel of our ego, but our
ego is just a tiny little part
of this giant self. And that the
self is this knowing. It is this
inner healing intelligence. It
knows what we need to be whole
and balanced, and it's always
pushing to be known, whether
it's through dreams or
psychedelics or whatever. And so
teaching people how to
understand that these
experiences are glimpses. They
are, they're they're
instructional dreams, almost.
They're glimpses into their deep
self, and then teaching people
how to value and bring these
things forward is going to be
the key. So I do see things
moving along at a pretty quick
pace, quicker than I ever
thought. I mean, I was at the
point where I was like, Damn,
I'm like, 50. I don't know if
this is ever going to happen.
Maybe I need to think about
going into the underground. But
then MDMA showed up, you know,
and I was like, wow. Okay,
maybe, maybe it's not too late.
I'm still up, right? Maybe I got
another 10 or 15 years. That's
good. So I was really excited to
see that happening. And you
know, I think we all again, have
such a responsibility to educate
other people, people that are
curious about these things, so
that they get good information
that's grounded in science,
that's grounded in tradition,
that's grounded in love and self
caring and self acceptance. It's
also important as we go forward
with this, what was the second
part of your question,
Ehren Cruz: yeah, I think for
the insight as to advice of us
moving forward as a collective
Yes, Vann, you know what you see
immediately, too, with the MDMA
and Pearl. Oh, yeah,
Raymond Turpin: yeah, the MDMA
is interesting right now, what
I'm hearing, and Haley, correct
me if I'm wrong, is that maps is
in the process of getting their
new drug application in place to
submit to the FDA. The phase
three studies are over. We are
treating our last three for us
MDMA patients, and that's all
been closed. The last patients
are being treated. And then I
understand that there is about a
pallet or two of paper that have
to be submitted to the FDA and a
new drug application, and so
that all is going to get
submitted, hopefully, maybe by
early next year, maybe it sounds
like and then everything I'm
hearing is that, hopefully, if
things go well, sometime next
year, around this time, maybe
late 2024 we might find it
approved for PTSD. The problem
is, is that, how long is it
going to take for insurance
companies then get on board and
be willing to reimburse for
these treatments. They are 4647
hour protocols. There's two
guides or therapists every step
of the way. For good reason. I
don't see that model changing
after acceptance. One of the
things I do see is right now in
the expanded access model, is
the treatment team has to be
made up of a lead therapist
that's either an MD or a
psychologist, and then the CO
therapist has to be a licensed
therapist. And I think what
we're going to see after we move
into approval is that one of the
treatment team is going to need
to be a licensed therapist who's
been trained by maps, and then,
technically, the other person
could be someone that's not a
therapist. It could be a nurse.
It could even be a clergy
member. It could be somebody
else, as long as they have been
properly trained by maps. And so
I think that's going to be key
to bringing the cost down, is
having that be the team makeups
be a little bit more reasonable
like that. And one of the
reasons we did our nonprofit was
to try to figure out a way to
generate funding so that people
could access things like
ketamine and MDMA, because it is
going to be expensive for most
people until insurance companies
do get online. So, and I also
think that there's going to be
an enormous need to train
therapists and how to do MDMA
work. Maps has been doing a
really good job of getting
people through their training
program, but it gets you all the
way to the last step, and so
essentially, we have hundreds of
therapists out there that have
gone through the maps training,
but they lack what's called the
supervised clinical experience,
which is where you actually
treat somebody from the
beginning to the end of the
protocol under clinical
supervision. That's the final
step to being certified. So
we're going to have a bit of a
bottleneck, I think, of
therapists at when it gets
approved. And so one of the
things we're trying to do at the
pearl is that my treatment
partner, Kim Skelton and I are
trying to treat enough folks and
beg the folks at maps enough to
where we could be a facility
where some of these folks from
Asheville and in North Carolina
could come and hopefully finish
their training, get their
certification done with us,
without having to go out of
state and do that so. So I would
suggest for people that are
interested in continuing to
facilitate this opening of
psychedelics, or this reopening
of psychedelics, or wanting to
get involved in it. It's really
about educating yourself. There
are wonderful things out there
that you can learn from. There's
YouTube videos, there's great
books for people that want to do
MDMA work right now, you're
going to have to go through the
maps program. Or that may open
up in five. Who knows years? Who
knows? But right now, they're
the ones that have the protocol
all down, and they're ready to
train folks, but and then I
think Psilocybin is probably,
maybe everything I'm hearing is
like, maybe three years behind.
They're starting some of the
phase three studies. And so
that'll move on, and hopefully
that'll be, I think Psilocybin
is going to have greater utility
than MDMA. I think MDMA is
always going to be dynamite for
trauma work and PTSD work, and
also for relational problems,
interpersonal communication
issues like marriage counseling,
couples work. That was what MDMA
was shown to have great value
for in the early 80s, before it
became a schedule one. And so I
do see it continuing to do that,
and then I see Psilocybin having
really wide applicability to
many different kinds of issues.
And I never thought I'd see LSD
getting studied in my lifetime.
And it's actually the doors
cracking open on that one too.
And that's a little harder,
because you're looking at 10 to
12 hour sessions, which, as Stan
said, were brutal, you know, to
have to be in there that long,
even an eight hour MDMA session
can be long. We're exhausted by
the end. By six o'clock, when
the overnight person gets there,
we're like, man, we're ready. So
So anyway, I think things are on
a good track. I'm always worried
something crazy is going to
happen and be on the headlines,
and then it's going to set
everything back. But you know,
so far, we've gotten pretty
lucky, and I think part of that
is because of the internet, and
there's been a dissemination of
information out there. There
wasn't there back in the 70s and
60s, about what how these things
operate, what they do in the
brain, the importance of set and
setting, and how to have, how to
be able to use these things
safely and responsibly. So my
advice would be able to just
keep your eyes open and see
what's coming down the pipe.
MDMA is, I think, going to be
the first one that gets
approved, hopefully. And if
you're interested in going into
that work, get the background
that you need to be able to
apply to maps, to get the work
done, to get the stud the
training done, and and then
again, just continue to model
for people out there that this
is serious work, and we all take
it responsibly and we have an
ethical it's incumbent upon all
of us to have this ethical
responsibility as we conduct
ourselves out there, because
people look at us and go, Oh,
you're a psychedelic person, and
they want us. And I think it's
important that we are able to
comport ourselves in a way that
we're doing our part to help
push these things forward.
I let me expand the context. I
completely agree with everything
you're saying, Raymond. I really
do in terms of particularly
applications of MDMA and the
broader role and range of
Psilocybin, and we haven't
talked about five Meo DMT and
its therapeutic potential. I'd
like to expand the context a
little bit. Those of you who
know my work know that my
visionary experience is that we
are coming into a time of
profound social catharsis,
crisis, transformational Press,
Press pressure. And so when I
look ahead 10 years, 20 years,
and I picture this gathering
here 10 years from now. 20 years
from now, the background, social
context, will be radically
different. We're moving into
profound crisis, an ego
environmental crisis, global
climate change crisis, which is
triggering, going to be
triggering all sorts of economic
and social crises, and that
means political crises. And you
know, when the ocean level is
rising and cities are flooding
and millions of ecological
refugees are moving across the
planet, the social instability
is going to be enormous. And so
that means, if we ask, well,
what is the role of psychedelics
in that changing world? It's not
the simple therapeutic processes
of today, but my background. I
believe in reincarnation. I
don't think that's a hard sell
in this crowd. It's a it's a
standard part of my experience
in psychedelic work and and that
means that each one of us, if
our collective culture, is
coming into a time of crisis
where we have to make life and
death decisions about how we
live on this planet and how we
live with each other inside, we
are carrying large pieces of the
history of humanity inside our
being, in our reincarnational
history. So what's trying to
take place in the world around
us is also trying to take place
in the world inside of us. And
if I, if you are like me, you
know that there's a tremendous
purification process taking
place is a tremendous
intergenerational, inner
evocative process, inner healing
process, and it's like that's
why I think so many people are
doing yoga and meditation, and
they need all the help they can
get to handle the up rush that's
coming from deep within the.
Psyche, and that's going to
increase. That's going to
increase in the decades ahead.
Because this this process, we
can't make the jump to where we
need to go to live on this earth
until we have digested and
processed and transcended the
history of our behavior on this
earth and the history of our
behavior with each other, and it
has to come out, and it has to
be dealt with at an individual
and a collective level in order
for us to be receptive to the
inflow, the increased inflow of
salvific energy that's coming
into us and moving us into a
different phase. So that means
the dance is changing. The
stability of our current world
hopefully will last long enough
to allow us to get these
substances internal to our
system. But when we move deeper
into crisis, I would see the
role of psychedelics for
individual and collective
healing to increase
exponentially if we've done our
work at this stage well. And I
think that's just really,
really, really critical,
important. And so my suggestion
for how we move forward is we
can't simply focus on our
internal work. We have to be
focused as well on the external
work, we have to be working at
the political level and the
social level and the larger
intellect international level,
as well as working on the inner
level. And those are not
separate processes. Those are
actually deeply, deeply
integrated, synergistic
processes as we move forward.
You know, it all changed with
the invention of the nuclear
bomb. Right? When Eisenhower,
who led us in World War Two, saw
the pictures of the nuclear
bomb, he said, That's it. That
changes everything. And LSD is
kind of like that came into
existence at the same period of
history. The inflow of
indigenous cultural wisdom comes
in shortly thereafter,
psychedelics change everything.
Tremendous intellectual
revolution is right around the
wing, right around the corner.
Tremendous religious and
spiritual revolutions are right
around the corner because, you
know, it just unleashes
tremendous evolutionary forces
in our individual lives and in
our collective lives. How we
handle that is going to be
really important the festivals
which will be coming, the the
collective healing that takes
place in these festivals will be
really important as we move
forward. Yeah, something like
that.
Ehren Cruz: Thank you so much.
Chris, you know the power of the
social responsibility that you
gentlemen charge us with is
quite profound, and not only for
how we hold these medicines
ourselves and care take them and
leave them out there, but how we
work with them collectively, how
we allow them to be a part of
our larger maybe the catalyst
for some important shifts in our
life and our culture. And one of
the things that I've recognized
working with Psilocybin for so
many years is it reminds us of
us being first and foremost
children of this world, you
know, like the mycelium that is
underneath us. You know, we are
stewards and caretakers of this
body. We are gifted with a
garden for us to tend and and
the more that we learn how to do
that and honor our differences
and and symbolic relationship
with those around us that
creates the foundation for, you
know, beautiful fruit, you know,
intellectually, spiritually,
emotionally, that we create
together. So that's it's as old
as time that lesson, but it's
new, and it's needed more than
ever as well as we step into
this greater age of
responsibility and
accountability. So So thank you
all, as you're continuing to
work with these medicines, you
know these are powerful and
profound. You know harm
reduction principles,
preparation, navigation,
integration and synthesis of
those, caretaking of those
around you is all very, very
important part of the process
and and more than we know. So
we're going to open up to
questions here for from a couple
of you, but let's just again,
give a big round of applause and
a big thank you to Dr Bache for
their wisdom today.
So we have time for maybe two or
three questions. If you guys
wanted to share real quick,
anybody have something? Steve,
right here? Do I need the mic?
Or just shout it out?
Unknown: If you can then. Dr
Bache, I've read your book, and
if anybody has it, right? LSD,
in the mind of the universe,
read that thing. I've read about
six times, and every time I go
in, I go deeper and deeper. I'd
like you to pontificate about,
or elaborate about. You've
talked about the 200,000 year
gestation period that humanity
is in, or just coming to
transition, like in the birth
Could you talk about that?
Elaborate on that a little
Raymond Turpin: bit you. Only
way I can speak about that, of
course, is if I speak out of my
visionary experience. And so
it's just visionary experience,
and it is only visionary
experience, and it is visionary
experience. The creative
intelligence of the universe is
not things small. It thinks
large. It doesn't really think
in terms of just individuals. It
thinks it's in terms of whole
species. It thinks in terms of
whole ecosystems and planetary
development. And so
ask yourself, what is the finest
that human beings can become,
what is, if we look ahead, what
is the finest that human beings
can be? And then imagine that
the divine wants it to be like
that, and it wants it to be even
more than that. The question
then is, how do we go from
baboons or chimpanzees to that,
and it takes time. It's a
repetitive cycle, lifetime by
lifetime, we accumulate more
knowledge, more wisdom,
hopefully more understanding,
more wounds. So we're taking
care of the wounds. We're taking
care of the past, while we're
expanding potential, lifetime
after lifetime, 1000s of years,
10s of 1000s of years, hundreds
of 1000s of years we've been at
this process. We have such a
tendency to think in terms of
short term perspective. Achieve
salvation, go to heaven, achieve
enlightenment, go to pari
nirvana. It's an up and out
cosmology which has been driving
us. But the divine doesn't think
in terms of up and out
cosmology. It's about a
continual receding and a
fruition that's taking place on
the planet and bringing us into
ever, ever deeper levels of
communion with the creative
wisdom of the universe and the
joy of the universe, and holding
it in our body, and holding it
in place, and holding it in this
world together in peace and
harmony with the other members
of this other species that we
share this planet with and with
everyone of the human species
that would share the planet
with. My sense of what's
happening is that we're coming
into a pivot point in history
where all of the lives that we
have lived, each of us can just
look around this room, imagine
how many lives are being are
sitting in these chairs, how
many hundreds of lives are
sitting in each chair, and all
of those 1000s of years of
experience sitting in each
chair. And my sense is, what's
happening in history is that
there's a coming together. Not
only a coming together on the
planet, forcing of the changes
that that's taken, but there's a
coming together in the soul,
that all of our former lives are
coming together. And as they
come together, the first thing
we have to deal with is all
their unfinished business. So we
got this pain and that pain and
that issue and that trauma that
comes from this life and that
life, and we have to deal with
that, but as we deal with that,
it makes it easier for these
lives to come together. And
although it's not just the
problems that they're bringing
that that may be the first wave
that shows up, but it's all the
learning that they're bringing,
it's all the knowledge that
they're bringing, it's all the
history and texture of their
relationships that they're
bringing. And remember, these
lives have been, black, white,
every every imaginal possibility
on the planet, every position in
society, every position in
class, all the adventures, and
they're all coming together. And
I think they're coming together,
and they're beginning a process
of fusing. And went in my
experience, in my sessions when
I experienced all my former
lives coming together and
fusing. There was an explosion.
It was like they hit a critical
mass and there was an explosion.
And there was an explosion of
diamond consciousness that just
broke out of my chest, and it
threw me into a deep and
profound condition where I was
an individual, but I wasn't an
individual. I wasn't Chris
Bache, and I wasn't an
individual with any frame of
reference that I had known
before, but I was an individual,
but I was in a deep and profound
cosmic communion as an
individual. And I think that's
what's happening to all of us in
history, every continent, every
person on the planet is part of
this process of facilitating an
integration of all of our lives.
And this is what I call the
birth of the diamond soul. It is
simply the birth of the soul
consciousness inside our human
incarnation, so that when we
experience ourselves, we do not
experience ourselves in any way
as defined by the beginning and
ending of this life. We have a
natural, intuitive, awake
awareness, conscious awareness
of our deep history, which means
a conscious awareness of our
profound social connection, a
profound awareness of the
relativity of all these little
fights that. To get into, you
know, all these stupid things
that we have reasons to get in
conflict with their Twitter are
not important and not relevant.
We're swallowing all these
things as we come together. And
I think we're moving towards an
explosion of soul consciousness
on the planet. I don't think we
can live on this planet out of
egoic consciousness. And I think
the ego is a beautiful, you
know, individual ego
consciousness is a beautiful,
magnificent thing, but we cannot
afford to live on this planet.
Out of that state of
consciousness. We either evolve
into the next state of
consciousness, which I think is
fundamentally the soul
consciousness, or we go extinct.
And extinction is a powerful,
psychedelic, powerful
transformational motivator, and
I think that's the process that
we're coming into now. So how
long will this take? How fast
can it happen? I don't know. And
when I've seen it, when I've
experienced it in my sessions,
it didn't come with dates, and
it didn't come with the with the
brochure, the detailing how it's
going to take place. But I, but
I've know in my bones that it's
happening, and I also know from
my, I offer you, from my
visionary experience, that we
will make it through this
process. We will survive. We
will transform humanity. Will
make it through. It won't look
like we're going to make it
through for a time. It will look
like we're going to die in this
process. That is the death and
rebirth process. We're going to
have to put it all on the line.
We're going to have to lay it
all down and make a complete,
radical commitment to this
process. But my experience is
that the diamond soul is born in
history, the future human is
born, and that future human is
magnificently beautiful, just
beautiful beyond description.
And we see glimpses of it in the
Great. We see it in Christ, and
we see it in the great in the
Buddhas and the prophets of
history. Catch glimpses of
what's emerging forward and
what's coming forward in all of
our lives. We're being taken
there, and we're not in control
of this process, right? We're
not in control of evolution.
We're hardly in control of our
own individual evolution. There
are deep, forces at work that
are pushing us, driving us. And
lastly, we all knew what we were
getting into before we
incarnated. We made a choice to
be part of this, and we'll make
a choice to be part of the next
generation. We chose to be part
of this evolutionary transition.
When you die, you don't want to
just have a comfortable life or
an easy life. You want to have a
meaningful life. And is there
anything more meaningful than
supporting this transition that
humanity is making collectively
so that we can really learn to
live together in peace on this
planet, healed, truly healed on
the heart of all the wars and
all the wounds and all the
terrible things we've done to
each other and all the things
that were left unfinished
lifetime after lifetime. Imagine
a species that's truly healed
all that stuff, individually,
collectively healed. It Robert
Monroe, whom some of you know
from his books on out of body,
and is the Monroe Institute. He
his in his intelligent guides
took him to a place in the
future, which he estimated was
about 3000 ad and in that time
in the future, when he went
there, the entire Bardo, where
souls go in between their
incarnations, was empty. We had
integrated the Bardo, because
the Bardo is basically filled
with soul fragments, just pieces
of our lives which we didn't get
finished or whatnot. Imagine all
of those pieces integrated into
us so that we are now whole and
complete within ourselves,
within our history, and so is
everybody else that we're living
with. If the Bardo is empty, the
divine intelligence can reach
more deeply, more easily, more
fluidly, right into the very
center of our hearts and into
our minds. And that's what I
think we're all working for.
That's what we're all yearning
for. So we feel it. We can feel
it in our bones. We touch it
when we do our in our individual
healing, we touch that and we
know that there's something
afoot which is much deeper even
than our personal healing, but
our personal healing is part of
it. We have to go through that
if we're going to contribute to
the birth of the diamond soul in
history. Yeah. Wow.
Ehren Cruz: Well, I think we
might have gone on time with
that, but, and I almost don't
feel like it seemed, I don't
know how you could actually
follow that up. Be honest. I.
Um, but we will be here for some
time. So if you guys want to
connect afterward and mingle,
and please do come up and share.
And these, these gentlemen be
here for a little bit of time to
connect. And so we're going to
be wrapping up this session. But
on behalf of the psychedelic
Society of Asheville, we are so,
so grateful and honored to have
these wonderful guests do a
fireside chat with us here this
evening. So once again, thank
you guys so much, and please do
stay in touch with us here.
We're psychedelic society,
avl.com, we do once a month,
usually the final Sunday, or you
know, of a gathering together.
We shift different topic
matters. We have, sometimes more
back and forth sessions. We're
connecting with people, you
know, cross pollinating.
Sometimes it's more harm
reduction guidance, you know,
getting insights how to do this
safely, ethically, stepping into
this work in medicine, with
education resources, sometimes
bringing our creative friends in
there. We had a panel of artists
that came in and gave how this
medicine has influenced their
beautiful crafts. So please do
be a part of this community
where we're open hearted and
welcoming of all peoples and and
stick around for a little bit
and say hello to each other.
There's a lot of beautiful folks
in here that we'd love to, you
know, continue to establish
relationships and friendships
here. So once again, thank you
to Melissa and Joe from Sky
Mountain as well, helping us
have this beautiful setting for
the talk. Kind of wish I was
facing this one, but this was
excellent as well. And Blessings
to you all. And have a wonderful
evening. Thanks for coming out
tonight. You.