Jeffrey Mishlove: New thinking
allowed is presented by the
California Institute for Human
science, a fully accredited
university offering distant
learning graduate degrees that
focus on mind, body and spirit.
The topics that we cover here,
we are particularly excited to
announce new degrees emphasizing
Parapsychology and the
paranormal, visit their website
at C, i, h, s.edu,
thinking allowed conversations
on the leading edge of knowledge
and discovery with psychologist
Jeffrey Mishlove.
Emmy Vadnais: Hello and welcome.
I'm Emmy Vadnais, co host with
Jeffrey Mishlove. Our topic
today is psychedelics and the
Cosmic Mind, with my guest,
Chris Bache, who is professor
emeritus in the Department of
Philosophy and Religious Studies
at Youngstown State University
in Ohio, where he taught for 33
years. He is also adjunct
faculty at the California
Institute of integral studies,
Emeritus fellow at the Institute
of Noetic Sciences and on the
Advisory Council of Grof legacy
training. Chris is author of
four books, life cycles,
reincarnation in the web of
life, dark night, early dawn,
the living classroom, teaching
and collective consciousness and
LSD in the mind of the universe,
diamonds from heaven. If you
enjoy this program, please like,
subscribe, press the bell icon
and share. Chris is joining us
from just north of Asheville in
Weaverville, North Carolina. Now
I'll switch over to the internet
video. Welcome Chris. It's a
great joy to have you with me on
new thinking allowed
Jeffrey Mishlove: today. Thank
you, Emmy, it's a pleasure to be
here today.
Emmy Vadnais: We're going to
discuss your deep exploration of
yourself, your own spiritual
journey and into the cosmic mind
when you had 73 LSD sessions
between the years of 1979 to
1999 and you outline that in
your book LSD, in the mind of
the universe, before we get into
all that you experienced and
what you gleaned and learned
from that. From those sessions,
can we just begin with talking a
little bit about what you've
noticed in the last, oh, I don't
know, 10 plus years or more,
where it seems that the taboo
related to psychedelics seems to
be shifting the types of
psychedelics there are out there
and and what their uses are, for
not each one, but sort of
overall, why people do this, and
today we're going to focus on
specifically the cosmic
exploration of them.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Well, as you
know, there is a worldwide
renaissance of research taking
place in psychedelics. At the
forefront of that research is
the focus on therapeutic
healing. That's what's bringing
psychedelics back into the
intellectual and clinical
community, the capacity of these
amplifying substances to bring
forward the personal unconscious
and to unearth the wounds of the
personal unconscious and to
assist and deepen, accelerate
people's healings of trauma,
various issues Post Traumatic
Stress, depression, things like
this, a second use of
psychedelics, overlapping but
different from therapeutic
Healing, is using psychedelics
to promote spiritual awakening,
an awakening to our of the true
nature, our deeper nature,
underneath our personality,
nature to deepen our
understanding, our experience of
the wisdom of the universe, the
intelligence of the universe,
the consciousness of the
universe. Classic kind of
spiritual awakening to the to
the nature of spiritual reality,
and that's why I got started in
this work. Really was to deepen
my spiritual awakening. But the
protocol that I ended up using
was so strong and so evocative.
Within a few years, I was having
experiences that went far beyond
anything that could be
understood in terms of either
therapeutic healing or spiritual
awakening. And I came to
understand over time, that the
project that I was involved in
was cosmological exploration,
that is a systematic attempt to
explore. Or the deep structure
of spiritual reality, or the
deep structure of the
consciousness of the universe
itself. So that's really what my
work is about. I'm not a
clinician. I am a trained as a
philosopher of religion. What
interested me from Stan Grof
early work was the capacity of
these substances to lay bare,
not only of the personal issues,
but to enter into deep communion
with the consciousness that lies
behind existence.
Emmy Vadnais: Can you share give
us an overview of the different
types of psychedelics, just to
kind of list them off, of
course, because there are, there
are many, but we're going to
primarily talk about your
experience with LSD today.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Many
psychedelics. I mean, there, I
guess the primary ones that come
to mind are LSD, Psilocybin,
MDMA, though that's probably
that's an in pathogen, more than
a straight psychedelic. Five,
MEO, DMT, salvia divinorum San
Pedro. I mean, I think these are
the types of psychedelics that
most people are familiar with.
There are all sorts of
derivatives. MDMA. They're
derivatives off of each of these
little tweaks along the way.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah. And we also
want to say upfront that you're
not recommending necessarily
that people engage in the same
process you engaged in, or
advocating necessarily for the
use of these per se, is that
right?
Jeffrey Mishlove: Absolutely,
there are a large percentage of
the population who shouldn't be
doing psychedelics at all. These
are very powerful amplifiers of
consciousness. They have
tremendous evocative potential.
And there are persons who should
not be venturing into these
waters, and no one should be
venturing into these waters
without really good, high
quality professional guides
accompanying you to keep you
safe as you enter into this
territory. Now, the protocol
that I chose to work with was
high doses of LSD. I worked at
500 to 600 micrograms, and
looking back at it on it, at the
end of it, I think, what was I
thinking? That was ridiculous,
but I had a deep hunger to
explore the nature of existence,
and working at these high doses
took me on an adventure of a
lifetime. But this is very
demanding work, which requires a
lot of concentration, a lot of
safeguards and a lot of time to
assimilate the experiences, and
I really knowing what I know
now, at the end of this journey,
I strongly recommend against
using the protocol that I used.
If I were doing it over again, I
would work with lower doses of
psychedelics. I'd be much
gentler on myself. I'd be
willing to sort of peel back the
layers of the psyche much more
gradually than I did in this
work.
Emmy Vadnais: So to begin into
your journey, what was the
impetus for you to embark on
this deep exploration with high
doses of LSD.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Well, I had
just finished my graduate work.
I had just started my academic
career. At the time, I was a
pretty convinced atheistically
inclined agnostic. And then I
met the work of two people, Ian
Stevenson, whose work on
reincarnation convinced me that
reincarnation was a simple fact
of life, and the other one was
Stanislav Grof. And I read his
book, realms of the human
unconscious. And I read it in
1978 two years after it had just
come out. And as soon as I read
that book, I recognize that
Stan's work had tremendous
significance, not only for
psychotherapy, but it had
tremendous significance for
philosophy of religion,
philosophy of consciousness. And
I knew that if I was ever going
to make a contribution in this
field, I had to undergo, I had
to undergo my own therapeutic
exploration, my own regimen so
very uncomfortably, I made a
decision to break the law in a
very, I hope, disciplined and
restrained way, and I began a
series of psychedelic sessions,
which ended up, much to my
surprise, ended up lasting 20
years. I worked for four years.
I stopped for six years, and
then I worked for another 10
years, finishing in 1999 and
then I spent 20 years after
that, digesting these
experiences, analyzing them,
sifting them, sorting them, and
then wrote El. University in the
mind of the universe in 2019, 20
years after I had stopped my
sessions.
Emmy Vadnais: Can you give us a
sense of what your sessions were
like? How you began? You
mentioned that you had a sitter,
somebody with you in that
process. How did you choose to
set up your set and setting.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Well,
basically, I followed the
protocol established by stand
reflected in his book, realms of
the human unconscious, and then
clarified further in his book,
LSD psychotherapy, where he lays
out all the nuts and bolts of
working in this modality. You're
always, I was always in a room,
separated from the world,
protected from the world, no
interruptions by myself with my
sitter, who was my wife at the
time, who was a clinical
psychologist who studied the
psychedelic literature with me.
I'm lying down. I'm using eye
shades and Muse and headphones
conventional kind of classic
psychedelic, deep introspection,
deep meditative orientation,
very carefully curated music to
support the opening and the
peaking and the closing of a
session. So the basic idea is to
profoundly energize the
unconscious, and then to create
an environment where the the
energies rising through your
unconscious can be engaged
cleanly and clearly if you stay
in contact with the physical
world, if you're in dialog with
friends, or if you're going to a
concert, that's all fine and
good, but that's just not what
this work is about. It requires
a powerful amplification of the
unconscious, but then creating a
very carefully controlled
environment that lead allows you
to engage what rises
conscientiously and most
importantly, to follow whatever
arises to its very bottom level,
to the bottom line, to let it
take you wherever it wants to
take you.
Emmy Vadnais: If I recall
correctly, it was typically on
Saturdays because you had a very
important day job teaching at a
university, and I think your
sessions lasted about was eight
hours each, roughly,
Jeffrey Mishlove: yeah, pretty
much I would start in the early
morning, and I would finish by
nighttime. That night, late
afternoon, night time. So a
session would last 810, hours or
so of the carry over tail, but
basically a good, hard eight
hours each session. So it's a
major commitment. It's a you
have eventually, I developed
spiritual protocols that I would
adopt in the weeks leading up to
a session and in the weeks after
a session, and particularly the
day or two before a session, and
the day or two after the
session. You really have to work
with those that time and with
the energy that is stirred in
you, because if you're working
with very high doses of a
powerful psychedelic like LSD,
it taps into very deep levels of
the universe, and it takes your
body and mind and subtle energy
system a time to process that
material. And so it's it's a
major time commitment. It's just
not the day of. It's several
days before and several days
after.
Emmy Vadnais: You also took
meticulous notes from your
sessions as well, which is a lot
of what's in your book.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Yeah, that's
the first step of integration is
to act to create an accurate
phenomenological description of
exactly what happens in your
sessions, because integration is
the foundation of your future
sessions. If you don't integrate
your sessions thoroughly and
conscientiously, then you're not
going to have as likely to have
as deep an experience the next
session out. So there's a circle
where you open, but then you
integrate what you experience,
which lays the foundation for
the deeper opening in your next
session.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah. It seems
like they built upon each other.
Jeffrey Mishlove: In my
experience, they did. Again, I
kind of standardized my sessions
as much as possible, eliminating
as many variables. I always was
using the same substance, the
same dose, the same set and
setting, the same sitter, even
in the same part of the country.
If you change those variables,
it changes the subtlety of the
interface between your mind and
the universe's mind that you're
engaging. So by trying to
standardize those variables, you
create an environment of
sustained communion or dialog.
With this deeper consciousness.
And by by treating that
sustained, clear contact point,
my experience was that the
universe, or the consciousness,
whatever it was that I was
engaging, that consciousness,
took me deeper and deeper in a
systematic fashion. It was like
taking a series of graduate
courses in consciousness. It was
a tremendous, rigorous,
systematic expansion of my frame
of reality.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah. Why did you
choose this path versus, for
example, sitting in meditation
or some other spiritual path
that can lead you deeper into
these realms.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Well, I had
been meditating since college. I
was familiar with meditation. I
meditated in a couple of
different traditions by that
time, and I'm a professor of
religious studies, so I had a
good, solid grounding in the
world spiritual traditions. I
taught courses in psychology of
religion and Transpersonal
studies and comparative
mysticism. So I understood the
world of meditation and
contemplative practice. I
started by thinking that these
sessions would basically help me
break through some of the
obstacles that had risen in my
contemplative practice. What I
found, however, was that this
was a protocol of spiritual
exploration that took me deeper
than I had ever imagined being
possible when I began this work,
and once I was into it a couple
of years I had developed an
aptitude for working in these
states, and I never stopped
meditating. I was always
meditating through this time. I
was always doing yoga and
various spiritual practices. In
fact, I think that the deeper
you want to go in working with
psychedelics, the more important
it is to have a daily spiritual
practice that helps anchor you
and helps you absorb the
experiences that you unleash
with psychedelics. It was a
different protocol. It gave me
access to states of
consciousness that you can reach
with meditation, but only with
lifetimes, not just one
lifetime, but many lifetimes of
meditation. So I differentiate
between what I call the path of
temporary immersion, which is
working with psychedelics as you
only, you're only immersed in
these states for hours at a
time, versus the path of
presence, of contemplative
presence, where it's a slower
path, but it tends to produce
states of abiding transparency,
whereas the temporary path
pushes you deep into these
conscious domains, and then it
wears off and you Come back.
They're they're complementing
approaches, but they are
different.
Emmy Vadnais: Let's begin with
your very first session, just to
get us started, because I know
you've done many of them to give
the listeners, the audience, the
viewers, a taste of what your
experience was like, that led
you to keep wanting to come back
for more.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Probably the
most significant thing that
happened in my first session was
that I entered a phase of the
work where I could not remember
who I was. I could not remember
what I was, what I did for a
living, living. I could not
remember whether I was a man or
a woman, even it was a complete
interruption of my stream of
consciousness that was telling
me who and what I was. And this
was a frightening experience, a
jarring experience, but in the
end, I learned that it was a
very helpful experience, because
it showed me that it would be
pointless for me to try to stay
in control, because if you can't
control your self knowledge,
then what that's about as basic
as you can get. And this session
taught me that in this work, you
have to surrender radically to
whatever arises. And it saved me
a lot of time and energy later,
when more demanding experiences
open, there's a tendency to sort
of want to maintain control, to
hold on to reality as you know
it. And in this type of work,
you have to let go of reality as
you know it. You have to
completely surrender and go
where it wants to take you. And
so that was just the first
lesson that basically said,
Don't waste time trying to
maintain control
Emmy Vadnais: before we go
further into some of your
sessions and giving us a taste
of your experiences and what you
learned. Have you come to.
Understand the physiology of
what LSD is doing on the human
physiology the nervous system.
Of course, a lot of people think
about connect consciousness with
the brain, which, of course,
it's more than that. However, I
recently spoke with Jill Bolte
Taylor, who is a neuroanatomist
from Harvard, and she had a
wrote a well known book her
Stroke of Insight, where she had
a stroke and she had an eight
year journey of recovery back,
but she described that our
personal sense of identity is
just the size of a peanut in our
brains.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Yeah, and, you
know, I followed the discussion
of the science scientist about
how what is biochemistry of LSD
and how it affects brain
structure and Default Mode
Network interruption and those
type of discussions, but I'm not
really drawn to that
conversation. I'm not primarily
a scientist, a scientist in
training. I basically have taken
more of a psychological approach
to understanding that these
substances, whatever their
mechanism, they amplify
consciousness, they open they
hyper sensitize consciousness,
and they allow you to experience
dimensions of your mind, and
eventually, of reality beyond
your mind, which usually were
kept in a space time, kind of
focus where we don't experience
these subtler textures, right,
Emmy Vadnais: where we can feel
trapped inside our bodies or in
the what most people consider is
primarily the materialistic
world, which we know is there's
much more than that, which is
what we're talking about today.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Yeah, yeah.
And that's, that's the real draw
to me. And so I basically work
within the frame of reference
that I had acquired from Stan
Grof and some of the other
earlier researchers, using a
description of the dynamic
qualities of psychedelic
consciousness, or the
consciousness that arises with
psychedelics. And I'll let the
science guys sort out the
physiology of it. I know that
that's interesting, and I find
that often the physiological
discussion is carried out within
reductive metaphysical
assumptions, which really is not
helping our conversation right
now.
Emmy Vadnais: You mean the
conversation in general. We're
having a good conversation,
right?
Jeffrey Mishlove: I mean the
attempts to sort of understand,
to correlate what's happening in
the brain physiologically,
right, with the states of
consciousness that one is
experiencing. But often these
discussions take place within a
certain set of metaphysical
assumptions. And too often those
metaphysical assumptions tend to
be reductive. They tend to sort
of lean in the direction of
thinking that physical reality
is the dominant and determining
reality of one's experience. But
when you actually look at the
experiences that emerge in
psychedelics, that restrictive
metaphysical framework is
shattered,
Emmy Vadnais: yeah, well, I just
want to touch on it for now, and
primarily because there may be
those listening thinking, well,
this is just, you know, your
brain on on drugs, and it's
causing, you know, the whole
chemical reaction. Yeah, that's
been discussed with near death
experiencers and so forth, but
research has shown that there's
more going on with that. So I
definitely understand what
you're what you're saying, and
we can get into the veracity or
the trusting of these
experiences a little later in
our conversation, can you take
us more into some of your
experiences with your sessions
with LSD, to give us a taste of
what that was like for you?
Jeffrey Mishlove: Ooh, that's a
hard question. I mean, let's
give a context some very
influential books were written
based on a very limited number
of psychedelic experiences. So
Aldous Huxley wrote his very
important, beautiful book, The
Doors opening the doors of
perception after only one
Mescaline experience. And Huston
Smith wrote his book, his
collected reflections on
psychedelics, cleansing the
doors of perception after only
taking LSD six times over the
course of his lifetime. Michael
Pollan wrote his book, after
which is a very important, very
helpful book, but after only a
handful of psychedelic
experiences. So the challenge
that anyone faces coming into my
work are the challenges that I
have conveying my experiences is
just how long the journey was,
how many layers of consciousness
opened in that journey. It's not
simply a matter of opening 73
times. To the same interface is
that there is a cycle of death
and rebirth that reproduces
itself so that death breaks you
free of one level of reality,
physical reality in the
beginning and enters, takes you
into a non physical, spiritual
reality. And you work there for
a while, but if you work
consistently, eventually you'll
go through another death and
rebirth that will take you into
another level of reality, where
you have to learn the whole
rules of that level of reality,
which would then will be
followed, taking you to another
level. So the problem I have
with answering your question is
so many levels of reality. Any
if I focused on any one, I'd be
leaving out so many others. So
let me just say this in the
beginning, when I was looking
over the whole of my sessions
and putting them together, in
order to write this storyline of
what happened on those sessions,
I eventually differentiated or
distinguished five different
broad categories that my
sessions fell into. First,
having to do with personal mind,
your personal unconscious, your
personal story. Second,
collective mind, which has to do
with the collective psyche, the
psyche of humanity, the species
mind, the third archetypal mind,
which in my case, I'm primarily
addressing, not archetypes in
the Jungian sense, but
archetypes more in the Platonic
sense, the levels dimensions of
reality which lie outside time
and space and outside the
collective psyche, causal levels
of reality are the level of
oneness, the level where oneness
becomes the dominant reality,
and then beyond that diamond
Luminosity, a particularly clear
dimension of light that I
encountered and worked with in
the last five years of my work.
So all of my experiences, I can
kind of lay them out as a
sequential journey, starting at
the level of personal mind,
moving into the level of
collective mind, archetypal
mind, so on and so forth.
Emmy Vadnais: Well, I would love
to discuss each of those levels
you went into, what I recall
reading in your book that seemed
to be common themes of your
sessions were that it was, like
you said earlier, a letting go,
and that there was, it seemed a
lot of pain and suffering to
actually reach to these deeper
levels of consciousness. Can you
share what that was like for you
Jeffrey Mishlove: in the early
stage and when I was working at
the level of personal mind, that
the pain and suffering came in
the form of what Stan Grof is
very well discussed and
presented in his discussion of
the perinatal level of
consciousness, basically
sometimes reliving your birth,
but confronting the fundamental
existential questions that
dominate life and physical
reality. Is there any meaning in
the universe? Is there any
order, any design to it, any
intelligence of it? Because at
just the physical level,
everything we love, everything
we know, will be destroyed at
death. Is there any reality
beyond death? I mean, that's and
therefore you, you have to face
the deepest levels of
metaphysical angst in order to
move through this until
eventually your identity is just
crushed and shattered. That's
easier for some people to
undergo than it is for other
people. But you, you have to
surrender your time, space,
identity, in order to gain
access to the next level of
reality. At that next level of
reality, I continue to have a
deepening confrontation with
pain, suffering and violence. It
was so deep and it lasted so
long, and it seemed to encompass
so many hundreds of 1000s of
persons in so many 1000s of
years that I eventually came to
the decision that this was not
some didn't represent a
deepening or cleansing or
healing of my personal psyche,
that what was being healed here
was some aspect of the
collective psyche of humanity
itself, that something was using
my sessions in order to set in
motion a reconciliation and a
healing of levels of pain that
were fundamentally collective,
not personal, And then more
levels of death and rebirth,
where the nature of death and
suffering changes the deeper you
go. But the basic principle is
pretty simple, if you want to
experience oneness with God, or
if you want to experience a deep
experience of the nature of the
mind of the universe. So the
problem is our historical
consciousness is just too small
if you want to literally
experience it. I mean, it's one
thing to think about it, but to
actually immerse yourself in the
communion with these levels of
reality, your small identity has
to be surrendered, and you have
to flow, be willing to flow into
a larger level of identity. So
eventually you're going into
levels of reality where it would
be a misrepresentation to think
that Chris Bache went and had
those experiences. Rather, Chris
Bache has to be destroyed,
dissolved in order for these
levels of consciousness to
manifest inside Chris Bache his
awareness. But the fact that I
remember those experiences
doesn't mean that my personality
identity was present when those
experiences were being had. It's
kind of like you have to lose
yourself, enter into communion
with the universe. And then when
you come back, you gather your
experiences back. And then my
personality synthesizes them,
digests them, trying to
integrate them. But it's, it's a
it's a pulsing. You learn to
sort of surrender completely,
open, breathe deeply. You
receive teachings, then you
bring it all back in, and then
you try to integrate it and
consolidate it.
Emmy Vadnais: What are some of
the teachings you received
Jeffrey Mishlove: that the
universe is a manifestation of a
single consciousness, a massive
consciousness beyond anything
that we've ever begun to grasp
in our Western religious and
philosophical traditions, that
it is an intent, that creation
is an intentional act. It is an
act of, I hate to use the word
design, because those theories
are problematic, but that there
is an intelligence manifesting
itself in time and space, that
we are part of this
intelligence, that our nature is
of the same nature as its
nature. So this is an ancient
idea. Atman is Brahman. The
essence of the individual is the
essence of the totality that
reincarnation is simply a fact
of life. I don't think we get
anywhere in trying to understand
existence, unless we understand
the pulse of life, unless we
understand that our current life
is just the most recent in many,
many repeating cycles of life
and death, that there is an
underlying logic to the
circumstances within which we
find ourselves. Of the hint the
Buddhists and the Hindus talk
about karma, that there is a
deeper intentionality working
itself out in the circumstances
of our of our existence, and
that in that our evolutionary
existence is not simply driven
by blind chance and mechanical
processes which are which are
purely mechanical, but that
there is a deeper intelligence
manifesting itself in the
circumstances of our life, in
the challenges that we are
facing and inviting us to become
more by the end of our life than
we were in the beginning. So
just a few touch points.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, yeah. Going
back to your experiences in
these sessions, it seems that
death and rebirth and a
purification process happened in
many, if not all of your
sessions, yeah, what did you
come to understand was the
reason for that
Jeffrey Mishlove: first, the
general structure of the
sessions, as I experienced them,
is that every session there's a
sort of a rhythm of a cycle with
variations, but basically the
first early hours of a session
are spent in some type of deep
purification process, deep
confrontation. And then if you
surrender to that process and
let it take you, it reaches a
culmination point. There is a
surrender, a Death-Rebirth
process, in which you are then
spun into Transpersonal,
ecstatic places for the
remainder of the session, and
then that runs its course. And
then the next session, however
many months between and I was
doing about five sessions a year
on average, starts you right
back into the purification part
and carrying you then forward
into the ecstatic portion. So
the purpose of the purification
and the purpose of the death is
simply cleaning, just cleaning,
cleaning, cleaning, cleaning.
When you eventually come to have
deep experience of the
fundamental identity. Theory of
your nature and the divine
nature are the infinite nature
that you are the infinite, then
it gives you a different
perspective on what it is that
was present, preventing you all
those years from realizing that
what was keeping you from it and
it's, it's this tight
conditioning of the psyche.
It's, it's, it's the type
conditioning which is associated
with your time space
consciousness. And that has to
be softened, it has to be
released. It has to be let go in
order to move into these
expansive places. So the the
Death-Rebirth cycle is actually
a purification cycle. In fact, I
learned that death is actually
an intense stage of
purification. Once you've died
many times, you learn that
truly, it's impossible to die.
What you are can die. The
structure of your life can die.
Reality as you have known it can
die, but the Phoenix always
rises. The essence of the person
always emerges in a different
reality with new potentials,
with new capacities. But it's
impossible to die. And the
reason we can't die is, I think,
because our nature is the nature
of the Divine. So the form can
die, but the essence cannot die.
Once you know that, then I began
to understand that the
experience of death, which kept
coming up in my sessions, was
actually an experience, an
advanced experience of
purification, when purification
reaches a critical portion
position so that it begins to
dissolve the fundamental
structures of what you had known
as real. Then you have reached
the death point, the death and
rebirth point, and death has
come back to grace you again. So
from my perspective,
experiencing death in a
psychedelic session, or to
experience horrendous suffering
or pain is actually it's an
exciting stage in the work. It's
not something to be avoided. A
lot of people worry about, oh, I
don't want to have a bad
session. We got to do everything
we can to avoid having a bad
session. But I think that's a
radical misunderstanding of the
depth of consciousness and the
power that this technique gives
you. In my experience, you come
you begin to understand that the
deeper the purification, the
deeper the ecstatic immersion,
so that you begin to welcome the
purification. You begin to
welcome the challenges that you
face, you begin to welcome the
bad sessions in order to
actualize a higher, more
intimate experience with the
Divine Consciousness. Now that's
assuming that you're working in
a completely controlled
environment. You have done all
the homework, you've done your
preparation, you can have a bad
session for a lot of bad
reasons. You can be in the wrong
place, the wrong time, not
preparing yourself, wrong set
and setting. Those can give you
bad sessions which are not of
the quality that I'm talking
about.
Emmy Vadnais: Yeah, I will share
that when I was in high school,
a group of friends wanted to do
LSD, or acid, as it was called,
as well, and I did not partake.
However, I was the sitter, and
my role was to make sure that
everybody did have a good
experience, which actually the
few times that that happened,
was always the case. But I know
you mentioned that a bad trip is
not necessarily a bad trip,
yeah? So you suggest that that's
part of the process, but one
needs to be have done the
preparation ahead of time to
know what they're getting into.
Yeah.
Jeffrey Mishlove: I mean,
psychedelics amplify
consciousness, and most people
will take us like, I don't want
to over generalize. Some people
take a psychedelic and what
they're looking for is a good
afternoon. A little more
openness to the life of the
universe, a little more openness
to the to the love that's in the
universe. And they they maintain
their the fundamental parameters
of their personality get softer
and expansive and let some of
these experiences in which is
perfectly fine, but if you if
you want to go into a deep dive,
if you want to explore the deep
structure of existence, if you
want to transcend space,
transcend time, move into the
deep future that requires a more
carefully laid out strategy in
working with these states. So
I'm not suggesting that the way
I work with these states is the
only way, beneficial way to work
with these states is simply for
me. See, as a philosopher, I was
looking for depth of immersion,
depth of understanding, and that
takes some serious, some serious
work.
Emmy Vadnais: So while we're on
the topic of this death and
rebirth, surrendering
purification, can you share with
us what is it that dies and
reborn? I know you outline in
your book a few different areas
that you've come to understand.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Yeah, well,
basically, this became a real
intellectual issue for me. I
mean, when you experience dying
and being reborn through
multiple levels of reality, it
then becomes a question, what is
it that's actually dying? You
may have deep and profound
experiences of dying years after
you've gone through ego death.
And it's not simply the ego
dying over and over and over
again. It's a different kind of
death. So at the at the appendix
in LSD, in the mind of the
universe, I have an appendix on
what dies and is reborn, and I
suggest four levels of maybe
beginning to address that
question. One of them is, what
dies is our personal ego. Second
is, what dies is some aspect of
the collective ego, of the
collective psyche. Third, what
dies is what I call the shamanic
persona, complicated concept.
But when you've been on the
journey for a long time, when
you move into psychedelic space,
you resume your psychedelic
persona. You resume your
shamanic persona. It's like, as
a friend of mine said, you walk
with the old ones once again.
You kind of, you've made the
transition often enough that you
you're and your shamanic persona
is the living integration of all
of your psychedelic experiences
up to that point in time. So
let's say in this case, it was
20 sessions in working at the
level of the collective psyche
into what I call the ocean of
suffering, you stabilize a
psychedelic identity, shamanic
persona that integrates all the
experiences that you have had of
Transpersonal states of
consciousness beyond your
physical consciousness. If you
are going to go into yet a still
deeper level of consciousness,
beyond where you had lived
before, then that shamanic
persona has to die. It has to
surrender in order for a new
category, instead of a category
of experiences, to emerge, and
for a still deeper shamanic
persona to emerge. And so I
think in some advanced sessions,
what is dying is the previous
identity that or the identity
which we had developed from
sustained psychedelic
experiences over many years. So
that's, I think, the third thing
is, I would suggest it's what I
call the shamanic persona, or
the shamanic self, is dying.
It's not the egoic self, it's
your psychedelic self, which is
dying. And then at a more subtle
level. I think what is dying is
actually some dimension of
consciousness itself. And this,
this gets harder to discuss
because it requires a more
subtle level of understanding.
But basically sometimes in my
late work, when I was working at
very deep levels of
consciousness. When I was
working in deep levels of divine
communion, I had the experience
that the divine level that I was
experiencing came itself into a
crescendo which opened up a
higher level of divine communion
than had been actualized up to
this point in time. Sri
Aurobindo says, when he's
talking in his metaphysical
system, he says, looking down,
the divine sees all the levels
of reality, that it's
manifested, but it's a one way
mirror, so the divine looking
down sees everything, but we,
who are the divine looking up,
tend to see only the level that
we are at. So it's a one way
mirror, and that means even at
Deep, deep levels, should we
say, there are aspects of divine
consciousness which cannot see
or experience de in distilled
deeper levels of divine
consciousness, and somehow, when
we do this work, we actually can
facilitate a communion which
takes place between two
different levels of divine
consciousness, far beyond space
time, far beyond personal
reality. And there is a
celebratory joy that takes place
when the divine wakes up to a
still deeper level of the
Divine. There is a communion
that takes place. There is a
joyful celebration when the
higher is able to infuse itself
more deeply into the lower. And
so I think that one of the
things, one way of thinking
about what dies in very advanced
stages, is some aspect of divine
consciousness itself.
Emmy Vadnais: And yet, according
to your experiences, that death
then precipitates a rebirth.
Typically, did you discover that
with consciousness itself as
well? Yes, the divine itself?
Jeffrey Mishlove: Yeah. I mean,
it's, again, we're, it's, it's
complicated, because we're
rushing into an area where
angels fear to tread. Right?
Emmy Vadnais: We're trying to
put language to an experience
that many sometimes, for
example, with near death
experiencers, they'll say, it's
ineffable. So I understand
there's a language barrier.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Well, there is
a language barrier. But for me,
the biggest issue is not the
language barrier. It is to lay
the foundation, to lay the
prerequisites, to put things in
place so that you people can
understand the language that
you're want to use to describe
these phenomena. And it's not
ordinary day language. It's not
everyday experience. It requires
kind of a conceptual reframe, a
conceptual understanding, so
that you can describe certain
things that lie far beyond our
ordinary sensate experience. But
in some ways, it's not that
different from what a near death
episode person experiences. In
fact, I find I feel the greatest
correspondence and collegiality
with people who have had deep
near death episode experiences
because deep nd ease are the
experiences of the closest
correlate to my experience with
deep psychedelic work. I think
if you work with psychedelics in
a focused way, over long periods
of time, you can access the same
dimensions of consciousness that
someone accesses with an n de a
Near-Death Experience. The
difference is that where, for
most people, the nd ear
experiences this only once in
their life. With sustained
psychedelics, you can go back
multiple times into this
territory. And because you can
go back multiple times, you're
taught, there are more nuances
that are brought out in terms of
how this all works in the
interplay of consciousness.
Emmy Vadnais: Can you help
expand the conceptual framework
for us? A little bit about what
that experience has been like
for you?
Jeffrey Mishlove: Let me narrow
it into one particular just to
take one example, when I was in
the work. Now, I guess four or
five years into the work, I
began to get systematic access
to archetypal reality, and I
began to have experiences every
time I went into my session, I
entered this level of reality
that I knew was more real than
space time, it was the primary
reality. Space Time was the
secondary reality. I had
encounters with vast beings that
I could not comprehend. I could
not wrap my mind around them,
but I knew that these were the
beings who were responsible for
creating space time and creating
fundamental conditions within
space time. But to have access
to these realities, everything
that I had known about human
history, about human thought,
everything about the history of
humanity, had to fall away,
because the entire collective
psyche had to fall away in order
to enter into levels of
consciousness that humanity as a
whole has not had access to or
has not experienced. Very few
number of people have access to
these deep dimensions of
reality, but even in archetype
or reality, you're dealing with
very profound levels of
consciousness. But there is
still dualism there. There is
still a sense of self and other.
Archetype and self are different
archetypes. So it's there is a
dualistic quality to it. When I
went beyond archetype of reality
into causal reality, that's the
signature of causal reality,
that all dualisms dissolve, so
that you begin to experience the
world in whatever aspect you're
experiencing it you're
experiencing. World as a
unified, single entity, a single
consciousness. I think it was
Plotinus who says the world
breathes as one, and that's the
experience there, that there is
a radical transparency that
opens where you are
fundamentally encountering the
wholeness of life that doesn't
negate differentiation. In fact,
it affirms differentiation, but
that differentiation is
experienced as different
manifestations of the single,
integrated whole, undivided
reality that we call God, or we
call the divine, or the one
that's a different category of
experience altogether from
archetype or reality.
Emmy Vadnais: Can you share a
little bit more about why it's
termed archetypal reality, or
that layer, for those who maybe
aren't familiar with archetypes,
Jeffrey Mishlove: I use the term
archetype in sort of two senses
here. One is Jung talked about
archetypes as the you know, the
primary themes, the repetitive
themes of human experience that
become concretized in forms, old
man, old woman, trickster,
jokester. You know those clacks
of shadow, and then so I think
of them as kind of archetypal in
the sense of the primary, the
dominant themes of the of the
collective psyche. I see the
second way in which archetypes
is used is in the Platonic
tradition, where Plato talks
about the discovery of a level
of reality that lies beyond
time, space altogether. And I
experience both. I experience
Plato's sense of archetypes. I
experience that reality, but not
in the way that Plato describes
it. Plato thinks of archetypes
as eternal principles within an
eternal being. So they are the
unchanging prototypes that are
used in creation, and they exist
within the mind of an
unchanging, divine, unchanging,
infinite being. That's not how I
experience those archetypes. I
experience them as living
entities, but living on a vast
scale of time and space, far
beyond anything that we know
inside time and space. But what
is shared is that for something
to manifest inside time and
space, it comes out of the
oneness, through these
fundamental intermediate
structures, which are very
profound, super intelligent,
super powerful structures, and
then focusing this energy down
into concretizing it,
concretizing it into eventually
manifesting in space, time,
reality as we know it, when I
experienced the collective
psyche and I experienced a lower
level of archetypes in Jung's
sense of archetypes, it was
similar to Jung's sense in that
there were these archetypal
themes within humanity, but I
did not experience what Jung
experienced as archetypes. I
didn't have the experience of
wise old man, wise old woman,
things like this. It's not that
I don't think those exist, but
what I experienced was humanity
as a single organism, over and
over and over again, as a single
organism, and that there were
metameridians within humanity
that wove all of our individual
lives into the life of the human
species as a whole. So I learned
that our minds are woven into
the collective mind. There are
aspects. They are seed crystals
within the collective mind. Even
our bodies and the diseases that
we have to manage are all part
of the body of humanity evolving
itself over long periods of
time. So it was archetypal in
the sense of trans individual
motifs within the human psyche.
But it wasn't the way, quite the
way Jung conceptualized it. So
basically, archetypes in this
way, reflect the insight that
there are dominant structures
that are super personal. They go
beyond the functioning of
individual beings, and then in
platonic sense, there are
metaphysical archetypes that
basically inform the
manifestation of time and space
itself.
Emmy Vadnais: So at the causal
level, you mentioned, this is
where you connect with the
divine intelligence, or what we
perceive as as God. I imagine
those. There may be people
listening, wondering. Did you
discover that there is a God
Jeffrey Mishlove: I generally
tend not to like to use God
language, though I do. The
reason I don't like to use God
language is because, as someone
who knows the history of world
religions pretty well, I also
know all the theologies that
have gone into God language, and
all the cultural limitations
that go into it, and all the
abuse that went into it, and all
the crimes and the horrible
things that have been done in
the name of God. And certainly
I'm not talking about God in
anything like that. And so I
would use the word the divine
instead of God. But that's
really that's just an end run,
because even the concept of the
Divine carries into it certain
carry overs from our time space
experience. And so on the one
hand, I want to affirm the idea
that there is this profound
generative intelligence
manifesting as time and space.
That time and space is not
something which is independent
of the Divine, but it is, in
classic Hindu thinking, it is
the manifestation of the body of
the Divine. So in that way, I
want to affirm a very wide
vision of the Divine of God, but
because I've gone so deeply into
the future and so deeply beyond
space and time, so many times,
My understanding or my feeling
for this cosmic principle. I
can't fit it inside the
theologies of the religions of
the world. It's just it's much
larger than that. And so I So on
the one hand, okay, I can call
it God, but then I have to
qualify that it's not this, it's
not that. It's not what you mean
by God here. It's not what you
mean by God there,
Emmy Vadnais: right? Like a lot
of people think of, at least in
the mono theistic traditions,
think of it as a individual or a
being that we're made in the
form of, right? And that's what
I think people are maybe curious
about, is what you discovered,
as far as you know, did you
connect with a being or beings,
or angels or other divine
entities? And if you could share
a little bit about what that
realm was like
Jeffrey Mishlove: in all the
years when I was doing this
work, and all the work I did, I
never encountered a being, a
divine being, said, I'm God, you
know, this is what I am. It
wasn't like that. It was like I
would go deeper into a level of
consciousness, and I would
experience a communion with this
consciousness. And this
consciousness would teach me. It
knew me, it would teach me and
show me things, and it would
crush me, and then bring me
forward into still deeper
levels. And I would go into
those deeper levels, and I would
enter into communion with those
levels and and I internalized
the energy of those levels, and
I was with this consciousness,
but it never crystallized into a
specific form. I always felt its
presence. It guided my sessions.
I could enter into dialog with
it. I could enter into communion
with it. It would, it would
dissolve me into itself. But it
never crystallized into a what
you might call a personality of
God, or a person of God, and it
just kept getting larger and
larger, deeper and deeper, more
and more vast. And I think that
many of our theologies of God,
or thinking about God, is really
based upon what I would call the
early encounters with an
infinite intelligence, that that
this infinite intelligence is
far larger, far too large to
ever be concretized in the
historical lineages that we
recognize in the world
traditions. It's It's infinite
in itself. In fact, when I was
in the deepest level of
consciousness that I ever went
into, when I was in the diamond
Luminosity work, and that's the
work that occupied me for the
last five years, when I was as
deep into the diamond Luminosity
as I had ever entered. And I was
far beyond time, space, reality.
I was dissolved in the luminous,
you might say, the body of the
Divine. All of a sudden, my
visual field turned 90 degrees.
A window opened up, and I saw
reality Far, Far in the
distance, and I saw a light in
that reality. And. Beam of light
came out of that reality and hit
me, and I was in the diamond
Luminosity condition, but this
light was so powerful it
shattered my mind. And it took
me minutes to recover from this,
and that's when I began to
realize it's an infinite
progression. The Divine is truly
an infinite reality, even using
this powerful method, I would
never get to the end of this
reality. And that's one of the
reasons why I would be much
gentler with myself if I were
doing this again today, because
I discovered see when I began
this work, I thought that the
purpose was to reach a state of
consciousness, to reach
enlightenment, or to reach
oneness with God, or to dissolve
into the primal void. And I had
known oneness with God at many
different levels, and I had
entered into the primal void
several times, and I learned
that there are different depths
of the primal void. And so now I
begin to understand that it's
not about getting to some end
state which is going to
magically transform your life.
It's a matter of opening up and
letting the love and
intelligence of the universe or
the divine into you as much as
you can bring it in, as much as
you can hold on to it as much as
you can distill into your the
fabric of your living existence,
your earthly existence. It's not
about getting to some end point.
It's about deepening the ongoing
communion that exists between
ourselves inside time and space
and this larger spiritual
reality,
Emmy Vadnais: very beautiful.
Can you share more with us about
the diamond Luminosity?
Jeffrey Mishlove: Light surfaces
many times in our psychedelic
work, I mean, every time you go
through a Death-Rebirth
experience, very typically,
people encounter the light, many
forms of light, and I had
encountered this light at many
different levels along the
journey. After I'd gone through
ego death, after I'd gone
through the ocean of suffering
work, after I'd gone through
archetypal reality, after I'd
gone into the causal level
reality. About 15 years into my
work. When I had been given so
many spiritual treasures, I felt
completely existentially
satisfied. I mean, I just I had
been to experience radical
Shunyata, emptiness of self,
oneness of all existence. Had
been offered so many treasures,
and then I went through yet
another cycle of death and
rebirth, and I accessed a level
of light, a dimension of light
that was so pure and so clear,
it absolutely stunned me, and it
became my sole objective in the
rest of my psychedelic work to
return to this reality. Because
once you touch what I'm calling
the diamond Luminosity, once you
touch it, it's a reality which
is so far beyond anything that I
had ever touched in any of my
earlier work that I just lost
interest in archetype of
reality. I lost interest in
causal reality. I wanted to get
back into this level of reality.
It's so pure. It's just
breathtakingly magnificently
pure, and the levels of ecstasy
associated with it are just
staggering. And in the next five
years of work, in 26 sessions,
which is 1/3 of my entire
journey, I only got access to
this level of reality four more,
four times. So in between those
four sessions were lots of
purification, more purification
at a very deep level, more
learning, more teaching, but
accessing this reality four
times. And I think as I look at
the world's literature, the
spiritual literature and
Buddhist literature is probably
the tradition that I know the
best. They call this level of
reality Dharmakaya, the clear
light of absolute reality. So it
is considered, in their
tradition, the the absolute
foundational reality of of of
time and space, all time and
space, reality, all the
galaxies, all the big bang
emerge out of this crystalline
light, which is a pre Samsara.
It's what we would call an extra
samsaric reality. It's outside
of the cycle of space and time.
So it's outside of physical
reality, and it's also outside
of the Bardos of post mortem
existence. It's outside. An
entire system. Once you touch
it, you just you're hopelessly
in love with it for the rest of
your life. It just is something
that illumines everything. I
understood what the Buddhists
meant when they said, touch it
once, it can undo hundreds of
years of living in the shadows
of karma, because it's such. It
has such a penetrating,
transformative effect impact
that just to touch it, it
changes your whole understanding
of existence, in your whole
experience of what it means to
be alive.
Emmy Vadnais: Is this also what
you refer to in your book as the
beloved?
Jeffrey Mishlove: Well, you
know, everybody has to find a
word to describe this
transcendent reality. You know,
we can talk about God, or we can
talk about the divine. Some
people call it the absolute
Taoism. Calls it the eternal Dao
Jewish mysticism calls it the
Ein Sof, the great nothingness,
the great emptiness. I call it
my beloved because when you in a
path of temporary immersion, you
move into intimacy with this
reality, and then you come back
out of it, and then you move
into intimacy, and you come back
out of it, and it becomes like a
love relationship, but it's a
love relationship which actually
dissolves the bodies of the two
different beings. The Communion
that arises is it's a deep and
profound spiritual communion.
And so I just adopted the
vocabulary that felt most
natural to me, and I called it
my beloved, the beloved. And so
yes, to me, the beloved
manifests itself at all sorts of
different levels. It's it's
manifesting itself at the early
level, early stages, the middle
stages and the advanced stages,
but in the end, you recognize
that you're always in dialog
with this profound creative
intelligence, which,
interestingly enough, feels more
like a she in my experience,
than a he. And I associate the
feminine side of God with the
act of creation, and what you
might think of as the masculine
side of God, as the radically
transcendent aspect of God. The
basic idea is that the primal
one divides into two. One stays
outside of space time. The other
manifests space and time, and
manifest all life within space
and time. So for me, the beloved
is more the feminine side of the
Divine, the Divine Mother.
Emmy Vadnais: Yes, it seems that
light is a theme in your
experiences, and also, how much
of a role did or does love play
in these experiences. For you,
Jeffrey Mishlove: it played,
eventually, a very large role.
There were some sessions in
which I encountered or was
blessed with experiences of
cosmic love, I mean, and it's
just, it's love, not like
anything I've ever experienced
before. I mean, it's just
absolutely shatters me and
overwhelmed me. I experience
that all of existence was
generated, not out of simply a
sheer power. I mean, can you
think the power of the Big Bang
and everything that emerged from
it, not only the intelligence
there, but that love, a
profound, cosmic love. Why is it
the very act of creation itself?
And that's obviously a kind of
love that's not like anything
that we know in human parlance.
It's not anything nearly that
small, but it is the it is the
fiber of the Divine, of the
Divine itself. And I think it's
you can think of it as love and
oneness are kind of two
different sides of the reality,
because love, if the world is
truly one, if it's all one, love
is the emotion of this oneness.
Love is the fact of oneness
asserting itself in a world of
duality. Yeah, love has been
really important, which really
surprised me, because you know
of the four yogas in Hinduism,
Yana, the path of the mind,
Raja, of the path of meditation,
Karma Yoga, bhakti yoga, bhakti
yoga, the yoga of loving
devotion, is the form of yoga
that I identified with the
least. I've always been more
intellectually oriented,
meditatively oriented, not
bhakti oriented. And yet. Began
to have a series of very
profound bhakti experiences that
it's kind of what led me to talk
about the beloved in this very
lover kind of context.
Emmy Vadnais: How much is love
the fabric of the Divine,
Jeffrey Mishlove: anything I say
at this point. I mean, first of
all, please forgive my hubris at
daring to describe the nature of
the Divine. I mean, come on, get
real. I mean, this is just like
so anything I say is going to be
totally inadequate to the
reality itself. So we could
describe the divine nature as
infinite knowledge, infinite
power, infinite love. And all of
those are equally true. And I'm
sure that there are other
qualities which we want to add
to that. But then let's start
with those three. The challenge,
I think, of understanding the
love aspect of the Divine is
because life, as we experience
it, is an often dirty, nasty,
mean, cruel thing, and so any
suggestion that somehow the
world as we know it, with all of
its pain and suffering, is
somehow a manifestation of a
supremely loving Consciousness,
it's just it's horrendously
difficult to reconcile those and
and I understand that. I mean as
a as a philosopher of religion,
I understand the challenge, and
I think the only way of
overcoming that challenge is to
really understand the deep
structure, or the deep
intentionality that's
manifesting itself in the
creation itself, in the our
evolving universe, in the
project of the universe, you
have to radically expand your
time horizon to understand
what's taking place here. You
have to understand that the
human condition, as we currently
know it, is just a small.in a
long developmental process that
not only has been going on for
13 point 7 billion years, but
will continue to go on for 13.7
plus more years. So that, as Sri
Aurobindo said, we are a
transitional species. We are
actualizing ourselves within a
long developmental trajectory.
And if we think that, Well, God
must not be real, because we
could have written, done a CH,
we could have done a better job
creating universe. If I had
infinite power, I could have
certainly created a better
universe in this where children
die and all the terrible things
that happened to us, but that
assumes that we know what the
divine intention is, what the
project of existence is. And I
think we are like children and a
playpen. We are just beginning
to get a grip on the enormity of
the project of existence. We're
just beginning, really since
Hubble in modern theories of
cosmology, beginning to
understand the size and depth
and textures. I think
psychedelics are kind of like
the Hubble of psychological
insight. They are giving us an
experience of the depth in which
consciousness exists. But that
just gets us, at the beginning
of beginning, to comprehend,
what is the project? What will
humanity be 5 billion years from
now? What will we be a million
years from now, or even 100,000
years from now? The Divine seems
to think on on that scale. We
have to radically stretch
ourselves to think on that
scale. So the problem of
suffering really challenges our
understanding of the role of
love, the principle of love in
the divine nature. But once we
have an experience, an
experiential access to some of
the deeper trajectories of the
Divine intent, then things begin
to make more sense. I think the
Divine is creating a
masterpiece. I mean, I think
refined, elevated, potentiated
human experience is a
masterpiece of creation that
takes 1000s, 1000s, millions of
years, billions of years to to
orchestrate and to bring
forward, especially since it's
it's not done. We're not we're.
That we intentionally cooperate
and participate in this creative
process. It's not being done to
us. It's something we are
carrying forward in the very
fiber of our being. But we we
really have to kind of grasp the
scale of things to even
understand our present
circumstances
Emmy Vadnais: at the same time,
it sounds like you found that
the Atman is Brahman, that you
found that we are part of the
Divine, and the Divine is part
of us, yeah,
Jeffrey Mishlove: yeah, and that
there's really, there's very
little that's new in any of the
experiences that I lay out, I
mean the vision of reality, the
cosmology that emerges out of
psychedelic work, is
fundamentally the same as the
cosmology that emerges out of
deep, mystical, spiritual
traditions in the very highest
and most refined levels of
spiritual traditions in the
world. It's not that we're
bringing something new to the
table, maybe a little bit, but
we're not bringing a whole lot
of new to the table. What we
have is a different protocol, a
different strategy, for
accessing these very deep levels
of reality, which yield deep
insights into the structure of
existence, but you will find the
same fundamental cosmology
emerging out of the great
spiritual traditions of the
world.
Emmy Vadnais: Since you brought
up the Hubble telescope, and
we've primarily been talking
about what we consider it's just
another word as consciousness.
What did you discover in our
universe, what we consider, sort
of the physical universe, what
we consider as space or outer
space? Did you traverse that
aspect of experience in your
sessions?
Jeffrey Mishlove: I wasn't taken
into the to journeys into our
galaxy or journeys into other
galaxies that just wasn't part
of the work. For me, other
people may have those experience
or says or have had those
experiences. So while I was
given this a particular session
called the cosmic tour. I called
it the cosmic Tour, where I was
taken on this cosmic tour and
shown so many things, much of
which I could not reproduce when
I came back into my time space
consciousness, because my time
space consciousness just did not
have the vocabulary, the
intellectual tools to articulate
those and that's why I've often
wished that I had a PhD in
physics and astrophysics, that I
would better be able to
articulate some of the
experiences that I was given.
But I didn't spend a lot of time
traveling within time and space.
It was more a matter of going
underneath time and space and
getting into the underlying deep
structure that that informs time
and space and our experience in
time and space.
Emmy Vadnais: I feel like I
recall in your book that you
were shown that like the
universe. I think you've kind of
already said this, like goes on
and on, essentially. Is that
right? Do I recall that
correctly? Yeah.
Jeffrey Mishlove: I mean,
basically it there are two
different models of the
universe. One is that it'll keep
expanding forever, and the other
is that we reach a point where
there's a maximum expansion,
expansion, and then it begins a
contraction. So is it a
pulsating universe, expanding
and contracting and then re
expanding, or is it an
infinitely expanding universe? I
don't really have an answer to
those, to that particular
question, but clearly, the
universe is just it's on tear.
Yeah, it's going on for billions
and billions and billions of
years. Yeah. Now that's a
deflating insight. If you think
that a human being is simply 100
year old being, if we're simply
100 year old being, then we're
basically sand on the beach
beside the ocean. We don't
really get to participate in
that deep future. But if
reincarnation is true, and I
think there's plenty of factual
evidence that it's true, if
reincarnation is true, and if
it's true, that our essence is
indestructible, and that we take
everything that we've learned
and roll it over into continued
learning over 1000s and 1000s
and millions of years, then we
get to actually participate in
this divine unfolding. It's not
somebody else's future or some
other future, but it's our
future. We are, you know, we are
co participants, eternal
participants in. This eternal
process
Emmy Vadnais: in your
experiences, you talked about
the birth of the future human,
yeah. Can you shed a little
light on what that is about?
Jeffrey Mishlove: Yeah, there's
a chapter in the book called The
Birth of the future human, and I
really think this is maybe the
most important chapter of the
book, and it's also the one that
caught me completely by
surprise. I wasn't expecting
anything like this in my in my
journey. I mean, I thought first
it was a personal journey about
personal healing, personal
awakening. Then when that
expanded, I still thought, Okay,
it's a journey about an
individual being given
experiences that provide insight
into the deep structure
underlying our lives. But then
about halfway through my work,
starting in about 1990 and
continuing through 1995 I began
to be given a series of visions
that were internally consistent,
that were dropped into my
sessions talking about
humanity's evolutionary destiny,
where humanity was in its
evolutionary journey, that we
were coming into a turning point
in history, that we were coming
into a culmination of a
crescendo of the evolutionary
journey that was going to
catalyze a tremendous
transformation inside humanity
that would mark a true before
and after moment in time, that
and that there was A profound
spiritual transformation that
was coming to a crescendo,
coming to a head, and it this
kept repeating itself in my work
in different ways, but I did not
know how the universe was ever
going to pull this off. I didn't
understand how it didn't didn't
show me how it was going to
happen. And then about a year
and a half later, when I was in
the middle of the diamond
Luminosity work. So I was
working at a very deep level. In
one particular day, I
experienced, I was given an
experience taken far into the
future. I had died and dissolved
into the human psyche. So when I
say I was taken into the future,
it's not so much that Chris
Bache was taken into the future.
It's like ask the human family.
I experience the human family in
a trans temporal dimension of
time and in a time expanded
state, and I experience, in an
accelerated way, the death and
rebirth of the entire human
family. I experienced a profound
geopolitical crisis that seemed
to be being seeded by a
cascading series of ecological
crises, but I experienced some
type of fundamental loss of
control, an unraveling of life
at the basic level, a tremendous
global crisis that was so deep
and so profound that no one was
going to be able to isolate
themselves or protect themselves
from it. It was a crisis so deep
it was going to bring humanity
to our collective knees. But
just when the crisis reached its
peak, I experienced that. We
moved through it, and then there
was the beginning of a lightning
we made it through this crisis,
and when we began to pick
ourselves up in this post crisis
period of history, we've
discovered that we had been
profoundly changed. Something
happened in this crisis that
opened us up changed us at the
very center of our being, one
way of talking about is that
there was a birth of oneness.
That oneness instead of being a
private mystical experience of a
very select few, oneness was
born within the human psyche as
a whole. We tapped into certain,
certain depths of our nature
that allowed us to become first
of all, it allowed us become no
longer enemies with all of the
human beings, all the divisions
of history that have been used
to justify, you know,
differences of race, differences
of class structure, difference
of religion, all those
differences which we think of
and have used to divide history
national identity. All those
were dissolved, all those were
transcended, and we began to
experience a fundamental oneness
at the core of our life and all
life itself. And this led to a
creativity began to reinforce
itself, and we began to create
new social forms, new.
Structures. And eventually, over
time, I came to understand that
what this was about was that
there was a pressure building up
within the collective psyche,
and that this pressure was
taking humanity through a
collective Death-Rebirth process
that represented a fundamental,
irreversible shift in the
collective psyche. I think of it
as the shift in the plate
tectonics of the collective
psyche, so that any child born
after we make this transition
will be operating within a
psychic field which is
fundamentally different, more
elevated, more spiritually
informed then we are operating
out of now, or we've been
operating out of the past. Well,
that this isn't simply a crisis
with economic ramifications or
industrial ramifications or
political or civic
ramifications. It's a revolution
in the fundamental structure of
the human psyche. It's a it's a
revolution in our human nature.
Now I think that we have entered
this, this period, this process.
I think we're in the very early
stages of it. We're just getting
started on it. I think the 21st
Century will be pivotal in going
through this transformative
crisis. I wasn't given a lot of
details on names, dates and
places and stuff like that, what
I was given was this core
experience of what it's going to
feel like for the human family
when they go through a
collective dark night of the
soul, go through a collective
ordeal that eventually will
awaken an underlying revolution
in the human psyche, a spiritual
opening of the human psyche. Now
I'm not alone. This is nothing
you know unique to me. I mean,
this is an insight that many
spiritual teachers have had,
many indigenous people have had,
many psychedelicists have tapped
into this understanding. And I
think this is the flow of
history underneath us that we
can tap into in different ways.
I think many of the spiritual
mystical traditions have tapped
into and begin to understand
some of this dynamic. But I
think we're coming into a
century where we are at a
critical turning point. I really
believe that the 21st Century is
pivotal here, because if we just
look at the scientist scientific
data of on the ecological
crisis, if we look at what is
now an increasingly shared
understanding of the depth of
ecological disruption that we're
going into and the change of
interrupting, well, I won't go
into the scientific material,
but clearly, we cannot continue
on Earth operating the way that
we have been operating in the
past. We don't have enough
resources. Inequality is just
too extreme. I don't think we
can continue to govern the earth
or out of the psychological
structure of the ego. The ego is
fundamentally a divided psychic
structure. And I think the ego
is a beautiful thing. It's a
magnificent thing, but it
fundamentally is cut off from
the core of existence, the
foundation of existence and each
other, we need to evolve into a
higher level of consciousness,
which is post egoic, in order to
have the wisdom to rise to the
challenges that the ego has
created for humanity over its
last 1000, multi 1000 year
history. And I think we will, I
think we will come through this
crisis. I think we're going to
go through unbelievable
suffering in the centuries
ahead, but I do believe that we
come through it, because that's
at least, that's been the nature
of my experience. We do come
through this, and humanity does
make this evolutionary
Emmy Vadnais: pivot? Well, I
know there's more you can share
about this topic, and I think
we'll do a whole other
conversation about the birth of
a future human. And also we want
to talk more about
reincarnation, yeah, can you
share why you stopped these LSD
sessions in 1999
Jeffrey Mishlove: Well, I talk
about this in the book, in the
last chapter, coming off the
mountain, and I basically boil
it down to two reasons, pain and
heartache. My subtle energy
system. Psychedelic states open
you up to huge flows of energy.
You're taking an enormous flows
of energy. It takes years and
years to manage the flows of
energy. And I basically realized
that I was running so hot that
even months after my session was
over, I was still running. I was
permanently uncomfortable in my
body because the quantum. Day of
energy that was running in my
subtle energy system, my Qi
system, or my Prana. So that was
telling me that it was time to
let my body calm down and let
that subtle energy system find a
new equilibrium point. But the
main reason I stopped was
because of heartache, because
once you dissolve into the
Divine Light, once you dissolve
into diamond Luminosity and
dissolve into the crystalline
nature of consciousness at this
very, very deep level, coming
back into time and space is just
difficult. It's very hard. It
you know you lose your your zest
for living inside time and
space, when you know how much
more is available to you outside
of time and space, and going
into and coming out of, and
going into and coming out of
this was it just was, became too
painful. And so eventually, my
beloved and I came to an
agreement that I would not
return to these states of
consciousness until I could stay
with her forever. And that's
really when, that's really what
lies behind my stopping. I just
had to stop and for the rest of
my life, focus on internalizing
the gifts that I had already
been given, rather than trying
to acquire or be given more
gifts.
Emmy Vadnais: You've been in
communication with Stanislav
Grof and Ralph Metzner, who are
pioneers in this area of
psychedelics and psychological
consciousness, cosmic
exploration. Have you shared
your experiences with them, and
what have they shared with you
about that
Jeffrey Mishlove: I've been in
dialog with both of them, and I
have shared my sessions with
Stan, and he quotes from some of
my sessions scattered throughout
his books, some of them are
anonymous, and in some of the
later works, they're they're
identified as mine. And Stan,
very graciously wrote a
beautiful forward to my book,
Dark, night, early dawn, which
was my first major book on
psychedelic work, psychedelic
theory. I think that there's a
fundamental I mean, we have
different projects, different
agendas. I mean, Stan is a
therapist. He's a world healer.
He's he has worked with 1000s of
individuals and collected 1000s
and 1000s of session experiences
and organized them into an
understanding of the vast scope
of the landscape that one
experiences in these states. My
work has been different. I'm
really been doing an individual
journey penetrating deeper and
deeper and deeper into the
universe. So I see our work as
complementary in that way. But
yeah, I've been in dialog with
both of them. Yeah, I love them
both very dearly. Ralph has now
transitioned on, I love them
dearly. We've been in dialog.
Ralph gave me feedback on LSD in
the mind of the universe before
I published it. So yeah, I
consider them close colleagues
and good
Emmy Vadnais: friends, so they
were supportive of your process.
Yes, yeah, that's wonderful. The
last area I want to touch on
with you is that, of course,
people listening, some may
think, Well, how much can we
trust these experiences? And I
know that you had a conversation
or an interaction with Kenneth
ring, who is the co founder of
the International Association
for near death studies, I was
wondering if you could share a
little bit about your
correspondence with him, or what
you have to say or say about the
how much we can trust your
experiences?
Jeffrey Mishlove: Yeah, that's a
really important question. I
mean, how? How do we know that
we aren't simply exploring some
hidden corner of my personal
unconscious or even some hidden
corner of the collective psyche?
I mean, I know I understand how
radical the assertions are that
I'm making, making them sound
almost Cavalier. How do we know
that we can trust these
experiences to be what I'm
suggesting that they are? And
Ken ring and I had a dialog
about this. Ken is a wonderful
scholar, and his good friend,
and so after he had read LSD in
the mind of the universe, he
wrote me, and we went back and
forth around precisely this
issue. How trustable are these
deep psychedelic experiences?
How do we know that they're not
better understood as a man?
Manifestation of something
coming out of the personal
psyche or the collective psyche
that they really are have these
metaphysical, ontological
ramifications that I've been
interpreting them to have. And
so he and I went back and forth
in an exchange of letters about
this, and Ken worked me over
pretty hard. I mean, he was
asking hard questions, and I
loved it. And eventually we
decided that this was a dialog
that was worth sharing. So we
wrote it up in an essay called
our deep psychedelic
experiences, trustable, and we
published it online, and it's
available. If you just Google
that title, you'll find it, and
I in it, I try to address that
specific issue, and I also bring
in other people's experiences,
which provide levels of
objective verification, because
many psychedelic experiences
lead us to have experiences that
can be verified because they
relate to something inside time
and space, the deeper
cosmological experiences cannot
be verified in that way, but the
existence of verifiable
experiences when they refer to
time space reality certainly
lends points to the credibility
of the deeper cosmological
experiences. So I bring in a lot
of evidence in the footnotes and
in the literature that speak to
the issue of the trustability of
these experiences. I think most
of our doubt about their
trustability is completely
understandable, but I think it
comes from first not having
personal experience of these
states and trying to understand
them within a metaphysical
framework that's based upon time
of physical sensation,
experience, mental experience,
sensate experience. We're trying
to understand these things
within a framework which is
smaller than we want they need
to be. It's just like, you know,
we had to have 10s of 1000s of
near death episodes in print and
published before the medical
community began to take them
seriously, because they didn't
want to interpret these as an
indication of the existence of
spiritual reality. They wanted
to interpret it as something
going on inside the physical
process. And I think that's true
for psychedelic experiences too.
We need to, we need to develop a
more sophisticated ontology,
metaphysical understanding, even
to have a framework for
understanding some of these
experiences, and this is why I
didn't rush into print on any of
these experiences. I mean, after
I stopped my work in 99 I really
spent 20 years digesting them,
analyzing, looking at other
people's experiences, looking at
the other metaphysical systems,
and trying to put all the pieces
of the jigsaw puzzle together
before I published LSD in the
mind of the universe. So a lot
of thought, it's not simply, you
know, here's my experience. You
can trust it because I had it.
It's not that at all. It's
really, what we really want is
not just one person's
experiences, but we want to have
a critical protocol with which
involves many people's
experiences, putting all of our
experiences on the table and
finding out which one of the
which of these experiences are
idiosyncratic and which one of
them are common ground. We
haven't really begun that work
yet. We're in the early stages
of doing that. But this is
psychedelics are not going to go
away. We're going to be using
them for decades and hundreds of
years to come. And this
challenge of collective
verification of the visions that
emerge in these states is just
getting started, is just moving
forward.
Emmy Vadnais: It sounds like
you're suggesting that we need
more research in this area,
which can be tricky because of
the taboo and the legalities
around it, although it seems
that with other studies on
Psilocybin and other
psychedelics, that maybe that's
beginning to shift.
Jeffrey Mishlove: I think it is
beginning to shift. I think
what's happening is
psychedelics. The psychedelic
community is demonstrating, with
increasing convincing research,
that these substances have a
tremendous power to heal, and
that's what's bringing them back
into public discussion. We're
going to find, over time, that
the same amplifying qualities
which allow them to have a
therapeutic impact continued, if
we continue to apply these
methodologies, they continue to
open up deeper and deeper levels
of consciousness, and when we
get deep enough, eventually we
begin to hard. Harvest the
philosophical and cosmological
significance of these
substances. I gave a talk at the
Herodotus conference at Oxford
last fall, and I called it
seizing the philosophical and
cosmological significance of
psychedelics. We're not there
yet, but I think we're going
there. We will get there to move
in this direction.
Emmy Vadnais: Well, Chris, I
know this is a very large topic,
and I just want to ask this last
question, and I'm excited we're
going to have another
conversation. Is there anything
you want to share more today
about psychedelics and the
cosmic mind?
Jeffrey Mishlove: I want to
return again to the cautionary
words that we shared in the very
beginning. This is, this is
deep, challenging, demanding
work. You do not try to climb
Mount Everest unless you have
all the best equipment and all
the best guys going with you.
You do not want to go deep into
the psyche unless you have all
the best equipment and the best
context for doing this type of
work. So I want to affirm that.
I want to affirm the importance
of a rigorous protocol. If you
want to go deep, you have to
have a particularly rigorous
protocol, protocol first just to
survive the encounter, but also
to take experiences and distill
them into increasingly clear,
clear, articulate experiences
that are not lost into you know
that your mind just doesn't
swallow them up, you can really
bring back the core of the
experience. Once you do that,
once you've taken all the
cautions, all the precautions,
and once you have spent time
doing your due diligence in
this, then I think we are at the
cusp of a completely new chapter
in philosophy of consciousness,
a new chapter in our
understanding what is happening
in existence. Why is human
existence the way it is? Why is
existence the way it is? What's
going on underneath the surface?
What is the nature of the the
intelligence that's manifesting
the body of the universe? What
is the nature of the
intelligence that's manifesting
inside our own hearts and mind
over time. This, I think, is the
beginning of a whole new chapter
of philosophical and spiritual
reflection. In conclusion, I
just wouldn't want to leave with
your viewers a sense of
excitement or this tremendous
turning point that we are at
this pivot point of this
profound deepening of our
understanding, of our
experience, of these deep
structures of reality, and a
deepening of our understanding
of what's taking place behind
the scenes and the opportunity
to enter into conscious
communion with the source of our
existence, which was previously
maybe just the privileged domain
of very, very advanced
meditative and contemplative
mystics. But now we have a new
modality that allows even
ordinary human beings to have
just a touch taste of these
experiences, which can be life
changing,
Emmy Vadnais: and for people to
know the risks and the benefits
right. Because, you know, each
person might have a different
reaction, a response to these
kinds of substances.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Yeah, there
are screening criteria, and more
important, more criteria that
will be weird, which are used in
order to make sure people who do
this work are safe and only
people who should do this work
do do this
Emmy Vadnais: work. Chris Bache,
thank you so much for being with
me today. Thank you so much for
going beyond the Beyond and
bringing it back for all of us.
I really have enjoyed our
conversation, and I look forward
to our next one.
Jeffrey Mishlove: Thank you,
Emmy. I have enjoyed our
conversation, too. Thank you for
the work you're doing. We need
all the wisdom we can get in the
years ahead.
Emmy Vadnais: Yes, and for those
of you watching or listening,
thank you for being with us,
because you are the reason that
we are here.
Unknown: You book
Emmy Vadnais: three in the new
thinking aloud dialog series is
UFOs and UAP. Are we really
alone? Now available on Amazon.
Jeffrey Mishlove: You can now.
Download a free PDF copy of
issue number eight of the new
thinking allowed magazine or
order a beautiful printed copy.
Go to new thinking allowed, dot,
O, R, G.