Manda Scott: Chris, welcome to
the accidental goals podcast.
How are you and where are you?
This slightly gray December day
over here, but it might be
lovely where you are.
Chris Bache: Hi, Amanda. It's
pleasure to be here with you.
I'm speaking to you from
Weaverville, North Carolina,
which is just outside of
Asheville, North Carolina, and
it's a sunny day here. It's
going to be in a lovely
afternoon in the mid 40s. Wow.
Manda Scott: Okay, now I have
weather envy, but, but hey,
you're in a swing state, which
at some point we might get onto.
That must have been quite
entertaining for a brief period
of time. Let's not go there.
That's two pages. All right. So
you've written a number of
books, you've had a very
inspiring life, and my
projection onto you, which I am
almost certain is not true, is
that you have the answers to
life, the universe and
everything. So we'll lay that
one to bed as it's my
projection, and you don't see it
that way, just so it's clear
we're there. And from where you
are, what is most alive for you
at this inflection point of
humanity?
Chris Bache: Well, we've just
gone through an election in our
country, which was for the
liberal side of the continent
like me, was very disappointing
and very upsetting what's
happening in politics, in my
country and in many countries
around the world, this whole
movement to the conservative
right is very much of concern,
especially since they are
denying fundamental facts that
are clearly critically important
for humanity To address. First
and foremost is the fact of
global climate change. And yeah,
so that's happening. And in my
book, LSD, in the mind of the
universe, I have a whole chapter
on what I call the birth of the
future human, which summarizes
all the transmissions that were
given to me over a 20 year
course of high dose LSD sessions
about humanity's future, where
we are in our evolutionary
development, the critical crisis
that we are moving into, the
birth of of a new form of
humanity coming out of that
crisis. So when I and a great
future for humanity, but for
deep, spiritualized realization
to emerge in humanity, there
must take place, first, a dark
night of the soul, a collective
dark night of the soul. So I see
what's happening politically
against that backdrop of a
growing dismantling of
assumptions, a growing
unraveling of our social
contracts, and a growing global
crisis, which seems to be
generated by seems to be
generating by a series of eco
crises.
Manda Scott: Okay, so that gives
us an opening into the birth of
the future human. For those
watching on YouTube, my cat is
on the desk. It's easier to let
him just ramble across, and then
he'll go away and it'll be fine
before we go there. So it seems
to me, let's just address the
politics, because it's a lie for
everyone. This is going out at
the start of the new year 2025.
Is going to be the year when
everything changes. America
sneezes, the world gets a cold,
and nothing will be the same,
particularly not geopolitics is
about to shift enormously. I
think a US Russian Alliance has
never happened before, and it
looks like it's arising in real
time. And it seems to me, 71
million people voted vote for
Trump. That means, by my
reckoning, 259 million didn't.
And yet there's been effectively
a bloodless coup by the fascist
right. And yet no amount of
ideology, however forcefully
they try to impose it can
actually overcome biophysical
reality. You cannot stop climate
change by pretending it's not
happening. The ostrich position
is only useful until the flood
waters fill the hole that you've
stuck your head in. Yeah. So it
seems almost to me that also to
me, that the shifts that we
need, need to be inner and
collectively inner, which is
exactly the field that you're
working in. Yeah, and we don't
want to go back over everything
that you experienced, but I
wonder if you've got a kind of
an elevator pitch of where you
started and where it took you to
in terms of your own spiritual
process is that something that
we could go into sure
Chris Bache: I can give you a
kind of a quick overview. I
began my psychedelic work when I
was just hired as a university
professor in Northeast Ohio, and
I began this work as a pretty
well educated. Dedicated
agnostic with strong atheistic
inclinations. That's where all
the years of graduate school had
brought me. But just when I
started teaching, I came across
the work of Stanislav Grof and
his book, realms of the human
unconscious, changed the
direction of my life. I saw the
importance of his work from my
discipline, which was philosophy
of religion. I'm not a
psychologist, I'm not a
therapist, I'm a professor of
philosophy of religion. And so I
began an underground regimen of
psychedelic therapy because I
knew that in order to speak
intelligently using this new
methodology, you had to do the
work yourself. And even though
it was illegal by this time,
this was 1978 when I started my
career, I started my psychedelic
work in 1979 psychedelics were
illegal. I made a decision to do
this work in underground
fashion, completely isolated. My
never let my students and most
of my faculty never knew what I
was doing. In this regard, I
continue this work for 20 years.
I started it when I was 30, and
I finished it when I was 50, and
I did 79 high dose LSD sessions,
which is an a very aggressive
protocol. I don't recommend this
protocol today.
Manda Scott: You did this so we
don't have to, as far as I can
see, and I'm enormously
grateful.
Chris Bache: Yeah. And then I
spent another 20 years digesting
those experiences, writing about
them, integrating them, trying
to integrate them, and written
two books based on those
experiences. One of them is dark
night, early dawn, which came
out in 2000 and probably the
more important one for a wide
audience, is LSD in the mind of
the universe, which came out in
2019 so I did this work for 20
years, and then LSD in the mind
of the universe came out 20
years later, after I stopped,
Manda Scott: after you'd
integrated a lot of what
happened, and after you were
also, it seems, from the book,
just beginning to be able to
start talking about it, because
you had issues where you
couldn't speak. You physically
couldn't speak, because he
couldn't speak of what you
understood and what you knew.
Can you tell us a little bit
about that that seemed to me
quite an integral part of what
was happening?
Chris Bache: Well, I love
teaching, I love working with
the students. I just really love
being in the classroom. And I
knew that if I began to speak
openly about psychedelics in the
70s, 80s, 90s, even, I very
likely would lose my perfect my
position at the University, and
so I could not speak openly
about my work. I mean, I really
I spoke indirectly by giving
teaching courses on psychedelic
therapy and Stan Grof work and
other people's research. But
like I didn't, wasn't able to
own my experiences publicly at
my university until the very,
very tail end of my career, I
retired in 2011 in order, a
little bit early, in order to
give me time to bring forward
what I consider my most
important work, and my
conviction is that psychedelics
represents a revolution, not
just in therapy, not just a
clinical revolution, but a
revolution in how we do
philosophy and this methodology
is that we move systematically
into very carefully controlled
Non-ordinary states. We
experience them as consciously
as we can. We bring them back,
preserve them, write a detailed
written account within 24 hours,
and then spend some time
digesting them, integrating them
with our other bodies of
knowledge, then going back into
that state and coming in. So
this method of systematically
entering into Non-ordinary
states and coming back
represents a new methodological
platform for the doing of
philosophy. So what we're
looking at is what the emergence
of what I would call a
psychedelic philosophy, the
psychedelic that's grounded on
the systematic application of
Non-ordinary states of
consciousness through the use of
psychedelics.
Manda Scott: Yeah, can I
interrupt you, because this is
already opening doors, and I'd
like to go down a few of them.
So we're talking about
integrating with other systems.
And in the book, you are
becoming quite deeply involved
in some Buddhist practices. Were
they Buddhist, I think. And so
it strikes me, within the
shamanic world, we get a lot of
people who want to go off and do
Ayahuasca or do mushrooms. And
it seems to me there it's short
cutting and not universally. I
have spoken to people who are
absolutely prepared to go and
spend six months in the forest
alone with the plants and
integrate it, but there are an
equal number of people who seem
to think they can go from point
A to point. Ed without actually
doing any of the steps in
between. And what I'm think, I'm
hearing from you is that the
steps in between are absolutely
crucial and that they need to be
undertaken in a structured
fashion, in in spite of the fact
that it we feel to me, to be
moving away from the reductive,
scientific space where atoms
move around like billiard balls,
and everything is predictable,
as long as we have enough data
points to a point of where
everything is emergent and
complex and actually nothing is
predictable, but experience, the
phenomenology of living, is what
matters, and the more than human
world comes in and takes part,
it seemed to me, reading,
certainly the second book, to an
extent the first, but
particularly in the second, that
there was an extraordinary
coherence. You had a six year
gap in the middle, and yet when
you when you went back, you
basically took off. It was like
a serial Dream, which those of
us who practice dreaming you
sometimes night after night
after night after night, you're
in the same story. And you were
getting this. You were in an
almost linear progression,
except it was more fractal than
linear, I would say, you
building on previous knowledge,
and you were being taught quite
clearly. And so can you unpick
for us a bit of the structure
that you see that is useful in
order for this to be something
that helps us move towards being
future humans.
Chris Bache: Okay, well, there
several things rolled into your
observations and all good.
They're all good observations.
So some process comments. First,
I think integration is very
important. We're finding we have
the technology, the chemical
technology, to trigger very deep
states of consciousness, but
these states of consciousness
may have very little lasting
impact on how our deeply
ingrained psychological cultural
habits, if we don't take time to
sit with these experiences and
integrate them as deeply as we
can into our embodied existence.
And over the course of my work,
I learned that even though I was
paying a lot of attention and
doing as good a job as I could
to integrate each individual
session and doing an adequate
job. I think I still
underestimated the long term
challenges of integrating an
entire spiritual journey, but I
did not fully comprehend this
until I had stopped my journey
at the end and then realized how
hard the stopping hit me, which
then exposed the the imbalance,
the failure to integrate the
radical, the most extreme, most
radical experiences, which were
the deepest experiences, being
drawn into intimacy, into
communion With, I want to say
the divine, but I'm cautious
about that, because we have to
unpack all sorts of theological,
you know,
Manda Scott: distortion on this
podcast, actually, you could we
talk about the heart, mind of
the universe all the time, which
I think is, is, for me, what you
would call the divine. So I
think we can assume that
unpacking has been done in the
past five years.
Chris Bache: The universe is
good. I like. That's why the
book is called LSD. In the mind
of the universe, it could be the
heart mind of the universe,
Manda Scott: but you came to a
point where you were basically
marking time, waiting to die in
order to return to Unity with
the divine. Yes, did I
understand that correctly?
Chris Bache: No, you understood.
You got it correctly. It's kind
of jumping ahead to the story.
Let me back up and work to that
point. Okay, if you work, and I
think in order to extract the
maximal psychological, psycho,
spiritual and philosophical
value of these experiences, it's
very important to create a
container, what I call the Kiva
of practice, a container which
affords you the best opportunity
for absolutely clear contact
with these deeper states of
consciousness, without
interruption, without confusion,
no outside contact. You're in a
therapeutic environment. You're
lying down, you're with a
skilled sitter. You're listening
to carefully curated music. It's
a it's a complex process, which
you have to prepare for. You
have the session you need.
You're integrating the session
acutely for several days after.
So each session takes a week,
essentially, to, you know, just
for the immediate session, and
then as you build on these
sessions over time, you're
right. It's a linear, I found a
linear progression. Relatively
speaking. You know,
consciousness is a holistic
phenomenon. So you may
experience multiple levels of
consciousness simultaneously.
You may experience some deep
levels. Of consciousness early
in your journey work, but if you
work systematically, my
experience at least, is that
there was a progressive
deepening, so that I went
through rounds of deepening when
I was writing up my journey at
the very end, I looked at the
total landscape of my
experiences, and I broke it down
into five fundamental landscapes
that I had been exploring. One
is personal mind, your personal
unconscious. Second is the
collective mind, the species
mind Carl Jung would have called
the collective psyche. Third,
archetypal mind. Fourth, causal
mind, the mind of oneness. And
fifth, the diamond Luminosity.
So my experience was I would
work. I would go through success
of success, succession of death
and rebirth experiences.
Eventually I would have a
breakthrough that would catapult
me into a new level of
consciousness where I would have
to learn how it worked. It was a
totally different it was like a
different physics governing this
level of reality. I would work
there. I would continue to learn
there. But in that process, I
would go through more
purification exercises, more
episodes of death and rebirth
that weren't simply repeating
ego death, but were taking me
into a deeper cycle of death and
rebirth. And eventually that
would culminate, and it would I
would have a breakthrough into a
completely different level of
reality, and that level of
reality, I would all start over
again. I wouldn't understand how
it would work. It would be
confusing. Then I would keep
going back to it. I'd get my sea
legs. I would acclimate to it.
My visionary experience would
get clear. And then I would go
and get propelled into another
level of reality. And when I was
in the middle of the deepest,
deepest level. I went into the
diamond Luminosity. I had an
experience in which I was I had
an experience of a level of
Light Beyond the diamond
Luminosity, and a ray of light
came out of that reality hit me,
shattered me, and what it taught
me was it's an infinite
progression. It I had thought in
the beginning it was a matter of
becoming one with God or getting
to the meta, cosmic void stage
of work. But what I found is
that there are many, many levels
of God. There are many levels
even of the primal void. That's
an infinite progression. You'll
never reach the end to of it,
even using as powerful a
protocol as high dose LSD work,
and that really is one of the
things that shifted my entire
orientation, because if I were
doing it over again, I would be
much gentler with myself. I
would use lower doses. I would
balance and vary the psychedelic
that I was using, because I've
learned that the goal of the
work is not to get to some end
stage or end point, which would,
you, know, change your life
forever, but the goal is simply
to open, let as much of the
wisdom of the universe in as
possible, as much of the love as
much of the insight, and then
spend weeks, months, years,
integrating that those
experiences changing whatever it
is about your life that is
keeping you from experiencing
those realities on everyday,
daily basis, and then continuing
work. So at the end of my
journey I had I found that I had
gone so deep into intimacy with
the divine, into the Divine
Light, dissolving completely
into fields of light,
transcending space and time, so
deeply that when I stopped this
work and and I'll go later if
you want to why I stopped the
work, but I stopped it after 20
years, and then in the years
following, I found that I was
missing the transcendent clarity
so deeply that I found I was
just waiting to die so that I
could return when I died, and
after reflecting on this for a
long period of time, I began to
realize something's not right.
This is not the way this work is
supposed to end. It's not
healthy. And I spent a lot of
time then studying my work to
try to find out where I had gone
wrong. And I realized, I came to
realize that I had I had gone so
deeply into Transcendence that I
had created an imbalance within
my incarnation, an imbalance
which was tilted towards
Transcendence at the expense of
embodied affirming my deeply
physical, embodied existence.
And both of the these are two
fundamental truths. We are
always tapped into
Transcendence. We're always
tapped into the physical world.
But I had tilted the balance
very far, and I had to make a
conscious choice to reground
myself in physical reality so
that I could become more
comfortable. In my own skin, and
this began, and writing LSD in
the mind of the universe was a
tremendous help, because I was
speaking about my experiences.
And I'm an academic, and I, you
know, I love to talk, so I love
to teach, and by speaking about
these experiences, it empowered
my integrating the experiences,
and by sharing them publicly,
after so many years of keeping
them private, it allowed a
healing to take place inside my
own psyche, between that which
had been hidden and That which
had been public between the
higher and that, which is,
quote, lower or the Earth year.
Yeah, yeah.
Manda Scott: Again, many doors
opened. We want to come back to
why you ended. I would like to
make clear to people listening.
First of all, this was
industrial doses of LSD, and
you've explained that you went
through death and rebirth
experiences. I think it's worth
pointing out that there were
points where you were vomiting
so hard for so long that the
vessels in your eyeballs
ruptured. Yeah, it wasn't
sounding like a whole lot of fun
to me. And you also had your
then wife, who was a trained
psychologist, psychotherapist, I
can't remember, but she was very
good at holding the space, so
you had a lot of anchoring. And
it still sounds like the early
part of every single journey was
living hell, as far as I can
tell. Would that be fair?
Chris Bache: Yeah, it's, it's
what I discovered eventually,
that there's a purification
cycle, and early, traditionally,
we would call it the
Death-Rebirth cycle. But we
often think of death as
something that happens to us one
time, and a lot of the
therapeutic literature and
psychedelic work circles focuses
on ego death, which is for me,
is only the first round. And
what I learned later, after
you've died many times in this
process, I mean completely loss
of control, metaphysical
confusion, just complete
surrender to overwhelming,
metaphysical waterfalls. You
learn that first you cannot die.
It's impossible to die. The form
that you are can die. The
structure of life as you have
known it can be extinguished,
but the inner essence of your
being always re emerges. The
Phoenix always rises. And I in
that process, I also learned
that death, what we experience
as death, is actually an
extremely intense form of
purification. When your
purification reaches so deeply
that it reaches into the
fundamental assumptions that
structure your experience of
reality, then death has returned
to grace you, right? So it's
purification breakthrough
experiencing a deeper state, and
if you want to stop at that
level, it's perfectly fine.
Different people use different
psychedelics, different
modalities at different powers,
and some psychedelics only have
sufficient power to reach
certain levels. Happened that
the method that I was using, the
substance I was using, was so
powerful, it had the power to
keep breaking me through level
after level in this systematic
fashion. Yeah.
Manda Scott: And did you choose
LSD because of Stan Grof and and
it was the thing back in the 70s
at that I suppose that's a head
mind question, but my spirit
mind question is, you could have
done a lot of different things.
Ayahuasca wasn't around much,
but mushrooms were there were
other things that were there. Do
you think that whatever it is
that guides you through this
incarnation led you to that
because you said you wouldn't do
it again now, but you wouldn't
be who you are now if you hadn't
gone through the Erdogan, the
military, the military version
of completely destroying
yourself many times. Can you
speak to that?
Chris Bache: Well, to understand
why I chose LSD, you have to go
back to 1979 1980 Ayahuasca was
still not yet on the playing
field for the most part. Just
early mushrooms certainly were.
I understood LSD to be more
powerful than mushrooms. So the
primary reason, though, is that
my work was based upon Stan Grof
work, and I trusted Stan. I
trusted his research, and Stan
did most of his work with LSD.
So that's where I dug in. I dug
in there. Later. After I
finished my 20 year journey,
I've done many psychedelics.
I've done mushrooms and five MEO
and salvia divinorum and San
Pedro, different psychedelics in
Ayahuasca, which are beautiful,
and they've taught me a lot, and
I have a certain sense of that
each of these psychedelics
impact the spectrum of
consciousness, or open some
portion of the spectrum of
consciousness. The the kind of
contact I experience with
Psilocybin, for example, is very
body grounded, very emotional.
Body grounded. LSD tends to be
have a high cosmological ceiling
tendency, certainly at high
doses, it tends to push the high
ceiling, whereas Psilocybin is
much more grounded earthy in my
earthly existence.
Manda Scott: Yeah, and it's
seems to me, it's more to do
with opening doors into the rest
of the web of life, rather than
necessarily cosmic awareness.
Not that the two are mutually
exclusive, but there's, as you
were saying, there's a tilt one
way or the other tilt. Yeah, I
want to move towards the future
human. But just before we go
there, I'm wondering how was it
taken in academic circles when
you wrote these books? Were
there people who then came to
and went, Yes, I've been wanting
to do this, or I have been doing
this, and thank you for opening
the doors. Or were there others
for whom the door was now shut
and you your access was denied?
How did it land with your
people?
Chris Bache: My work has been
well received in the
consciousness community and in
the academic community. They
don't even know I exist. For the
most part, it's been ignored.
There hasn't been a single
professional review published of
my work out of a hardcore
academic philosophy journal or
religious studies journal.
Manda Scott: But you must have
friends who could publish in
those journals. You must have
ways into that if, if people
wanted to, is it just not worth
their career to do that?
Chris Bache: You know, I just
one of the things I decided
early on in my career was not to
try to address the reservations
which were abundantly clear to
me coming out of the traditional
academic mindset. I decided that
if I tried to justify the method
and justify the experiences to
my colleagues, it would it would
hamper me, it would hold me
back. I just decided to push
deeply ahead and let the chips
fall where they may and and I
understand how exotic, how
strange my claims are, how they
sound to people, right? You
know, raised educated in a
traditional environment, and
I've just decided to let that go
and let history sort things out.
I am acutely aware that I'm
writing not from my present
generation. I'm writing for my
for future generations. Who
will, you know, paradigm change
take place in evolutionary
context, and so I'm just doing
the work and letting other
people sort out what they think
it's worth and with any
Manda Scott: luck, I already
give my it to be one of your
students and it sounds like
there are, particularly we
touched on the earlier moments
when you were having what we
would now consider to be psychic
experiences where you knew
things that from non ordinary
reality, not when you're on the
LSD, but just when you were
teaching and then, and then you
had to hold them in, because if
you said something, It was
basically going to blow
everybody's fuses. And there
fuses, and they were going to
wonder how you knew it and
explain how you knew it. But
those students I am thinking,
have been in the in the field of
your awareness, at a point when
you are experiencing, I've begun
to see the world in a different
space. So with any luck, they'll
go off and change the world.
Chris Bache: So I'll tell you
one aspect about that particular
I never let my students know
that I was doing this work, but
I began to find that even though
they didn't know about my
psychedelic work, they began to
have experiences which were
moving, showing that they were
being impacted by my psychedelic
work. And secondly, my work was
changing me at a deep structural
level, so that my person became
a lightning rod that was
sparking transformational
insights or breakthroughs among
my students without me
consciously intending it. I
began when I would be lecturing.
I was drawing into my lecture
examples which were purely
random for me, but the examples
I was being told were actually
exactly the same thing that had
been happening to my students
that week, and the thing. Things
I was saying began to touch them
in very, very deep, personal,
intimate places, places they
were wounded, places they were
blocked from going forward. This
became such a common feature of
my work that eventually I spent
a lot of time studying this and
developing an entirely new way
of teaching to take into account
the truths that I was
discovering in the classroom and
in my psychedelic work that
revolved around the boundaryless
nature of consciousness. Fields
of consciousness that fields
develop in groups, there's an
energetic resonance which
happens underneath the verbal
exchange of ideas as a
consciousness, directly engaging
consciousness. And so I
published a book in 2008 after I
stopped my sessions called the
living classroom in which I lay
it all out. But I never
mentioned psychedelics, because
the issue is not psychedelics.
The issue is consciousness, the
potential of consciousness. So
if you do very deep
consciousness work without
psychedelics, I think you can
trigger the same things that I
experienced. But eventually,
just recently this actually,
this month, SUNY press is
bringing out a second edition of
the living classroom, and in
this edition, they invited me to
tell the truth about my
psychedelic practice, because
I'm out of the closet by now.
LSD, in the mind of the universe
was out. So the new edition of
the living classroom makes clear
that it was my psychedelic
practice that was driving the
phenomena that were emerging in
my classes, even though I think
other people not using
psychedelics can experience the
same thing, so that's that's a
whole nother, another aspect
that has to do with integration.
Because integration here means
taking care, not only of
yourself, but taking care of
anyone whom your practice
touches, which for me, included
many of my students, and 1/3 of
the book is just essays that my
students have written, very deep
essays, personal essays about
their own spiritual experiences,
their experience of death. It's
that's a beautiful section of
the book,
Manda Scott: right? I will find
that and put a link in the show
notes. And you were still
teaching the philosophy of
religion at this point you
hadn't branched out into other
things. Is that?
Chris Bache: Right? Yeah, I was
teaching classically Religious
Studies courses, Introduction to
world religions, Eastern
religions, Buddhism, psychology
of religion, mysticism and
meditation. You know, classic
curriculum.
Manda Scott: Gosh, I wish they
were the classic curriculum when
I went through but with my my
senior apprentice. And I don't
work with psychedelics, but we
work, we teach shamanic studies.
And I found, even when I'm
talking about the book in front
of a literary festival, that's
that basically full of ordinary
middle class people who've come
along and had nothing better to
do, and wanted to get out of the
rain, as far as I can tell. And
we end up drawing in examples
that seem to come out of
nowhere. And then someone goes,
Oh, you just mentioned Boston,
and something about streets in
Boston, about which I know
precisely nothing. I come from
Boston, and the streets are just
like that. So so I'm sure that
what you said is absolutely true
and and at a deeper level when
we're teaching a held circle,
then then the resonances move
across the circle, but becoming
aware of these such that
everyone in the circle is
engaging with that strikes me as
a step towards future humanism,
if we're I think we're becoming
conscious of the things that can
help us to be different humans.
Chris Bache: Once you understand
how fields work, and once you
develop a protocol that
maximizes potential of the
emergence of conscious of these
consciousness changing fields
within groups, then you you do
it in a way that accelerates. It
deepens not only the learning
experience, but it accelerates
the transformational value of
these exercises for everyone
involved. And this applies not
just to university courses. It
applies in research
laboratories, in boardrooms,
wherever citizens gather in
sustained conversations, which
is where most of our change
takes place, in dialog with
other human beings. And so this
is very relevant to the
challenge moving into, yeah,
Manda Scott: yes, so let's go
there. So let's lay out where I
think roughly we're at. And you
can tell me, because you live in
the US, and I'm just watching it
with kind of squinched up eyes
from across the water waiting
for it to come over here. Musk
has already said he's going to
basically buy the next election,
and we have always had the best
democracy money could buy. So
unless we can change the
democratic process, that's it.
So Moscow and Starlink, I've
been floating across substack
watching something. Very
interesting, very geeky people
pointing out how he managed to
steal the election and how the
numbers don't add up. But you
know, if you're going to feed
everything through Starlink, the
person who owns the Starlink can
make it say what they want it to
say. You and I are talking
across many 1000s of miles using
technology that, in the end, is
basically owned by an individual
who might be very interesting,
but I don't necessarily want
them knowing everything that I
think can do. So it seems to me
that evolution only happens
under moments of intense
pressure. I would like this
moment not to become any more
intensely pressurized. Probably
will, but yeah, this is as much
as I ever want. Therefore, can
we evolve our consciousness to
become future humans. And it
seems to me that you have a
doorway and a framework and a
concept within which that could
happen. Does that? How does that
land with you?
Chris Bache: That all aligns
fine, and I think you're
absolutely correct. I'm not sure
that I have a doorway that I
would recommend as such, but I
do think that psychedelics have
entered our historical scene at
precisely a time when we need
more awareness. We need it for
therapeutic, prosperous
processes. We need it for
political processes. We need to
wake up and grow. And so I think
it's historically important. And
there are 1000s and 1000s of
people working conscientiously,
not superficially, but very
conscientiously, working with
psychedelics in order to heal
the accumulated trauma of many
lifetimes and to open up a
deeper communion with the
intelligence that's resides
within the universe to help us
make a transition from a
mechanical, Dead universe of
dead matter to a living universe
that's alive at its core, that's
expressing its intentionality
through the quantum jumps that
take place in our evolutionary
journey. And I think we are
coming into a quantum jump right
now, in a nutshell. Well, let me
back up a sec. This chapter, the
birth of the future human, and
everything that it contains is
completely came into my work by
complete surprise. I thought of
myself doing the work I was
doing for personal
transformation, personal
healing, maybe even personal
enlightenment. But what happened
is that the method was so
powerful it pushed beyond all
those categories, and I had to
reframe my understanding of the
boundaries of conscientious
psychedelic work in a way that
dropped the model of personal
transformation and opened up
into a model of collective
transformation. I had years and
years of experiences where the
shadow that I was engaging was
not my personal shadow. I did
that work, but this was a
collective shadow. The pain and
the excruciating suffering that
I was processing had to do with
the pain of my entire species.
And there that I came to
understand that there is a
collective psyche that that
holds the trauma of humanity's
history, just as our individual
psyche holds the trauma of our
individual history, and this
collective trauma and collective
pain encumbers the free
functioning of the collective
psyche, just as our individual
trauma encumbers our individual
health and well being. So by
doing this work, I began to
understand that something in the
universe was using my sessions
to make a small contribution to
healing the collective psyche in
order to make it more available
to the influx of energy from
divine consciousness to allow it
to manifest more completely in
humanity.
Manda Scott: Now that that bit,
can you just say that again?
Because I think that's really
important. It's not that it's
that opening of the door to
something that's trying to come
in. Is that what I just heard
you say, can you just repeat
that? Because I think that needs
emphasizing.
Chris Bache: I think we're
living at a time of ascending
spiritual energy. There's, it's
almost like there's an influx of
higher light energy, spiritual
energy, pushing in on us and our
the pain of our history, the
karma of our narrowness of our
smallness of our trying to live
within a framework of individual
ego, at cost of anyone else's
well being, keeps us locked away
unsen insensitive to this
incoming light and as. In any
mystical development before
there is a breakthrough into non
dual or unitive consciousness,
there is a dark night of the
soul where you have to undo, you
have to let go of all of the
obstacles, all the blocks. And I
think this is happening at a
collective level, not only
inside intense psychedelic
sessions, but everywhere. If
you're doing past life therapy,
many of the lives that come up
to be cleansed or not
necessarily your personal former
lives, but they can be lives
within the system social
movements to end child abuse, to
End Abuse of our daughters, to
end racism, to end speciesism.
These things are tackling. These
movements are tackling pains
which are much deeper than
simply our personal pain and we
are. The whole system is kind of
straining against the burdens of
the past in order to open
itself, to take in more
powerfully, the energy of our
future, the light of our future.
So So in that context, in the
middle of this work, I began to
receive visions that were
stable, they were consistent,
and they stretched over several
years. They were dropped into my
sessions about where humanity is
in its evolutionary journey,
where it's going, and there was
a message of we were coming into
a time of radical, Pivotal
breakthrough, a before and
after, time that the past would
become quickly irrelevant,
because something fundamentally
new was emerging, but it never
showed me. For years how nature
was going to accomplish this. I
had no idea. And then in 1995
years later, I had a fundamental
experience where and I was
working at very deep levels. By
this time, I was into the
diamond Luminosity material. But
this session took me and it
broke me open. It dissolved my
mind into the species mind, and
then asked the consciousness of
the species. And I understand
how radical an assertion that
is, and I don't take it lightly,
but the species mind opened into
it took me into future time. It
took me into what I call deep
time. And in that future, I
experienced the death and
rebirth of humanity. I
experienced humanity coming to
an absolute breaking point, a
point of breakdown, an
unraveling of fundamental trust,
fundamental convictions within
our culture, a deep,
systematically, systematic
breaking down until the entire
planet, it seemed, was faced
with the task of mere survival,
just trying to survive. And it
looked like it was an extinction
event. At first it looked like
that was it. We were we had
overloaded the system so badly,
we had overdrawn the ecological
balance sheet of the planet, so
badly that we weren't going to
come out of it. But then what
happened in the visionary
experiences? Just when things
were at their worst, we began
things began to get lighter. We
and people who had been brought
to their knees, began to stand
up, and it began to reconstate.
And as we reconstulated After
these series of crises, and I
don't know how long they will
last, I think of this as kind of
a three generational pivot. I
can't imagine it lasting less
than that. It seems to be the
21st Century is a major pivotal
point, because we know by by
2030 2040, 2050, we're going to
be getting into worse and worse
and worse. Yes, environmental
crises. And I think what ha what
I think is happening is that by
the time we go through this
crisis, will we will crack open
something so deep in the human
spirit, so deep in the human
psyche, that what will emerge is
a literally transformed
humanity, not simply transformed
individuals, but a
transformation of the
fundamental substructure of the
human psyche. I think of this as
a shift in the plate tectonics
of the collective unconscious,
so that every human being born
after this period of history
will be experiencing
consciousness within the context
of a collective psyche that is
different than how we were
experiencing it in the 19th and
20th century
Manda Scott: now, or for a long
time before that, within our
time before that.
Chris Bache: Yeah. Now, there's
another theme that came in where
it gave me some. Of the details
of what the future human is, and
and then other sessions, I was
taken far into the future and
experience the this archetypal,
new archetype of the future
human. But in a very profound
experience, I had an experience
of, I believe in reincarnation.
I My first book was on
reincarnation. I think the
empirical evidence for
reincarnation, from a
philosopher's perspective, is
overwhelming. That's how I'll
put those cards on the table.
It's always been part of my
thinking while I went into these
sessions based on the evidence,
not because of religious
beliefs, and I experienced
reincarnation dynamics many
times in my sessions, not only
my personal reincarnational
history, but I experienced
reincarnation as a dynamic
process for the entire planet.
The entire species is pulsing in
the rhythm of reincarnation. And
if that's true, that
reincarnation is a basic fact of
life, then we have been we have
been building the future human
for hundreds of 1000s of years,
we have been growing bit by bit,
bit by bit, bit by bit. We
remember our former lives,
usually when we die and we
return to the domain of the
soul. But I think we are coming
into a point of history where
the soul is actually coming,
becoming conscious inside our
historical existence. And the
way I experienced this was one
day in my session, former lives
were coming into me, just coming
into me. And it was like
wrapping bright white light
filament around a kite spool.
And there came a moment where
they seemed to hit critical
mass, and when they hit critical
mass, they fused into one, and
when they fused into one, there
was an explosion of diamond
light from my heart, and I was
catapulted into a state of
consciousness where I was an
individual, but I was far beyond
Chris Bache. I was an individual
like I had never known
individuality before. And I came
to call this the birth of the
diamond soul. Now many people
are experiencing this. They give
it different names. How I call
it is simply my way of
languaging at the birth of the
diamond soul. And I think what's
happening is that the soul,
which is the consciousness that
holds all our former life
history, is waking up inside our
historical existence and is
supplanting egoic existence, so
that we have lived egoic
existence for 1000s and 1000s of
years, but now the ego has
driven the planet into red line
conditions, into unacceptable,
stressful conditions, and now we
either grow up or we go extinct.
And what growing up amounts to,
I think, is owning the deep
history and the deep
consciousness, which is our
truer nature. It's all divine,
of course, but the form of the
Divine is our soul nature. And
it's not just individuals, I
mean, who are waking up, but now
nature is putting enormous
pressure to wake up the entire
species. The entire species is
becoming a species of Christ, a
species of Buddhas, a species of
Prophets, of great spiritual
saints and sages of of history.
That's the pivot we're trying to
make. We're trying to make the
pivot of growing up, taking the
long view, the seven generation
view, really looking at and when
the soul wakes up, of course,
the whole our whole history
becomes kind of dynamically
alive within us. We have been
male, female, we have been every
race on the planet. We've been
every religion on the planet,
all of these relative
Manda Scott: on the other
species, absolutely.
Chris Bache: And so I think
that's what's happening. And I
think we are being brought to a
critical choice point driven by
the ecological crisis and the
other systemic crises which are
contingent upon the economic
realities of the past. We're
coming into a meltdown point of
those realities, a choice point.
Manda Scott: So definitely, I
totally take what you're saying,
and I would agree with it, if
somebody is listening to this
podcast, pretty much, by
definition, they still have an
amount of resource and
privilege, because they have the
time and the resources to do
that. And I hear you that this
is perhaps a three generation
span, but I'm wondering where
we. Are in those three
generations. We might not be the
first or the three generations
alive on the planet. At the
moment, the kind of Boomers, Gen
X, Gen Z, but then all the
others that we've got, more than
three generations alive, anybody
listening, wherever they are in
the span of age or gender or
race, what would you recommend?
As clearly, we don't have a
formula go and do this and this
and this, but the concepts
within which they could
prioritize their life, this is
where this is going out on New
Year's Day. So what do we do
between, what do we create as
our soul, as in s, O, Ul,
priorities for 2025, that would
help to move this process
forward. Yeah, a
Chris Bache: couple of quick
background assumptions that I
make. One is that this is a
transition which will take the
entire resources of the human
family. So there is no one
formula. It'll take everything
we have, everything we are.
It'll take scientific knowledge,
economic knowledge, political
skills, educational skills,
medical skills. It'll take
everything we have to move us
through. Second thing is, my
assumption is, and this is based
upon years of studying the past
life literature, that each one
of us has chosen where and when
to incarnate with a certain pre
vision of what we're getting
into and what will be the
dominant themes of that
incarnation and the resources
available within that
incarnation, that this is part
of our incarnational psychic
makeup, And that means each one
of us is already positioned by
the soul, by our soul, to make a
contribution to this transition
that we are coming into. So it's
not a matter of looking around
outside of oneself or somewhere
else. It's a matter of looking
deeply into where we are, what
we are. The key question is, not
so much, what can I do? The key
question, I think, is, will we
have the courage to do what is
within my reach to do? That's
the key question. If everybody
does what is within their reach
to do, we will make it through
this now, going one step beyond
that. There are many people, I
think, who are giving us good,
wise elder advice on how to
engage this moment in history,
how to move it forward. Very
simply put, I believe one of the
ways to do this is to become
what you believe the planet
needs right now, to become it in
your own personal life, to be to
internalize the beliefs, the
habits of mind, the generosity
of heart, the clarity of our
thinking and our social skills
and social community networks to
become what the planet needs. If
you have a clear understanding
of what the planet needs, and we
begin to do that, then we become
kind of a microcosm of the whole
evolutionary pivot and what is
alive within us stimulates and
activates what is the people
around us who are struggling to
do the same thing? So we're all
in this together. Our arms are
all interlinked. One cell
awakens another cell.
Manda Scott: Yes, the field
effect you were talking about
earlier. If we can come into
alignment, connect to the web of
life. Ask, what do you wanted me
and be that? Yeah. Then that in
itself, ripples out, and it
stops our head minds having to
plan, which seems to me quite a
letting, letting heart, mind
lead and head mind follow, is an
inversion of how we got here,
but seems to me quite important.
Chris Bache: For example, we
think that the future human, the
planet, needs more of a heart
based epistemology, a heart
based source of action. And so
to put the heart mind kind of
ahead of the mind, mind the mind
head mind, that's a reading of
what's emerging, of what we need
to do, right,
Manda Scott: right, and the and
our understanding may yet
evolve. I wouldn't say that's
necessarily an end point, but
it's it's a starting place to
move from here. This is Chris
learning
Chris Bache: deeply biomimicry,
learning the rhythms of nature,
learning what's alive and what's
in the in the physical world, in
the animal world, in the world
of insects, everything around
us, understanding how we have
created imbalance, how we can
restore systems, how to create
harmony with those systems, how
to learn from the engineering
that nature has already
accomplished through billions of
years of evolution within those
systems, so many ways.
Manda Scott: Yes, and, and I'm
thinking healing the trauma, if
Francis Waller is right, and we
are the trauma culture and the
indigenous peoples are are more
whole version of humanity. We
have 10,000 years of ancestral
trauma and potentially previous
life trauma. And it seems to me
that I end up talking sometimes
with people who are fixated on
healing their ancestors, and I
am increasingly feeling that if
I can heal in the moment, that
that ripples up and down the
timeline, that time is not
necessarily one linear thing
chucked into identical portions,
but that healing now, if I can
become a fully realized human
being, yeah, that ripples to my
parents and their parents and
their parents all the way back
down the line, and I don't know
how physical descendants, but
down a spirit descendant line,
and that that saves me feeling
that I have to heal 10,000 years
of ancestors, which is a big
Ask, and quite demoralizing. How
does that land?
Chris Bache: It lands Well, now
within a reincarnational
framework, we add the writer
that we were our ancestors. So
we can think of our ancestors in
this way we were our ancestors.
So when we're healing our
ancestors in part, we're healing
our own lineage. But anybody
worth their salt, any mother,
any father worth their salt, who
sees a child which is not their
own, in need, in pain, actually
reaches out to help heal that
child. So healing, once you
really immerse yourself in that
process, the boundaries of
healing. Expand that, healing
the trauma of ancestors, healing
the traumas of your neighbors,
healing the trauma of actually
creating traumaless societies
for our future children. It's
it's all good work. It's all
hard work, and it's the work of
the hours, right?
Manda Scott: And people, I have
a suspicion, are going to be
emailing me afterwards, asking
where they can get enough LSD to
start on the process. Read the
book first people, because Chris
did things that the rest of us,
I don't necessarily think we
want to do, but psychedelics are
big now. Is it your belief that
everyone should be within a
structured and held way and with
suitable reflection exploring
psychedelics. Or is it that a
critical mass does that and the
effect rolls out to the rest of
us?
Chris Bache: I don't think it's
wise for everybody to have a
value that everybody should try
psychedelics. Get into
psychedelics. Psychedelics are
basically amplifiers of
consciousness. They amplify
consciousness. What you do with
those amplified states of
awareness in those precious
hours really determines the
value how you use them. You can
use them recreationally. You can
go to a Grateful Dead concert.
You can talk with some friends,
or you can use them to expose
your shadow, to heal your
shadow, and to move into deeper
cosmological exploration. But
many of us are carrying tensions
within our psyche which should
not be amplified, and this I
mean Carl Jung would listen to
people's dreams on their first
day when they came to work with
them. And he wouldn't work with
some people because he knew that
they were not ready to undertake
the depth of work that would
emerge working with him. And I
think this is true for
psychedelics. There are some
people who should there are a
lot of people who should not use
psychedelics. The circumstances,
the patterns of their
consciousness. Currently, it's
too strong a medicine. They need
a gentler way in, slower way in.
But among people who are, say,
basically healthy, a healthy
psyche we're not caring.
Manda Scott: Do you know anyone
who has a healthy psyche?
Chris Bache: I know somebody
have a healthier psyche.
Manda Scott: Yes, yes. I'm
thinking of a lot of my friends
who are just really wounded
guys. I think a lot of people
that I know have have healthier
psyches. But I think all of us
are carrying quite deep, frozen
hearts still.
Chris Bache: And if you go in,
if you're working, choose to
work with psychedelics, I would
say, very controlled
circumstances. You know, you
really want to batten down the
hive just carefully before you
set out into the deep water.
Very conscientious control of
dose, first, purity of
substance, because that's always
an issue. And, you know, pure
substance, because a lot of crap
comes in. What you get on the
street, pure substances, careful
containers, therapeutic
structure, you know,
therapeutically monitored,
structured experiences. Groups
are, I don't think it's good to
do what I did to work solo. Uh,
it adds unnecessary burden. It's
good to have a group, even
Manda Scott: though you were
held by the person who held you.
Chris Bache: I was held by I
wasn't totally alone. I was held
by my wife, uh, Carol, that my
manager was a PhD psychologist,
but it wasn't healthy in the
sense that I didn't have a group
that I could share my
experiences with beyond that
inner circle, I wasn't able to
talk about it and to take in
other people's experiences until
way too far down the road. So
you know, Ayahuasca communities,
Psilocybin communities, where
people can work, journey
together, process together, be a
mirror to each other. Help
expose the shadow in their post
session personalities. The
greatest danger of working with
psychedelics is psychic
inflation, right? You can think
that because
Manda Scott: you have become God
now I can tell you everything.
Chris Bache: Yeah, exactly, we
just because you've had a
special experience, you think
you're a special person, and you
know it that's just a big
fallacy.
Manda Scott: Yeah, there's
Ayahuasca is in the incoming
administration in the US, or at
least not Ayah scares, but
people who have taken Ayahuasca
in the incoming administration
in the US, and, yeah, yeah. I'm
sure they're wonderful human
beings, but breaking everything,
yeah. And I think one of the
things that I heard from an
Ayahuasca who has spent very
large amounts of time in the
forest is that Western people
tend to want to come and do it
and go away again, and don't
want to spend the weeks and
months of really getting to know
the plant and letting go of the
ego. It's, yeah, it's a process,
not an event, long process.
We're not used to that in our
culture.
Chris Bache: And let me
recommend a book on Ayahuasca to
your read to your audience, and
that is Bill Barnard's book
published by Columbia University
Press, which is insignificant,
and his book is liquid light.
And Bill is a university
professor at Southern Methodist
University. He had several books
under his belt. He's a very well
recognized philosopher of
religion. He has a book on
William James, a book on Henri
Berkson, but the book liquid
light tells a story of years and
years and years decades of going
down to South America, living in
the Santo dynamic community,
working every sabbatical and
every vacation with his teachers
there. And it's a it's an
analysis of the scientific
dynamic community, and it's also
an analysis of his own
experiences in the Santo dynamic
community. So it's another
academic becoming
autobiographical without being
trapped within his personal
story. And it's specifically
focused and he is a beautiful
writer, and his experiences are
very powerful, brilliant.
Manda Scott: I will find that
and put it in the show notes. I
could go on forever we are
heading towards the end of time,
the end of our time, not
necessarily the end of all time.
A number of questions with all
of the coders of what we just
said, it strikes me that you are
probably familiar now with an
emerging network of people who
are working together with a
variety of different psychedelic
substances. Are you seeing
networks of consciousness such
that people are this is about to
sound really flaky, but a lot of
the push that I'm getting is to
do the work so that I can
actually connect with all of my
students in the dream in a way
that we're both fully aware of,
not I just get an email going. I
saw you in the dream last night.
You did this. I think, well,
that's really nice, but I have
no awareness of that that we
move to methods of human
networking that are similar to
but beyond the digital
networking that we just moved
into within the last 20 years.
Are you seeing anything
approaching that? Or, if not,
would you like to speak to what
is happening in terms of a
collective community, if
anything?
Chris Bache: Yeah, well, first I
want to own my limitations in
that even though I've published
this book, and even though I
speak at some conferences, I
don't speak at most psychedelic
conferences, because my work is
pretty radical, and the focus on
the psychedelic renaissance
right now is on therapy and
careful scientific studies
demonstrating The therapeutic
efficacy of psychedelics, and
that's perfectly fine. That's
that's where we need to be. But
there the movement is not yet
pushing the cosmological
territory that I've pushed in my
work.
Manda Scott: Yeah, it'll get
there. Must be somebody
somewhere that can't be that
just you did it well,
Chris Bache: like Bill Barnard,
and there are people, but. I
think a lot of it is still
underground at this point. So I
am aware of certain trends in
the Renaissance community and in
the psychedelic community, but I
I don't have a Catholic,
comprehensive breadth of access
to the what's happening. So I,
you know, I worked in isolation.
My work is unusually intense and
extreme, and I live basically a
pretty quiet life around that.
But what I do see, and there are
some people doing, as you're
describing, cultivating kind of
communities of paranormal
contact within the dream state,
extended dreaming, doing
different things. There are
people who are working in
meditation, trying to integrate
psychedelics into meditation
circles. There's a lot. There's
a lot going on. A lot moving. I
think the internet is a physical
manifestation, in a sense, the
the hard wires of an emerging of
this emerging field
consciousness. So that even if
we don't accomplish these
networks psychically, we
certainly can. We're on a
network right now. We're, this
is a global network that we're
part of.
Manda Scott: It is but somebody
could pull a plug on it
tomorrow, if China or Russia or
somebody decides to just switch
it or monitor it such that it's
not safe to say anything outside
a certain narrow bandwidth, it
could vanish. The freedom that
we have just now is not, is not
a given, I would say, whereas if
we could talk to each other
without needing the internet, it
would be quite hard to interfere
Chris Bache: with that, it would
be great that the complication,
of course, is the clarity of the
transmission, the purity of the
transmission, because the
personal psyche throws up all
sorts of filters. Yeah.
Manda Scott: Ego gets in the
way. Basically, head, mind gets
in the way. Yeah, okay, I think
we never got to. Actually, you
said, I'll come to it later. Of
why I stopped. Did you feel that
you covered that? Did you want
to cover that? If not, is there
anything else that you feel we
could usefully cover in the time
that we go,
Chris Bache: that's actually
might be a good place to wrap up
some of the discussion, because
it's relevant to where we might
go. I stopped for two reasons. I
stopped first because my
physical system that my subtle
energy system, my Prana or qi
energy system was running so hot
after all these years of
practice that it was producing
certain physical symptoms that
was leaving me continually
physically uncomfortable, and I
describe these in The book, but
basically I understood enough
about chronic energy and
Ayurvedic medicine and to
understand what was happening,
and I was just running too much
energy. But that's not the major
reason I stopped. The major
reason I stopped was heartache.
That is, it was getting
increasingly difficult to come
back from the deep states of
ecstatic Transcendence,
immersion in the divine fabric,
to come out of that, back into
my time, space, reality. And
there are beings. There are
great beings who are able to
sustain that those
transcendental states in their
time, space personality, they
are great masters, and truly,
all honor to the great masters.
I'm not one of those beings.
This is a path of temporary
immersion that's different than
the path of contemplative
presence. So I can go into those
states, but I have to come out
of them, and eventually coming
back out just became too painful
of a separation, so I stopped,
and I knew I would be stopping
for the rest of my life, because
it takes years and years of
momentum to develop the energy
to break into these high, high
energy states I could, if I did
a massive dose of LSD right now,
I would not be able to go back
to where I was working at the
end of my 20 year journey. Yeah,
so I knew I was stopping for the
rest of my life, but it was
important for me to stop, and I
had to first learn how to manage
the heartache, and then to begin
the process of working the
slower process of integrating
those living memories, actively
living memories, into my
physical existence, which
conversations like this actually
helped me do. So it's a very
it's. Healing for me to talk
about these things with you so
and the way that applies to
maybe some of your listeners, is
to be careful about how much you
bite off in your sessions,
because even if you're really
committed to conscientious
integration, you can bite off
more than you can chew, or more
than it's wise for you to chew.
So I think we can learn a lot
from the contemplative
traditions. It's one of the
advantages I had going into this
work. I was teaching courses in
mysticism and meditation,
teaching courses in Shamanism
and Buddhism. So I understood
the literature of mysticism. I
understood the practices of
mysticism, the purification
processes, and Ian and I tried
to use those processes in my own
work. And there's a lot of
wisdom there. So it's it serves
you to be well read, and I think
to recognize the limitations of
any one incarnation. I think
that in some ways, I went to
places that were so deep, it
will take me not just one
incarnation, but multiple
incarnations, to truly integrate
them. And by that, I mean being
able to manifest those levels of
a consciousness inside my
physical consciousness,
comfortably,
Manda Scott: okay, right? Yes,
yes.
Chris Bache: So I would
basically hate for anyone to try
to do what I did and get into
trouble and hurt themselves.
That would just break my heart.
Manda Scott: Yeah, yeah. I think
we've, we've got the health
warnings fairly clear on here.
If you're going to work with
things, work with somebody who
knows really what they're doing.
Me and my apprentice are working
to find people that we can pass
people on to, because we get
emails saying I took substance
X, and basically I'm having a
psychotic breakdown. What can I
do? And we're shamanic
practitioners. Actually, it's
not our field, so we're trying
to pass this on to people who
can actually help, but they're
few and far between, because
there's a lot more people who
think they can help than the
ones who can actually help. So
take great care, find test your
people out before you decide to
do something that is
irreversible. I would say it's
really clear. And then do the
work beforehand, and do the work
during, and do the work after
after, to integrate and
integrate and integrate and do
it because you're doing it in
service to life, and not because
you're trying to make your ego
feel happy. Yeah, strikes me as
a quite important one. Have I
missed anything out on the
Chris Bache: health world? I
think it's great. And if you do
your work well, one of the
things that happens is you lose
all fear of death. You once, you
transition several times into
that reality. You know, in your
bones, from your own experience,
that death is not an end of
anything. It's simply an end of
an incarnational cycle, and
there is absolutely nothing to
fear about death. Death is
homecoming, all of the Hollywood
bullshit that are thrown up at
us for, you know, dark places
and demons and ghosts and all
this stuff, it's just nonsense.
99% of people die and make a
transition into the light
perfectly naturally and
comfortably. If you're afraid of
dying, you've got your entire
metaphysics upside down. Death
is homecoming. Death is the end
of your this matriculation. It's
the harvesting of your life.
Birth should be mourned. Birth
is where the work begins. It's
like being a freshman in
college. It's hard. Graduation
is wonderful, right? And when
you lose your fear of death, and
you begin to understand the
deeper, meaningful challenges
which are embedded in our time
space experiences, then the
whole, if you lose your fear of
death, your whole game of life
changes, because death is what
people fear more than anything
else. And if you don't have that
fear, then you're you're going
into a different lifestyle, a
different way of living, a more
joyful way of living.
Manda Scott: Yes, yes. Thank
you. Thank you. That feels to
me, a fantastic place to end.
Does that feel good to you? It
feels good to me. All right, in
that case, Chris, thank you so
much for coming on to the
accidental gold podcast. This
has been an absolute delight. I
have enjoyed every moment, and I
think what a way to start the
year.
Chris Bache: Thank you. Thank
you, Amanda, and thank you for
your work. We need all of the
awareness that we can bring to
ourselves, and you are certainly
bringing awareness to many
people. Thank you. You.