Emmy Vadnais: Did you connect
with a being, or beings, or
angels or other divine entities?
And if you could share a little
bit about what that realm was
like
Chris Bache: in all the years
when I was doing this work, and
all the work I did, I never
encountered a being, a divine
being. Said, I'm God. You know,
this is what I am. It wasn't
like that. It was like I would
go deeper into a level of
consciousness, and I would
experience a communion with this
consciousness, and this
consciousness would teach me. It
knew me, it would teach me and
show me things, and it would
crush me, and then bring me
forward into still deeper
levels, and I would go into
those deeper levels, and I would
enter into communion with those
levels and and I internalized
the energy of those levels, and
I was with this consciousness,
but it never crystallized into a
specific form. I always felt its
presence. It guided my sessions.
I could enter into dialog with
it. I could enter into communion
with it. It would, it would
dissolve me into itself. But it
never crystallized into a what
you might call a personality of
God, or a person of God, and it
just kept getting larger and
larger, deeper and deeper, more
and more vast. And I think that
many of our theologies of God,
or thinking about God, is really
based upon what I would call the
early encounters with an
infinite intelligence, that that
this infinite intelligence is
far larger, far too large to
ever be concretized in the
historical lineages that we
recognize in the world.
Traditions.